清算

/

第一章

“新实施的婚姻法将是：你不应对自我不忠。”

表示赞同的呢喃声响起，填满整个画室。当她丈夫从临时搭建的讲台上走下来时，克莱门特·韦斯托尔的太太透过烟雾看见他融入到一群对他表示祝贺的女士当中。韦斯托尔对于“新伦理学”的非正式发言为他吸引来了一群精神匮乏的热情拥护者，用他自己的话说，这群人喜欢别人把精神食粮切好喂到嘴边。这一系列的发言并非计划好的。众所周知，韦斯托尔的思想属于“先锋派”，但是迄今为止，他并没有打算公开宣扬这些先锋思想。在他妻子看来，一直以来，他几乎是小心翼翼地不让自己的个人观点给自己的专业地位带来不良影响。然而，他近期表现出越来越武断的倾向让人疑惑。他发起了挑战，在公众社会的面前炫耀自己的个人准则，而且两性关系的话题肯定能吸引大量的眼球。有几个欣赏他的朋友说服他把自己晚餐后的谈资总结成一系列的演讲，在范·西德伦的画室里发表，让这些观点可以面向更多的听众。

赫伯特·范·西德伦夫妇在社交世界中安身立命的根本，便是他们所拥有的这间画室。范·西德伦画作的主要价值在于充当妻子聚会场所的背景装饰，使他妻子的午后聚会有别于其他在纽约那些长长的客厅里所举办的枯燥乏味的活动，也让她有机会给朋友们提供威士忌苏打而不是茶水。对范·西德伦夫人而言，她非常擅长于利用人体模型和画架所创造出的氛围。而如果时不时地，她觉得这种假象难以维持，甚至沮丧到希望赫伯特能再画些画时，她便会迅速地找来一些有才华的新鲜血液，加强一点儿艺术气氛，缓解此时的脆弱心理。也就是在寻找这种外援的时候，她逮住了韦斯托尔，哄着他——出乎他妻子的意料——让他倍感荣幸地变成了自己骗局中的一位参与者。在范·西德伦的圈子里，人们能够微妙感觉到，所有的大胆妄为都被看成是艺术性的。一位宣称婚姻是不道德的教师，就像是一位把草地画成紫色、天空画成绿色的画家一样与众不同。而范·西德伦那一帮人已经厌倦了艺术和行为上传统的色彩搭配。

茱莉亚·韦斯托尔一直以来都对婚姻的不道德性有着自己的看法，或许她的确早已把她的丈夫纳为门徒。在他们的婚姻初期，她在心里对于丈夫不愿意宣称自己是新信条追随者这件事是感到怨恨的。她一直都更倾向于指责丈夫在道德方面是怯懦的，他根本没能履行二人婚姻理应坚持的信念。那是她第一次萌发了想要公开自己信仰的念头，正如普通女人一样，她想把自己的不服从变成合法的。现在她有了不同的感觉。她根本无法解释这些变化，可作为一个女人，她是永远不会允许自己的冲动无法得到合理解释的。为了使自己的冲动得到合理的解释，她说她不介意表达自己信念的文章被俗人所曲解。抱持着这样的想法，她开始觉得几乎所有人都是粗俗的。当然，她也觉得几乎没有什么人值得她去信赖，值得她去向他们阐释如此深奥的学说。然而也恰在此时，韦斯托尔决定抛开他保持沉默的原则，选择从隐私的制高点上走下来，开始站在街角兜售自己的信念。

在这种情况下，是尤娜·范·西德伦无意之中把韦斯托尔夫人摇摆不定的怨恨招惹到了自己身上。首先，这女孩儿根本就不应该出现在那里。光是一想到一个年轻的女孩儿竟然能够被允许去听这样的讲话，韦斯托尔夫人就觉得“可怕”——她发现自己又置身于过时的女性主义词汇之中——简直太“可怕”了。尤娜抽烟、偶尔抿一口鸡尾酒的这些行为，丝毫没有玷污她那光彩夺目的单纯形象，反而使她看上去更像是父母庸俗行为的受害者，而不是他们的帮凶。茱莉亚·韦斯托尔感到非常无助，她觉得必须得做点什么——有人应该要跟这女孩儿的母亲聊聊。而正在此时，尤娜溜到她身旁。

“哦，韦斯托尔夫人，刚才的演讲太棒了！”尤娜用清澈的大眼睛盯着她：“我想，你相信他所说的全部？”她的语气中带有一丝神圣的力量。

“全部……全部什么，我亲爱的孩子？”

女孩儿脸上露出了光彩。“关于更高级的生活……个人更自由的拓展……忠于自我的法则。”她流利地背诵出来。

韦斯托尔夫人大吃一惊，脸涨得通红。

“我亲爱的尤娜，”她说，“你根本不理解这是怎么一回事！”

范·西德伦小姐瞪大双眼，脸渐渐红了起来，回答道：“那么，您理解吗？”她喃喃说道。

韦斯托尔夫人笑了。“并不总是能理解……或并不能完全理解！但是我想喝点茶，麻烦你了。”

尤娜带着她来到了分发无酒精饮品的角落，茱莉亚接过她的茶，更仔细地打量着这个女孩儿。这并不是一张未经世故、天真无邪的脸庞，毕竟在青春岁月的朦胧美好之下，棱角分明的轮廓也逐渐形成。她想起来尤娜大概是二十六岁，好奇她为什么尚未结婚。要是能有许多好的想法作为嫁妆该多好！如果想法可以成为现代女孩儿嫁妆的一部分……

韦斯托尔夫人被自己的想法吓了一跳。仿佛就像是一个陌生人借用了自己的声音在说话：她觉得自己就像是被什么神奇的心理腹语术给骗了。她突然觉得房间里闷得透不过气来。尤娜的茶太甜了，她放下茶杯，四处张望，寻找韦斯托尔——和他的双目对视已经成为她面对一切不确定性时的避难所。现在，她找到了韦斯托尔的眼睛，但是她感到它们只是擦身而过而已，它们顺带把她捎上了一次更远大的飞行。她跟随着这班飞机，而它载着她来到了尤娜退避到的一个角落里——范·西德伦太太认为是这个热闹角落促成了她周六的聚会。韦斯托尔先生没过多久，就追赶上自己眼神的脚步，在女孩儿身边找到了一席之地。女孩儿倾身向前，急切地说着什么，他向后靠着，带着轻蔑的微笑听着，仿佛那笑容能将尤娜的吹捧过滤掉，让他能够在享用最大剂量的奉承之余，又不显现出自己对它的饥渴。茱莉亚对这个微笑的定义让她脸部的肌肉抽搐了一下。

在回家的路上，冬日的黄昏时分，街上没多少人，韦斯托尔突然像个小男孩儿似的握住了他妻子的胳膊：“我有没有让他们开了一点儿眼界？我有没有把你想让我说的告诉他们？”他开心地问道。

几乎是无意识地，她把自己的胳膊从他的手中抽了出来。“我想让你说的……？”

“为什么，你不是——一直以来都？”她从他的语气里可以听出来，他是真的很吃惊。“不知怎么的，我觉得你……之前……还挺责怪我不愿意更公开地谈论……有时候，你几乎让我觉得我这么做是在为了私利而牺牲原则。”

她停顿了一会儿没答话，然后她平静地说：“是什么让你决定不再继续……？”

她又感到了一丝丝的惊讶。“为什么？为了能取悦你！”他回答得似乎太轻松了。“那我希望你不要继续了。”她突然说。他本来步伐飞快，突然停了下来，然后她感受到他在黑暗之中盯着自己看。

“不再继续——？”

“请你叫辆马车吧，我累了。”她突然之间觉得全身疲惫，不想再继续这个话题。

他立刻开始嘘寒问暖起来。那房间里热得要命……然后是那些可恶的烟味……他有一两次注意到她看上去脸色煞白——下个周六她不能再来了。她感到自己要彻底投降了，就像她往常一样，屈服于他对她关怀的暖意之中，清楚地意识到自己放任心中女性柔弱的部分，轻轻地依靠在他内心中的男性特质上。

他把她扶进马车，黑暗之中，她把手偷偷伸进他的手中。眼中泛起了一两滴泪珠，她任由它们淌落脸颊。为想象出来的麻烦而哭泣是多么诱人的一件事啊！

当晚吃完晚饭后，出乎她意料的是，他把话题又带回到自己的演讲上。他讲话时结合了两种技巧，一种是当男性遇到让他感到不适问题时表现出厌恶情绪，另一种是近乎于女性化回避问题的说话方式。而她知道，如果他再回到这个话题上来，一定有什么特殊的原因。

“你似乎并不在乎我下午说的话。我解释得很不清楚吗？”

“不——你说得非常清楚。”

“那你说不想我继续是什么意思？”

她紧张地瞥了他一眼，弄不清他的意图加深了她内心的无助感。

“我想我不愿意在公众场合听到讨论这些事。”

“我搞不懂你了。”他大叫。她再一次感到他的惊讶是发自内心的，这使她自己的态度显得有些暧昧不明。她不确定自己是否了解自己。

“难道你不想解释一下？”他的语气中有一丝不耐烦。

她的双眼游走于熟悉的客厅之中，这里曾是无数个夜晚中他们交换心声的地方。那些昏暗的灯、那些挂着金属版画的朴素墙面，浅色的春季花朵散落在各种威尼斯玻璃花瓶和老塞夫勒碗里。不知为何，她回想起在第一次婚姻中度过了无数夜晚的那所公寓——房间里有一大堆红木家具和室内饰品，壁炉上方挂着的画是一个罗马农民，客厅后方两扇折叠门之间放着一个希腊奴隶的大理石雕像。

她从未能与那个房间建立任何深入的联系，她和那个房间的关系，不会比一个旅客和火车站之间的关系来得更亲密。而此刻，当她环顾着这个与她有着最亲密关系的环境时——她为了这个房间而离开了另外那个房间——她被似曾相识的陌生感和不适感吓到了。那些画、那些花朵和那些老瓷器柔和的色调，看上去似乎仅仅是一种表面精致的象征，和生活之中深层的意义毫无关联。

突然之间，她听到她的丈夫重复了一次他的问题。

“我不确定我是否能解释。”她支支吾吾地说。

他把扶手椅向前拉了拉，这样就能隔着壁炉正对着她。台灯的灯光照在他那轮廓分明的脸上，那张脸看上去有一种肤浅的灵敏度，和房间里表面上精致的摆设完全是同一种性质。

“难道说你不再相信我们的理念了？”他问。

“我们的理念指的是——”

“我正在传授的理念。你和我都应该支持的理念，”他停顿了一下，“我们的婚姻就建立在那些理念之上。”

血液涌到头上，她的双颊变得通红。那么他这么做是有自己的理由的——她现在敢肯定他有自己的理由。在他们十年的婚姻里，二人中没有哪个人经常停下来思考过彼此婚姻所立足的那个理念。人们隔多久才会把自己家的地下室挖开去检查地基呢？根基当然还在那里——整个房子都建立在根基之上——但是人们住在楼上，而不是住在地下室里。的确，一开始是她坚持偶尔回顾一下当时的情况——扼要重述一下坚持该道路的理由，时不时宣称一下自己信奉的是称之为个人独立的宗教理念。但她早已不再想坚持任何这些理想的标准，而是坦率而自然地接受了她的婚姻，就像它是建立在心灵原始需要的基础上的，并不需要特别的认可来解释或证明它是正当的。

“我当然还相信我们的理念！”她惊呼。

“那么我再说一遍，我搞不懂。应该尽可能地公开我们对婚姻的看法是你理论的一部分。在这方面你的想法已经改变了吗？”

她犹豫了一下：“这取决于具体情况——取决于是对哪些人公开。范·西德伦找来的那帮人根本不在乎信条的真伪。他们只是图个新鲜。”

“而恰好我们正是在这样一群人中相遇，了解到彼此内心之中的真实感受。”

“那不一样。”

“怎么不一样？”

“首先，我那时已经不是年轻姑娘了。年轻姑娘在……在这种时候……出现在这样的场合、听人们讨论这样的事情是完全不合适的……”

“我以为你觉得从不在年轻女性面前探讨这些问题才是这个社会最严重的错误之一，但那都无关紧要，因为我根本不记得在今天的听众里有看到任何年轻女性……”

“除了尤娜·范·西德伦！”

他轻轻地转过身，用胳膊肘子把台灯往后推了推。

“噢，范·西德伦小姐……当然……”

“为什么是当然？”

“她是那家人的女儿……难道你要让家庭教师和她一起离开？”

“如果我有女儿，肯定不会允许这样的事情在我家里发生的！”

韦斯托尔捋着他的胡子，面带微笑往后靠了一下。“我想范·西德伦小姐有足够的能力照顾好自己。”

“没有一个女孩儿知道该如何照顾自己——直到一切已经为时太晚。”

“而你却故意地阻止她得到最可靠的自卫手段？”

“你所说的‘最可靠的自卫手段’是什么？”

“对涉及婚姻牵绊时人性本能的相关知识的初步了解。”

她做了一个不耐烦的动作：“你愿意娶那种女孩儿作为妻子吗？”

“很乐意——如果她在其他方面是我喜欢的类型的话。”

她又从另一个角度继续这场争辩。

“如果你觉得这样的演讲不会影响年轻女性，那你就大错特错了。尤娜正处于一种极度可笑的亢奋之中……”她说了一半，突然停了下来，不知道自己为什么要说这句话。

韦斯托尔重新打开了一本杂志，在他们开始讨论之前，他把杂志先放到了一边。“你告诉我的话是对我演讲才能的极大恭维——但恐怕你高估了它的影响。我能向你保证，范·西德伦小姐不需要别人替她思考问题。她绝对有自己思考的能力。”

“你似乎对她的心理状态非常了解！”他妻子一时没忍住回击道。

他从正在翻的页面上静静地抬起头来。“我希望如此，”他回答，“她引起了我的兴趣。”

第二章

如果被误解能获得勋章，那茱莉亚·韦斯托尔离开第一任丈夫的时候，没能获此殊荣。当时每个人都愿意原谅她，甚至还想为她辩护。她的社交圈都认为约翰·阿蒙特简直是“让人无法忍受”，所有的女主人一想到再也不用邀请他一同进餐都松了一口气。

她第一次离婚并不涉及任何丑闻——夫妻双方甚至都没有婉转地指控对方触犯了什么。阿蒙特夫妇的确有责任把他们的忠诚奉献给自己所在的州，毕竟在他们的法律辖区里，公开遗弃是可以作为离婚理由的，而且该理由还能如此开明地得以阐释，以至于“遗弃”的种子开始出现在各个婚姻当中。就连阿蒙特夫人的第二次婚姻也没能使沉睡的传统道德激起一丝波澜。众所周知，她是在和第一任丈夫分开后，才遇到第二任丈夫的，更何况，她以一个穷丈夫取代了一个有钱的丈夫。虽然克莱门特·韦斯托尔被公认为律师界冉冉升起的新星，可人们普遍认为他的财富并不会像他的名声那样迅速增长。因此韦斯托尔夫妇大概一直也只能安静地生活，乘马车外出用餐。这不正好证明阿蒙特夫人是彻彻底底公正无私的吗？

就算说她朋友们为她行为辩解的理由听上去比她自己对此事的阐述显得更为简单粗暴，但两种解释都得出了同一种结论：约翰·阿蒙特根本让人无法忍受。这两者之间唯一的区别在于，对他的妻子来说，他的“无法忍受”要比起他社交方面的拙劣表现更难以容忍一些。她曾经以嘲讽的方式为自己的婚姻“辩护”说，至少这样一来她就不用坐在他身旁用餐。只是她当时并没有意识到，为了不用坐在他身旁用餐将要付出多大的代价。约翰·阿蒙特的确让人无法忍受，但他让人无法忍受的痛处在于，他让身边的人除了变成像他一样的人之外，别无他选。在无意识的淘汰过程中，他把所有自己觉得不需要的东西都排除在他的世界之外，就好像他已经变成了一种只能满足他个人需求存活的气候。这似乎暗示着他的自私自利是故意的，但是阿蒙特完全不是刻意而为之。他就像是动物或者小孩儿一样完全凭借本能。正是他天性之中孩子气的特质，让他的妻子对他的评价暂时有点儿摇摆不定。有没有可能他只是发育不良，是他的成长过程比普通人要来得更长，是他艰辛的成长过程被推迟了吗？他偶尔会表现出一种精明，也正是这种精明让人推翻了他很迟钝这一说法，觉得他“并不傻”。恰恰，这种特质让他的妻子最忍受不了。即使对于博物学家来说，当他的推论因为他所研究的生物的形式和功能出现了不可预料的反常现象而受到干扰时，该情景也是十分令人恼火的。对一个妻子来说更是如此，因为不可避免的，她对自己的评价总与她对丈夫的判断息息相关！

事实上，阿蒙特的精明并不意味着任何潜在的智慧力量，相反地，它暗示着一种情感上的潜力、一种感知痛苦的潜力，或者正是这种盲目而不成熟的精明方式让茱莉亚自然而然地想要赶快离开。她对于自己要离开他的理由是如此清晰，以至于简直无法想象她丈夫竟然不怎么理解她为何离开。她在分析问题的时候，丈夫脸上困惑的表情，困扰得她语无伦次起来，而他听着这些解释，最终默许了离婚。

这种时刻对她来说是很少有的。她婚姻的痛苦太过于具体，很难从哲学的角度来审视。就算造成她不幸福的理由是复杂的，可她的不幸真实得让这些理由都显得不再复杂了。灵魂比肉体更容易受伤，而茱莉亚的每一丝灵魂都伤痕累累。她丈夫的个性似乎在逐渐朝她逼近，遮挡住天空、切断了氧气，直到她觉得被困在了失去希望的腐烂躯体之中。她就像受到极其古老的阴谋的诱骗，进入到这种灵与肉的束缚之中，这种感觉让她满心绝望。如果婚姻指的是需要用漫长的一生去偿在无知时欠下的债务，那它就是对人性的犯罪。她可不会同流合污维持这种伪装，她一直以来都是这种伪装的受害者：这种伪装就是男人和女人被迫进入一段最狭隘的个人关系之中，还必须在里面待到人生尽头。虽然他们可能就像幼苗时缠绕在树干上的铁圈困不住成年的大树一样，彼此个性的空间早已容不下对方。

她第一次从道德方面感到愤怒的时候，恰巧遇见了克莱门特·韦斯托尔。她立即就看出来自己引起了他的“兴趣”，并且对这一发现感到非常排斥，生怕有任何影响将她再次拉回到传统关系的束缚之中。为了避免危险，她几乎是以一种粗鲁急躁的态度把自己的观点告诉了他。让她感到惊讶的是，她发现他和自己的想法一致。她被这位追求者的坦率所吸引，他在追求自己的同时，也承认他并不相信婚姻。她最大胆的举动似乎并没有吓着他：她所感受到的他早就发现了，而他俩得到了同一个结论。人们成长的速度不同，对一个人来说很容易适应的束缚可能很快就会让另一个人感到不适。这就是离婚的目的：重新调整个人关系。只要双方必要的磨合期一过，彼此就能够获得尊严与和谐。再也不需要为了维持不完美的婚姻而卑微地退让和纵容；再也不需要为了维持不完美的婚姻永久地牺牲个人的优雅和道德尊严。在婚姻合约中的双方都要尽心尽力，必须达到自我发展的最高标准，违反者会以失去另一方的尊重和爱意论处。落后的那一方不能拖先进一方的后腿，而是必须要努力进步，否则只能独自一人停留在低等水平上。和谐婚姻唯一的必要条件是坦率地承认这一事实，并在缔约双方之间达成一项庄严的协议——对自己忠诚。当双方步调不再一致的时候，一刻也不会再继续生活在一起。对自己的不忠才是新的通奸行为。

正如韦斯托尔之前提醒她的那样，他们的婚姻建立在这样的共识之上。婚礼只是对于社会偏见无关紧要的让步：既然离婚的大门已开，没有一个婚姻应该成为牢笼，因此婚姻合同也不再涉及任何有损自尊的内容。他们感情的属性尽可能地避免了这样的偶然性发生在他们身上。因此对他们来说，也更容易以开放的态度来讨论这些问题。而茱莉亚的安全感使她对于韦斯托尔的承诺有种柔情的坚持，他答应一旦不再爱她，就会提出重获自由的要求。在某种意义上，交换这样的誓言似乎使他们成为新法律的拥护者，成为在个人自由遭到禁锢的国度里的先驱：他们觉得自己从某种程度上来讲，好像在没有殉道的情况下获得了至福[4]。

当茱莉亚回顾过往的时候，她意识到，从理论上讲这一直是她对婚姻的态度。在她毫无意识的情况下，正是她和韦斯托尔在一起十年的幸福生活，不知不觉间使她对这段姻缘产生了另一种看法。更确切地说，是回归到过去那种，有强烈的依赖感和占有欲的原始本能，这种回归让她只要察觉到一丝变化的迹象，就会热血沸腾。改变？重新开始？他们用愚蠢的专业术语就是这么说的吗？“破坏”，甚至是“根绝”——这撕裂了与另一个人交织在一起的无数纤维。另一个人？但他不是别人！他和她是一体的，这是一种神秘的感觉，而正是这神秘的感觉赋予了婚姻意义。新法律不是为他们制定的，而是为那些本来就不和谐、被迫进入到一段让人耻笑的婚姻之中的男女制定的。她觉得有必要宣扬的福音与她自己的情况无关……她叫来医生，告诉他自己肯定需要安神剂。

她按时按点地服用安神剂，但这药对她的恐惧起不到镇静作用。她不知道自己在害怕些什么，而这反而让她更难逃脱开自己的焦虑。她丈夫没有再重提周六演讲的话题。他和往常不同，变得非常和蔼体贴，急躁的脾气也有所软化，在体贴的同时略带羞涩，但这种恶心的感觉让她更害怕。她对自己说，正是因为她的脸色不好——因为他知道医生和安神剂的事——他才表现出顺从于她的想法，表现出这种急于把她从道德草案中屏蔽掉的态度，但这一解释只是为新的推论扫清了道路。

这周过得很慢，很空虚，就像是一个漫长的周日。周六早上，邮差送来了范·西德伦太太的一张字条。“亲爱的茱莉亚，是否可以请你让韦斯托尔先生比平常早来半小时，因为在他的‘演讲’之后，会有些音乐表演。”他妻子读到这字条的时候，韦斯托尔正要出门去办公室。她打开客厅的门，把他叫回来告诉他这个消息。

他瞥了一眼字条，把它扔在一边。“真麻烦！我得提早结束壁球。好吧，我想这也是无可奈何的事。你能写信告诉他们没问题吗？”

茱莉亚犹豫了一会儿，她的手僵硬地放在她靠着的椅背上。

“你打算继续这些演讲？”她问。

“我……为什么不呢？”他回答。而这一次，她意识到他的惊讶显得有点儿虚伪，这种想法让她找到了接下来要说的话。

“你之前说你开始这些演讲是为了取悦我……”

“然后？”

“上周我告诉你它们并不能让我高兴。”

“上周？……噢……”他看上去在努力回忆，“我以为那时你只是太紧张了，你第二天就叫了医生。”

“我需要的不是医生，而是你的保证……”

“我的保证？”

突然之间，她感到地板在她身下崩塌了。她滑落到椅子里，喉咙哽咽，她想说的话、她的理由就像置身洪流之中的稻草一般，从她口中溜走。

“克莱门特！”她大喊道，“难道你知道我讨厌那些讲话还不够吗？”

他转身关上他们身后的门，然后走到她身边坐下。“你讨厌的是什么？”他轻声问道。

她竭尽全力重新组织语言表达自己的论点。

“我无法忍受你说得好像……好像……我们的婚姻……就像其他的婚姻一样……就像那种错误的婚姻一样。那天下午，我听到你在那里，在那些爱打听别人闲话的人面前，宣称丈夫和妻子只要感到厌倦了……或是在和其他人约会……就有权利离开彼此……”

韦斯托尔面无表情地坐在那里，他的双眼直直地盯着地毯上的一个图案。

“那就是说，你已经不认同这个观点了？”他等她停下来之后说道，“你不再认为丈夫和妻子……在这种情况下是有理由分开的？”

“在这种情况下？”她结结巴巴地说，“不是……我还是相信的……可是我们如何替其他人做决定？我们怎么知道具体的情况是什么……”

他打断了她：“我以为这是我们信条的根本条款，即婚姻所产生的特殊情况不应妨碍个人自由的充分履行。”他停了一会儿：“我还以为这是你离开阿蒙特的理由呢。”

她的脸一下子红上了额头。在争论时进行人身攻击并不太像他的作风。

“这的确是我的理由。”她简单地说。

“好吧，那么……为什么你现在不愿意承认它的有效性呢？”

“我没有……我没有不承认……我只是说没人能够替别人做判断。”

他做了一个不耐烦的动作。“这简直令人毛骨悚然。你的意思是说，你需要的时候教义为你的目的服务，现在你却拒绝接受它。”

“好吧！”她大喊，脸上又烧了起来，“如果我就是呢？那对我们来说有什么所谓？”

韦斯托尔从椅子上站了起来，脸色煞白，他站在妻子面前，就像是陌生人。

“对我来说有所谓，”他低声说，“因为我并不拒绝接受它。”

“那么……？”

“而且因为我已经打算引用……”

他停顿了一下，深深地吸了一口气。她静静地坐着，几乎被自己的心跳声给震聋了。

“……它作为我接下来行动的全部理由。”

茱莉亚依旧面无表情。“你的行动是什么？”她问道。

他清了清喉咙：“我打算让你履行你的承诺。”

刹那间，房间里晃动起来，变得一片昏暗。然后她的视力突然之间变得敏锐得让人备受煎熬。她周围的每一个细节都在朝她逼近：时钟的嘀嗒声、斜射在墙上的阳光、她抓在手中椅子扶手的硬度，这些东西刺伤着她每一种知觉。

“我的承诺……”她迟疑了一下。

“我们共同协议之中你承诺的那部分，如果其中有一方希望得到解脱，另一方就放对方自由。”

她又沉默了。他等了一会儿，紧张地变换着姿势。然后，他略带恼怒地说：“你还承认这个协议吧？”

这个问题让她大吃一惊。她骄傲地抬起头说：“我承认这个协议。”

“那么……你不打算否认它？”

壁炉中的一块圆木向前倒了下来，他机械地上前把它推回去。

“不，”她回答得很缓慢，“我不打算否认它。”

他没有立刻回话。他留在炉边，胳膊肘搁在壁炉架上。他的手旁边放着一个小翡翠杯子，那是他在他们某个结婚周年纪念日的时候送给她的。她模糊地想知道此刻他是否注意到了那个杯子。

“那么，你是打算离开我了？”她最后说。

他的手势似乎是在对这种暗示的粗鄙表示反对。

“去和其他人结婚？”

他的眼神和手又表示起抗议。她站起来，站在他面前。

“你何必害怕告诉我？是尤娜·范·西德伦吗？”

他陷入了沉默。

“我祝你好运。”她说。

第三章

她抬起头，发现自己独自一人在房间里。她不记得他是什么时候、是怎样离开房间的，也不记得在那之后自己在这里坐了多久。壁炉里的火苗还在冒着烟，但是斜着投射在墙上的阳光已经消失不见。

她第一个清醒的意识是她并没有食言，她履行了二人之间协议的每一个字。她并没有大哭小叫，没有徒劳地借助过往的回忆，没有试图拖延或者逃跑。她径直大步地走向了枪口。

既然一切都结束了，她嫌恶地发现自己还活着。她看了看四周，试图恢复自己对现实的掌控。她的身份在身体衰弱的过程中渐渐消失，似乎伴随着晕厥，已经悄然离她而去了。“这是我的房间——这是我的房子。”她听到自己喃喃自语。她的房间？她的房子？她几乎都能听到周围的墙壁在嘲笑自己。

她站了起来，浑身上下每一根骨头都感到疲惫不堪。房间里的寂静让她害怕。现在她记起来好久之前听到前门关上的声音——那声音突然之间在她脑中再次响起。她丈夫肯定是那时候离开房子的——她的丈夫？她已经不知道该用什么称呼他——最简单的词语也有恶毒的一面。她又瘫倒在椅子上，一种奇怪的脆弱之感向她袭来。时钟敲响十下——才十点！她突然意识到还没有点餐……还是说他们晚上要出去用餐？晚餐……外出用餐……那毫无意义的措辞抓着她不放！她必须要像另外一个人那样思考，她要把自己变成一个和这里过去熟悉的所有日常彻底脱离的人，必须要逐渐了解另外这个人的习惯和想法，就像一个人要窥探出奇怪的动物的生活习性……

钟表又敲响了——十一点。她再次站起来，走到门口，她想上楼回到自己的房间里去。她的房间？她又被这个词嘲笑了一次。她打开门，穿过狭窄的门厅，走上楼梯。路过时，她看到韦斯托尔的手杖和雨伞——他的一双手套摆在门厅的桌子上。一切都没有改变，两面墙之间的楼梯上铺着同样的地毯，当她走到楼梯口时，映入眼帘的还是同样的一幅法国旧版画，嵌在又黑又窄的画框里。这种视觉上接连不断的场景让她忍无可忍。她内心深处有一个巨大的裂口，而外部的一切依旧是如此平静和熟悉。她必须远离这一切，才能够尝试着思考。但是一走进自己的房间，她坐在沙发上，恍惚的感觉便开始笼罩着她……

她的视野逐渐清晰起来。在这段时间里发生了许多事情——情绪、争论和思想的激烈交锋——反叛者冲动的怒火又重新燃烧起来。起初，她试图把这些混乱的力量团结、组织起来。如果她能控制住内心的骚乱，一定有什么方法可以改善这一切。生命不能因为一时的心血来潮、一个幻想，就这样突然被中断。法律本身会支持她，会保护她。法律？她能对法律提什么要求呢？她成了自己选择的囚犯：她是自己的立法者，她是自己所制定的法典注定的受害者。但是这是荒唐可笑的，是不能容忍的——这是一个疯狂的错误，不能让她为此负责！她所蔑视的法律仍然存在，也许还能执行……执行，但目的在于什么呢？她能让法律把韦斯托尔拴在她身边吗？当她要求得到自由的时候，她被允许自由地离开——难道她不该表现得比她之前所要求的更宽宏大量吗？宽宏大量？这个词以它的讽刺鞭笞着她——当一个人在为生命而战时，是不需要装腔作势的！她会威胁、她会摇尾乞怜、她会用甜言蜜语去哄骗……为了保住幸福，她愿意放弃一切。啊，但是困难重重啊！法律帮不了她——她背弃自己的信仰也帮不了她。她是她所抛弃的理论的受害者。就好像是她被自己制造的一台巨大的机器卷进轮子里，磨成了碎片……

她发现自己出门时已是下午了。她漫无目的地匆匆走着，生怕遇见熟悉的面孔。这种日子就是最能反映真实的美国的日子：阳光明媚，金光闪闪，照出了街道上没有打扫干净的地方，暴露出我们建筑的拥挤。这些街道看上去光秃秃的，十分丑陋，所有的东西都很显眼，闪闪发光。她叫住一辆过路的马车，给出了范·西德伦太太的地址。她不知道是什么原因导致了这个行为，但她突然下定决心要说出来、要大声地警告。现在想拯救自己已经太迟了——但或许她还能提醒那个年轻女孩儿点什么。那辆双轮马车嘎吱嘎吱地驶过第五大街，她目不斜视地坐在车里，避免被认出来。到了范·西德伦家的门口，她跳下马车，按响了门铃。行动使她的头脑清醒了，她感到平静和镇定。她现在清楚地知道自己想说什么了。

两位女士都出去了……侍女站在那儿等着茱莉亚递上卡片。茱莉亚嘟囔了一声，转身离开门口，在人行道上逗留了一会儿。然后她想起她还没有给车夫付钱。她从钱包里掏出一美元递给他。他摸着帽子示了示意，然后就赶着马车走了，把她一个人留在空荡荡的长街上。她徘徊着往西边走去，走到一条陌生的大道上，在这里她不大可能遇见熟人。漫无目的的感觉又回来了。有一次在一个下午，她发现自己置身于百老汇大街的洪流中，掠过花里胡哨的商店和色彩鲜艳的戏剧海报，一连串毫无意义的面孔从她面前朝相反的方向一一消失……

一阵眩晕的感觉突然袭来，她想起自己从早上起就没吃过东西。她拐进一条满是破旧房子的小巷，被弯曲的栏杆围了起来，栏杆后面放着一排排的灰桶。在地下室的一扇窗户上她看到了“女士餐厅”的招牌：一块馅饼和一盘甜甜圈靠在满是灰尘的玻璃窗上，就像民族博物馆里的石化食品。她走了进去，一个嘴巴轮廓不明显、眼睛很大的年轻女人在窗边给她收拾出一张桌子。桌上铺着红白相间的棉布，上面摆着的装饰是一只又大又重的玻璃杯，里面放着一束芹菜，盐瓶里装满了灰白色的盐块。茱莉亚点了茶，等了好长时间都没上来。她很高兴能够远离街道上的嘈杂和混乱。天花板很低的房间里空无一人，两三个瘦削的女服务员懒洋洋地站在后面，一起盯着她窃窃私语。最后，茶水装在一个脏兮兮的金属茶壶里端了上来。茱莉亚倒了一杯匆忙喝下去。茶又黑又苦，但它就像是万灵药一样流过她的血管。她兴奋得几乎头晕目眩。啊，她实在是太累了，累得筋疲力尽！

她又喝了一杯，茶变得越来越黑、越来越苦，现在她的头脑又清醒了。她觉得就像是站在范·西德伦家的台阶上时那么精力充沛、那么果断——但她并不打算再回到那里。她现在看到了这样的企图是徒劳的——这可能使她蒙受耻辱……遗憾的是她不知道下一步该怎么办。冬季短暂的白昼即将过去，她意识到自己不能在餐馆里待太久，不然就会引起别人的注意。她付了茶钱，走到街上。路灯已经亮起来了，地下室里的一家家店铺把长方块状的煤气灯影投射在裂开的人行道上。暮色中，这条街的样子有一种不祥的感觉，她急忙向第五大街走去。她不习惯一个人在这个时候外出。

在第五大街的拐角处，她停下来，站在那里看着川流不息的马车。最后一个警察看见了她，示意要带她过马路。她本不想过马路，但不自觉地跟着过了马路，没多久就发现自己来到了更远的街角。她在那儿又停了一会儿，但是她觉得警察在看着她，这让她急匆匆地跑到最近的一条小街上去……之后她迷迷糊糊地走了好长时间……夜幕降临了，透过一辆辆驶过的马车窗户，她不时地瞥见一件巨大的晚礼服，或是一件闪闪发光的歌剧斗篷……

突然之间，她发现自己来到了一条熟悉的街道上。她静静地站了一会儿，急促地喘着气。她刚刚转过这个拐角的时候并没有注意它通向哪里，但现在，她看见前面几码远的地方是她曾经住过的房子——她第一任丈夫的房子。百叶窗都拉上了，窗户和门上方的横梁上只有一抹模糊的光线。当她站在那里时，她听到身后有一阵脚步声，一个男人朝房子的方向走了过去。他走得很慢，脚步有着中年人的沉重之感。他的脑袋稍稍缩在两肩之间，大衣的毛皮领子上露出脖子上的红色皱褶。他穿过街道，走上了房子的台阶，拿出一把钥匙，开门进去了……

眼前没有别人。茱莉亚在墙角的栏杆上靠了好久，眼睛盯着房子的前面。身体疲倦的感觉又回来了，但是浓茶仍然在她的血管里跳动着，使她的大脑格外清醒。不久之后，她听到又有脚步声走近了，她赶紧往前走，也穿过马路，跨上了房子的台阶。把她带到那儿去的那种冲动随着按下电铃后的急促声响，继续延长了一段时间——然后她突然感到虚弱和颤抖，抓住栏杆支撑着自己。门开了，一个年轻的男仆站在门槛上，他的表情看上去略微稚嫩。茱莉亚立刻知道他会让她进去的。

“我看到阿蒙特先生刚刚进去了，”她说，“你能让他见我一下吗？”

男仆犹豫了一下：“女士，我想阿蒙特先生已经上楼更衣准备用晚餐了。”

茱莉亚走进门厅。“我敢肯定他会见我的——我不会耽搁他太久。”她说。

她说这些话的时候很平静、很有权威，一个好的仆人是不会把这种语气搞错的。男仆的手伸到了客厅门上。

“女士，我会告诉他的。请问，该如何称呼您？”

茱莉亚抖了一下，她没想到这一点。“就说是一位女士吧。”她漫不经心地回答。

男仆有点儿动摇，茱莉亚还以为自己败下阵来，但就在此时，门从里面开了，约翰·阿蒙特走进了门厅。他一看见她就猛然后退，他那红润的脸吓得变成了土黄色，然后血液又重新涌了回来，让他太阳穴上的血管肿胀起来，使他厚厚的耳垂变得通红。

茱莉亚已经很久没有见过他了，她对他外貌的变化感到吃惊。他变得又肿又胖，被一大团肉包裹起来。但是这是她无意间注意到的，她唯一有意识的想法是，既然现在和他面对面地见到了，在他听完自己想说的话之前一定不能让他逃走。她身体里的每一丝血脉都因急切要讲的话而激烈地跳动着。

他往后退的时候，她朝他走去。“我有话必须对你说。”她说。

阿蒙特满脸通红、结结巴巴地犹豫起来。茱莉亚瞥了一眼仆人，她的表情像是在警告。从“现场”离开的本能压倒了其他所有的冲动，阿蒙特慢吞吞地说：“请往这边走，好吗？”

他跟着她走进客厅，关上了门。茱莉亚往前走着，模模糊糊地意识到至少房间没有任何变化：时间并没有减低它给人带来的恐怖感觉。康塔迪娜[5]的味道依旧徘徊在烟囱壁上，希腊奴隶挡住了内室的门槛。关于这地方的回忆再次鲜活起来——一开始是从黄色缎子窗帘的每一个褶裥里开始，然后游走于红木家具的夹角之间。

但是，当大脑之中某个分支正在传递这些信息的时候，她的整个意识都努力集中在支配阿蒙特的意志上。她怕他会拒绝听自己说话，这种恐惧就像高烧一样，在她脑中沸腾起来。她感到自己的计划在恐惧之前慢慢融化，在她滚烫的渴望之中，每一个词句、每一个论点在相互碰撞。她一时之间说不出话来，她想着自己可能还没来得及说话就会被推出门外。但正当她努力想找话说的时候，阿蒙特把一把椅子推到她前面，平静地说：“你不太好。”

他的声音使她镇定下来。这声音既不友好，也不冷酷——它使你大脑的判断和思考悬在那儿，等候意料不到的事态发展。她靠在椅背上，深深地吸了一口气。

“要叫他们给你准备点什么吗？”他继续说，礼貌之中带着一丝冷漠与尴尬。

茱莉亚做出了恳求的手势。“不……不需要……谢谢你。我很好。”

他本打算按铃的手停在半空，然后转向茱莉亚：“那么，我能问……？”

“是的，”她打断他，“我到这里来是因为我想见你。有些事我必须告诉你。”

阿蒙特继续打量着她。“我对此感到惊讶，”他说，“我本以为你有任何想要沟通的内容，都可以通过我们的律师。”

“我们的律师！”她突然微微笑了起来，“我不认为他们能帮得了我……这次不行。”

阿蒙特面露难色：“如果有什么需要帮忙的问题……当然……”

奇怪的是，她突然想到，以前有个衣衫褴褛的混混儿拿着认捐簿出现在他们的门口时，她曾看到过这种表情。也许他认为她为了博取他的同情——甚至是为了钱——想让他捐款……想到这里，她又笑了起来。她看到他的神色慢慢变得困惑起来。他所有的面部表情变化都是缓慢的，她突然记起，正是那种表情使她提出了离婚，从而不用再见到那种惹人烦的情景。她第一次意识到自己一直以来太残忍了。“是有需要帮助的问题，”她用比较柔和的声调说，“你只需要听我说完就是帮助我了……我想告诉你一件事……”

阿蒙特还是没有放弃抵抗。“写信……的话不是更容易？”他建议说。

她摇了摇头。“没时间写了……而且也不会太久的。”她抬起头，二人四目相对。“我的丈夫已经离开我了。”她说。

“韦斯托尔……？”他结结巴巴地说，脸色又变得通红。

“是的。今天早上。就像我离开你一样，因为他已经厌倦我了。”

这些话的音量比在耳边私语大不了多少，可又像是响亮到填满了整个房间。阿蒙特朝门口看了一眼，然后他那窘迫的目光又回到茱莉亚身上。

“我很抱歉。”他尴尬地说。

“谢谢你。”她呢喃了一句。

“但是我看不出……”

“不……但过一会儿……你就会……你就不能听我说完吗？拜托！”她本能地改变了姿势，让自己挡在他和门之间。“事情是今天早上发生的，”她气喘吁吁地接着说，“我从来没有怀疑过什么……我以为我们……非常幸福……他突然对我说他厌倦我了……他更喜欢另一个女孩儿……他去找她了……”当她说话的时候，潜伏在她心头的痛苦又一次笼罩着她，把其他所有的情绪都排除在外了。她眼睛开始疼痛，喉咙也肿了起来，两颗痛苦的眼泪从脸上流淌而下。

阿蒙特显得越来越拘谨。“这……这很不幸。”他开口，“但我想说的是法律……”

“法律？”她讽刺地回答，“当他要求得到自己的自由的时候？”

“你没有义务给他自由。”

“你也没有义务给我自由——但是你给了。”他做了一个不同意她的看法的手势。

“你明白法律帮不了你的忙——是吗？”她接着说，“这就是我现在看到的。法律代表的是物质权利——在此之外，它无能为力。如果我们不承认内在规律……不承认爱所创造的责任……爱与被爱……那就没有什么能阻止我们传播势如破竹的毁灭……不是吗？”她悲哀地抬起头来，眼神流露出孩子般的迷惑不解。“这就是我现在看到的……我想告诉你的。他离开我是因为他厌倦了……但我并没有厌倦，我不明白他为什么会感到厌倦。这就是可怕的地方——不理解，不明白这是什么意思。但我一整天都在想这件事，而我又记起了一些事——那些我没有注意到的事情……当你和我……”她走近他，用一种难以言表的目光盯着他：“我现在明白了，你当时根本不理解……是吗？”

两人的目光在恍然大悟之中相遇：二人之间的那层面纱似乎被揭开了。阿蒙特的嘴唇在颤抖着。

“不，”他回答，“我不理解。”

她轻声叫了起来，几乎是胜利的声音。“我就知道！我就知道！你不理解……你试图告诉过我……但是却什么都没说……你看到自己的生活分崩离析……你的世界离你而去……而你什么都说不出，也动不了！”

她又滑落到之前靠着的椅子里。“现在我知道了……现在我知道了。”她重复着。

“我很替你难过。”她听到阿蒙特结结巴巴地说。她很快抬起头来：“这不是我来的目的。我不想让你为我感到难过。我是来请求你原谅我的……原谅我当时并不理解你的不理解……这就是我想说的全部。”她站起身来，迷茫地觉得差不多该结束了，用手摸索着伸向门口。

阿蒙特面无表情地站在那里。她转向他，脸上带着无力的笑容。

“你原谅我了吗？”

“没什么好原谅的——”

“那你愿意和我握手告别？”虽然感觉很无力也不情愿，但她还是握到了他的手。

“再见。”她重复了一次，“我现在理解了。”

她打开门，走到门厅离去。正当她要出去的时候，阿蒙特冲动地向前迈了一步，可是就在此时，男仆明显非常尽职，从后面走了出来准备让她出去。她听到阿蒙特退了回去。男仆猛一下把门打开，然后她发现自己身处于屋外的黑暗之中。

[4]至福，指耶稣在山上垂训时所说的八种幸福。

[5]意大利风味番茄产品和面包屑品牌。

地毯上的花纹

一

我写过几篇稿子，赚过一点儿小钱，我甚至没准儿有时会动一动这样的心思：我本人要比那些居高临下之人眼里的我更为出色。不过，在略微追溯了一番我的路径（这习惯纯属无事生非，因为我走过的路并不算太长）之后，我把乔治·考威克气喘吁吁、忧心忡忡地跑来找我帮忙的那个晚上，算作我真正的起点。他写的东西比我多，赚过的小钱也比我多，不过在我看来，有时他会错过几个抖机灵的机会。不过，在那天晚上，我只能向他表示，他从来都不会错过一个做好事的机会。他请我替那份专门刊登学究文章的周刊《中点》——因其出刊时间位于每周中点而得名——备一篇稿，原先这稿约是他接的，现在他把文章的素材用一根结实的绳子扎成一捆，放在我桌上，我不禁一阵狂喜。我扑上去抓住了这个机会——抓住了那部作品的第一卷——至于我的朋友何以有此诉求，我没怎么留心他的解释。这份活儿显然适合我来接，有什么样的解释会比这一条更关键呢？以前我写过休·维里克，但是没有一个字发在《中点》上——在那里，我主要是炮制一点儿跟女士和小诗人有关的零碎。这是维里克的新小说，试读本，无论这本书对他的名声能起到多大或者多小的作用，我反正是当即明白，这事对我的名声能产生怎样的影响。非但如此，虽说我向来是一拿到他的书就要先睹为快的，但眼下我有了个特别的理由，恨不得马上读到他的作品：我收到了一份请柬，下周日去布里奇斯，简恩斯太太的便笺里提到维里克先生也会来。我正年轻，能见到像他这样有名的人物，难免激动，难免天真地相信，在这样的场合，必须好好显摆一下，我对他的“近作”是了然于胸的。

考威克本来答应给它写一篇书评，到头来却连读一遍的时间都没有，他被一则消息折腾得六神无主——一转念的工夫他便做了决定——要搭夜班邮船去巴黎。他收到一封来自格温德琳·埃尔梅的电报，回复他前一封表示想飞奔过去施以援手的信。对于格温德琳·埃尔梅，我已有所耳闻。我从未见过她，却也有点儿概念，大致说来，只要她母亲一死，考威克便能娶她。那位老太太眼下似乎颇有可能成全他：从国外回来的路上，因为在气候或者某种“疗法”上出了点糟糕的岔子，她突然病倒。她的女儿孤立无援，惊恐万状，急着赶回家，又害怕路上遇险，于是接受了朋友的帮助，而我却暗自相信，恐怕埃尔梅太太一看到他就能缓过来。至于他自己确信什么，那几乎是昭然若揭了，反正他相信的事显然跟我相信的事不一样。他给我看过格温德琳的照片，他说她算不得漂亮，但很有意思。她在十九岁那年出版了一部三卷本长篇小说——《内心深处》，他在《中点》上写过十分精彩的评论。对于我现在的跃跃欲试，他深表谢意，并且担保我们在谈论的那家杂志也会同样满怀热忱；末了，他一只手扶在门上，跟我说：“你当然没有问题，你知道。”他看出我多少有点儿迷糊，就加了一句：“我的意思是，你不会犯傻吧。”

“犯傻——对维里克！对于他，除了感叹聪明绝顶以外，我还能有什么想法？”

“呃，这不就是犯傻吗？‘聪明绝顶’到底是什么意思？看在上帝的分儿上，你得尽力懂得他。不能因为我们俩如此交接，就对他不利。请按照我谈论他的方式谈论他，如果你能做到的话。”

我踌躇片刻。“你的意思是，他在这些人里绝对是老大——诸如此类？”

考威克几乎在哀号了。“哦，你知道，我一般不会这样给他们排座次的，在艺术的婴儿期才会来这套！可他给我如此罕有的愉悦，那感觉——”他沉吟片刻——“有某种东西。”

我又困惑起来。“那感觉，请问，是什么？”

“我亲爱的朋友，这就是我想让你说的呀！”

甚至在他砰的一声关上门之前，我已经拿起那本书，准备把那种感觉说出来了。我读着维里克的书熬到半夜，考威克也不可能有我这么上心。维里克聪明绝顶——我坚持这一点，不过他在这些人里怎么也不能算是老大。不过，我在文章里并没有提及这些人。我颇为自得，觉得这一回应该是摆脱了艺术的婴儿期。“不错，”他们在办公室里热烈宣告，当那一期出版时，我觉得我有了与那位大人物会面的资本。这事给了我一两天的信心——紧接着信心又坠落。我想象过他津津有味地读我的文章的画面，但是，如果考威克都不满意，那维里克本人又怎么会满意呢？我真的琢磨过，有时候，爱慕者的热情甚至比写作者的胃口还要显而易见。无论如何，考威克从巴黎写来了一封郁郁寡欢的信：埃尔梅太太缓过来了，而我根本就没有说出维里克给了他怎样的感觉。

二

布里奇斯之行让我洞察更深。就我当场亲眼所见，休·维里克委实教人无从揣摩，以至于我不禁为自己事先对此缺乏思想准备而汗颜。即便他看来情绪不错，也并不是因为他读过我那篇文章；事实上，我相信在那个周日上午，他根本就没读过——尽管《中点》已经在三天前出街，并且，我确信它就在某张镀金桌子上的那个傲气而挺括的期刊花园中怒放，这张堆满期刊的桌子看起来有点儿像是车站里的杂志摊。他给我留下的印象就是如此，所以我很想让他读一读。为了达到这个目的，我的手鬼鬼祟祟地给杂志原先或许不够理想的位置做了点儿修正，挪到既引人注目，又不显得太刻意的地方。实话说，我甚至还观察了一下我的这番动作有没有什么效果，然而直到午餐时分，看来还是白忙了一场。

此后，在我们一群人闲庭信步之际，我有半个小时都跟在这位大人物身边——或许多少也是用了点儿花招的，他的和蔼可亲让我越发蠢蠢欲动，我对他做出了如此特殊而恰当的评论，真不希望他对此一无所知。而他似乎并不渴望什么恰当的评论；相反，在他的话语中，我捕捉不到一丁点儿愤愤不平的怨言——反正凭着我涉世不深的阅历，没有一点儿能让我听出端倪的信号。最近对他的赞誉越来越多，正如我们在《中点》中指出的那样，看到这些好评令他脱颖而出，真是一桩快意之事。他当然不算流行，但我断定，他之所以总是和颜悦色，原因之一恰恰是他的成功并不取决于作品是否流行。从某种角度看，他也算领风气之先，至少评论界骤然加速，奋力赶上他的步伐。我们终于发现他是多么聪明，而他就此失去了神秘感，只能随遇而安。我在他身边漫步，恨不得告诉他，世人揭开了他神秘的面纱，而我在其中起了多少作用；有那么一瞬间，要不是同行的某位女士在他另一侧的手肘边抢到个位置，以某种较为自私的劲头向他倾诉，我也许已经把这事儿做成了。真叫人沮丧：我几乎觉得她这是故意跟我本人作对了。

就我本人而言，确乎有一两句话掠过舌尖，关于在适当的时间用适当的词语之类，不过，事后想起，我庆幸这话没有讲出口，因为当我们回到屋里，聚在一起喝茶时，我发现刚刚没跟我们一起出门的简太太[1]正伸长胳膊挥舞着《中点》杂志。她刚才闲来无事，随手拿起来，发现了那一篇，顿时兴高采烈。我看得出来，某些男人做了便是错的事情，若是换到女人身上，常常倒是一件值得庆幸的事。实际上，她是把我自己没能办到的事给做成了。“这里有几条小小的、甜美的真理，值得一说，”我听到她如此宣称，并把杂志塞给壁炉边一对神情茫然的夫妻。休·维里克跟我们一起散完步之后，上楼去换了衣服，他刚刚再度露面，简太太就把杂志从那对夫妻手里抢了回来。“我知道你向来是不看这类玩意儿的，不过这回你确实需要看看。你还没看过？那你一定得看。此人确实懂你，抓住了我一向的感觉，你知道的。”简太太眼波流转，那眼神确乎想把她一向的感觉传递出来，可她还是加了一句，说她终究难以表达。而杂志上的那个人用某种震撼人心的方式表达了出来。“就看看这里，还有那里，我画过的地方，看看他是怎么把那感觉提炼出来的。”她果真把我文章里最亮眼的部分标出来给他看。如果说，当时我多多少少被她逗乐的话，那么维里克本人就完全可能被她逗得乐不可支。当着我们所有人的面，简太太想要大声读几句，维里克顿时就表现出他有多么忍俊不禁。他和和气气地从她手里抽走了那本杂志，就此打消了她的念头——无论如何，我喜欢他用这一招。等他换礼服时，他会把杂志带上楼，顺便看一看。半小时之后，他果然这么做了——当他回自己房间的时候，我看到杂志就拿在他手里。就在那一刻，为了让简太太开心，我跟她提起，我就是这篇书评的作者。我断定，我确实让她开了心，但是，也许，不像我原先期盼的那么开心。既然这位作者“只不过是我而已”，那么事情就显得没什么了不起了。这么一来，我岂不是非但没有替自己增光添彩，反而使这篇文章为之失色吗？这位太太反正向来是一惊一乍的。这不要紧，我唯一在意的是，维里克此刻待在卧室的炉火边，那文章会让他作何感想。

晚餐席间，我一直留心着蛛丝马迹，试图想象他的眼睛里闪烁着更为愉悦的光彩。然而，让我失望的是，简太太并没有给我一点儿可以证实的机会。我本指望她会得意扬扬地在餐桌上大呼小叫，当众问他，她有没有说错。宴会的场子很大——还有一些从外面来的人，不过，我以前还从来没有见过有哪张餐桌长到连简太太都招呼不过来的地步。正当我在认真寻思，这回碰到了一张长得仿佛无穷无尽的桌子，恐怕是要剥夺我的机会了，坐在我边上的客人，一位亲爱的女士——她是教区牧师的妹妹博伊尔小姐，健壮而刚硬——灵光一闪，拿出非凡的勇气向维里克发问，后者坐在她对面，但不是正对面，所以他回答的时候，两个人的身体都只能向前靠。她不事矫揉，直接打听他对简太太的“歌颂”作何感想，文章她已经读过了——只是没有把文章跟坐在她右侧的客人联系在一起。我竖起耳朵听他的回话，他嘴里塞满面包，轻快地接口，答案让我呆若木鸡：“哦，过得去吧——反正就是那套胡说八道呗。”

维里克说话的当口，我们四目相对，好在博伊尔小姐的大惊失色掩饰了我的惊讶。“你是说，他的说法并不公正？”这位了不起的女士说。

维里克笑出了声，我很高兴我居然也能跟着一起笑。“这文章很迷人。”他回答我们。

博伊尔小姐的下巴往前伸，横跨了半张桌布的宽度。“哦，你可真够深邃的！”她穷追不舍。

“像海一样深！我想宣告的是，这位作者看不出——”恰在此时，一盘菜从他肩上传过来，我们只能等他拿好自己的那份菜再说。

“看不出什么？”我的邻座继续追问。“什么都看不出。”

“天哪——真蠢啊！”

“一点儿都不，”维里克又笑起来。“没人能看到。”

有位离他较远的女士跟他搭讪，博伊尔小姐便又坐回原位，跟我说话。“没人看得出一点儿东西！”她兴高采烈地宣布，对此，我只能回答说虽然我过去也常常这么想，但是，无论如何，现在我反而用这种想法来证明自己具有某种惊人的眼力。我没有告诉她这篇文章是我写的，我还看到简太太在桌子的另一头忙忙碌碌，没有听到维里克刚才说了什么。

饭后我处处避开他，因为我得承认，他在我眼里显得既残忍又自负，他流露的真实想法也让我痛苦。“那套胡说八道”——那可是我敏锐而精巧的研究成果！对他钦佩之余，难免略有保留，就因为如此，他心里便怨恨到这种地步吗？我原以为他为人沉着，而他也确实足够沉着，表面如同坚硬的抛光玻璃盒子，里面装着精致而无用的虚荣心。我着实气恼，唯一聊以安慰的是，既然没人能看出什么来，那乔治·考威克也跟我一样被关在了门外。不过，在女士们散去之后，这点安慰并不足以让我以得体的仪态——我是说，穿着一件斑点外套，哼着小曲——走进吸烟室去。我多少有点儿沮丧地走向卧室，却在过道上又撞上维里克先生，他刚刚又上楼换了衣服，此刻正从自己的房间里出来。他正哼着小曲，身穿一件斑点外套，看到我那瞬间悚然一惊，猛地收住了那股子得意劲儿。

“我亲爱的年轻人，”他嚷起来，“能找到你真是太好了！刚刚晚餐时跟博伊尔小姐的一番话，怕是伤到了你，这实在不是我的本意啊。仅仅半小时之前，我才听简太太说起你便是《中点》上那篇小小的评论的作者。”

我并不同意，说这事也伤不到我的骨头，可他一路跟我到门口，手按在我肩膀上，好心好意地想摸摸我有没有骨折。他听说我上楼来是想就寝的，便恳求我允许他跨进门来跟我聊几句，说说他先前对我的文章作如是评价，究竟是什么意思。显然，他确实怕我受到伤害，而我一旦体察到他的担忧，一切在我眼里似乎突然就有所不同了。我那廉价的评论顿时飞入虚空，即便是我那文章里的精华，在他本人的光环辉映之下，也显得平淡无奇。他当时的形象此刻依然历历在目，他就站在我房间里的小地毯上，在壁炉火光的映照下，他那件斑点外套，精致而清朗的脸庞，都熠熠生辉，闪烁着某种急欲对年轻人表达善意的渴望。我不知道他起初想说什么，但是我估计，看到我为之释然的样子，他颇受触动，进而兴奋起来，将心底深处的言语调动到唇边。就这样，他很快就跟我说了那些话，事后我才得知，这话里包含了以前他从没跟任何人说过的意思。对于他这番慷慨的冲动，我一向有公允的看法：那纯粹是出于后悔，因为他无意中怠慢了一个地位比他低微的文人，而且还是一个正对他褒奖有加的文人。为了有所弥补，他才会与我平等对话，并且出于我们同样最为珍视的理由。时间也好，地点也好，那份意料之外也好，都加深了这样的印象：没有比他这一招更有效的办法了。

三

“我不太懂得怎么跟你解释，”他说，“正是因为你给我写的书评颇有点儿智慧，正是因为你那非同俗流的敏锐，才会激发那种感觉——对我而言，这也有一段长久的渊源，请你相信我——出于一时冲动，我跟那位好太太说了那样的话，你听来自然不入耳。报纸杂志我是向来不看的，除非有人塞给我，这一篇便是如此——塞给我看的总是最好的朋友！不过我以前有时候也会看看——十年前吧。我敢说，一般而言，那时的文章要蠢得多。无论如何，在我看来，那些文章都完美地错过了我小小的主旨，不过，无论是轻拍我的背还是给我的小腿踢上一脚，都是同样值得赞赏的。无论何时，我若是碰巧朝它们瞥上一眼，它们总是照样光彩夺目——我是说，照样美妙绝伦地抓不住要点。你没抓住，我亲爱的朋友，虽然你的自信无与伦比。你聪明绝顶，你的文章也十分好看，但这些却没有让事实发生一丁点儿变化。恰恰是因为跟你们这些冉冉上升的年轻人在一起，”维里克笑道，“我才最深切地感到自己有多么失败！”

我怀着热切的兴趣听他讲，他说得越多，我的兴趣越是浓厚。“你失败——天哪！那么你所谓的‘小小主旨’，到底是什么呢？”

“在经过多年劳碌之后，我难道非得把这一点告诉你不成？”这句亲切的嗔怪——诙谐而夸张——蕴含着某种意味，使得我这个一向狂热追求真理的年轻人脸涨得通红，一直红到头发根。如今我跟以前一样懵然无知，不过，在某种程度上，我已经对自己的愚钝习以为常了。然而，在那一刻，维里克那欢乐的语调却让我在自己眼里，或许也在他眼里，成了个罕有的大傻瓜。那一刻，我正准备嚷起来：“啊，对啊，别告诉我——为了我的面子，为了我们这一行的面子，不要说！”而他却径自往下说，他的举止神态表明，他已经看穿了我的心思，至于我们是否终有一天能把面子找补回来，他自有看法。“说到我那小小的主旨，我的意思是——我该怎么说呢？——就是那个特别的原因，我之所以要写书，主要就是为了这个。每一个作家不是都有这样特别的原因吗？那个让他全神贯注的东西，若不是要努力达成这个目标，他根本就不会去写作，那是他真正的激情，对他而言，唯有在这部分，艺术的火焰才燃烧得最为激烈。对，就是这样！”

我思忖片刻——也就是说，我跟着他，保持着一段恭敬的距离，几乎上气不接下气。我给迷住了——你可以说轻而易举，不过，无论如何，我可不打算丢盔弃甲。“你的描述当然很美，可你描述的东西却并未因此变得清晰可见。”

“我向你保证，你一旦恍然大悟，它就会清晰可见。”我发现，我们这个话题充满魅力，在我同伴身上也激起了与我一样强烈的情感。“无论如何，”他继续说，“我能代表自己说话：在我的作品中，总有那么一个观念，要是没有它，我对整个工作都不会有一丁点儿兴趣。它是作品最好、最完整的内涵，它能在作品中得以贯彻，我认为，这胜利应该归功于持久的耐心和巧妙的设计。这话我应该留给别人说；可是偏偏没人能把我们正在聊的话题准确地说出来。我那点小小的花招，从一本书延伸到另一本，至于其他种种，相对而言不过浮于表象而已。我那些书，叙述的顺序也好，形式也好，结构也好，或许总有一天会让内行的人看出门道，发现将它们合在一起，就能完整地体现作品的内涵。所以它自然是评论家们应该去寻觅的东西。我突然觉得，”我的客人微笑着补了一句，“它甚至应该是评论家们必须找到的东西。”

这似乎确实成了一种责任。“你管它叫‘小花招’？”

“这只是我的谦辞而已。究其实质，这是一个精巧的体系。”

“你相信你已经把这种体系建构出来了？”

“我建构这种体系的方式，便是我平生聊以自慰之事。”

我踌躇片刻。“难道你不觉得自己应该——稍稍——向评论家施以援手吗？”

“施以援手？我的每一笔每一画，不都是在施以援手吗？我对着他茫然的面孔，大声吼叫着我的意图。”说到这里，维里克又笑出了声，一只手搭在我肩膀上，表明他的话并不是冲着我个人的面相。

“可你说到了内行。既然如此，那要成为内行，总得有个先入门的过程吧。”

“天啊，除此之外，所谓的批评还能是什么呢？”这话恐怕又让我脸红了，可是我也找到了抵挡的办法：我不断重申，就一个普通人的认知而言，他对于那“一线真谛”的描述未免太过粗疏，难以理解。“那是因为你从来就没窥见一二，”他回敬我，“但凡你看到一眼我们正在谈及的要素，它马上就会实实在在地占据你整个视野。对我而言，它就像这个壁炉上的大理石一样清晰实在。更何况，评论家可不是什么普通人：如果他是的话，那么请问，他跑到邻居的花园里忙活什么呢？你本人就绝不是一个普通人，你们所有人‘存在的理由’[2]是——

你们都是抓得住精妙奥义的小精灵。如果说我的头等大事是一个秘密，那也只是因为它本身就是个秘密——这项令人惊叹的事业将它塑造成了一个秘密。我不仅从未采取过一丁点儿预警措施来保守这个秘密，而且做梦都没想过会出现这样的出人意料的局面。但凡我有所预料，我就没有心思再继续下去了。事实上，我自己也是在完成作品的同时，才渐渐明白过来的。”

“现在你很喜欢它？”我斗胆问道。

“我的作品？”

“你的秘密。一回事。”

“你既如此猜测，”维里克答道，“就证明你和我一样聪明！”在这话的鼓励下，我说他显然已经与那个秘密难舍难分了，而他也承认，如今这确实成了他生活中的一大乐趣。“我活着，几乎就是为了看看它到底会不会被人发现。”他看着我，仿佛在发起一项半开玩笑的挑战，他眼睛深处似乎有什么东西在向外窥视。“不过我也无须担忧——没人发现得了。”

“你把我整个人都点燃了，以前我可从未这样过，”我宣称，“你让我下定决心，做不到，毋宁死。”紧接着我又问：“这是什么圈内人士的机密吗？”

这话让他面色一沉——他伸出一只手仿佛要道晚安。“啊，亲爱的朋友，这事儿可不是用廉价的新闻语言就能描述清楚的。”

我当然知道他喜欢吹毛求疵，可是我们这番话聊下来，我也能感觉到他多少暴露了一些心事。我心有不甘——紧紧抓住他的手。“那我就不用这种说法好了，”我说，“最终我会在文章里宣告我的发现，不过，我敢说，如果不用这个词儿，那我还得下好多苦功夫。话说回来，为了让我快点度过这场‘难产’，你就不能给朋友一点儿线索吗？”此时我觉得自己放松多了。

“我为整个作品付出的努力清晰可见，给过线索啦——每一页，每一行，每个字母。那玩意儿就像笼中的小鸟、钩上的鱼饵、鼠夹上的奶酪一般具体。它塞在每一卷里，正如你的脚塞进你的鞋。它统治着每一行，它挑选了每个词，它给每一个字母i画上那个点，它给每一个逗号找到合适的位置。”

我挠挠头。“这种东西究竟存在于文体中，还是观念中？是一种形式的要素，还是情感的要素？”

他再度宽宏大量地握了握我的手，我顿时觉得刚才的问题粗糙浅陋，我对概念的区分显得可怜巴巴。“晚安，亲爱的孩子——别操心这事了。不管怎么说，你确实很像一个研究员。”

“是不是有一点儿小聪明反而会把这事儿搞砸？”我还是不肯放过他。

他犹豫了一下。“呃，你的身体里有一颗心脏。心脏是一种形式的要素呢，还是情感的要素？我的主张是，在我的作品中，迄今还没人提到的东西就像是生命的器官。”

“我明白——这是关于生命的观念，某种哲学。除非，”我热切地接着往下说，一个也许更让人快乐的想法冒出来，“某种你在文体中设计的游戏，某些你在语言中追求的东西。也许是对字母p的使用偏好！”我说着说着便信口开河起来。“papa（爸爸），potatoes（土豆），prunes（西梅）——诸如此类？”他得体地由着我胡说，只是表示我没有选对字母。不过他已经不觉得这事有什么意思了，我能看出他渐生倦意。然而，还有一句话我非得追问一下。“你能不能，执笔在手，亲自把它清清楚楚地写下来——给它命名，为它修辞，将它条分缕析？”

“哦，”他近乎热烈地叹了口气，“如果我是你们这些‘执笔在手’的家伙，就好了！”

“毫无疑问，这对你会是个很好的机会。可是，为什么，就因为我们这些家伙没做你自己也做不到的事，你就要鄙视我们呢？”

“做不到？”他瞪大了眼睛。“在这二十卷作品里，难道我没有把这事做到吗？我用我的方式做到了，”他继续说，“走你的吧，别用你那套方式。”

“我们的方式真是无比艰辛呢。”我有气无力地说。

“我的方式也一样！我们各选各的路。谁也不用强迫谁。你不想下楼抽根烟吗？”

“算了。我想把这事琢磨透。”

“那么明天早上你就要揭穿我，让我‘一丝不挂’了？”

“且看我能做点什么吧，我睡觉的时候也要琢磨琢磨。不过还有一句话，”我继续说，此时我们已经离开了房间——我又跟着他沿着走廊走了几步，“这不同凡响的‘整体意图’，我是按照你的说法——这是我能引诱你对此做出的最生动的描述——也就是说，总体上看，它是一种被掩埋的珍宝？”

他脸上闪着光。“好吧，就这么说吧，尽管这话也许不应该我来说。”

“胡说！”我笑起来，“你明明对此深感自豪。”

“呃，我本不想告诉你，不过这份喜乐确实发自我的灵魂！”

“你是说，它是稀世绝美之物？”

他再次犹豫了一会儿。“全世界最美妙的东西！”我们打住了，他扔下这些言辞，便离我而去，然而，我的目光仍然热切地追着他来到走廊的尽头，于是他转过头，一眼看见我困惑的脸庞。见状，他热诚地，其实在我看来是近乎不安地摇摇头，挥挥手指。“放弃吧——放弃吧！”

这并不是挑战——这是满含父爱的忠告。假如我手头有他的某本书，我就会把近来满怀信仰、忙忙碌碌的过程再重复一遍——我会彻夜研读他的作品。凌晨三点，我还是睡不着，进而想起，他对简太太而言是如何不可或缺，于是我拿起一支蜡烛，偷偷下楼。却发现整栋房子里看不到一行他的作品，反正我找不到。

四

回到城里，我狂热地把他的书都收齐了；我按着顺序把每本都单独挑出来，挑灯夜读。如此这般，我度过了发疯般的一个月，有几件事在这段时间里接连发生。其中之一，也就是最后发生的那件，我不妨先提一提，就是我听从了维里克的忠告：我扔掉了我那荒唐的企图。此事我确实无能为力，事实证明这样做满盘皆输。不管怎么说，正如他自己察觉的那样，我一向都是喜欢他的，眼下的情形，只不过是我那乍现的灵光和徒劳的心血损害了我的一腔热爱而已。我非但没能一鼓作气，挖出整体意图，而且还发现，就连以前那些能让我乐在其中的次要内涵，都消踪匿影。他的书甚至不再像以前那样让我入迷，这一番寻寻觅觅令我愤懑不已，以至于我没法对它们再抱有什么好感。没有新添什么乐趣，反而减少了种种快意。因为自从我没法参透作者的暗示之后，我当然就认定，原先我以职业的眼光来感知这些作品，如今为了维护体面，这一套是再也不能拿出来说事了。我一无所知——人人都一无所知。真丢人，不过我能忍——现在最多是让我有点儿气恼而已。到头来这事甚至令我厌倦，于是我把我的困惑归咎于——我得承认这想法有悖情理——维里克耍了我。被掩埋的珍宝只是个恶作剧，所谓的整体意图是荒诞不经的装腔作势。

不过，在此期间，最重要的一件事是我把自己的这番遭遇告诉了乔治·考威克，这个消息让他颇为震撼。他终于回来了，可不幸的是埃尔梅太太也回来了，因此，在我看来，他的婚礼尚属空中楼阁。我在布里奇斯经历的逸事让他激动不已。这种说法与他的感觉完全吻合，从一开始他就认为，维里克的作品里含有某种用眼睛无法看透的东西。我说，把书印出来，就是特意为了让你用眼睛看的，他立马就指责我因为深感挫败而心怀不满。我们俩的交往，历来就是这么愉快而自由的。维里克跟我提到的那一点，恰恰就是他考威克想让我在书评里表达的东西。我提议说，既然如今我已经提供了帮助，他一定准备自己来畅所欲言了吧，而他坦白承认，他还得有更深入的理解，才能着手做这件事。当初要是他来给这部新作写评论，他会说，在这位作家的叙事艺术的最深层面，显然还有某些特质有待解读。我连这样的暗示都没有，难怪作家并不觉得受到了褒奖！我问考威克，关于作家所说的他那精美微妙的奥义，他究竟作何感想，考威克的回答无疑是激情满怀的：“这可不是说给俗人听的——这可不是说给俗人听的！”他已经抓住了什么东西的尾巴，他会努力拽，把它整个拽出来。他不放过维里克与我的这番奇怪的密谈的所有细枝末节，把我说成是最走运的那种人，同时又列举了半打问题，说真希望我当时能机灵一点儿，能把这些问题提出来。然而，在另一方面，他又不想知道太多——那会破坏静观其变的乐趣。当我们俩见面时，我的乐趣尚未丧失殆尽，但彼时我已经能预见那结果，而考威克也看出我已窥见端倪。至于我，同样也看出他马上要干的一件事，就是冲出门去，把这个故事讲给格温德琳听。

在我跟考威克谈话之后的第二天，我惊讶地收到一张来自休·维里克的便条，他说起在一本杂志上偶然看到一篇我署名的文章，不由得想起我们在布里奇斯的会面。“我兴致勃勃地读完，”他写道，“由此回忆起我们在你卧室壁炉边的愉快的对话。进而，我开始琢磨自己有多么冒失，非要把可能会对你造成负担的知识压在你身上。如今冲动已过，我简直无法想象当初何以如此激动，居然一反常态。以前，无论把话题扩展到怎样的程度，我都从来没有提过我那个小秘密，而且以后我也永远不会再说起这个奥秘了。偶然间，我对你直言相告，那份坦率远远超过以前此事进入我的游戏时所达到的程度，以至于我发觉这个游戏——我是说玩游戏时享受的乐趣——因此而蒙受巨大的损失。简而言之，如果你能听懂的话，我把我的娱乐活动搞砸了。我真的不想透露给任何人，我相信你们这些聪明的年轻人管那个叫‘要诀’。这当然是一种自私的焦虑，我告诉你这一点，也许这说法对你有点价值。如果你乐意迁就我，就不要把我透露的事情再说给别人听。就当我精神错乱好了——这是你的权利；但是不要把个中缘由告诉任何人。”

这番交流还有下文，次日一早我就斗胆驱车直奔维里克家门。那些年他住在肯辛顿广场的一栋朴实的老房子里。他马上接待了我，我一进门就发现，我并未丧失逗他开心的能力。他一看见我的面孔就笑起来，因为我脸上的表情无疑显得颇为不安。我太轻率了——我后悔不已。“我已经告诉别人了，”我喘着粗气说，“而且我断定，那人已经转告他人！更何况，那是个女人。”

“就是你告诉的那位？”

“不是，另一位。我相信，他肯定已经告诉了她。”

“这对她能有什么好处——对我也一样！女人永远也弄不懂这些的。”

“没错，可是她会走到哪儿说到哪儿：她要做的，就是你不愿意它发生的事情。”

维里克思忖片刻，不过并没像我担心的那样惊慌失措，在他看来，既然伤害已经造成，那就是他应得的。“没关系——别担心。”

“我会尽力，我向你保证，不让我们俩谈的事情再扩散出去。”

“很好，你尽力就好。”

“同时，”我继续说，“乔治·考威克得到了这个要诀，就他而言，倒是真有可能会有所收获的。”

“那可就是个大日子了。”

我跟他说起考威克有多么聪明，对维里克是多么欣赏，对我这件逸事又是抱有怎样浓厚的兴趣。我并未渲染我们各自的判断有多大分歧，只是提到我的朋友已经认定，在某些特定的事情上他要比大多数人都看得深远。他就和我在布里奇斯时一样热血沸腾。而且他正在跟那位年轻女士相爱，也许这两位凑到一起，能把某些疑问解开。

维里克似乎为之一动。“你是说他们快要结婚了吗？”

“我敢说迟早会有这一天。”

“那可能对他们有点好处，”他只好承认，“不过我们得给他们一点儿时间！”

我说到我又狠下了一番功夫，也承认处处碰壁，于是他又翻出以前的忠告念叨起来：“放弃吧，放弃吧！”他显然认为我在心智上并不具备从事这番冒险的条件。我待了半小时，他生性善良，可我不得不说他的情绪很不稳定。他曾一时兴起便畅所欲言，也曾一时低落便懊悔不已，如今又换了一种情绪，开始变得无动于衷。如此反复无常，使得我越发相信，关于那个“要诀”的事，其中并无太多玄机。但我还是想法让他回答了几个问题，尽管他显然很不耐烦。在他本人看来，毫无疑问，那个让我们不胜迷惘的东西，明明是清晰可见的。那玩意儿，我猜想，就藏在最初的规划中；宛若波斯地毯上的一个复杂的纹样[3]。当我使用这个意象时，他表示高度赞赏，而他自己则用了另一种说法。“它就是那根线，”他说，“把我的珍珠穿起来的那根！”他之所以要给我写那张便条，是因为他真的不想给我们一丁点儿帮助——我们之间的这种相处方式完美到无从触及。他早已养成习惯，心安理得地听天由命，所以如果要破解这魔咒，那只能靠它自身的某种力量，不攻自破。如今，他在这最后一次会面时的样子仍历历在目——因为此后我再也没跟他说过话——他就是那种独步游戏禁地、确信安全无虞之人。我移步走开，心里不禁纳闷，他自己又是从哪里搞来“要诀”的呢？

五

当我跟乔治·考威克说起维里克给我的告诫时，他的反应让我觉得，只要对他审慎应对的能力稍有怀疑，就几乎对他是一种侮辱了。他当时确实马上转告了格温德琳，格温德琳回应热烈，这种态度本身就能保证她必会谨言慎行。如今他们俩的所有心思都用来研究这个问题，这种消遣方式何其珍贵，他们根本不舍得与众人分享。他们似乎本能地抓住了维里克关于娱乐性的高见。不过，尽管他们在智力上颇为自负，但我在此事上可能提供的进一步线索毕竟唾手可得，他们还不至于骄傲到对此漠不关心。他们确实具有“艺术气质”，而我的这位同人一碰到艺术问题便能让自己如此兴奋，这一点也给我带来新鲜的震撼。他时而称之为文学，时而称之为生活，归根结底都是一回事。从他的话里，我现在似有所悟，他同时也要代表格温德琳讲话。话说埃尔梅太太的境况一有好转，好歹给了女儿一点儿空闲，他便特地安排，把我介绍给她。我记得，在八月里的某个周日，我们相聚在切尔西区的一座拥挤的房子里，我不禁再次嫉妒起考威克能有这么一位心气相通的朋友。那些我永远不会跟他说的话，他却是可以跟她说的。其实她这人毫无幽默感，她把脑袋歪向一边的样子很好看，她是那种你想——那个词儿怎么说的——就是你想要“搅乱”的人，这种人靠自学就能掌握匈牙利语。她没准儿跟考威克就是用匈牙利语来交谈的；她跟他的朋友说话，极少用英文，这一点让人印象深刻。考威克后来告诉我，我显然并不乐意把维里克跟我说的话一五一十都讲出来，这让她颇为不悦。我承认，我觉得我已经对那番指示有过深思熟虑：难道我没有判定，这全是白费工夫，必将找不到出路吗？他们对这些话如此重视，让我好生气恼，弄得我的怀疑好像成了什么有毒的东西。

这说法看起来不太友善，也可能因为我看见一个只能带给我懊恼的实验却让别人深深着迷，便觉得受到了侮辱。我被排除在外，周围寒气逼人，而他们却置身于傍晚的壁炉边、灯光下，忙于追踪捕猎，可那号角明明是我吹响的。他们做的事情跟我一样，只是更刻意更善解人意——他们从头开始，把作者细细研读。这事急不得——考威克说——未来就在他们眼前，作品的魅力只会越来越大。他们会一页一页地读他，就像读一部经典名著，将他慢慢吸入肺腑，让他整个沉淀下去。若非深陷爱河，我想，他们是不太可能像上足了发条这般亢奋的：可怜的维里克的内涵给了他们无穷无尽的机会，好把他们年轻的脑袋凑在一起。然而，它代表了考威克特别乐于钻研的那类问题，勾引出他那种特殊的、富于洞察力的耐心，如果他活下去，就会给出更震撼人心、想必也更富有成效的例子。用维里克的话说，他至少是那种“抓得住精妙奥义的小精灵”。我们始于争论，但我很快就看出，若非我稍稍出手相助，他这番昏头昏脑的热情必会饱受挫折。他会像我一样，闻到误导的气味就跳起来——看到新的光便拍手称快，然后眼看着翻飞的书页掀起一阵风，将烛火吹灭。我告诉他，维里克平平无奇，只是个疯子，怀抱着某种癫狂的理论，认定莎士比亚的内涵晦涩神秘。对此，他答道，如果我们听到莎士比亚本人说自己晦涩神秘，那他会马上接受这种说法。至于现在这件事，情况完全不同——我们别无凭据，只有“不屑一顾先生”的话。我马上反驳，说看到他连维里克先生的话都如此重视，真是目瞪口呆。于是，他说他想知道我是不是把维里克先生的话当成了谎言。我当时郁郁不乐、心灰意懒，其实本来并不打算说得这么过头，可还是坚持说，在相反的情况得到证实之前，我会将它视为过于深情的想象。我得承认，我并没有说出——当时我还不太知道——我的所有感想。在内心深处，用埃尔梅小姐的说法，我是颇为不安的，也是抱着某种期望的。在我仓皇失措的状态的核心——因为我那出于习惯的好奇心在灰烬中生生不息——是一种尖锐的直觉，觉得考威克也许终究会从哪里突围而出。他为了替自己的轻信辩护，反复强调：从很久以前开始，他在研究这位天才时，就捕捉到些许不知就里的气味和线索，微弱的音符似有若无地飘过。这正是难得之处、迷人之处：它是如此完美地契合我所报告的内容。

尽管有几次我回到切尔西的那座小房子，但我敢说，我去的两个目的是同等重要的，既打听埃尔梅小姐的母亲的病情，也想知道关于维里克有什么进展。在我的想象中，考威克就像一位棋手，眉头紧锁，一言不发，在需要灯光照明的整个冬天里，低下头盯着棋盘，运筹帷幄。我的想象逐渐填满整个画面，挥之不去。一个如幽灵般的身影出现在桌对面，淡淡的轮廓勾勒出一位生性和蔼、胸有成竹却也略显疲态的对手——他靠在椅子上，双手插在口袋里，俊朗优雅的脸上挂着笑容。紧跟在考威克身后的是个姑娘，起初她看起来苍白而消瘦，多看几眼以后渐渐觉得她颇为秀美，她靠在他肩上，紧盯着他的一招一式。他抓起一颗棋子，攥在手里，在棋盘的某个小方格上方盘旋了一会儿，然后失望地长叹一声，又把棋子放回原位。见状，那位年轻女士不安地稍稍变换姿势，以某种拼尽全力且相当诡异的方式久久凝视对面那位轮廓模糊的对手。早在此事刚刚开始时，我就问过他们，若是能跟维里克亲密接触，会不会有助于他们大功告成。鉴于情况如此特殊，我当然有理由把他们介绍给维里克。考威克立即回答，在他准备好祭品之前，实在无意靠近祭坛。他完全同意我们的朋友的说法，追猎既是出于乐趣，也是为了荣誉——他要用自己的来复枪，把野兽撂倒。我问他，埃尔梅小姐是否也热衷射击之道，他思忖片刻之后说：“不是，我真是羞于启齿，她其实想铺设陷阱。若能见他一面，她什么都愿意；她说她想再讨一条线索来。对于此事，她实在有些病态了。可是她得恪守规则——她不能见他！”他加重语气补了一句。我猜想他们是不是在这个问题上吵过几句——这种疑虑并没有被他打消，因为他只是一再对我嚷：“她对文学的热情高得难以置信，你知道——真是异想天开！”我想起他说过她以斜体感知，用大写思索。“哦，待我将他的谜底揭开之时，”他还说，“你知道，我就会去敲他的门。我宁愿如此——请你相信我。我要听他亲口说出来：‘你是对的，我的孩子，这回你做到了！’他将给我这位胜者加冕——戴上批评界的桂冠。”

与此同时，既然在伦敦生活，就难免有不少与这位杰出小说家不期而遇的机会，他确实躲开了好几个。不过，随着维里克无限期离开英国——据报上说是去南方，原因与他太太的健康有关，她已经因病退隐很长一段时间了——这个危险也消失了。布里奇斯的会面之后，已经过去了一年——还不止一年，可我再也没有见过他。我想，内心深处，我是深感羞愧的——我不愿意让他想起，尽管我无可救药地错过了他的要旨，但“思维敏锐”的名声还是很快压得我不胜负荷。这一层顾虑给我惹来不少麻烦，弄得我不敢踏进简太太的房子，甚至，当她出于好意，不顾我向来礼数不周的毛病，第二次暗示我、邀请我去她那美丽的宅院时，我也只能拒绝。有一回，我注意到她在维里克的陪同下出席一场音乐会，而且也确信他们都看到了我，可我还是溜之大吉，没跟他们狭路相逢。那一次，我走在雨中，一路上被雨水溅湿，只觉得我别无选择，即便如此，我记得我当时对自己说，这样做很难，甚至未免残忍。我非但失去了那些书，而且也失去了这个人：对我而言，书和书的作者都已经给毁了。我也知道哪种损失最让我遗憾。毕竟我爱人，还是胜于爱书。

六

在我们的朋友离开英国之后，又过了六个月，素来以文字为生的乔治·考威克签下一纸合同，打算写一部书，而为了完成这项工作，他得离开一段时间，还得踏上一段艰苦的旅程——他居然会接受，这可真让我吃惊。起因是他的姐夫当上了一份外省大报的编辑，而这份外省大报，出于某种天马行空的心血来潮，构思了把“特派专员”送到印度去的计划。特派员在如今的“大都会报刊”上渐成时尚，而前面提及的这份报纸一定是觉得，它在人们心目中留下的“乡下小弟”的印象实在是太久了。当一名记者动静不小，考威克并不善于此道，可这是他姐夫的事情，而且，当某项任务并非他所长时，反而恰恰会成为他欣然接受的理由。他打算赶超“大都会报刊”，他严阵以待，防止笔下学究气泛滥，费尽心机地糟蹋文字的品味。没人知道——那些违反原则的事儿都是他自愿的。除了报销他的生活费用之外，他还会得到一笔合适的酬劳，我发觉自己也能帮上他的忙，帮这本平平常常、有利可图的书，做出看起来还说得过去的安排——找了家平平常常、有利可图的出版社。顺理成章地，我做出了这样的推断：他明显是想赚点钱，而这跟他想与格温德琳·埃尔梅共结连理的愿望并非没有关系。我知道，她的母亲之所以反对，主要是因为他资产匮乏，也没有什么能赚大钱的手段。然而，说来也巧，上次我见到他时，随口说了句什么，牵扯到他和我们那位年轻小姐分手的问题，他着重强调的话吓了我一跳：“啊，你知道，我和她根本没订过婚啊！”

“就是没有公开吧，”我答道，“因为她母亲不喜欢你。可是，我一直以为，你们私下里是有默契的。”

“呃，也算有过吧。不过现在没有了。”讲到这里他便打住了，只说埃尔梅太太居然又能站起来了，这可真是非同寻常——我猜想，这话指明了一个道理，私下达成的默契几乎百无一用，除非医生也入了伙。我擅自做了更为缜密的推断，想来那姑娘多半已经用某种方式疏远他了。好吧，即便他会因此转变性情，比如妒火中烧，那也不太会妒忌到我头上。真要是那样的话——且不说这个假设有多么荒唐——那他就不会一走了之，反而让我们俩有机会在一起。我们任性地虚掷了他走之前的那段时光，没有提那被掩埋的宝藏，从他的沉默里——我那矜持克制的腔调就是从他那里学来的——我能得出一个尖锐的结论。他的勇气已经一落千丈，他的热情也和我一样烟消云散——至少他把这样的表象留给我去揣摩。并不仅仅是他做不到的问题；一旦他明确承认失败，也许会让我得意扬扬，这种可能性是他无法面对的。他其实没必要害怕的，可怜的家伙，因为那时我已经觉得没有一丁点儿得意的必要了。实际上，我并没有指责他垮掉，我觉得这一点足以表明我的宽厚，因为一想到他已经放弃这场游戏，我就比以往任何时候都感觉到我对他有多么依赖。如果考威克一溃千里，我就永远不会知道真相了；如果连他都没用的话，那任何人都不会有用。实际情况并不是我已经没了求知欲，渐渐地，我的好奇心不仅又开始作痛，而且已经成了绵延于朝朝暮暮的熟悉的折磨。毫无疑问，在有些人看来，这样一种折磨，并不见得会比疾病给人带来的痛苦更为自然，话说回来，毕竟我自己也不明白，我有什么必要在这种情况下提到他们。无论如何，在与我这件逸事扯得上关系的那几位——不管正常与否——看来，文学是一场关乎技术的游戏，而技术就意味着勇气，勇气则意味着荣誉，荣誉意味着激情，意味着人生。押在桌上的赌注是一种特别的东西，而我们的轮盘赌就是不停旋转的思绪，但是我们围坐在绿色的赌桌周围，像蒙特卡罗的冷血赌徒一样聚精会神。如此说来，格温德琳·埃尔梅，那一张苍白的脸庞和那一双全神贯注的眼睛，正是那种你会在“机遇殿堂”[4]里遇上的纤瘦女子。在考威克离开的那段日子里，我意识到，她的行为生动地诠释了这个比喻。我得承认，她全身心浸淫于写作艺术的方式过于奢侈。她显然受困于自己的激情，在她面前，我觉得自己几乎毫无热情。我又拿出了《内心深处》——那是一片沙漠，她置身于其中便迷失了自我，不过，她同时也在这沙漠里挖出一个精美的洞穴——更惊人的是，考威克把她从这洞里拽了出来。

三月初，我收到她发来的一封电报，于是我马上赶到切尔西区，她见到我劈头就是一句：“他懂了，他懂了！”

我看得出，她的激动是如此深切强烈，所以她指的一定是那件天大的事。“维里克的观念？”

“他的整体意图。乔治的电报是从孟买发来的。”

她把电报在那里摊开，虽然简洁，却力重千钧。“我已发现[5]。浩瀚无边。”仅此而已——为了省钱，他没有署名。对她此时迸发的情感我感同身受，可我自己挺失望的。“他没有说那是什么。”

“他怎么能说呢——在一封电报里说吗？他会写下来的。”

“可他是怎么知道的呢？”

“你是问他怎么知道这是真货？哦，我相信，等你亲眼看到，就会知道了。‘凭步态便足以证明她是女神！’[6]”

“埃尔梅小姐，你给我带来这样的消息，真是大好人啊！”——我格外兴奋，极尽言辞。“不过，想想看，在毗湿奴[7]的神殿里找到我们的女神！多么神奇啊，置身于那样迥然不同、异常强烈的诱惑中，乔治居然还能一头钻到那件事里去！”

“他并没有钻进去，我知道，是那事情自己浮现的，六个月来他庄严地将它抛在脑后，如今它就像一头母老虎从丛林中跃出，向他扑过去。他随身没有带一本书——每一页都被他，就像我一样，记在心里。它们在他心里共同作用，直到某时某地，当他的心思完全不在这上面时，它们所有高超复杂的机关，都突然形成唯一正确的组合。地毯上的花纹悄然浮现。他知道结局终究会这样呈现，这就是真正的原因——你完全无法理解，不过我想我现在可以告诉你了——他之所以去，我之所以同意他去，就是为了这个。我们知道这样的变化会有用——不同的想法，不同的场景，会带来必要的触动，带来神奇的震撼。我们周密地、绝妙地盘算过。所有的元素都在他脑中盘旋，只须一次新鲜而强烈的经历带来的‘震撼’[8]，它们就会碰撞出火花来。”反正她本人是火花四溅了——她脸上真的在发光。我结结巴巴地念叨了几句关于无意识精神活动的词儿，而她只管接着自己的话头说：“他会直接回来——这事成了，他就回来了。”

“你是说，去见维里克吗？”

“见维里克——也来见我。想想吧，他会告诉我什么！”

我犹豫了。“说印度的事儿吗？”

“胡扯！说维里克啊——说地毯上的花纹。”

“可是，照你的说法，这事儿当然应该写在信上才对。”

她思索的样子就像是一个灵感勃发之人，我不禁想起很久以前考威克跟我说过，她的面孔耐人寻味。“既然它‘浩瀚无边’，那也许一封信都写不下呢。”

“也许是写不下，如果那尽是些浩瀚无边的蠢话。假如他没有抓住那种能够塞进一封信的东西，那他就没有抓住真谛。按照维里克本人对我的说辞，这‘花纹’恰恰是能塞进一封信的。”

“好吧，一个小时前我给乔治发了电报——就两个词儿。”格温德琳说。

“我是否能冒昧地问问是哪两个词儿？”

她犹豫不决，不过最后还是说了出来。“好人儿，写信。”

“好！”我嚷道，“我得让这事定下来——我要给他拍一样的电报。”

七

然而，我的电报并非跟她一模一样——我用了别的词代替“好人儿”。后来发现，似乎还是我用的昵称比较合适，因为当我们后来收到我们那位旅人的信时，我们只不过，或者说完全是，被他吊了一下胃口。他志得意满，容光焕发，把他的发现说得石破天惊一般，然而他的狂喜只是让事情本身更显得含含糊糊罢了——在他把想法呈交给最高权威之前，不会透露任何细节。他扔掉了特派任务，扔掉了他原本要写的书，扔掉了一切，一心只想马上赶到热那亚海岸边的拉帕罗[9]，维里克正好在那里。我给考威克写了一封信，寄往亚丁[10]，等着他过去收——我恳求他能稍许缓解悬在我心里的疑团。此后又过了好多个无聊的日子，我写给他的简短电报发到孟买后也迟迟没有回音，最后终于来了一封电报，表示他收到了那封信，显然，他是想用这封电报作为对我先后两次联络的回应。电文上寥寥数语，用家常的法文、时下流行的法文写成，考威克通常是拿这个来标榜自己并不是个老古板。对于某些人而言，这样做可能会起到反作用，不过，他的电文大致意思可以这样翻译：“保持耐心。我想看着它突然从天而降时，你脸上是什么表情！”

“Tellement envie de voir ta tête！”[11]——这就是我不得不坐下来面对的局面。其实我压根谈不上“坐下来”，因为我好像记得自己当时躁动不安，在切尔西的小房子和我自己的住所之间来回穿梭。我们都不耐烦，不管是格温德琳还是我，不过我总是希望她那边能更有灵感。在这段时间里，我们这几个囊中羞涩之人，扔了大把大把的钱在电报和出租马车上，我满心指望着发现者和被发现者在会合之后，能马上从拉帕罗发来新消息。这段时间似乎长得遥遥无期，但是，某一天，天色已晚，我听到一辆双轮出租马车向我家门飞驰而来，从那股子冲劲里，多少能猜出来人是乐于慷慨分享的。我的心都提到了嗓子眼儿，赶紧跳到窗口——立马看到一位年轻女子站在马车踏脚板上，热切地抬头看着我的房子。她一看到我就用力挥舞一张纸，那动作就像是在情节剧里，有人在绞刑架下挥动着手帕和缓刑令。

“刚见维里克——分毫不差。拥抱我——留我住一个月。”我在她那张纸上就读到这几个字，坐在高处座位上的马车夫冲着我咧开嘴笑了笑。我一时兴奋，好好打赏了他一番，而她也激动得顾不上心疼钱了，直到车夫驾车离去，我们才开始散步聊天。天知道，我们以前就聊得够多的了，但这回着实振奋人心。我们想象着拉帕罗的整个场景，想象他先是写信要求拜见，信里还提到了我的名字；这画面是我描述的，毕竟我比我身边这位朋友有更多的材料可以用。当我们故意停在橱窗前、眼睛却并不往里面看的时候，我能感觉到她在认认真真听我的一字一句。有一件事我们很清楚：如果他在那里住下，跟维里克展开更充分的交流，那么他至少应该给我们写一封信，帮我们挺过这最后一点儿被拖延的时光。我们固然理解他为什么要在当地逗留，但是，在我看来，我们俩都能看出对方其实讨厌这样的局面。我们都心知肚明的那封信到底还是来了，是写给格温德琳的，为了让她省掉专程来一趟的麻烦，我及时上门拜访。她没有把信念出来，原因不言自明。不过她把信上的主要内容向我重述了一遍。信里有一句引人注目的话，他告诉她，等他们结婚之后，他会把她想知道的事情，一五一十全告诉她。

“只有到那时，在我嫁给他以后才行——不是以前，”她解释说，“也就是说——是不是？——我得马上跟他结婚！”她朝我微笑，而我失望得满脸通红，满脑子都是这刚刚冒出来的拖延理由，以至于我都没有意识到自己是多么惊讶。看起来这已经不仅仅是个暗示了——他也会向我提出让人讨厌的条件。她又跟我转告了几件信里提起的事情，说话间我突然想到，他当初在出发之前跟我说过的话。他发觉维里克先生本身就有种令人晕眩的趣味，而他独守秘密的行为，着实教人神魂颠倒。那被掩埋的宝藏，都是黄金和宝石。它们就在那里，在他眼前越堆越高；它们将历经时代变迁、语言转换，成为文学艺术领域最美妙的花朵之一。特别是你一旦跟它面对面，它所呈现的尽善尽美的完成度是无与伦比的。它一旦出现，就是真的出现了，自带万丈光芒，让你自惭形秽。而且，即便是置身于这个时代的深不见底的庸俗中——人人缺乏品位，个个遭到污染，感官迟钝闭塞——也没有一丁点儿理由忽视它。它伟大，却又是那么简单；它简单，却又是那么伟大——而它终将被我们知晓，这经历殊为难得。他暗示，这样的经历着实迷人，他渴望趁着新鲜劲儿将其饮尽，一滴都不放过，所以始终在源头打转。格温德琳把这些只言片语向我随意抛洒的时候显然容光焕发，她自恃比我更有把握，所以得意扬扬。于是我回过头来说起婚事的问题，忍不住问她，刚才她让我大吃一惊的话是不是意味着他们本来就已经订了婚。

“我当然订了婚！”她答道，“你不知道吗？”她看起来十分惊讶，但是更惊讶的人是我，因为考威克以前讲述的情况正好与此相反。不过我没有提那老话，只是提醒她，在这个问题上，她也好，考威克也好，都没把我当自己人，况且，对于她母亲的禁令，我并非不知情。在心底深处，这两位全然不同的说法让我颇为不安，但是，没过多久，我又觉得考威克毕竟是我最不该怀疑的人。于是我不禁自问，这位姑娘是不是临场即兴创作了一纸婚约——或是把一份旧的拿来拼凑修补，或是草草来一份新的——只为了达成她渴望的心满意足的效果。她一定具有我所缺乏的急智，不过她立刻回答了我，从而把她的情况稍稍挑明了一点儿：“事情其实是这样，我们曾经以为，在妈妈的有生之年，当然是无法有所作为的。”

“然而现在你认为可以无须理会妈妈是否同意了？”

“啊，也许还不用到那一步！”我还在纳闷会到哪一步，她就继续说下去：“可怜的人儿，她也许得吞下这剂药啦。确实，你知道，”她又笑起来，补充说，“她真的得吃下去了！”考虑到所有与此相关之人的想法，我完全明白这个主意有多大的分量。

八

这辈子没有别的事比这件更让我恼火的了：在考威克抵达英国时，我意识到自己没法跑去将此事了结。我突然得去一趟德国，因为弟弟身染重病，他当初不顾我的劝阻执意去慕尼黑，拜在一位大师门下，学习肖像油画。那个给他提供资助的近亲曾经威胁说：但凡他拿出什么似是而非的借口，要到巴黎去寻求更为高尚的真理——不知为何，在一位居住在切尔滕纳姆的姑妈看来，巴黎就是邪恶的学校，是可怕的地狱——那她就要把资助一笔勾销。当时我对这种偏见就颇为反感，如今由它导致的深度伤害也显现出来了——首先，实际上，不去巴黎并没有让这个聪明、羸弱又傻头傻脑的孩子免于肺充血之苦。其次，此事逼得我只能远远地离开伦敦。那几周过得异常焦虑，我满脑子就在琢磨，但凡我们当初选择的是巴黎，那我就能跑过去见考威克了。其实，从各方面看，这种假设都是不成立的：为了让我弟弟康复，我们俩都有一大堆事情要忙，他病足三个月，在此期间我没有离开他半步，末了，我们又不得不面对严禁回到英国的医嘱。出于气候方面的考虑是无法置之不理的，而他的状态也难以独自应付这局面。于是我把他带到意大利梅拉诺，在那里跟他共度了一个夏天，尽量举例教会他如何恢复工作，而另一种愤懑焦虑的情绪却在我心里渐渐滋长，我努力不让他看出来。

到头来，整件事成了一系列诡异地互相交织的现象的开端，把这些现象放在一起看——我只能这样看待它们——在我的记忆里，它们构成了绝佳的例证，表明命运有时会着手处置世人的欲念，从而使其灵魂受惠，这是确凿无疑的。我们此时心心念念的结局终究浅陋平庸——尽管我觉得那结局也值得郑重其事地说一说——相比之下，这些事件所具有的种种意义当然更为重要。无论如何，我承认，当时我被“流放”在外的恶果，主要就是在这样的角度下呈现在我面前的。甚至，当乔治·考威克从拉帕罗回来，用一种我并不赞成的方式给我写信时，由于我被那种我称为“欲念”的情绪所支配，所以起初我确实认为，这事一点儿也不能让那种情绪有所缓解。他的信起不到一丁点儿镇静剂的作用，如今回想起来我倒是必须承认，他当时肯定是希望有此功效的。此后，事情的进展也并未井然有序，因而也无法弥补原先的缺憾。他当时已经开始着手为一家季刊撰文，要写一篇关于维里克作品的定评，这番详尽彻底的研究，唯一仅存的举足轻重的评论，将会点亮新的光芒，将会宣告——哦，静谧无声，悄然宣告！——那无从想象的真谛。换言之，它将细细描摹地毯上的花纹，勾勒每一个盘旋的纹样，再现每一种色泽。按我这位朋友的说法，最终成果将是最伟大的文学肖像，而他对我的要求也颇为善意，只要不提问打扰他就好，等着他把杰作挂到我眼前。他很给我面子，宣称除了那位超然物外、安坐在那里等着被人画的大人物之外，我是他个人最乐意效劳的鉴赏家。因此我得当个好孩子，在演出万事俱备之前，不要想方设法从幕布底下偷窥：我现在愈是坐得气定神闲，将来就愈是乐在其中。

我竭尽全力坐得气定神闲，然而，当我在《泰晤士报》上看到可怜的埃尔梅太太突然去世的消息时，还是忍不住跳了起来。那时我已经在慕尼黑待了一两个礼拜，而据我所知，考威克尚未抵达伦敦。我马上写信给格温德琳询问详情，她回信说家母在被心力衰竭的阴影笼罩多年之后终于倒下。她没有说，但我冒昧地揣测她话里有话，考虑到她的婚姻和她的渴望——就跟我的渴望相差无几，这倒不失为一种解决方式，比原来预想中的情况更为迅速，也比让老太太吞下苦药更为彻底。我坦率承认，当时——因为我一再收到她的信——我从格温德琳的话里读出了某些不同寻常的意味，而在她沉默不语的部分，甚至能读出更加不同凡响的内容。此刻我手中握着笔，回首当时情状，那种极为古怪的感觉再度涌来，它不仅绵延数月，而且我不由自主地成了某种被胁迫着旁观的人。我的所有生活似乎都躲在我双眼的庇护所里，而随着事件推进，我瞪大的眼睛似乎根本无法挪开视线。某些日子里，我想给休·维里克写信，干脆求他发发善心算了。但我更深切地感到，我还不至于落到这么不堪的地步——何况，以我的所作所为，他要是把我赶走也是十分得体的。埃尔梅太太一死，考威克便立刻回来了。就在那个月里，他与那位他爱过又放弃过的年轻女子“安安静静地”结了婚——我看得出来，这种安静就跟他打算在文章里宣布他的“意外收获”一样悄无声息。顺便说一句，我之所以要用“放弃”这个词儿，是因为后来我渐渐确信，他当初去印度，在孟买发来那条重大新闻时，他们俩之间根本没有什么确凿的誓约。当她在跟我言之凿凿地说订过婚时，其实还不存在什么婚约。不过话说回来，他一回国当然就订了婚。这一对幸福的人儿直奔托基[12]度蜜月，在那里，可怜的考威克一时鲁莽，突然带着他年轻的新娘驾车出游。这事他可不在行：以前我们一起坐过一趟轻便马车，因此对这一点我心知肚明。这一回他让他的伴侣坐在轻便马车的高座上，驾车在德文郡的群山中疾驰，在其中一座看起来最惬意的山上，他把已经脱缰（千真万确）的马拽住，却用力过猛，以至于车上的人都被甩到前方，他头部着地，情状可怖。他当场就死了，格温德琳幸免于难，没有受伤。

关于这场十足的悲剧，关于失去最好的朋友对我意味着什么，我且草草略过吧。这一小段关乎我的耐心和痛苦的历史，我只想以如下坦诚的叙述来完成：在收到噩耗之后，我在给她写的第一封信末尾留了一句附言，询问考威克夫人，她的丈夫有没有可能至少写完了那篇论述维里克的大作。她的回答和我的提问同样飞快：那篇文章刚刚写了个开头，只不过是让人心碎的一鳞半爪而已。她解释说，当初我们的朋友在海外刚刚安顿下来开始动笔，就被她母亲的死讯打断了。回国之后，因为忙于种种丧葬事宜，他始终无暇工作。如今留下的只有开头几页，它们固然震撼人心、蕴藏潜力，却并未揭开蒙在偶像脸上的面纱。显然，那种彰显智慧的炫技，原本会构成他文章的高潮。她没再多说什么，没有什么能让我看出她自己究竟知道了多少——我本来以为她那些令人惊诧的行为就是为了千方百计地得到那点儿知识。我最想知道的是：她有没有见到偶像被揭开面纱？是否有过一场私密的仪式，观众席上只有一个心怦怦直跳的人？如果不是为了这样的仪式，那为什么要结婚呢？那时我不愿逼她，可是一想到当初考威克不在时我们说起这个话题的情形，我便对她此刻的沉默寡言颇为惊讶。所以，不久以后，鉴于她继续对我守口如瓶，于是我再次鼓起勇气——战战兢兢地鼓起勇气——从梅拉诺发信给她。“你在狂喜中突然遭遇飞来横祸，那短短几天里，你可曾听到我们如此渴望听到的东西？”我故意说“我们”，是为了给她一点儿小小的暗示，而她的回答表明她是能够心领神会的。“我什么都听到了，”她答道，“我打算守住这个秘密！”

九

不对她抱以最强烈的同情，是不可能的事，所以我回到英国以后就对她无微不至。她母亲的去世倒是让她财力丰厚，于是她搬到了一个生活更方便的区域。然而她的损失毕竟惨重，探望她也教人不胜悲伤。而且我也从来没有产生过那样的念头，认为拥有一条技术上的秘诀、一点儿文学经验，就能够抵消她的悲伤。不过，说来诡异，当我见过她几次之后，我忍不住相信自己多少窥见了一点儿这样古怪的事情。我得马上做个说明，以前也有一些别的事情是我忍不住要相信，或者至少是忍不住要去想象的。既然我向来觉得自己对这类事并不是很清楚原委，那么，对于眼前说到的这个问题，我就权且假定她的记忆毫无瑕疵。她深受打击，孑然一身，却也擅长社交，如今，在深切的悼亡中，她的优雅风范愈显成熟，哀伤却无一句怨言，洋溢着某种不容争辩的美，让人觉得她过着一种富有独特尊严和美感的生活。起初，我说服自己，在那场大灾之后的一周里，她以沉默回应我的诉求，我并非没有意识到那个时机是很不合适的，不久以后，我应该就能打破这个僵局了。当然，她的沉默让我多少有点震惊——越寻思当然就越疑惑不解，尽管我努力解释（有时也能成功），把问题归咎于高尚的情感、出于迷信的忌惮和某种出于忠诚的教养。当然，与此同时，维里克的秘密的身价又在无形中被大大提高，尽管这个谜本来似乎已经够昂贵的了。我不妨谦卑地承认，考威克太太出人意料的态度在钉子上敲了最后一下，把我那不幸的念想牢牢钉住，将它转化成我永远为之魂牵梦绕的迷思。

然而这只是让我行事更狡猾、更灵巧而已，于是我等了一段时间以后再旧事重提。在这段时间里不乏大量推测，其中有一条颇为有趣：考威克对他那年轻的朋友一直守口如瓶，要等到他们之间的亲密关系的最后一道障碍被扫除之后才松口——只有到那时他才会亮出底牌。格温德琳是否从他那里得到提示，如果要她亮出底牌，也唯有建立诸如此类的崭新的关系以后才能如愿？是不是唯有展现在丈夫和妻子——永结同心的爱人——眼前，地毯上的花纹才能被发现或者描述出来？在某种神秘莫测的氛围中，我突然想起当初在肯辛顿广场，我提起考威克会对他爱上的姑娘言无不尽，于是维里克回了一句话，这话是能替这种可能性增添一点儿色彩的。也许话里并无深意，却足以让我踌躇——若是为了得到自己想要的东西，我是否有必要娶考威克太太为妻。为了拥有她的知识，我是否准备好付出这样的代价？啊，那样可真够疯狂的！——至少，在我茫然无措的时候，我是这么跟自己说的。与此同时，我能看见她不愿意传递的火炬仍在她记忆的密室里燃烧——在她双眸流转之间，一道光倾泻而下，照亮她那孤独的宅邸。时间过去将近六个月时，我完全确信，这温暖的画面对她而言能构成怎样的补偿。我们一遍又一遍地说起那个把我们连接在一起的男人——谈起他的才华，他的性格，他的个人魅力，他的特定成就，他那可怕的厄运，甚至还说到他的那场伟大研究有个清晰的目标，想要成就一幅精妙绝伦的文学画像，成为类似于评论界的凡·戴克[13]或者委拉斯开兹[14]那样的人物。她多次向我表示，凭着她的倔强和虔诚，她将缄默不语，她绝不会打破沉默，除非把它交给“合适的人”（照她的说法）去打破。然而那个时刻终究还是来了。某天晚上，我和她坐在一起，比平常坐得更久，我坚定地把手搭在她的胳膊上。“说吧，到底是什么？”

她一直预料我会有这样的举动，所以做好了准备。许久，她缓慢而无声地摇头，脸上浮现的慈悲仅仅是因为穷于言辞。虽则慈悲，她还是向我猛地扔出了那句最宏大、最锋利、最冷酷的“永不”！在我屡屡遭到拒绝的一生中，还从来没有当面领受过这样的打击。我承受了这严酷的打击，并且感觉到眼泪随之涌入眼眶。于是，我们坐了一会儿，互相对视，然后我慢慢起身。我在寻思有朝一日她是否能接受我，但我没把这话说出来。我一边把帽子抚平，一边说：“我知道接下来该怎么想。没事！”

她朦胧的微笑中堆积着某种针对我的孤傲而鄙夷的怜悯，接着，她开口，那话音仿佛此刻仍在我耳畔回响。“那是我的命啊！”我站在门口时，她又加了一句，“你侮辱了他！”

“你说维里克吗？”

“我说的是辞世之人！”

走到大街上，我便意识到她的指责不无公正之处。是啊，那是她的命——我也意识到了，然而，随着时过境迁，她的生命又为另一种兴趣匀出了空间。考威克去世一年半之后，她出版了她的第二部长篇小说——单卷本，名为《征服》，我赶忙去弄了一本，希望在其中能找到一点儿泄露天机的回音或者一张正在偷窥的脸。结果我只是发现，这一部比她年轻时写的那本要好得多，我觉得这表明她曾有过比以往更好的伴侣。作为一种颇为复杂精致的织物，这条地毯的花纹是它独有的；但这花纹并不是我在寻找的那种花纹。我给这本书写了一篇评论投给《中点》，却惊讶地从编辑部那里得知，已经有另一篇书评上了版。待杂志出街，我毫不犹豫地认定，这篇俗气而过火的文章出自德雷顿·迪恩的手笔，此人昔日也得算是考威克的一个朋友，直到最近几周才跟他的遗孀相识。我算是很早便弄到了一本初版，而迪恩显然比我更早。尽管如此，以往考威克善于替华而不实之物镀上一层金，如此轻灵的手法迪恩是没有的——他就只会把金箔金线什么的瞎堆一气，看起来污迹斑斑。

十

六个月之后，《通行权》面市，那是我们救赎自己的最后机会，尽管我们当时并不知情。这本书完全是维里克旅居海外的那段时间里写的，在一百来篇短评中备受赞扬，不外乎是那一套傻里傻气的陈词滥调。我弄来一本——自我标榜那是最早的一本，拿着书直接去找考威克夫人。这本书我也只能派到这点用场了，至于《中点》杂志难免要为这本书唱的赞歌，我就留给某个头脑更敏锐、脾性更温和的人去操心吧。“可是书我已经有了，”格温德琳说，“德雷顿·迪恩真是好心，昨天就给我带了一本，我刚读完。”

“昨天？他下手怎么能这么快？”

“他干什么都能这么快！他打算替《中点》写篇书评。”

“他——德雷顿·迪恩——评论维里克？”我没法相信我的耳朵。

“为什么不呢？反正一种无知跟另一种无知之间，并没有高下之分。”

我心生畏怯，不过还是马上说：“你应该自己评论他啊！”

“我才不评论别人呢，”她笑起来，“我是被人评论的！”

恰在此时，门被猛然推开。“啊，对，你的评论家来了！”德雷顿·迪恩赫然出现，两条长腿，高高的脑门。他来一是打听她对《通行权》有何评价，二是带来一个特别要紧的消息。几份晚报都登了一份关于本书作者的电报，说是他在罗马罹患疟疾。起初并不觉得严重，但是经过一系列并发症，如今病况急转直下，令人忧虑。

实际上，那种忧虑的情绪，我是直到最后一刻才渐渐有所感知的。面对这些消息，考威克太太显然是关切的，但这份关切并没能掩盖她骨子里的超然物外，这态度委实让我震撼——由此可见，她的独立精神之彻底到了怎样的程度。这种独立乃是基于她的知识，如今已经没有什么能摧毁这种知识了，也没有什么能改变它了。地毯上的花纹也许还得再添一两道螺旋，可是判词其实已经写好。作家也许将走向坟墓，她便成了这世上最不需要他继续存在的那个人——就好像她成了他最偏爱的继承人。这让我想起，在某个特定的时刻——考威克去世之后——我发现她原先想亲眼见到维里克的渴望是如何一落千丈。她不用见到他，就已经得到了她想要的东西。我认定，假如她没有得到它，那她就会不遗余力，非得亲自去试探他，她会提出种种高妙的见解，在这方面通常男人比女人更容易领会，而对我而言，这些见解则会构成某种威慑。然而，我得马上补一句，尽管有这样令人反感的对比，但这并不意味着，我自己的心思不够暧昧复杂。一想到维里克也许已处于弥留之际，我心里就碾过一阵痛楚——那感觉是如此辛酸，我居然仍旧那么自相矛盾地依赖着他。我忍受着痛楚，仍然控制住自己，尽管如此矜持世故的姿态对我也算是种补偿，却毕竟使得我和他只能被阿尔卑斯山和亚平宁山脉隔开。然而，日渐衰微的情势又让我隐隐察觉，没准儿到最后我会陷入绝望，忍不住跑去见他。当然，实际上我决不应该做这样的事。就这样，我停了五分钟，而我那两位同伴还在谈论这本新书，当德雷顿·迪恩问我有什么看法时，我站起身，回答说我讨厌休·维里克，根本读不下去。离去时我心里很有把握，只要门在我身后一关上，迪恩就会一口咬定我这人太过肤浅。至于他那位女主人，对这说法至少是不会反驳的。

以下我便用更为简明扼要的调子，追溯此后发生的一连串无比诡异之事。三周之后便传来了维里克的死讯，这一年将尽时他妻子又跟着去世。这位可怜的太太我从未见过，但我有过一个无聊的想法，假若她能在他之后活得更长——长到足以让旁人合乎礼仪地觐见她，那我没准儿就能接近她，提出我那点虚弱的、如火星般转瞬即逝的恳求。她是否知情？如果她知情，那会不会说出来？完全可以预见，她有不止一个理由保持沉默。可是，后来，与她天人永隔之后，我觉得放弃确实是我的宿命。我被永久地困在了我的迷思中——我的监狱看守们已经把钥匙带走了。我发觉自己就像关进地牢的囚犯一样迷迷糊糊，直到考威克太太成为德雷顿太太，也不知时光流逝了多久。透过铁窗，我早已预见了这个结局，不过此事的进程不失得体，并未操之过急，而我们的友谊也早已坠入谷底。他们俩都是那么“知书达理”，在别人眼里自然是天造地设的一对，但我比别人更能估算出新娘在这段联姻中奉献出多少财富。纵观种种“文学圈婚姻”——报纸就是这么描述的——还从来没有哪位女士拿出过如此华丽的嫁妆。我的反应足够迅速，马上开始寻找这桩婚事的果实——我是指那种你能在丈夫身上一眼看出“先兆症状”的果实。既然认定新娘的嫁妆光彩夺目，我便以为能看到他展现出与其增值的财富相匹配的风采来。我知道他的“财富”原先有多少——我显然能从他那篇评论《通行权》的文章里掂出分量来。如今他恰巧站在一个我恰巧（甚至更为恰巧）够不到的位置上，于是我月复一月地在各种可能相关的期刊上寻找可怜的考威克没能发布的重要信息，现在这份责任已经落到了他的继承者手里。那位如今已经再嫁的寡妇，终将在重燃烈焰的壁炉边打破唯有再嫁的寡妇才能打破的沉默，而迪恩便会像彼时彼刻的考威克那样，像彼时彼刻的格温德琳那样，被新添的知识熊熊燃烧。好吧，他无疑会熊熊燃烧，但那团火却不会成为公之于众的烈焰。我将那些期刊一一浏览，终究是徒劳：德雷顿·迪恩倒是洋洋洒洒地四处泼墨，却没有哪一页上有我日思夜想的那一篇。他下笔染指种种话题，却从未与维里克有关。他长于讲述别人或者“畏惧”或者“忽略”（如他所言）的真相，却从未讲述如今我唯一看重的真相。我在那些被报纸称为“文学圈”的场合里频频遇见这对夫妇——我已经暗示过多次，我们这些人生来唯有在这样的圈子里才玩得转。正逢格温德琳第三部长篇出版，她越发专注于在圈里奔忙，而我自己则认为这部作品比不上前一部，持这样的看法当然会被圈里视为异己。作品逊色是因为她的伴侣比以前逊色吗？如果说，她的秘密（按照她的说法）便是她的生命——这一点，从她越来越容光焕发的样子就能窥见端倪，她那因为意识到自己享有特权而流露的优越感，被她优美而仁厚的举止巧妙化解，使得她的容貌教人过目难忘——那么，迄今为止，它并未对她的作品产生直接影响。那只是让人——一切都只不过让人——越发觊觎它，只是用某种更美好更微妙的神秘感将它打磨得圆润光亮。

十一

因此，我目不转睛地凝视着她丈夫：我对他的打扰也许让他颇为不安。我甚至缠着他跟我对话。难道他不知情？难道他没有理所当然地得到它？——这问题在我脑中盘旋。他当然知情，否则他就不会那么古怪地反过来也盯着我。他的妻子跟他说过我想要什么，于是，面对我的无能，他和蔼可亲地觉得这是一件好笑的事。他并没有笑出来——他不怎么爱笑：他的套路就是在言谈中以空洞茫然（就像他的大脑门一样空洞茫然）来应对我的恼怒，这样一来我便会粗率地暴露自己。事情总是这样：我怀着坚定的信念，毅然从那些杳无人烟的空旷地带转身离去，那些地方似乎在地理位置上互相补足，共同象征着德雷顿·迪恩在表达能力和风格气度上的匮乏。他根本就没有本事利用他已经知晓的秘密，他其实没有能力继承考威克留下的责任。于是我做出更进一步的假设——这是我唯一瞥见的开心事。我认定，这份责任对他而言并没有什么魅力。他不感兴趣，他不关心。没错，我相信他蠢得根本无法领会我所缺少的东西能带来怎样的快乐，想到这一点我不禁深感安慰。无论事前事后，他都是那么愚不可及，而这一点也使得环绕在那不解之谜周围的金色光泽愈显深邃。不过，我当然也考虑到，他妻子也许曾给他强加过几条清规戒律。我首先得提醒自己，既然维里克已经撒手人寰，那最要紧的动机便随之消散。他固然留名于世，能从那些可能实现的举措中获得赞誉——但毕竟肉身消逝，再也不能表态了。唉，除了他之外，谁还能有这个权威呢？

夫妻俩生了两个孩子，然而第二个让母亲送了命。打击过后，我似乎又看到了一丁点儿似有若无的机会。我心里几乎想猛扑过去，但出于礼貌还是等了一段时间，最后我的机会终于以某种看起来有利可图的方式降临了。德雷顿夫人死后一年左右，我在一家小俱乐部里的吸烟室里见到了德雷顿·迪恩，我们俩都是这家俱乐部的会员，但是我有好几个月——也许是因为我很少去——没见过他了。房间里空无一人，机会难得。为了一劳永逸地了结这件事，我故意提出要给他点好处，我觉得这是他一直都想要的。

“我甚至比你更早就认识了你已故的妻子，”我开口道，“你一定得让我把长久以来一直积压在心头的话说出来。我乐意接受任何你认为合适的条件，来换取你肯定已经从乔治·考威克那里得来的信息——你知道，这可怜的人儿在他平生最快乐的日子里，从休·维里克那里直接得到了这条信息。”

他就像一尊黯淡无光的、具有颅相学特征的半身像那样看了我一眼。“信息——？”

“就是维里克的秘密啊，我的好人儿——他那些作品的整体意图：把珍珠穿起来的那根线，被掩埋的珍宝，地毯上的花纹。”

他开始脸红——脑袋上隆起的地方眼看着就要冒出一串数字来[15]。“维里克的书有整体意图？”

这下轮到我跳起来。“你的意思不会是你不知道这件事吧？”一时间我还以为他在耍我。“迪恩太太知道这件事，按照她的说法，她是直接从考威克那里听来的，而考威克耗尽心力、苦苦追查，才终于找到了洞口，这让维里克本人也深感快慰。洞口究竟在哪里？他婚后便和盘托出——而且只告诉一个人——而这个人，当这样的境况再度重演时，一定告诉了你。我理所当然地认为，考威克去世之后她成了那个知识的唯一的托管人，一定会准许你分而享之，作为维系你们之间关系的最高特权之一，难道我想错了吗？我只知道那知识价值连城，我想要你理解的是：如果你也能恩准我得其门而入，那你真是对我做了莫大的善事，我将为此感激不尽。”

他的脸终于涨得通红，我敢说他已经开始琢磨我是不是神志不清了。渐渐地，他跟上了我的思路，至于我自己，瞪大眼睛盯着他，我的惊讶比先前更为鲜活。然后他开口说话：“我不知道我们在说些什么。”

他不是在演戏——这是荒诞的真相。“她没有告诉你——？”

“没说过什么关于休·维里克的话。”

我大吃一惊。房间在旋转。它是如此珍贵，连这样的关系都难以得到！“以你的名誉起誓？”

“以我的名誉起誓。你他妈的出什么问题了？”他吼道。

“我惊呆了——我很失望。我原本想从你那里打探到真相的。”

“不在我这里！”他尴尬地笑起来，“即使——”

“如果是的话，你就会让我得到它了——哦，是啊，毕竟是人之常情。不过我相信你。我懂——我懂了！”我继续说。眼看着轮子转了一整圈，我才意识到我那巨大的幻觉，关于这可怜的人儿的态度举止，我原先的看法是错的。虽然我无法明说，但我看得真切：他太太并不觉得他值得被点醒。在我看来，这发生在一个认为他值得嫁的女人身上，真是件怪事。最终我找到了一点儿可以自圆其说的理由：她嫁给他，不可能是因为他悟性过人。她嫁给他，是出于别的考虑。

如今他倒是在某种程度上被点醒了，可这样一来，他越发惊讶、越发慌张了：他寻思了一会儿，把我的故事和他飞快的回顾做了一番比较。最终，尽管有气无力，他还是努力维持着体面，他说：“你提到的事情，我还是第一次听说。德雷顿·迪恩太太有什么未曾提及的——更不要说什么不能提及的——关于休·维里克的知识，我想你这么说一定是搞错了。假如这种知识与他的文学风格密切相关，她当然会希望它被善加利用。”

“它确实给用上了。她自己用的。她亲口告诉我，她就靠它‘活着’呢。”

我话一出口就后悔了，他的脸色骤然苍白，就好像刚刚挨了我的打似的。“啊，‘活着’——！”他喃喃地说，猛地转过脸不看我。

我的悔恨是真心的。我一只手搭在他肩膀上。

“请你原谅我——我错了。你其实并不知道那件我以为你知道的事情。如果我猜得对，那你本来是会帮我一把的。我也曾经自有一番理由，以为站在你的立场上，也可能会满足我的要求。”

“你的理由？”他重复了一遍，“你有什么理由？”

我注视着他，犹疑不定，思前想后。“你过来，坐在我身边，我来告诉你。”我拉着他坐上一张沙发，又点燃一支雪茄，开始讲述维里克那一回从云端倏然降落。我向他细细描述那一连串异乎寻常的意外事件，尽管它们起初也曾带来一道微光，但直到此时此刻，它们始终把我笼罩在一团黑暗中。总之，我把我在这里写下的事情，全都告诉了他。他听着，越听越入神，而我也渐渐惊讶地意识到，从他突然发出的惊叹看，从他提出的问题看，归根到底，他并不是那种不配得到他太太信任的人啊。他突然察觉到她并不信任他，这种感觉在那一刻让他好生烦恼。不过，我看到，起初那出于震惊的悸动先是渐渐消散，接着又再度聚拢，汇成一波波讶异而好奇的浪花——我完全可以断定，这些浪花最终会跟我自己内心中掀起的那股达到最高点的狂怒的潮水分道扬镳。不妨这么说吧，今时今日，作为欲望难以达成的受害者，我们俩之间并没有高下之分。这个可怜人的景况差不多成了我的安慰，时不时地，我觉得这完全可以算是我的报复。

[1] 即前文说到的“简恩斯太太”的昵称。（说明：书中脚注均为译者注。）

[2] 引号中的原文为法语：raison d’être。

[3] 这是本篇中第一次出现直接对应标题的文字，原文是a complex figure in a Persian carpet，直译便是指波斯地毯上的复杂花纹。事实上，这种花纹通常因为烦琐而密集，并不能一眼就看清其纹理，因此a figure in the carpet如今也常用来比喻那些不是能马上判断清晰的事物。

[4] 指赌场。

[5] 原文为希腊语Eureka，即“我发现了”的意思。相传阿基米德根据比重原理测出金子纯度时曾说过这个词，从此成为典故，常用来表达对重大发现的惊叹。

[6] 原文为拉丁文Vera incessu patuit dea，引自古罗马诗人维吉尔叙述埃涅阿斯在特洛伊陷落之后经历的史诗《埃涅阿斯纪》。

[7] 印度教主神之一，守护之神。

[8] 原文为法语词secousse。

[9] 意大利风景区。

[10] 亚丁是现也门首都，也是世界著名的港口。

[11] 此处的法语就是前面已经翻译成英文的电文的后半句：“真想看看你脸上会是什么表情！”作者在翻译之后又把原文列在这里，加以强调。从法语的原文看，这个句子的口吻比较随意、强烈、口语化，有比较明显的戏谑意味。

[12] 英国西南部原德文郡的南部海滨城市。

[13] 凡·戴克（1599-1641），佛兰德斯画家，英王查尔斯一世的宫廷画师，作品尤以贵族肖像画著称。

[14] 委拉斯开兹（1599-1660），按照发音又作贝拉斯克斯，但委拉斯开兹是他约定俗成的译名。委拉斯开兹出生于西班牙塞维利亚，是17世纪西班牙影响最大的现实主义画家，他同样以肖像画闻名于世。

[15] 颅相学家认为头盖骨上隆起的部分是才能的象征，此处显然是呼应前文的比喻——说迪恩就像一尊“具有颅相学特征”的半身像。

译后记

毫无疑问，亨利·詹姆斯是我的翻译生涯里遭遇的最难啃的骨头之一。《螺丝在拧紧》之后，我再次面对他的中篇小说《地毯上的花纹》，既跃跃欲试，又一筹莫展。

一筹莫展是因为，詹姆斯的文本，无论是对其语法的理解层面，还是对其意义的阐释层面，都有着让人深感受挫的难度。第一遍读下来，小说里的情节和人物都如鬼魅般忽明忽灭，躲开一切明确的结论——你横竖抓不住什么。十九世纪末英美文学圈的生态，隐约在小说中现出轮廓，有时细节纤毫毕现，有时又仿佛置身于半透明的罩子里，被看不见的手夸张而剧烈地摇晃。显然，这不是一部以古典现实主义准则构建的小说，它具有某种詹姆斯笔下特有的迂回而不安的现代性。

跃跃欲试是因为，这一篇虽然译成中文后仅三万字，却在詹姆斯的写作生涯中具有非常独特的风格和相当特殊的地位。小说首次发表于一八九六年一月号的《大都会》月刊（Cosmopolis），这本杂志虽然只存在了三年，却有过不小的排场：总部在伦敦，且在柏林、巴黎和圣彼得堡同时发行当地的版本，很吻合小说中描述的当时杂志期刊日益“国际化”的风潮。同年，这篇小说被收入詹姆斯的中短篇小说集《尴尬种种》（Embarrassments），英国版与美国版同时面市。回过头来看，《地毯上的花纹》是这本书里影响最大的篇目，而标题“地毯上的花纹”（The Figure in the Carpet）也渐渐成了一个被后世频繁引用的文学典故。英国小说家、评论家福特·马多克斯·福特（Ford Madox Ford）曾经说过，自从这篇小说出版之后，詹姆斯的同龄人就开始追求“地毯上的花纹”，希望能将原本复杂难辨的“花纹”变成清晰可鉴的物质实体。在发表于一九四一年的散文中，T.S.艾略特几乎把同样的话又说了一遍：“如今，我们都在寻找‘地毯上的花纹’。”

小说的第一人称叙述者，是个赚过一点儿稿费却苦于在圈里寂寂无名的写手。明显比他更为资深、主要以写评论为主的考威克因为来不及完成著名作家维里克的新作的书评，把这个机会转给了“我”。“我”以为抓到了在文学圈里进阶的机会，不料却像是一头撞进了一座迷宫。维里克对于这篇评论不屑一顾，并且抛出了一系列炫目的名词和意象，引诱“我”追逐对于其作品的终极破解：

在他本人看来，毫无疑问，那个让我们不胜迷惘的东西，明明是清晰可见的。那玩意儿，我猜想，就藏在最初的规划中；宛若波斯地毯上的一个复杂的纹样。当我使用这个意象时，他表示高度赞赏，而他自己则用了另一种说法。“它就是那根线，”他说，“把我的珍珠穿起来的那根！”

此后的情节发展就进入了詹姆斯最善于营造的诡异疯狂的叙事链。“我”对于维里克（毋宁说是小说这种文体）的“整体意图”的追寻，注定要像《螺丝在拧紧》中那个关于“庄园里有没有鬼”的命题那样，经受百般折磨，经受“真谛”在眼前闪现又幻灭的海市蜃楼般的瞬间。洞悉维里克的秘密的人（或者说“我”以为洞悉秘密之人）一个接一个遭遇不测。詹姆斯得心应手地折磨着读者的耐心，在人物细节和对话里嵌入可以引发多重理解/误解的隐喻。熟悉詹姆斯套路的读者，几乎在小说写到一半时就能判断：直到结尾，我们也得不到答案。

但我们还是会一口气读完它。我们知道，像很多具有元小说特质的现代主义作品一样，这是一个用来阐述小说观念的小说。小说里的小说家和评论家的关系，是一种近乎猫捉老鼠的关系。小说文本的“整体意图”被层层包裹，被繁复衍生，被渐渐失去节制地神秘化。批评家疯狂地追逐它，而小说家则似乎一直在使用各种障眼法躲开这种追逐，这样的关系越来越具有奇特的仪式感。地毯上到底有没有花纹，这并不重要；重要的是，作者、批评家和读者的兴趣和精力，在这个过程中被刺激、被撩拨，同时也被消解，被损耗——像表演，像爱情，像生死。作为由古典主义向现代主义过渡的代表人物，詹姆斯对于时代风气的观察，对于小说作为一种叙事游戏的深层思考，都渗透在文本的肌理中。

在这篇小说里先后出现的几个命运多舛的人物，我们无法确认哪一个更能让詹姆斯产生代入感；我们同样无法确认詹姆斯是否要通过《地毯上的花纹》表达现代小说家和批评家的使命和宿命。（是使命多一点儿，还是宿命多一点儿？）可以确定的是，詹姆斯之后的写作者，越来越深切地体验到他在这篇小说里传达的那种时而狂喜、时而虚无的复杂感受。第二次世界大战结束之后陆续涌现的文学名词和小说流派，可能比此前的总和都更多。对于普通读者而言，弄清现代主义究竟在哪个时间点进入后现代主义，“后殖民”与“新历史”分别代表什么意思，或者推理小说究竟分出多少亚类型，并没有太明显的意义。社会现实的动荡和传播方式的剧变，使得小说作者与读者之间的信任感渐趋微妙。叙事套路仿佛已经穷尽，连“生活比小说更精彩”都成了老生常谈。小说家进退两难，时而希望勇往直前，沿着文体实验的道路越走越远；时而又希望重温现实主义的荣光，回归古老的故事传统。

在现代文学的语境中，小说家与批评家，作品的创造者和诠释者，他们之间究竟有没有可能实现真正意义上的默契，密码有没有可能被完美破解？我们从这个既抽象又具体甚至有时候颇具哥特风格的故事里，看不到詹姆斯对此有任何乐观的表示。故事的荒诞走向甚至让人联想到那个著名的思想实验：两位将军A和B各自盘踞在两座山顶，需要同时攻击山谷处的敌人，但他们之间的通信只能穿过敌方阵线进行。A给B发了个信息：“明天出击？”B回答：“可以。”但B不知道自己的回复有没有到达，而A必须给B发送另外一条信息来确认已经收到了B之前的信息，从而确保B会行动——实际上，为了达成完美的共识，他们需要发送无穷无尽的信息。

《地毯上的花纹》就在这种看不见尽头的努力沟通中戛然而止。然而，也许，无论是密码被（简化地）破解，还是因为无法破解而失去对破解的渴望，都会使小说的魔法黯然失色。这真是个绕不出去的悖论，但叙事艺术的奇迹和荣光，也恰恰蕴含在这悖论中。毕竟，詹姆斯狡黠地在绝境中也留着一星微暗的火：

如果说，她的秘密（按照她的说法）便是她的生命——这一点，从她越来越容光焕发的样子就能窥见端倪，她那因为意识到自己享有特权而流露的优越感，被她优美而仁厚的举止巧妙化解，使得她的容貌教人过目难忘——那么，迄今为止，它并未对她的作品产生直接影响。那只是让人——一切都只不过让人——越发觊觎它，只是用某种更美好更微妙的神秘感将它打磨得圆润光亮。

黄昱宁

2019年6月

巴塔哥尼亚

1833年12月6日

小猎犬号航离拉普拉塔河，离开了它混浊的水道。我们将驶向位于巴塔哥尼亚的海岸线上的德西雷港。在深入航程以前，我必须先整理一下在海上的种种观察。

有几次是在小猎犬号距离拉普拉塔河口数英里[1]之处，另外几次则是在巴塔哥尼亚北部的海岸边，我们遇到了被昆虫团团包围的情况。有一天傍晚，在距离圣布拉斯湾大约10英里的地方，数量庞大的蝴蝶成群结队，覆盖了视线所及的全部天空。即使借助单筒望远镜，也看不见蝶群中有任何一丝缝隙。水手们大喊大叫：“下蝴蝶雪啦。”而这也确实是当时的景象。现场的蝴蝶种类并不单一，不过大多为同一物种，非常接近但区别于普通的英国红点豆粉蝶（Colias edusa）。其中夹杂着一些蛾类和蜂类与蝴蝶共舞；还有只漂亮的星步甲（Calosoma）飞上了船。有证据表明，有人曾在远海抓到过几次这种甲虫；然而眼前这情景可大为罕见，因为大多数步甲科（Carabidæ）昆虫很少甚至从不飞行。那日的天气一直晴朗平静，前一天也同样如此，只有几丝轻盈而多变的微风。因此我们推测这些虫子不可能是从大陆吹来的，而是自行飞来的。起初，数量巨大、密密团团的豆粉蝶（Colias）似乎又一次证明了那些记录在册的小红蛱蝶（Vanessa cardui）的迁徙。但其他种类昆虫的出现使之非同寻常，并且很难解释。日落之前，从北面吹来了一阵强风，而这无疑会使数以万计的蝴蝶和其他昆虫就此毙命。

另有一回，在离科连特斯角17英里远的地方，我往水里抛了一张网，捕捞深海生物。收网后，我相当意外地发现里面有数量可观的甲虫，即使远在外海，咸水也没有对它们造成太多的伤害。我遗失了部分标本，但保存下来的则分别属于切眼龙虱（Colymbetes）、平基龙虱（Hydroporus）、毛跗牙甲（Hydrobius）（两个种）、锥须步甲（Notaphus）、黑步甲（Cynucus）、新麻萤叶甲（Adimonia）和圣蜣螂（Scarabæus）。起初，我以为这些虫子是被风从海岸边吹来的，但经过反复思考，鉴于这八个种类的甲虫里，有四种是水生，另外两种也有部分水栖习性，我觉得它们最有可能是随着一小股水流从科连特斯角附近的湖泊中一路漂流进入大海的。无论出于哪种假设，在距离最近陆地17英里的地方，发现昆虫在开阔的海面有活力地游动，都是非常有趣的现象。曾有几次记录显示有昆虫被风从巴塔哥尼亚海岸吹来的现象。库克船长就观察到过，而最近一次，金船长在冒险号上也遇到了。昆虫被吹离海岸的原因极有可能是缺乏遮蔽，在既没有树又没有山的情况下，一只正在飞翔的昆虫很容易被吹向大海。在所有远离陆地观察到的昆虫中，最令我惊讶的是一只体形较大的蝗虫[飞蝗（Acrydium）[2]]。它飞上小猎犬号时，我们正迎风驶向佛得角群岛，而离得最近的一块陆地，是不完全在季风风向上的布兰科角，位于非洲海岸线上，距我们有370英里之远。

有好几回，当船只位于拉普拉塔河口范围之内时，帆缆上便会结满飞航的蜘蛛的网。有一天（1832年11月1日）我特别留意了这一现象。那天天气晴朗无云，早晨的空气中满是一片片毛乎乎的网，就好像身处英格兰的秋天。船离陆地有60英里，一阵稳定而轻柔的微风顺着我们的航向吹拂。有无数的小蜘蛛，体长约1/10英寸[3]，呈暗红色，黏着在一张张网上。我估计这艘船上一定有数千只小蜘蛛。它们刚接触帆索的时候，总是凭一根单独的蛛丝来固着，而不是停留在絮状的网上。这些网看起来就像是许多根单独的蛛丝纠缠在一起。这些蜘蛛都是同一个属种，有雌有雄，同时还有一些幼蛛，体形较小，颜色也更暗淡。对此我不再赘述，在我看来，它似乎并不属于拉特雷耶[4]分类系统中的任何一属。这小小的搭船客一落到船上就四处跑来跑去，异常活泼；有时会故意坠下来，然后再沿着同一根蛛丝往上爬；有时候则在角落的绳索间织一个小小的不规则的网。它能在水面上相当灵活地移动，受到惊吓的时候会抬起前腿，摆出一副防御的姿态。这些蜘蛛最初抵达时似乎极为口渴，用一对突出的颚叶急切地喝着水；斯特拉克曾经观察到一模一样的情形：或许这是由于这些小小的虫子经过了一片干燥而稀薄的空气而来？它似乎能无穷无尽地吐丝。在观察某些悬垂在独根蛛丝上的小蜘蛛时，有好几回我都看到，哪怕是最轻微的一阵风也能把它们横吹出去，瞬间消失不见。另有一回（25日）环境情况类似，我反复观察到同一属种的小蜘蛛，不论是被放置还是自己爬行，只要到了一片微微隆起的高地，便会抬起腹部，往前射出一根蛛丝，然后沿侧面滑走，速度之快，令人百思不得其解。我以为我看到了小蜘蛛在做出上述准备动作之前，用最纤细的蛛丝把腿黏在了一起，然而我并不能确定这一观察是否正确。

有一天，就在圣菲，我得到一个更好的观察相似情形的机会。有一只身长约3/10英寸的蜘蛛，外形接近于游走蛛（Citigrade）（因此与那些借助于风从远处来的飞航的蜘蛛截然不同），它落在一根木杆的顶端，从纺器里往前喷射出四五根蛛丝。这些在阳光中闪闪发光的丝，看上去有如一根根光线；它们不是笔直的，而是曲折起伏，像被风撩动的绸面。蛛丝长度超过1码[5]，从吐丝口向上散射出去。紧接着，蜘蛛突然离开了木杆，迅速消失在我的视线中。那天热得很，显然也没有风，但即使在这样的天气里，气流也不可能让蛛丝这般纤弱的风向标纹丝不动。如果在晴暖的日子里，我们观察物体投射到岸上的影子，或者眺望平原上距离较远的地标，热空气向上蒸腾的气流几乎是显而易见的。而这气流也足够吹起蛛丝上的小蜘蛛。在距离陆地数里格[6]之遥的很多海域上，都有人发现了不同性别不同年龄同一属种的蜘蛛大量依附在蛛丝上，这证明它们正是这些网的制造者，并且那乘风而行的习性，也极有可能是它们属种的特征，一如潜水之于水蛛（Argyroneta）。我们或许可以就此推翻拉特雷耶的设想，即这些蛛丝来自某些属种的幼蛛，比如球蛛（Epeira）或者蟹蛛（Thomisa），然而，如同我们所观察到的，其他一些种类的幼蛛的确拥有随风远航的能力。

在拉普拉塔河以南不同的航段里，我常常在船尾拖一张旗布结成的网，因此捕捞到不少稀奇古怪的生物。栉水母（Beroe）（水母的一种）的结构最为奇特，有成排颤动的触手，以及复杂但并不规则的循环系统。甲壳动物（Crustacea）有许多新奇、未见描述的属。有一种，就某方面而言类似于某些十足目的蟹类[7]（Notopods）（或是某种蟹，为了附着在暗礁的底部，这种蟹的后足指节几乎长到了背上），有着构造十分奇异的后足。它的倒数第二节关节，并非结束于单一的钳足，而是止于三个长度不一、刚毛样的附肢，最长的一节同整条足一样长。这些钳足非常细，锯齿状地分布着极其细密的齿，一直到基部。钳足弧形的顶端是扁平的，上面排列着五个极微小的杯状结构，其功能看起来类似于墨鱼触腕上的吸盘。鉴于这种生物生活在远海，大有可能需要歇脚之处，我猜测这一美丽的构造是为了能抓住水母以及其他海洋浮游生物球形的身体。

在远离大陆的深水区，生物的数量极其稀少：南纬35度以南，除了一些栉水母，以及切甲亚纲（Entomostraca）的几种丁点大的甲壳动物，我再也没有打捞到什么别的生物了。而在离岸数英里的稍浅一些的海里，有许多种甲壳类动物，以及众多其他动物，不过只在夜间出现。在南纬56度到57度之间，合恩角以南，我往船尾撒了好几回网，然而，除了零星捞到两种体形极小的切甲亚纲动物，简直一无所获。但这一片海域，却分布着数量极为可观的鲸鱼、海豹、圆尾鹱、信天翁。对此我总是疑惑不解，距离岸边如此之远，信天翁究竟是靠什么存活的。我推测信天翁有点儿像秃鹰，能够长时间地禁食，只要饱啖一顿腐烂的鲸鱼尸体便可抵挡长久的饥饿。然而并不能简单认定，它们以鱼为生，因为，那些鱼又以何为食呢？观察大西洋中部与南北回归线之间的水域里麇集的翼足目（Pteropoda）、甲壳纲和放射虫纲（Radiata）动物，以及吞食它们的飞鱼，再加上吞食飞鱼的鲣鱼和金枪鱼，我时常灵光一现地想到，那些处于最底端的远洋生物很有可能拥有分解二氧化碳的能力，一如植物王国的成员们。

船航行在这些纬度之间，每到黑夜，海洋就会呈现出一派壮丽的景象，美不胜收。清风微拂，白天海面上铺天盖地的浮沫，这会儿闪动着淡淡的微光。船首破开两道磷光灼烁的巨浪，而船尾则拖曳着一条乳白色的航迹。目之所及，每一道浪尖都熠熠生光，地平线上方的天穹在这些青灰色光芒的映照下，不再像其余的夜空那般晦暗不明。

我们驶向更南方，大海中几乎看不到磷光了。离开合恩角之后，记忆中只见过一回，而且这磷光也远谈不上明亮。这种情形多半与这片海域生命的匮乏息息相关。关于海洋中的磷光，在埃伦伯格写过阐述详尽的论文之后，我再对此做出自己的考察大概有点儿多此一举。然而，我或许可以补充，埃伦伯格所形容的破碎的、不规则的凝胶状颗粒，似乎是引起南北半球磷光现象的共同原因。这种颗粒非常微小，能轻易地透过细纱布；然而多数仅凭肉眼就可以分辨。把这海水放在一个玻璃杯里搅动，它就会闪闪发光，但如果往表面皿里倒上些许，就很少见它发亮。埃伦伯格认为，这些颗粒都有一定程度的应激性。而我的观察，有一些是在刚取出海水后就直接进行的，得出了截然不同的结论。我还要指出，有一天夜间，在用过渔网后，我任其晾得半干，12个小时后再次使用它时，竟发现渔网的表面就和刚从海水里捞出来时一样闪着亮光。在这种情况下，颗粒是不太可能存活这么久的。我的笔记里还记录过我养的一只和平水母（Dianæa），在它死后，盛放它的水开始发光。当海浪闪耀着绿色的光亮时，我认为这大体上确实是由微小的甲壳动物发出的。而且，毫无疑问，仍然有许许多多的浮游生物会在活着的时候发出磷光。

有两回，我观察到在离水面相当远的深处海水在发着光。就在拉普拉塔河口附近，一片片地，呈圆形或卵形，直径在2到4码之间，轮廓清晰，散发着稳定、黯淡的光，而周围的海水只是偶尔闪烁一下。这些发光区看上去就像是月亮或者别的什么发光体的倒影，它们的边缘随着海面的起伏而曲折。我们这艘船吃水达13英尺[8]深，驶过这些发光区，却并没有搅散它们。由此我们可以推测，这些生物聚集在比船底还深得多的海里。

费尔南多・迪诺罗尼亚群岛附近的海水一阵一阵地闪着光，看上去很像是一条大鱼疾速地穿过一片发光的海水所造成。水手们也确实是这么认为的，可那个时候，基于闪光出现的频率及其迅疾的速度，我倒是对此持有几分怀疑。就观察到的现象总体而言，我早已说过，这一情形在温暖的区域比在寒冷的区域要更加常见。我有 时候会设想，大气扰动的电磁状态极利于产生这种发光现象。当然，比起寻常天气，经过数天风平浪静的日子之后，这种发光现象最为强烈，因为此时的海水中聚集了各种各样的生物。我观察到充满凝胶颗粒的海水总是很混浊，而发光现象基本上都是由于和大气接触的海水被搅动而导致的，因此我一直倾向于认为磷光是源于有机颗粒的分解，在这一过程中（该过程差不多可以被称为呼吸作用）海洋得到了净化。

12月23日

我们抵达了德塞阿多港，就在南纬47度，巴塔哥尼亚海岸上。溪水深入内陆约20英里，时宽时窄。小猎犬号停泊在溪水入口内几英里之处，正对着古老的西班牙定居点的废墟。

我当晚就登上了岸。初次来到任何未知的土地总是令人兴奋的，尤其像这一回，风光景物都显得卓然殊异。在大约200到300英尺之间的高处，成片的斑岩之上，一块宽阔的台地延展开去，这正是典型的巴塔哥尼亚地貌。地面相当平坦，由浑圆的鹅卵石间杂着发白的泥土构成。瘦而坚韧如金属丝一般棕褐色的草，东一丛西一丛地散布着，间或夹有一些低矮多刺的灌木丛。天气干爽宜人，晴空如碧，少有云翳。站在任何一块荒凉台地的中央望出去，总有一边的视线为陡壁所阻挡，那是一块更高的台地，但同样地平缓、萧索；而另一边的景致则朦胧不定，地表受热蒸腾而起的气流让一切变得如海市蜃楼般缥缈。

有许多宽阔、底部平坦的山谷横穿台地，谷里的灌木丛尤为繁茂。如今这片土地的排水量显然不足以冲击出这般庞大的沟渠。在一些山谷里，一棵棵古老、矮小的树生长在干涸的河道正中，它们伫立在那里，仿佛为了证明自打洪水从此地奔流而去后，又有多少时间消逝如斯。地面上的贝壳表明，砾石台地是在最近一世[9]才上升到海平面之上的；而山谷也正是在那一时期由缓慢消退的水流冲击而成的。自从气候干旱以来，人们可能在这些台地之间走上几天，却看不见丝毫水的踪迹。即使在斑岩山脚下，也只有几口小小的水井，盛着少量半腐臭的咸水。

在这样一片土地上，西班牙定居点的命运很快就见分晓了。一年中大部分时间干旱的气候，以及游牧的印第安人时不时地怀有敌意的袭击，迫使殖民者废弃了尚未完工的建筑。不过，已见雏形的风格也显示出旧时期西班牙强烈而自由的气息。对于美洲南纬41度以南地区全部的殖民努力皆以悲剧告终。“饥荒港”[10]这一名字透露出有数百个受难者在此苟延残喘、苦不堪言的种种，其中仅有一人幸存下来，讲述了这一苦难。在巴塔哥尼亚海岸的圣约瑟夫湾，西班牙人设了一个小小的定居点，印第安人在一个星期日袭击了他们，几乎屠戮了整支殖民队伍，只有两人幸免于难，并在游牧部落里做了多年的俘虏。我曾在内格罗河与其中一人交谈，彼时，他也已至耄耋之年。

巴塔哥尼亚的动物种群和它的植物种群一样寥落。在贫瘠的台地上，大致能看到有些黑色的甲虫[异跗节类（Heteromera）]慢吞吞地爬来爬去，偶尔有一只蜥蜴飞快地从这一头蹿到另一头。至于鸟类，我们看到了三只吃腐肉的鹰，在山谷里则有几种雀鸟和以昆虫为食的鸟。黑脸鹮（Ibis malanops）[11]（据说在非洲中部也有分布）常见于不毛之地。在它们的胃里我发现了蝗虫、蝉、蜥蜴甚至蝎子。一年里总有一段时间，它们成群生活，另一段时间里则成对出行；它们的叫声响亮而奇异，有点儿像原驼的嘶鸣声。

对于后者我将于此阐述一番，这一相当常见的物种，是巴塔哥尼亚台地上典型的四足动物。有些博物学家认为原驼与大羊驼是同一种动物，前者是后者的野生状态，是东方骆驼在南美洲的远亲。它的大小与驴子相仿，修长的四肢使得身形更高，而脖颈则极长。原驼遍布南美洲的整个温带地区，从林木葱茏的火地岛，到整个巴塔哥尼亚地区、拉普拉塔的山区，以及智利，甚至到秘鲁山脉。尽管偏爱在较高处生活，在这些地区它却不如它的近亲小羊驼一般繁盛。在南巴塔哥尼亚的台地上，它们的数量较其他地区要多得多。通常它们以小群生活，数量从6头到30头不等；但在圣克鲁斯的河岸边，我们看到一个原驼群，至少有500头之多。在麦哲伦海峡的北海岸，它们的数量也十分庞大。

总体而言，原驼野性十足，也异常警觉。斯托克斯先生曾经告诉我，有一天他透过单筒望远镜看到一群原驼，虽然距离遥远，单凭肉眼根本不可能准确辨认，但能看出它们显然已经受惊，正全速奔逃。猎手经常能第一时间捕捉到原驼的踪迹，他们隔着很远就能听见原驼奇异、尖厉而带有警戒意味的嘶鸣声。倘若猎手留心察看，极有可能会瞧见一群原驼在远处的山坡上站成一排。当猎手逐步接近，原驼会发出更多的嘶叫，然后沿着狭窄、被踩平的小径转移到邻近的一座山上，尽管看起来像是在慢慢跑动，实则速度飞快。倘若猎手碰巧撞见一头落单的原驼，或者只是几头在一起，它们多半会一动不动，专注地盯着猎人；接着或许会迈开几码，转过头来再度盯视。它们胆怯的表现何以如此不同？它们是不是错把远处的人当成了它们的主要天敌美洲狮？还是好奇战胜了胆怯？原驼很好奇这点确凿无疑，如果一个人躺在地上，做出滑稽的动作，像是双足在空中蹬踢，它们几乎总是会渐挪渐近，探个究竟。这个小招数被我们的猎手反复地成功实践，有时甚至还能开上几枪，因为这全都被当成了滑稽行径的一部分。在火地岛的山里，以及其他地区，我不止一次地瞧见原驼在有人靠近以后，嘶鸣吼叫，昂首腾跳，样子极其古怪，而这显然是故作姿态，以进为防。原驼相当容易驯养，我曾看见过一些养在房子附近被驯化的，不过也是和它们在野地里一样，处于放养状态。这种状态下的原驼十分勇猛，随时会以双膝从背后对人发起攻击。据说，这种攻击的动机源于对雌性的争风吃醋。尽管如此，野生的原驼却毫无防卫的意识；仅凭一条狗便能看住体形庞大的原驼，直到猎人赶来。从许多方面来看，它们的生物习性比较接近羊群中的羊。因此，当骑手从各个方向接近原驼的时候，它们会立刻陷入混乱，不晓得从哪个方位奔逃。这使得印第安人的狩猎变得轻而易举，因为它们很容易被驱赶到一个中心点，被团团包围。

原驼很喜欢下水：在巴尔德斯港，好几次都有人目击到原驼从一个岛游向另一个岛。拜伦在他的游记里曾写道，他看到原驼在喝咸水。而我们的几位长官也同样瞧见，一群原驼似乎正从布兰科角附近的一个盐水湖里饮用咸水。我揣测，在这片土地的某些地方，如果它们不饮用咸水的话，就根本无水可喝。正午时分，它们常待在浅碟形的洼地里，在尘土中滚来滚去。雄性原驼总是打架，有一天，两头原驼和我擦身而过，它们尖声嘶叫，正在极力撕咬对方；有几头被射杀的原驼，兽皮上还有深深的咬痕。驼群有时候似乎会结队前去探险：在布兰卡港，距离海岸30英里的地区内，原驼是十分罕见的。有一天我观察到三四十头原驼的足迹，呈直线通往一条泥泞的咸水溪。随后，它们想必是察觉到了自己正在接近大海，于是便以一种骑兵队的规整步伐突然转了个方向，和它们来时一样笔直得像条线一般地往回走了。原驼有一个奇特的习性，令我相当费解：它们会连续若干日把粪便拉在同一个地方，形成明显的一堆。我曾见过其中的一堆，直径有8英尺，想必数量庞大。弗雷奇尔认为这一习性是原驼和美洲驼共有的；这对于使用粪便为燃料的印第安人极为有用，免去了收集的麻烦。

原驼似乎对于死亡的地点也有偏好。在圣克鲁斯河岸的一些特定区域内，地面上骨头累累，一片惨白，这些地点通常灌木丛生，全都靠近河边。在其中一处，我数到了约十几个头骨。我特意研究了这些骨头，它们看起来不像我以前见过的零星散落的骨头，那些骨头要么被啃噬过，要么就被折断了，似乎都是被猛兽拖到一起的。而这些骨头却不一样，从大多数骨头来看，这些原驼必定在死之前爬到了灌木底下，或者隐在灌木丛中。拜诺先生告诉我，在上一次旅程中，他在里奥加耶戈斯河岸注意到了一模一样的情形。我并不全然理解此中缘故，不过在圣克鲁斯，我观察到受伤的原驼无不走向了河边。在佛得角群岛的圣贾哥，我记得悬崖下面，一条与世隔绝幽深的沟壑里，集聚着数量可观的山羊骨头：当时我们都惊叫起来，认为这大概是岛上所有山羊的坟场了。我提及这些不足挂齿的事情，是因为在某些情况下，它们或许能解释数量不少、完好无损的骨头出现在山洞里或者河流冲积层中这一现象；同样地，也能说明何以在沉积矿床中一些哺乳动物比其他动物更为常见。圣克鲁斯任何一场大洪水都会冲刷出许多原驼的骨头，但大概连一根美洲狮、鸵鸟或狐狸的骨头都没有。我还观察到，几乎每一种水禽在受伤时都会到岸边等待死亡，也正是出于这一原因，在化石中很少见到鸟类的尸体。

***

1834年1月9日

天黑之前，小猎犬号停泊在圣胡利安港宽绰的港口里，距德西雷港南端约110英里。海港南边，一座高达90英尺的悬崖切断了上述构造的平原。它的表层散布着现代的海洋贝壳。与其他任何地区截然不同的是，这块地面被一层薄薄的、不平整的微红色淤泥所覆盖，包含一些小粒的钙质结核。这层淤泥有点儿类似于南美洲潘帕斯大草原上的那种，而且很有可能源于早先经此地入海的一条小溪流，还有点儿像如今还存在于港口前端的那种泥滩地。在某一处，这些淤泥填满了地面的空隙处及山谷，几乎蔓延至碎石层之下，而就在这层碎石中，也藏有很多大型的动物骨头。如同布兰卡港的情形，这些骨头所属的动物一定生活在贝壳出现很久以后的一段时期里，而这些贝壳至今还留存于该海岸。对于这一点我们基本可以确定，因为阶地或者台地较低的地质层的形成必然晚于它上面那几层，而在较高的两层地质层的表面，正散布着现代的海洋贝壳。从大陆最近一次抬升100英尺所产生的自然界的小小变化来看，在那些动物被埋藏的年代，气候以及巴塔哥尼亚总体环境，与今天相比几乎是一模一样的。根据这两个年代的贝壳种类来判断，关于这些动物出现时间的结论也站得住脚。难题紧随而来，在南纬49度15分这般恶劣的荒漠里，大型的四足动物是如何生存下来的呢？当时我对此一筹莫展，不清楚这些遗骸属于哪些动物。然而，当欧文先生察看这些骨头的时候，谜题却很快解开了：他判断这些骨头能拼出的动物的一部分，与原驼或者美洲驼是同一系的，但体形和真正的骆驼一样大。由于现存的所有骆驼科动物都生活在不毛之地，我们或许可以断定这是灭绝的一种。颈椎的结构，椎动脉所需的横突上未见穿孔，揭示了它与骆驼科的相关性；然而，该结构的另外一些部位，却是非常规的。

这一发现最重要的一个结果是，证实了一个原则，即现存动物与灭绝动物之间有亲缘关系。由于原驼是巴塔哥尼亚地区典型的四足动物，而小羊驼是白雪皑皑的科迪勒拉山脉最高峰的代表动物，所以在很久以前，与它们同属一科的这种体形庞大的动物也必定是南部平原上的主要动物。我们观察到了同样类型的关联，在现存栉鼠和栉鼠化石之间，在水豚和庞大的箭齿兽之间（欧文先生指出这两种间的关系并非那么明显），最后还有，在现生的贫齿类动物和灭绝的贫齿类动物之间。在今天的南美，至少有该目的19个物种间存在这种情形；而在世界其他的地区只发现了5种。那么，如果现生和灭绝的动物之间存有关联，我们当可期望发现数量庞大的贫齿类动物的化石。回答这个问题，我只需列举大地獭（Megatherium）以及在布兰卡港发现的三到四种大型的物种；在整个广袤的拉普拉塔地区也发掘出大量它们的遗骸。我早已指出犰狳和它们的祖先之间的奇特联系，这种联系甚至在它们外披的“铠甲”这样看似无关紧要的方面也存在着。

现今，存在于啮齿动物目的这种联系，在南美洲最为明显，这是由于该物种的数量庞大，物种多样化，加之个体数量繁多。根据同样的规律，我们应该能在化石中找到它们的代表。欧文先生揭示了谱系遥远的箭齿兽是怎样由这一规律联系起来的，所以，在另一种大型动物中，发现这种类似的亲缘关系，也并非不可能。

啮齿类动物与在布兰卡港附近被人发现的水豚有着几乎相同尺寸的牙齿，这也是值得记录的一点。

尽管难免遇见一些异常的例外，物种演变的法则，还是引起了每一位爱好哲思的博物学家极为浓厚的兴趣。人们第一次明确观察到这一法则是在澳大利亚，在那里的一个山洞中，有人发现了各种已灭绝的大型袋鼠以及其他有袋目哺乳动物的化石遗迹。在美洲，哺乳动物中最显著的变化是几种乳齿象、一种大象以及某种马的消亡。这些厚皮兽早先似乎遍布全世界，就像今天的鹿和羚羊那样。如果布封知道这些巨大的犰狳、美洲驼、大型啮齿动物，以及灭绝的厚皮兽类动物，他的结论或许会更为准确，即美洲丧失了它的创造力，而不是美洲从未拥有过创造力。

对于这片大陆的更迭变化，我们不可能不感受到深深的惊讶。以前，这里和非洲南部一样，巨大的兽类来来往往，如今我们却只能看到貘、原驼、犰狳和水豚；这些动物同它们之前的物种相比，都只是一些小矮种。其中大多数已灭绝的四足动物，即使不是全部，大多也都生活在一个非常近的时期，与现存的软体动物是同时代的物种。自它们绝迹以来，这片土地的自然环境并没有发生什么大的变化。那又是何种因素让这么多的生灵灭绝了呢？在南美洲潘帕斯大草原上，这些遗骸集中的大坟场，并没有经受涂炭的痕迹，反而平缓安宁，少有可见的变化。在布兰卡港，我努力设想，早先的贫齿类动物和今天的亲缘种一样，生活在干旱的不毛之地，就像如今在周边地区的环境。曾经，基于巴塔哥尼亚地区发现了大量美洲驼化石，我猜想这种和骆驼相似的动物曾经生活在巴塔哥尼亚地区。但由于该地区并没有发生过明显的气候变化，我曾对这一猜想感到疑惑。如今通过对美洲驼习性的揣摩，这种猜想奇异地得到了证实。不过，我们又该如何解释化石中出现的那种马的消亡呢？那些如今遍布了千万只西班牙殖民者所引进牲畜的平原曾经也经历过草场退化吗？在有些地区，我们可以认为，后来引进的一些物种吃光了以前动物的食物，这或许导致了它们的灭绝。但我们很难相信犰狳吃尽了巨大的大地獭的食物，水豚吃光了箭齿兽的食物，或者说原驼吃掉了那种很像骆驼的动物的食物。虽然从灭绝种群到现存动物发生的变化是微小的，但是鉴于我们对影响现存物种生存及健康（比如传染病之类的）的生理环境理解都相当有限，任何关于已灭绝物种的生存和灭亡原因的讨论都具有更大的不确定性。

人们倾向于相信物种的更替可以简单地归结为气候和食物的变化，天敌的引进以及其他物种数量的增长。但我们或许可以继续追问，这些变化是否在同一世内，席卷了整个北半球，以至于毁灭了西班牙海岸、西伯利亚平原以及北美洲的大象[真猛犸象（Elephas primigenus）]，同样地，还有分布范围几乎不亚于前者的野牛[原始牛（Bos urus）]？这样的变化能终结分布在欧洲和南美洲科迪勒拉山脉东坡的狭齿乳齿象（Mastodon angustidens）和化石中那种马的生命吗？如果答案是肯定的话，那这些变化就如同地球普遍降温一样具有全球性的影响，并且可以归结为地理环境的变化或者地球核心温度的降低。不过对于这些假设，我们还必须解决一个难题，即如何解释这些假想中的变化虽然不足以影响到在欧洲和南美洲的软体动物，却还是毁灭了多种分布于如今描述为寒冷、温和、热带气候地区的四足动物！这些灭绝的情形迫使我想起关于某些果树（我并不想做任何切近的类比），有人称，尽管这些果树嫁接在幼嫩的茎上，种植在不同的环境里，施以肥沃的养料，但还是在同一个时期全都枯萎凋零了。尽管是在不同时期萌发的，在这些例子里，成千上万的芽（或者说个体胚芽）都拥有一个相同的生命周期。对于大多数动物来说，每一种动物的个体看起来似乎是独立的，然而该种内的所有动物又遵循共同的法则，一如那些数量可观的单个的芽和树，或是植形动物（Zoophyte）中的珊瑚水螅。

在此还有另外一个观察需要补充。我们发现整个生物链都是以特殊的结构联结在一起的，隶属于一定的区域；但我们却很难认定这些架构只适用于某种特定的气候或者土地；否则，不同类型的动物被人类引进后，就不会繁衍得如此顺畅，甚至引起本土物种的灭绝。基于这些原因，我们认为，物种的灭绝，正如它们的诞生，并不完全取决于它们所处的地理环境（由物理条件变化而引起）。眼前我们能确定无疑的是，对于已经灭绝的生命个体及种群，它们的生命周期已经结束。

***

4月13日

小猎犬号停泊在圣克鲁斯河河口之内。这条河位于圣胡利安港以南约60英里处。在最近一次航行中，斯托克斯船长逆流而上30英里，但很快由于缺乏补给，被迫返航了。除了那趟航行时所发现的，我们对这条大河所知甚少。菲茨罗伊船长决心只要时间允许，就尽可能沿着河道而行。18日这天，三艘小艇起航，携带了三周的食品补给。船队有25人——这是一支足以抵挡一大群印第安人的力量。凭着强烈的涨潮，又加上天气晴好，我们的航行非常顺利，很快就喝到了新鲜的淡水，并且在晚间摆脱了潮汐的影响。

河流在此处呈一片宽阔的景象，非常优美，即使到了我们最后抵达的最上游，河流的宽度也几乎没有缩小。它大约有300到400码宽，中间深及17英尺。流速很快，从头到尾保持了每小时4到6节（海里/小时）的速度，这或许是它最显著的特点了。河水湛蓝，但略带一丝混浊，并不像第一眼看上去那么澄澈透亮。河床上布满了鹅卵石，与海滩和周边平原上那些鹅卵石非常接近。尽管河道弯曲，它流经的一座山谷却笔直地往西延伸。这座山谷宽窄不一，从5到10英里不等；两旁是阶梯形的台地，在大部分地方以500英尺一层的高度往上递增，而对面的谷壁与之惊人地对称。

4月19日

激流湍湍，显然完全没可能划桨或者扬帆前行。因此三艘小艇被头尾相连地紧紧系在了一起，每艘船上留下两个人，其余的人则到岸上拉纤。菲茨罗伊船长的总体安排十分妥帖，人人都工作得更顺手，也人人都搭得上手，因此我要讲述一下其中门道。这支队伍的所有人被分成轮替的两班，每班人轮换着拉纤一个半小时。每艘船的长官都和船员生活在一起，吃同一种食物，也睡在同一顶帐篷里，因此船与船之间各自独立。日落之后，遇到的第一处长有灌木的平地，会被选为我们的过夜地。每一队的每个船员轮番做饭。船一拖上岸，伙夫就生起火来；另外两个人则搭建帐篷；舵手从船上递物品；其余的人则把这些东西运到帐篷里，收集柴火。就这般井然有序，不到一个半小时，便万事俱备，只等着过夜了。始终有两个船员和一位长官一起值夜，他们负责看管船只、维护篝火，以及防备印第安人。队伍中的每个人每晚轮值一小时。

这一天，我们只前行了一段很短的距离，因为航路上有许多荆棘丛生的小岛，其间的水道极浅。

4月20日

我们越过了多岛的河段，开始工作。我们的日常跋涉虽然十分艰苦，但每天大致能抵达平均直线距离在10英里的地方，总的来说可能有15到20英里。远离昨天过夜之处，我们面对的便是全然未知的土地了，因为斯托克斯船长就是自此返航的。我们瞧见远处有浓烟升起，发现了一匹马的尸骨，因此我们知道印第安人就在附近。第二天（21日）早上发现了一群马奔腾而过的足迹，也观察到许多长矛在地面上拖曳的印痕。基本上可以判断，他们一定在夜间来侦察过我们。没过多久，我们来到一处地方，那里大人、孩子和马匹的足迹犹新，显然这一队人马刚刚渡河而去。

***

4月29日

站在一处高地上，我们兴奋地看见科迪勒拉山脉那积雪皑皑的峰顶于晦暗不明的云雾中若隐若现。在接下来的几天里，我们行程滞缓，因为河道曲折，还散落着各种古老的板岩和花岗岩的巨大碎块。在此处，河谷周围的台地高度可达1100英尺，而且地貌特征发生了明显的改变。浑圆的斑岩鹅卵石中混杂了许多巨大、棱角分明的玄武岩和上述两种岩石的碎块。我注意到的第一块漂砾距离最近的山有67英里；另一块，漂移的距离相对较近，有5码见方，从砾石地上耸起5英尺高。它的边缘棱角突出，体积庞然，起先我还误以为这是一块未经漂移的巨石，拿出指南针来观测它的节理[12]走向。此处的台地不似靠近海边的平原那般平整，然而也几乎没有迹象表明它们曾遭遇过剧烈的变动。我认为，在这种情况下，冰川运动是唯一合理的结论，即当这片土地还在水下时，冰川的移动使岩石呈现出此种形态。但针对这一话题，我还将进行更详细的讨论。

在过去的两天里，我们看到了马匹的足迹，还有几样属于印第安人的小物件——像是斗篷的残片以及一束鸵鸟羽毛——不过它们似乎被遗弃在地上很久了。印第安人最近刚渡河的地方与这里相距遥远，其间的这一片土地似乎人迹罕至。起初，鉴于这里原驼数量颇丰，我对此感到相当讶异；但是我随后又想到这一片的地面多石，没有打过马掌的马会在追猎中迅速败下阵来，因此这一处少见印第安人也就不那么令人惊讶了。尽管如此，我还是在这片中心的两处地方发现了一些小石堆，在我看来它们不像是偶然落在那里堆成的。它们被摆放成尖尖的一堆，凸立于最高的火山岩悬崖边缘，与德西雷港附近的石堆很像，但规模要小一点儿。

5月4日

菲茨罗伊船长决定不再让船往上游航行了。河道曲折蜿蜒，水流汹涌湍急；这片土地的景观也不足以吸引人前行。到处都是同样的物产，到处都是同样单调的景致。这时我们距离大西洋140英里，离最近的太平洋臂弯约有60英里。河谷在这一段上游处扩展成一个宽阔的盆地，北面和南面以玄武岩台地为界，前方则是一列白雪覆盖的科迪勒拉山脉。然而，我们相当遗憾地望着这些宏伟的大山，因为我们只能去想象它们的景致和物候，而不能如愿地站在山顶，俯瞰底下的平原。要尝试继续溯游而上，不仅是对时间的一种浪费，我们的补给也难以支撑。我们已连续数日只能吃半份口粮。尽管这点粮食对于大多数人的确足矣，但在我们一天的艰苦跋涉后，实在难以果腹。那些从未经此饥饿的人，才会说什么食宜七分饱、食轻宜消化的好处，快算了吧。

5月5日

我们在日出之前就起航下行了。我们顺流而下，航速迅疾，大致保持了每小时10节的速率。在这一天里我们走了相当于上行时耗费五天半艰苦跋涉的航程。8日，在经历了21天的探险后，我们抵达了小猎犬号。除我以外，人人都有这样那样的不满意；但于我而言，这一趟航程让我饱览了巴塔哥尼亚第三纪地质构造中最有趣的一部分。

[1]1英里约等于1.61千米。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明之外，均为编者注。）

[2]飞蝗原属名为Acrydium，现已改为Locusta。

[3]1英寸约等于2.54厘米。

[4]皮埃尔・安德烈・拉特雷耶（Pierre André Latreille），法国专门研究节肢类动物的动物学家，他在节肢动物分类学方面富有远见的工作为他赢得了尊重和赞誉，其中包括为乔治・居维叶（Georges Cuvier）《勒涅动物》写关于节肢动物的那一卷，那也是唯一一卷不是居维叶本人写的。

[5]1码约等于0.91米。

[6]1里格等于3.18海里。——译者注

[7]在拉特雷耶系统中，Notopods为一种短肢十足类甲壳纲动物，通常包括人面蟹（Homola）、关公蟹（Dorippe）、绵蟹（Dromia）、贝绵蟹（Dynomene）、蛙蟹（Ranina）等。

[8]1英尺约等于30.48厘米。

[9]地质年代分期中的一级。“世”（Epoch）以上为“纪”（Period），“世”以下为“期”（Age）。全新世是地质时代最新阶段，第四纪二分的第二个世，开始于12，000至10，000年前，持续至今。

[10]Port Famine，即哈姆布雷港（Puerto del Hambre），是麦哲伦海峡北岸布埃纳湾的一个历史悠久的定居点。

[11]现在的学名为Theristicus melanopis。

[12] 节理也称为裂隙，是一种常见的构造地质现象，是岩体受力断裂后两侧岩块没有显著位移的小型断裂构造。

火地岛

1832年12月17日

在结束了巴塔哥尼亚的考察之后，我打算说一说初抵火地岛的情形。正午刚过，我们绕过圣地亚哥角，进入了著名的勒梅尔海峡。我们紧靠火地岛航行，然而埃斯塔多斯岛[13]那怪石嶙峋、凶险的轮廓却在云雾中隐约可见。下午时分，我们在顺遂湾抛锚停泊。在驶入海湾时，我们便见到了这个蛮荒之地的典型居民。一群火地岛人停歇于突出在海里的尖岬上，身子半掩在枝蔓横生的密林里；当我们经过时，他们突然跳了出来，挥舞着破破烂烂的斗篷，向我们大声地喊叫。这些土著人追着船跑，刚到傍晚就见他们亮起了火把，接着又听见了他们狂野的呼喊声。港湾里的水相当澄澈，被一片低矮平缓的泥板岩山半围着，山上浓荫覆盖，幽林一直延伸到水边。只凭一瞥我就知道，眼前的风景与往日所见的其他景致截然不同。晚上刮起了一阵大风，从山顶刮来的风暴横扫过我们。这时候要还是在海上就糟糕透了，因此我们称这个给了我们庇护的港湾为“顺遂湾”。

清晨，船长派出了一个小队与火地岛人沟通。当我们迎着他们的欢呼声向前时，四个土著人代表中的一个上前迎向我们，极为热烈地对着我们大吼大叫，想要引导我们从哪里登陆。我们上岸后，他们看起来十分警戒，然而还是一边喋喋不休，一边快速地比画着手势。毫无疑问，这是我见识过的最稀奇、最有趣的情景了。我无法相信野蛮人和文明人之间的差距竟有这么大，它比野生动物和家养动物之间的差距要大得多，因为人的进化力要更强一些。领头说话的是一位老人，看起来像是一族之长；另外三位则是身强力壮的年轻人，约有6英尺高。妇人和孩子已经被送走了。这些火地岛人与更西边那些矮小、不幸的可怜人是完全不同的人种。他们在外貌上要出色得多，看起来更接近于麦哲伦海峡的巴塔哥尼亚人。他们唯一的衣服是一件原驼皮制成的披风，毛面朝外；他们就把披风挂在肩膀上，身子半遮挡半袒露着。他们的皮肤是乌沉沉的赤铜色。

老人头上缠着一圈白色羽毛的头带，略微拢住了他毛糙、纠结的黑发。他的脸上画着两道粗粗的横纹；一道鲜红色，从一只耳朵延伸到另一只耳朵，还覆盖了上嘴唇；另一道，像是白垩画的，在第一道的上方平行地展开，因此连眼睑也染成了白色。另外三个人中有两个的脸上装饰着木炭画的黑色粉状条纹。这几个人待在一起活像舞台上演出的魔鬼，诸如《魔弹射手》之类的。

他们的姿态卑微，脸上则带着狐疑、惊讶和恐惧的表情。我们赠送给他们几块红色的布匹，他们立刻就围在了脖子上，这才变得友好起来。这情谊是通过老人拍打我们的胸部来表达的，同时，他们还发出咯咯响的声音，就像人们在喂食小鸡。我和老人一道走路，这证明友谊的仪式重复了数次；最后以在我前胸后背同时重重地击打三下而告终。然后他向我袒露胸部，让我礼尚往来，待我做过这一套之后，他显得十分称心满意。这些人的语言，在我们听来根本不算是吐字。库克船长曾把它比作是一个人清嗓子发出的声音，然而毫无疑问，没有一个欧洲人会在清嗓子时发出这么多粗糙、刺耳、咯咯作响的声音。

他们是极为出色的模仿者：每当我们咳嗽，或者打哈欠，或者做出什么古怪动作，他们立刻就照样学起来。我们这边的人开始挤眉弄眼；然而一个年轻的火地岛人（整张脸都涂黑了，只在眼睛这里横抹了一道白色的带状纹）成功地做出了一个更骇人的鬼脸。他们能分毫不差地重复我们对他们说的一字一句，还能把这些单词记上好一阵子。可是我们欧洲人都知道，要分辨一门外语中不同的发音有多难。比如说，我们中有哪一位，能跟读一句美洲印第安人超过三个单词的句子呢？未开化的人似乎都拥有这种非凡的模仿能力。有人曾经跟我说过差不多同样的话，南非的卡非人有一模一样搞笑的模仿习惯；同样的，澳大利亚原住民很久以来都以擅于仿照、描绘别人的步态而闻名，并且以此来辨别外来者。这等天赋又该如何解释？这是否是由于与那些长期处于文明状态的人相比，所有那些未开化的人都有着更加熟练的洞察方式和更加灵敏的感官？

当我们这伙人唱起歌时，火地岛人惊讶得仿佛要跌坐在地。他们以同样惊诧的表情看着我们跳舞，不过有一个小伙子，在我们邀请他时，毫不抵触地跳了一小段华尔兹。虽然他们表面看起来并不适应欧洲文化，但他们还是知道并且害怕我们的火器；没有东西能诱惑他们用手去摸一把枪。他们十分渴求刀子，用西班牙语“库奇亚”来称呼这些刀子。他们还用动作来比画他们想要的东西，看起来就像嘴里叼着一块鲸脂，然后假装用刀去切，而不是用手撕扯。

观察这些人对待杰米・巴顿（一个火地岛人，在前一趟探险中被带到了英格兰）的举止十分有意思。他们立即意识到了杰米和我们的不同，并就此相互之间热烈地讨论起来。老人对杰米发表了长篇大论，似乎想要邀请他与他们生活在一起。可是杰米只听得懂一丁点儿他们的语言，此外，也根本看不上他的同胞们。当约克・明斯特（另一个到过英格兰的火地岛人）来到岸上时，他们同样注意到了他，并告诉他应该刮胡子了；尽管他脸上并没有多少胡楂，而我们则全都胡子拉碴。他们仔细察看他的肤色，还拿他和我们的做比较。我们中有一位的胳膊露了出来，他们对白皙的肤色惊讶不已，十分艳羡。我们认为他们误把两三位身材更矮小、长相更俊俏的长官错认为我们这伙人里的女士了，尽管他们也留着大胡子。火地岛人当中最高的一位对于有人注意到他的身高显然颇为自得。当他与船上个子最高的那位背对背站着的时候，还极力站在高一点儿的地方，拼命踮着脚。他张开嘴显露他的牙齿，偏过头展示他的侧颜；他乐意之至地做着这些事，我敢说，他一定以为自己是火地岛最俊俏的男子。等我们最初的大惊小怪过去之后，这些原住民每时每刻表现出来的混杂着惊讶和模仿的反应则成为最为搞笑、最为有意思的事。

第二天，我试图深入探索这一地区。火地岛或许称得上是多山地区，它的一部分沉在了海里，因此原本是山谷的地方，就变成了水深不见底的小洲和海湾。除了西海岸寸草不生的山坡，其余山坡从与水面相接的地方开始便被茫茫林海所覆盖。树木生长到1000至1500英尺的高度；随后是一条泥煤带，分布着矮小的高山植物；再往上则是终年不化的积雪了，按照金船长的记录，麦哲伦海峡的雪线高度为3000到4000英尺。想要在这片土地上找到哪怕是1英亩[14]平整的地都稀罕至极。我只记得在饥荒港附近有一小块平地，另一块面积大得多的则位于戈里路德附近。这两块平地以及其他平地上，地面全都覆盖着一层厚厚的沼泽泥煤。即使在森林里，地面也密覆着大量缓慢腐化的植被，浸透了水，脚一踏上去就会往下陷。

在密林中我几乎寸步难行，于是便改道，沿着一条山中径流探寻。起初，飞瀑横流，枯木倒地，简直举步维艰；不过水流冲刷两岸，溪床很快就变得宽一些了。我继续沿着崎岖、多石的岸边缓慢走了一个小时，壮丽的景色令我不虚此行。昏朦幽暗、深不见底的峡谷完美地呼应了无处不在的剧烈变动的痕迹。峡谷两侧尽是一些嶙峋的巨石和折断的树；而其余的树，虽然还直立着，但也已经从中间腐烂，随时可能倒下来。这种生机盎然的树和倒伏的枯树纠葛缠绕在一起的状态让我想起了热带雨林——然而还是有所不同，因为在这一片死寂的荒野之中，看起来是死亡主宰了一切，而非生机。我顺着水流的方向走，来到了一处地方，大滑坡给这里的山坡清出了一片直着向下的空地。沿着这条路，我攀登到相当高的地方，得以视角颇佳地一览周遭树林。这些树全都属于一个种类——桦状假水青冈木（Fagus betuloides），而其他种类的山毛榉和林仙树的数量简直可以忽略不计了。这种树的叶子终年不落，然而叶片的颜色呈一种颇为奇异的棕绿色，略微泛出一点儿黄色。由于这里的整个景观都是这个色调，便显得阴郁、沉闷，即使在阳光的映照下，也未见几多活力。

[13]此处原文为Staten，翻译时选用了更通用的Isla de los Estados。——译者注

[14]1英亩约等于4046.86平方米。

麦哲伦海峡

12月21日

小猎犬号再次起航。在接下来的几天里，受益于一阵难得的轻柔东风，航行异常顺利，我们离巴讷费尔茨越来越近了，船驶过欺骗角怪石嶙峋的海岬，又在3点钟绕过了风雨剥蚀的合恩角。当天夜里风平浪静，月色朗朗，宜于眺望远处，看山是如何在视线中越来越高。

火地岛人两度来袭，我们不胜其扰。由于岸上有不少器械、衣物，也不乏人手，我们觉得很有必要把他们吓走。头一回，在他们还离得相当远的时候，我们开了几炮。最滑稽可笑的是，我们从单筒望远镜里瞧见，每当炮弹落到水里，这些印第安人就捡起石块，勇敢地进行反击，朝我们的船投掷石头，尽管我们相隔约1.5英里！接着我们派出了一条小船，命令是用火枪横扫一气，但要避免射中。火地岛人藏身在树后面；对于我们的每一次射击，他们都会射箭回击，然而，所有的箭都不能到达船所在的范围之内，船上的长官指着他们哈哈大笑。这使得火地岛人怒火中烧，他们枉然地挥动着斗篷，恼怒不已。最后，他们看到枪弹击倒了树木，才落荒而逃；而我们也获得了和平与安宁。

上一回，当小猎犬号2月份泊在此地的时候，我在一个早晨4点钟出发去攀登塔恩山，这座山有2600英尺高，是邻近地区的最高点。我们划了一条小船到山脚下（不过并非最佳登山地点），然后开始了我们的登山之旅。森林从高水位线处开始生长，而在最初的两个钟头里，我几乎完全丧失了爬到山顶的希望。森林过于茂密，我们必须不断地求助于指南针；尽管是在山区，然而每一处地标都彻底地给遮蔽了。在一座座幽深的峡谷里，死亡一般的荒凉景象无法用言语来形容。峡谷外狂风大作，但在这些沟壑里，甚至没有一丝风来撩动最高的树木上的树叶。处处都阴暗、寒冷、潮湿，就算是真菌、苔藓和蕨类植物都不能生长。在这些山谷里几乎寸步难行，它们完全被巨大的、朽败的树干给横七竖八地堵住了。每当人们经过这些天然形成的木桥时，膝盖时常会陷入腐烂的木头里，行进的道路也会因此中断。而别的时候，当你想要倚上一棵牢靠的树时，却错愕地发现这树只是一堆摇摇欲坠的腐物，轻轻一碰便会散落。终于，我们置身于一片矮小的树丛中，接着很快就抵达了裸露的山脊处，顺着它，我们爬向了山顶。眼前是一派典型的火地岛风貌——不规则的山脉连绵起伏，间杂着斑驳的积雪，底下是黄绿色的幽深山谷，还有一道道海湾杂乱无章地切断了陆地。风相当大，冷得刺骨，雾气弥漫不散，因此我们并没有在山顶上停留很久。下山的行程不像上山那般艰难，体重使我们不自觉地向下滑去，而所有的下滑和跌落都是向着下山的正确方向。

***

地质学中出现的最棘手的问题，起码是近几年来最棘手的问题，是如何解释西伯利亚动物标本的完好保存。一方面已确凿无疑的是，这些动物尸体并非被水流从远处携带而来，另一方面也被认为几乎无疑的是，这些动物生活的时代，气候与现在大相径庭，周围地区不可能出现冰雪，如同恒河绝无可能结冰一般。莱尔先生曾在《地质学原理》中就这一问题进行了大量的阐述：他指出现在那些向北流去的河流可能将动物尸体携带到了同一方向；他表示（引自洪堡）那些栖息于最炎热地区的动物有时候会漫游到相当远的地方；他同时提出，当动物分属不同种时，不可妄断同一属的动物就拥有同样的生活习性。而他的贡献最大的地方则体现在他清晰地指出了这一地的气候可能经历了由海岛性向极端气候的转变，这种转变是陆地抬升的结果，而最近新发掘的证据也证明了这种地质变化的存在。

在本书稍前一些的章节里，我曾竭力证明，就食物的数量而言，毫无疑问可以推断这些大型的四足动物可以生活在不毛之地，这些地区只稀稀落落地出产些植物。而大象和犀牛身上覆盖的皮毛，则证明了它们至少能够在寒冷的气候中生存（尽管这一点颇有争议，生活在最炎热地区的有些动物也身披厚厚的皮毛）。我认为难有证据可以证明，在之前的纪年里，当厚皮动物广泛地分布于世界大部分地区时，其中有些种类会不适应北部区域，这就像现在鹿和其他几种动物的分布一样离奇。如果我们认为在上述陆地抬升运动发生之前，西伯利亚的气候和如今南半球的气候相似（这一假设与其他的证据并不矛盾），那么当我们把如今北半球的现象放入相似的南半球的环境中思考时，我们可以得出以下结论：首先，早先的气候并不十分寒冷；其次，积雪并没有在一段很长的时期里不间断地覆盖地面（在南美55度到56度的极端地区情况并非如此）；再次，植物，与今天同纬度地区的植物相比，体现了更强烈的热带特征；最后，在具备如此条件的区域再向北一小段距离（甚至还未到帕拉斯发现完整犀牛尸体的地点），就可能出现永久冻土：因此，任何一种动物的尸体一旦埋在地表下几英尺之处，它都将被保存数个世纪之久。

洪堡和莱尔都曾提及，如今，永久冻土带延伸至北纬62度，任何动物漂流进冻土带内，万一凑巧被埋在地表数英尺底下，便会无限期地得以保存。同样的情形发生在被河流冲刷而来的尸体上；而那些灭绝的哺乳动物或许正是这样葬身的。对我来说，这一理论只差一步就能完成，并且能够以一种比几个早先提出的理论更简洁的方式来解释这一现象。根据莱尔先生的描述，西伯利亚平原上堆积着来自世世代代动物的数不清的骨化石，毫无疑问这地层是从浅海或是河口堆积起来的。而正如比齐在埃舍尔茨湾的游记里曾描述的，这一过程也适用于美洲的西北海岸：那里的地质构造看起来与沿海常见的新近抬升的自然沉积相同，而我曾在同一片大陆的南部海岸见到过这种沉积。还有一点确定的是，西伯利亚遗骸只在河流截断平原之处暴露。这一事实，再加上全新世抬升的证据，说明这一过程似乎与发生在南美洲潘帕斯大草原的情形极其类似：也就是说，那些尸体是在早先漂流进入的大海，而遗骸是随后被逐步积累的沉积层包裹起来的。从那以后这些地层抬高；随着河流冲刷出它们的河道，掩埋的骨骼也就逐渐暴露。

那么这里，难点来了：尸体在海底是如何被保存的呢？值得引起充分注意的是，被保全的动物尸体并不常见，也并不会因为它们所处极北之地就变得容易保存。居维叶提到比林航海记中曾记载了在勒拿河以及茵迪吉尔卡河河口之间的岛屿上发现了大量的大象、野牛和犀牛的骨头，其数量是别处无可比拟的。甚至有这样的说法——除了一些由岩石组成的小山丘，整个地区都是由沙子、冰块和骨头构成的。这些岛屿位于亚当斯发现骨肉完好的猛犸象之处的北面，在维柳依河更向北10度的地方，而在维柳依河中也发现了保存完好的犀牛。对于发现的骨头，我们推测尸体漂浮到更深的大海，在那里它们停留在海底，肉身腐烂分解。但是针对第二种更为特殊的情形，腐败似乎被中止了，尸体很有可能迅速地被随之积累起来的沉积物覆盖住。或许有人会提出疑问，在那些底部终年冰冻的浅海，数英尺深的泥土温度是否高于华氏32度（零摄氏度）？但我们需要记住的是，要使盐水结冰，需要比零摄氏度更低的温度；而在海水深处的淤泥，温度一定相当之低，与那些夏天短暂但炎热地区的冰冻带底下的土层一模一样。如果这些条件得以满足，那么埋藏这些灭绝的四足动物就容易理解了，并且理解它们先前生存环境的主要难题也被解决了。

***

有一种海洋植物，因其十分重要，也值得被额外记录，它就是海带，或者说是巨岩藻（Fucus giganteus）。从低潮线到海底深处，这种植物生长在每一块岩石上，既分布于外海岸，也繁衍于海峡内。我相信，在冒险号和小猎犬号的航程里，近海面处发现的每一块礁石上，都有这种海藻，如浮标一样地漂荡着。因此，它给在这一带暴风骤雨的海域里行驶的船只所提供的巨大帮助是显而易见的；它确实拯救了很多轮船，使它们免于失事。看到这种植物在大洋西部的滔滔激浪中生长、繁盛，着实令人震惊。因为在海洋的这个部位，即使是那些巨大的礁石，无论有多么坚硬，都无法长久抵御波浪的侵蚀。它的茎是圆的，黏糊、滑溜，直径很少能达到1英寸。数根海带合在一起，就强壮到足以支撑起几块分散的大石头了，在切入内陆的海峡里，它们正是依附在这样的石块上生长的。而这些石块有的非常沉重，它们被拉到水面后，几乎不可能凭一人之力把它们搬到船上去。

库克船长在他第二次探险中说过，在凯尔盖朗地区，“一部分这种海藻长度达到了不可思议的地步，尽管它的茎还没有人的拇指那么粗。我曾提到过，在它们生长的有些浅滩里，我们用一根24英寻[15]长的线都没有探到底。因此，水下的深度，一定超过了这个数字。由于这种海藻并不是垂直生长的，而是和海底形成了一个很小的锐角，并且它的主体随后在海面上大幅度地伸展开去，我可以很有把握地说其中有些的长度达到了60英寻以上。”虽然在福克兰群岛（马尔维纳斯群岛）以及火地岛周围，宽广无边的海藻常常从10到15英寻深的水里突然冒出，但我不认为任何植物的茎能像库克船长所记录的那样，长达360英尺。它分布的地理范围相当广大；从合恩角附近最南端的小群岛，到东海岸的最北边（据斯托克斯先生提供给我的信息）南纬43度都有所发现——而在西边，南纬42度的智鲁岛，它的数量也颇为可观，但还不到繁茂的程度。它可能还略微往北延伸了一点儿，但很快被别的物种所取代。因此我们认为它分布的范围南北延伸15度；而据对这一物种相当熟悉的库克记载，他在凯尔盖朗地区也发现了这种生物，因此它分布的经度范围横跨了至少140度。

而海藻也成为其他数量令人惊讶的物种赖以生存的植物。光是描述栖居在这种海藻群落里的动物，大约就能写成鸿篇大论。除了漂浮在海面上的以外，几乎每一片叶子上都厚厚地结了一层珊瑚虫的硬壳，叶子几乎变成了白色。我们发现了这些栖息着珊瑚虫的叶子构成异常精巧复杂，有一些栖息着简单的水螅一样的珊瑚虫，另外一些则寄居着器官更复杂的种类，以及漂亮的群居海鞘。在叶片平滑的表面上还黏附着各种各样的笠状螺、马蹄螺、无壳软体动物，以及一些蚌类。无以数计的甲壳类动物时常出没于植株的各个部位。要是把庞杂、纠缠在一起的根部摇晃一番，就会有一堆小鱼、贝类、墨鱼、各种螃蟹、海胆、海星、美丽的海参（有一些呈现为裸鳃亚目软体动物的外形）、三角涡虫，以及形状殊异的蠕动的沙蚕，纷纷披落。我再三碰到这种海藻，每一根枝叶上都会发现新的、奇特的动物组合。我曾提到过在智鲁岛，这种海藻并不十分繁茂，因此并不能见到数量庞大的贝类、珊瑚虫类，以及甲壳类动物，但仍然有一些板枝介类动物和数种群居的海鞘类动物，而后者，与火地岛的海鞘动物种类并不相同。在这里，我们发现石衣藻比起寄居在它那里的动物，分布的范围要广泛得多。

我只能把南半球这些繁茂的水中森林与热带地区的陆地森林做比较。如果后者在任何地方遭到毁灭，我相信，其动物的种类消失的数量之巨，不会比在同样情况下，海藻灭绝引起的动物消亡更多。在这种植物的叶片之间生活着无数种鱼类，它们在别的地方找不到食物和庇护所。由于它们的灭亡，大量的鸬鹚、潜鸟，以及其他以鱼为食的鸟类、海獭、海豹和鼠海豚也会随即覆灭，那么最终，火地岛的野蛮人——这片悲惨土地的悲惨主人，同类相残的情形就会变本加厉，其人口会减少，或许也将绝种了。

6月8日

我们一大早就起了锚，离开了饥荒港。菲茨罗伊船长决定离开麦哲伦海峡，沿着前不久才发现的玛格达伦海峡而行。我们的航线设定为正南方，顺着我此前提到过的晦暗通道而下，仿佛要驶向另一个更糟糕的世界。一路顺风，但空气并不清明，因此我们错过了不少奇异的景观。群山间乌云滚滚，从山顶到山脚皆云倾雾缭。从团团浓云间瞥见的景致令人兴味盎然：参差起伏的山尖、形如圆锥的积雪、一碧如洗的冰川、苍白天空下分明的天际线，远近高低，各有不同。就在这一派风光中，我们在图恩角抛了锚，靠近当时正隐在云雾中的萨缅托峰。就在高耸、几近直立的山脚下，我们的小港湾这里，有一座废弃的棚屋，它形单影只，提醒我们曾经有人漫游到这一带荒无人烟的地区，而在这，他又是如何无可比拟地渺小、卑微。大自然所创造的没有生命的作品——石、冰、雪、风和水——彼此间相互争斗，但又联合起来与人为敌——在这里，它们拥有了绝对的权威。

6月9日

清晨，我们十分喜悦地看到一层薄雾从萨缅托峰冉冉升起，而山峰在我们眼前逐渐显露。这座山是火地岛最高的山峰之一，海拔6800英尺。山脚下，大约整个山体高度的1/8覆盖着幽暗的树林，再往上则是一片积雪，一直延伸到山顶。这铺天盖地的冰雪从不融化，仿佛命定要和这世界一起地久天长，呈现出一派崇高甚至超然卓异的光景。这座山峰的轮廓格外清晰、分明。由于雪白、闪耀的山表反射了十分充足的光线，山体上没有一处被阴影笼罩；而那些切断天际的雪线也明晰可辨：因此山体如同鲜明的浮雕般凸现出来。有好几条冰川蜿蜒而下，从积雪区绵延到海岸边：或许可以把它们比作冰封的尼亚加拉大瀑布；而这些凝结的蓝色瀑布也完全可以和湍湍而流的飞瀑媲美。夜晚，我们抵达海峡的西部；然而这里的水太深了，我们找不到可抛锚之处。因此我们不得不离岸前行，在大海的这条狭长的臂弯里，熬过长达14个小时的伸手不见五指的暗黑夜晚。

6月10日

黎明，我们竭力驶入了开阔的太平洋。这里的西海岸通常由低矮、和缓、颇为贫瘠的花岗岩和绿岩小山丘构成。约翰・纳伯勒爵士把一处地方称为“南部废墟”，因为这“看起来是多么萧疏的一方土地”，恐怕他所言确实。数不清的礁石散布在主岛之外，壮阔的大海掀起长长的骇浪，永无停歇地冲击着它们。我们从东、西弗里斯岛之间驶出，从那里略微往北，碎浪飞珠溅玉，这一带的大海因此被称为“银河”。陆地上的人只消看一眼这里的海岸，就会在一整个礼拜里都陷入关于沉船、海难和死亡的噩梦；伴随着眼前的景象，我们就此与火地岛永远作别。

[15]英寻是海洋测量中的深度单位，1英寻等于1.852米。

Patagonia

December 6th, 1833 – The Beagle sailed from the Rio Plata, never again to enter its muddy stream. Our course was directed to Port Desire, on the coast of Patagonia. Before proceeding any further, I will here put together a few observations made at sea.

Several times when the ship has been some miles off the mouth of the Plata, and at other times when off the shores of Northern Patagonia, we have been surrounded by insects. One evening, when we were about ten miles from the Bay of San Blas, vast numbers of butterflies, in bands or flocks of countless myriads, extended as far as the eye could range. Even by the aid of a glass it was not possible to see a space free from butterflies. The seamen cried out ‘it was snowing butterflies’, and such in fact was the appearance. More species than one were present, but the main part belonged to a kind very similar to, but not identical with, the common English Colias edusa. Some moths and hymenoptera accompanied the butterflies; and a fine Calosoma flew on board. Other instances are known of this beetle having been caught far out at sea; and this is the more remarkable, as the greater number of the Carabidæ seldom or never take wing. The day had been fine and calm, and the one previous to it equally so, with light and variable airs. Hence we cannot suppose that the insects were blown off the land, but we must conclude that they voluntarily took flight. The great bands of the Colias seem at first to afford an instance like those on record of the migrations of Vanessa cardui; but the presence of other insects makes the case distinct, and not so easily intelligible. Before sunset, a strong breeze sprung up from the north, and this must have been the cause of tens of thousands of the butterflies and other insects having perished.

On another occasion, when 17 miles off Cape Corrientes, I had a net overboard to catch pelagic animals. Upon drawing it up, to my surprise I found a considerable number of beetles in it, and although in the open sea, they did not appear much injured by the salt water. I lost some of the specimens, but those which I preserved, belonged to the genera, colymbetes, hydroporus, hydrobius (two species), notaphus, cynucus, adimonia, and scarabæus. At first, I thought that these insects had been blown from the shore; but upon reflecting that out of the eight species, four were aquatic, and two others partly so in their habits, it appeared to me most probable that they were floated into the sea, by a small stream which drains a lake near Cape Corrientes. On any supposition, it is an interesting circumstance to find insects, quite alive, swimming in the open ocean, 17 miles from the nearest point of land. There are several accounts of insects having been blown off the Patagonian shore. Captain Cook observed it, as did more lately Captain King in the Adventure. The cause probably is due to the want of shelter, both of trees and hills, so that an insect on the wing with an off- shore breeze, would be very apt to be blown out to sea. The most remarkable instance I ever knew of an insect being caught far from the land, was that of a large grasshopper (Acrydium), which flew on board, when the Beagle was to windward of the Cape de Verd Islands, and when the nearest point of land, not directly opposed to the trade- wind, was Cape Blanco on the coast of Africa, 370 miles distant.

On several occasions, when the vessel has been within the mouth of the Plata, the rigging has been coated with the web of the Gossamer Spider. One day (November 1st, 1832) I paid particular attention to the phenomenon. The weather had been fine and clear, and in the morning the air was full of patches of the flocculent web, as on an autumnal day in England. The ship was sixty miles distant from the land, in the direction of a steady though light breeze. Vast numbers of a small spider, about one- tenth of an inch in length, and of a dusky red colour were attached to the webs. There must have been, I should suppose, some thousands on the ship. The little spider when first coming in contact with the rigging, was always seated on a single thread, and not on the flocculent mass. This latter seems merely to be produced by the entanglement of the single threads. The spiders were all of one species, but of both sexes, together with young ones. These latter were distinguished by their smaller size, and more dusky colour. I will not give the description of this spider, but merely state that it does not appear to me to be included in any of Latreille’s genera. The little aeronaut as soon as it arrived on board, was very active, running about; sometimes letting itself fall, and then reascending the same thread; sometimes employing itself in making a small and very irregular mesh in the corners between the ropes. It could run with facility on the surface of water. When disturbed it lifted up its front legs, in the attitude of attention. On its first arrival it appeared very thirsty, and with exserted maxillæ drank eagerly of the fluid; this same circumstance has been observed by Strack: may it not be in consequence of the little insect having passed through a dry and rarefied atmosphere? Its stock of web seemed inexhaustible. While watching some that were suspended by a single thread, I several times observed that the slightest breath of air bore them away out of sight, in a horizontal line. On another occasion (25th) under similar circumstances, I repeatedly observed the same kind of small spider, either when placed, or having crawled, on some little eminence, elevate its abdomen, send forth a thread, and then sail away in a lateral course, but with a rapidity which was quite unaccountable. I thought I could perceive that the spider before performing the above preparatory steps, connected its legs together with the most delicate threads, but I am not sure, whether this observation is correct.

One day, at St Fe, I had a better opportunity of observing some similar facts. A spider which was about three- tenths of an inch in length, and which in its general appearance resembled a Citigrade (therefore quite different from the gossamer), while standing on the summit of a post, darted forth four or five threads from its spinners. These glittering in the sunshine, might be compared to rays of light; they were not, however, straight, but in undulations like a film of silk blown by the wind. They were more than a yard in length, and diverged in an ascending direction from the orifices. The spider then suddenly let go its hold, and was quickly borne out of sight. The day was hot and apparently quite calm; yet under such circumstances the atmosphere can never be so tranquil, as not to affect a vane so delicate as the thread of a spider’s web. If during a warm day we look either at the shadow of any object cast on a bank, or over a level plain at a distant landmark, the effect of an ascending current of heated air will almost always be evident. And this probably would be sufficient to carry with it so light an object as the little spider on its thread. The circumstance of spiders of the same species but of different sexes and ages, being found on several occasions at the distance of many leagues from the land, attached in vast numbers to the lines, proves that they are the manufacturers of the mesh, and that the habit of sailing through the air, is probably as characteristic of some tribe, as that of diving is of the Argyroneta. We may then reject Latreille’s supposition, that the gossamer owes its origin to the webs of the young of several genera, as Epeira or Thomisa: although, as we have seen that the young of other spiders do possess the power of performing aerial voyages.

During our different passages south of the Plata, I often towed astern a net made of bunting, and thus caught many curious animals. The structure of the Beroe (a kind of jelly fish) is most extraordinary, with its rows of vibratory ciliæ, and complicated though irregular system of circulation. Of Crustacea, there were many strange and undescribed genera. One, which in some respects is allied to the Notopods (or those crabs which have their posterior legs placed almost on their backs, for the purpose of adhering to the under side of ledges), is very remarkable from the structure of its hind pair of legs. The penultimate joint, instead of being terminated by a simple claw, ends in three bristle- like appendages of dissimilar lengths, the longest equalling that of the entire leg. These claws are very thin, and are serrated with teeth of an excessive fineness, which are directed towards the base. The curved extremities are flattened, and on this part five most minute cups are placed, which seem to act in the same manner as the suckers on the arms of the cuttle- fish. As the animal lives in the open sea, and probably wants a place of rest, I suppose this beautiful structure is adapted to take hold of the globular bodies of the Medusæ, and other floating marine animals.

In deep water, far from the land, the number of living creatures is extremely small: south of the latitude 35°, I never succeeded in catching any thing besides some beroe, and a few species of minute crustacea belonging to the Entomostraca. In shoaler water, at the distance of a few miles from the coast, very many kinds of crustacea and some other animals were numerous, but only during the night. Between latitudes 56° and 57° south of Cape Horn the net was put astern several times; it never, however, brought up any thing besides a few of two extremely minute species of Entomostraca. Yet whales and seals, petrels and albatross, are exceedingly abundant throughout this part of the ocean. It has always been a source of mystery to me, on what the latter, which live far from the shore, can subsist. I presume the albatross, like the condor, is able to fast long; and that one good feast on the carcass of a putrid whale lasts for a long siege of hunger. It does not lessen the difficulty to say, they feed on fish; for on what can the fish feed? It often occurred to me, when observing how the waters of the central and intertropical parts of the Atlantic, swarmed with Pteropoda, Crustacea, and Radiata, and with their devourers the flying- fish, and again with their devourers the bonitos and albicores, that the lowest of these pelagic animals perhaps possess the power of decomposing carbonic acid gas, like the members of the vegetable kingdom.

While sailing in these latitudes on one very dark night, the sea presented a wonderful and most beautiful spectacle. There was a fresh breeze, and every part of the surface, which during the day is seen as foam, now glowed with a pale light. The vessel drove before her bows two billows of liquid phosphorus, and in her wake she was followed by a milky train. As far as the eye reached, the crest of every wave was bright, and the sky above the horizon, from the reflected glare of these livid flames, was not so utterly obscure, as over the rest of the heavens.

As we proceed further southward, the sea is seldom phosphorescent; and off Cape Horn, I do not recollect more than once having seen it so, and then it was far from being brilliant. This circumstance probably has a close connexion with the scarcity of organic beings in that part of the ocean. After the elaborate paper by Ehrenberg, on the phosphorescence of the sea, it is almost superfluous on my part to make any observations on the subject. I may however add, that the same torn and irregular particles of gelatinous matter, described by Ehrenberg, seem in the southern as well as in the northern hemisphere, to be the common cause of this phenomenon. The particles were so minute as easily to pass through fine gauze; yet many were distinctly visible by the naked eye. The water when placed in a tumbler and agitated gave out sparks, but a small portion in a watch- glass, scarcely ever was luminous. Ehrenberg states, that these particles all retain a certain degree of irritability. My observations, some of which were made directly after taking up the water, would give a different result. I may also mention, that having used the net during one night I allowed it to become partially dry, and having occasion twelve hours afterwards, to employ it again, I found the whole surface sparkled as brightly as when first taken out of the water. It does not appear probable in this case, that the particles could have remained so long alive. I remark also in my notes, that having kept a Medusa of the genus Dianæa, till it was dead, the water in which it was placed became luminous. When the waves scintillate with bright green sparks, I believe it is generally owing to minute crustacea. But there can be no doubt that very many other pelagic animals, when alive, are phosphorescent.

On two occasions I have observed the sea luminous at considerable depths beneath the surface. Near the mouth of the Plata some circular and oval patches, from 2 to 4 yards in diameter, and with defined outlines, shone with a steady, but pale light; while the surrounding water only gave out a few sparks. The appearance resembled the reflection of the moon, or some luminous body; for the edges were sinuous from the undulation of the surface. The ship, which drew thirteen feet water, passed over, without disturbing, these patches. Therefore we must suppose that some animals were congregated together at a greater depth than the bottom of the vessel.

Near Fernando Noronha the sea gave out light in flashes. The appearance was very similar to that which might be expected from a large fish moving rapidly through a luminous fluid. To this cause the sailors attributed it; at the time, however, I entertained some doubts, on account of the frequency and rapidity of the flashes. With respect to any general observations, I have already stated that the display is very much more common in warm than in cold countries. I have sometimes imagined that a disturbed electrical condition of the atmosphere was most favourable to its production. Certainly I think the sea is most luminous after a few days of more calm weather than ordinary, during which time it has swarmed with various animals. Observing that the water charged with gelatinous particles is in an impure state, and that the luminous appearance in all common cases is produced by the agitation of the fluid in contact with the atmosphere, I have always been inclined to consider that the phosphorescence was the result of the decomposition of the organic particles, by which process (one is tempted almost to call it a kind of respiration) the ocean becomes purified.

December 23rD – We arrived at Port Desire, situated in lat. 47°, on the coast of Patagonia. The creek runs for about twenty miles inland, with an irregular width. The Beagle anchored a few miles within the entrance in front of the ruins of an old Spanish settlement.

The same evening I went on shore. The first landing in any new country is very interesting, and especially when, as in this case, the whole aspect bears the stamp of a marked and individual character. At the height of between 200 and 300 feet, above some masses of porphyry, a wide plain extends, which is truly characteristic of Patagonia. The surface is quite level, and is composed of well- rounded shingle mixed with a whitish earth. Here and there scattered tufts of brown wiry grass are supported, and still more rarely some low thorny bushes. The weather is dry and pleasant, for the fine blue sky is but seldom obscured. When standing in the middle of one of these desert plains, the view on one side is generally bounded by the escarpment of another plain, rather higher, but equally level and desolate; and on the other side it becomes indistinct from the trembling mirage which seems to rise from the heated surface.

The plains are traversed by many broad, flat- bottomed valleys, and in these the bushes grow rather more abundantly. The present drainage of the country is quite insufficient to excavate such large channels. In some of the valleys ancient stunted trees, growing in the very centre of the dry watercourse, seem as if placed to prove how long a time had elapsed, since any flood had passed that way. We have evidence, from shells lying on the surface, that the plains of gravel have been elevated within a recent epoch above the level of the sea; and we must look to that period for the excavation of the valleys by the slowly retiring waters. From the dryness of the climate, a man may walk for days together over these plains without finding a single drop of water. Even at the base of the porphyry hills, there are only a few small wells containing but little water, and that rather saline and half putrid.

In such a country the fate of the Spanish settlement was soon decided; the dryness of the climate during the greater part of the year, and the occasional hostile attacks of the wandering Indians, compelled the colonists to desert their half- finished buildings. The style, however, in which they were commenced, showed the strong and liberal hand of Spain in the old time. The end of all the attempts to colonize this side of America south of 41°, have been miserable. At Port Famine, the name expresses the lingering and extreme sufferings of several hundred wretched people, of whom one alone survived to relate their misfortunes. At St Joseph’s bay, on the coast of Patagonia, a small settlement was made; but during one Sunday the Indians made an attack and massacred the whole party, excepting two men, who were led captive many years among the wandering tribes. At the Rio Negro I conversed with one of these men, now in extreme old age.

The zoology of Patagonia is as limited as its Flora. On the arid plains a few black beetles (Heteromera) might be seen slowly crawling about, and occasionally a lizard darting from side to side. Of birds we have three carrion hawks, and in the valleys a few finches and insect feeders. The Ibis malanops (a species said to be found in central Africa) is not uncommon on the most desert parts. In the stomachs of these birds I found grasshoppers, cicadæ, small lizards, and even scorpions. At one time of the year they go in flocks, at another in pairs: their cry is very loud and singular, and resembles the neighing of the guanaco.

I will here give an account of this latter animal, which is very common, and is the characteristic quadruped of the plains of Patagonia. The Guanaco, which by some naturalists is considered as the same animal with the Llama, but in its wild state, is the South American representative of the camel of the East. In size it may be compared to an ass, mounted on taller legs, and with a very long neck. The guanaco abounds over the whole of the temperate parts of South America, from the wooded islands of Tierra del Fuego, through Patagonia, the hilly parts of La Plata, Chile, even to the Cordillera of Peru. Although preferring an elevated site, it yields in this respect to its near relative the Vicuna. On the plains of Southern Patagonia, we saw them in greater numbers than in any other part. Generally they go in small herds, from half a dozen to thirty together; but on the banks of the St Cruz we saw one herd which must have contained at least 500. On the northern shores of the Strait of Magellan they are also very numerous.

Generally the guanacoes are wild and extremely wary. Mr Stokes told me, that he one day saw through a glass a herd of these beasts, which evidently had been frightened, running away at full speed, although their distance was so great that they could not be distinguished by the naked eye. The sportsman frequently receives the first intimation of their presence, by hearing, from a long distance, the peculiar shrill neighing note of alarm. If he then looks attentively, he will perhaps see the herd standing in a line on the side of some distant hill. On approaching them, a few more squeals are given, and then off they set at an apparently slow, but really quick canter, along some narrow beaten track to a neighbouring hill. If, however, by chance he should abruptly meet a single animal, or several together, they will generally stand motionless, and intently gaze at him; then perhaps move on a few yards, turn round, and look again. What is the cause of this difference in their shyness? Do they mistake a man in the distance for their chief enemy the puma? Or does curiosity overcome their timidity? That they are curious is certain; for if a person lies on the ground, and plays strange antics, such as throwing up his feet in the air, they will almost always approach by degrees to reconnoitre him. It was an artifice that was repeatedly practised by our sportsmen with success, and it had moreover the advantage of allowing several shots to be fired, which were all taken as parts of the performance. On the mountains of Tierra del Fuego, and in other places, I have more than once seen a guanaco, on being approached, not only neigh and squeal, but prance and leap about in the most ridiculous manner, apparently in defiance as a challenge. These animals are very easily domesticated, and I have seen some thus kept near the houses, although at large on their native plains. They are in this state very bold, and readily attack a man, by striking him from behind with both knees. It is asserted, that the motive for these attacks is jealousy on account of their females. The wild guanacoes, however, have no idea of defence; even a single dog will secure one of these large animals, till the huntsman can come up. In many of their habits they are like sheep in a flock. Thus when they see men approaching in several directions on horseback, they soon became bewildered and know not which way to run. This greatly facilitates the Indian method of hunting, for they are thus easily driven to a central point, and are encompassed.

The guanacoes readily take to the water: several times at Port Valdes they were seen swimming from island to island. Byron, in his voyage, says he saw them drinking salt water. Some of our officers likewise saw a herd apparently drinking the briny fluid from a salina near Cape Blanco. I imagine in several parts of the country, if they do not drink salt water, they drink none at all. In the middle of the day, they frequently roll in the dust, in saucer- shaped hollows. The males fight together; two one day passed quite close to me, squealing and trying to bite each other; and several were shot with their hides deeply scored. Herds sometimes appear to set out on exploring- parties: at Bahia Blanca, where, within 30 miles of the coast, these animals are extremely unfrequent, I one day saw the tracks of thirty or forty, which had come in a direct line to a muddy salt- water creek. They then must have perceived that they were approaching the sea, for they had wheeled with the regularity of cavalry, and had returned back in as straight a line as they had advanced. The guanacoes have one singular habit, which is to me quite inexplicable; namely, that on successive days they drop their dung in the same defined heap. I saw one of these heaps which was eight feet in diameter, and necessarily was composed of a large quantity. Frezier remarks on this habit as common to the guanaco as well as to the llama; he says it is very useful to the Indians, who use the dung for fuel, and are thus saved the trouble of collecting it.

The guanacoes appear to have favourite spots for dying in. On the banks of the St Cruz, the ground was actually white with bones, in certain circumscribed spaces, which were generally bushy and all near the river. On one such spot I counted between ten and twenty heads. I particularly examined the bones; they did not appear, as some scattered ones which I had seen, gnawed or broken, as if dragged together by beasts of prey. The animals in most cases, must have crawled, before dying, beneath and amongst the bushes. Mr Bynoe informs me that during the last voyage, he observed the same circumstance on the banks of the Rio Gallegos. I do not at all understand the reason of this, but I may observe, that the wounded guanacoes at the St Cruz, invariably walked towards the river. At St Jago in the Cape de Verd islands I remember having seen in a retired ravine a corner under a cliff, where numerous goats’ bones were collected: we at the time exclaimed, that it was the burial- ground of all the goats in the island. I mention these trifling circumstances, because in certain cases they might explain the occurrence of a number of uninjured bones in a cave, or buried under alluvial accumulations; and likewise the cause, why certain mammalia are more commonly embedded than others in sedimentary deposits. Any great flood of the St Cruz, would wash down many bones of the guanaco, but probably not a single one of the puma, ostrich, or fox. I may also observe, that almost every kind of waterfowl when wounded takes to the shore to die; so that the remains of birds, from this cause alone and independently of other reasons, would but rarely be preserved in a fossil state.

* * *

january 9 th, 1834 – Before it was dark the Beagle anchored in the fine spacious harbour of Port St Julian, situated about 110 miles to the south of Port Desire. On the south side of the harbour, a cliff of about 90 feet in height intersects a plain constituted of the formations above described; and its surface is strewed over with recent marine shells. The gravel, however, differently from that in every other locality, is covered by a very irregular and thin bed of a reddish loam, containing a few small calcareous concretions. The matter somewhat resembles that of the Pampas, and probably owes its origin either to a small stream having formerly entered the sea at that spot, or to a mud- bank similar to those now existing at the head of the harbour. In one spot this earthy matter filled up a hollow, or gully, worn quite through the gravel, and in this mass a group of large bones was embedded. The animal to which they belonged, must have lived, as in the case at Bahia Blanca, at a period long subsequent to the existence of the shells now inhabiting the coast. We may feel sure of this, because the formation of the lower terrace or plain, must necessarily have been posterior to those above it, and on the surface of the two higher ones, sea- shells of recent species are scattered. From the small physical change, which the last 100 feet elevation of the continent could have produced, the climate, as well as the general condition of Patagonia, probably was nearly the same, at the time when the animal was embedded, as it now is. This conclusion is moreover supported by the identity of the shells belonging to the two ages. Then immediately occurred the difficulty, how could any large quadruped have subsisted on these wretched deserts in lat. 49° 15′? I had no idea at the time, to what kind of animal these remains belonged. The puzzle, however, was soon solved when Mr Owen examined them; for he considers that they formed part of an animal allied to the guanaco or llama, but fully as large as the true camel. As all the existing members of the family of Camelidæ are inhabitants of the most sterile countries, so may we suppose was this extinct kind. The structure of the cervical vertebræ, the transverse processes not being perforated for the vertebral artery, indicates its affinity: some other parts, however, of its structure, probably are anomalous.

The most important result of this discovery, is the confirmation of the law that existing animals have a close relation in form with extinct species. As the guanaco is the characteristic quadruped of Patagonia, and the vicuna of the snow- clad summits of the Cordillera, so in bygone days, this gigantic species of the same family must have been conspicuous on the southern plains. We see this same relation of type between the existing and fossil Ctenomys, between the capybara (but less plainly, as shown by Mr Owen) and the gigantic Toxodon; and lastly, between the living and extinct Edentata. At the present day, in South America, there exist probably nineteen species of this order, distributed into several genera; while throughout the rest of the world there are but five. If, then, there is a relation between the living and the dead, we should expect that the Edentata would be numerous in the fossil state. I need only reply by enumerating the megatherium, and the three or four other great species, discovered at Bahia Blanca; the remains of some of which are also abundant over the whole immense territory of La Plata. I have already pointed out the singular relation between the armadilloes and their great prototypes, even in a point apparently of so little importance as their external covering.

The order of rodents at the present day, is most conspicuous in South America, on account of the vast number and size of the species, and the multitude of individuals: according to the same law, we should expect to find their representatives in a fossil state. Mr Owen has shown how far the Toxodon is thus related; and it is moreover not improbable that another large animal has likewise a similar affinity.

The teeth of the rodent nearly equalling in size those of the Capybara, which were discovered near Bahia Blanca, must also be remembered.

The law of the succession of types, although subject to some remarkable exceptions, must possess the highest interest to every philosophical naturalist, and was first clearly observed in regard to Australia, where fossil remains of a large and extinct species of Kangaroo and other marsupial animals were discovered buried in a cave. In America the most marked change among the mammalia has been the loss of several species of Mastodon, of an elephant, and of the horse. These Pachydermata appear formerly to have had a range over the world, like that which deer and antelopes now hold. If Buffon had known of these gigantic armadilloes, llamas, great rodents, and lost pachydermata, he would have said with a greater semblance of truth, that the creative force in America had lost its vigour, rather than that it had never possessed such powers.

It is impossible to reflect without the deepest astonishment, on the changed state of this continent. Formerly it must have swarmed with great monsters, like the southern parts of Africa, but now we find only the tapir, guanaco, armadillo, and capybara; mere pigmies compared to the antecedent races. The greater number, if not all, of these extinct quadrupeds lived at a very recent period; and many of them were contemporaries of the existing molluscs. Since their loss, no very great physical changes can have taken place in the nature of the country. What then has exterminated so many living creatures? In the Pampas, the great sepulchre of such remains, there are no signs of violence, but on the contrary, of the most quiet and scarcely sensible changes. At Bahia Blanca I endeavoured to show the probability that the ancient Edentata, like the present species, lived in a dry and sterile country, such as now is found in that neighbourhood. With respect to the camel- like llama of Patagonia, the same grounds which, before knowing more than the size of the remains, perplexed me, by not allowing any great change of climate, now that we can guess the habits of the animal, are strangely confirmed. What shall we say of the death of the fossil horse? Did those plains fail in pasture, which afterwards were overrun by thousands and tens of thousands of the successors of the fresh stock introduced with the Spanish colonist? In some countries, we may believe, that a number of species subsequently introduced, by consuming the food of the antecedent races, may have caused their extermination; but we can scarcely credit that the armadillo has devoured the food of the immense Megatherium, the capybara of the Toxodon, or the guanaco of the camel- like kind. But granting that all such changes have been small, yet we are so profoundly ignorant concerning the physiological relations, on which the life, and even health (as shown by epidemics) of any existing species depends, that we argue with still less safety about either the life or death of any extinct kind.

One is tempted to believe in such simple relations, as variation of climate and food, or introduction of enemies, or the increased numbers of other species, as the cause of the succession of races. But it may be asked whether it is probable that any such cause should have been in action during the same epoch over the whole northern hemisphere, so as to destroy the Elephas primigenus, on the shores of Spain, on the plains of Siberia, and in Northern America; and in a like manner, the Bos urus, over a range of scarcely less extent? Did such changes put a period to the life of Mastodon angustidens, and of the fossil horse, both in Europe and on the Eastern slope of the Cordillera in Southern America? If they did, they must have been changes common to the whole world; such as gradual refrigeration, whether from modifications of physical geography, or from central cooling. But on this assumption, we have to struggle with the difficulty that these supposed changes, although scarcely sufficient to affect molluscous animals either in Europe or South America, yet destroyed many quadrupeds in regions now characterized by frigid, temperate, and warm climates! These cases of extinction forcibly recall the idea (I do not wish to draw any close analogy) of certain fruit- trees, which, it has been asserted, though grafted on young stems, planted in varied situations, and fertilized by the richest manures, yet at one period, have all withered away and perished. A fixed and determined length of life has in such cases been given to thousands and thousands of buds (or individual germs), although produced in long succession. Among the greater number of animals, each individual appears nearly independent of its kind; yet all of one kind may be bound together by common laws, as well as a certain number of individual buds in the tree, or polypi in the Zoophyte.

I will add one other remark. We see that whole series of animals, which have been created with peculiar kinds of organization, are confined to certain areas; and we can hardly suppose these structures are only adaptations to peculiarities of climate or country; for otherwise, animals belonging to a distinct type, and introduced by man, would not succeed so admirably, even to the extermination of the aborigines. On such grounds it does not seem a necessary conclusion, that the extinction of species, more than their creation, should exclusively depend on the nature (altered by physical changes) of their country. All that at present can be said with certainty, is that, as with the individual, so with the species, the hour of life has run its course, and is spent.

* * *

april 13th – The Beagle anchored within the mouth of the Santa Cruz. This river is situated about 60 miles south of Port St Julian. During the last voyage, Captain Stokes proceeded 30 miles up, but then, from the want of provisions, was obliged to return. Excepting what was discovered at that time, scarcely any thing was known about this large river. Captain FitzRoy now determined to follow its course as far as time would allow. On the 18th, three whale- boats started, carrying three weeks’ provisions; and the party consisted of twenty- five souls – a force which would have been sufficient to have defied a host of Indians. With a strong flood- tide, and a fine day, we made a good run, soon drank some of the fresh water, and were at night nearly above the tidal influence.

The river here assumed a size and appearance, which, even at the highest point we ultimately reached, was scarcely diminished. It was generally from 300 to 400 yards broad, and in the middle about 17 feet deep. The rapidity of the current, which in its whole course runs at the rate of from 4 to 6 knots an hour, is perhaps its most remarkable feature. The water is of a fine blue colour, but with a slight milky tinge, and not so transparent as at first sight would have been expected. It flows over a bed of pebbles, like those which compose the beach and surrounding plains. Although its course is winding, it runs through a valley which extends in a direct line to the westward. This valley varies from 5 to 10 miles in breadth; it is bounded by step- formed terraces, which rise in most parts one above the other to the height of 500 feet, and have on the opposite sides a remarkable correspondence.

april 19th – Against so strong a current, it was of course quite impossible to row or sail. Consequently the three boats were fastened together head and stern, two hands left in each, and the rest came on shore to track. As the general arrangements, made by Captain FitzRoy, were very good for facilitating the work of all, and as all had a share of it, I will describe the system. The party, including everyone, was divided into two spells, each of which hauled at the tracking line alternately for an hour and a half. The officers of each boat lived with, ate the same food, and slept in the same tent with their crew, so that each boat was quite independent of the others. After sunset, the first level spot where any bushes were growing, was chosen for our night’s lodging. Each of the crew took it in turns to be cook. Immediately the boat was hauled up, the cook made his fire; two others pitched the tent; the coxswain handed the things out of the boat; the rest carried them up to the tents, and collected firewood. By this order, in half an hour, every thing was ready for the night. A watch of two men and an officer was always kept, whose duty it was to look after the boats, keep up the fire, and guard against Indians. Each in the party had his one hour every night.

During this day we tracked but a short distance, for there were many islets, covered by thorny bushes, and the channels between them were shallow.

April 20th – We passed the islands and set to work. Our regular day’s march, although it was hard enough, carried us on an average only 10 miles in a straight line, and perhaps 15 or 20 altogether. Beyond the place where we slept last night the country is completely terra incognita, for it was there that Captain Stokes turned back. We saw in the distance a great smoke, and found the skeleton of a horse, so we knew that Indians were in the neighbourhood. On the next morning (21st) tracks of a party of horse, and marks left by the trailing of the chuzos were observed on the ground. It was generally thought they must have reconnoitred us during the night. Shortly afterwards we came to a spot, where from the fresh footsteps of men, children, and horses, it was evident the party had crossed the river.

* * *

april 29th – From some high land we hailed with joy the white summits of the Cordillera, as they were seen occasionally peeping through their dusky envelope of clouds. During the few succeeding days, we continued to get on slowly, for we found the river- course very tortuous, and strewed with immense fragments of various ancient slaty rocks, and of granite. The plain bordering the valley had here attained an elevation of about 1,100 feet, and its character was much altered. The well- rounded pebbles of porphyry were in this part mingled with many immense angular fragments of basalt and of the rocks above mentioned. The first of these erratic blocks which I noticed, was 67 miles distant from the nearest mountain; another which had been transported to rather a less distance, measured 5 yards square, and projected 5 feet above the gravel. Its edges were so angular, and its size so great, that I at first mistook it for a rock in situ, and took out my compass to observe the direction of its cleavage. The plains here were not quite so level as those nearer the coast, but yet, they betrayed little signs of any violent action. Under these circumstances, it would be difficult, as it appears to me, to explain this phenomenon on any theory, excepting through that of transport by ice while the country was under water. But this is a subject to which I shall again recur.

During the two last days we met with signs of horses, and with several small articles which had belonged to the Indians, – such as parts of a mantle and a bunch of ostrich feathers – but they appeared to have been lying long on the ground. Between the place where the Indians had so lately crossed the river and this neighbourhood, though so many miles apart, the country appears to be quite unfrequented. At first, considering the abundance of the guanacoes, I was surprised at this; but it is explained by the stony nature of the plains, which would soon disable an unshod horse from taking part in the chase. Nevertheless, in two places in this very central region, I found small heaps of stones, which I do not think could have been accidentally thrown together. They were placed on points, projecting over the edge of the highest lava cliff, and they resembled, but on a small scale, those near Port Desire.

may 4th – Captain FitzRoy determined to take the boats no higher. The river had a winding course, and was very rapid; and the appearance of the country offered no temptation to proceed any further. Every where we met with the same productions, and the same dreary landscape. We were now 140 miles distant from the Atlantic, and about 60 from the nearest arm of the Pacific. The valley in this upper part expanded into a wide basin, bounded on the north and south by the basaltic platforms, and fronted by the long range of the snow- clad Cordillera. But we viewed these grand mountains with regret, for we were obliged to imagine their form and nature, instead of standing, as we had hoped, on their crest, and looking down on the plain below. Besides the useless loss of time which an attempt to ascend any higher would have cost us, we had already been for some days on half allowance of bread. This, although really enough for any reasonable men, was, after our hard day’s march, rather scanty food. Let those alone who have never tried it, exclaim about the comfort of a light stomach and an easy digestion. 5th – Before sunrise we commenced our descent. We shot down the stream with great rapidity, generally at the rate of 10 knots an hour. In this one day we effected what had cost us five- and- a- half hard days’ labour in ascending. On the 8th, we reached the Beagle after our twenty- one days’ expedition. Every one excepting myself had cause to be dissatisfied; but to me the ascent afforded a most interesting section of the great tertiary formation of Patagonia.

Tierra del Fuego

December 17th, 1832 – Having now finished with Patagonia, I will describe our first arrival in Tierra del Fuego. A little after noon we doubled Cape St Diego, and entered the famous strait of Le Maire. We kept close to the Fuegian shore, but the outline of the rugged, inhospitable Staten land was visible amidst the clouds. In the afternoon we anchored in the Bay of Good Success. While entering we were saluted in a manner becoming the inhabitants of this savage land. A group of Fuegians partly concealed by the entangled forest, were perched on a wild point overhanging the sea; and as we passed by, they sprang up, and waving their tattered cloaks sent forth a loud and sonorous shout. The savages followed the ship, and just before dark we saw their fire, and again heard their wild cry. The harbour consists of a fine piece of water half surrounded by low rounded mountains of clay- slate, which are covered to the water’s edge by one dense gloomy forest. A single glance at the landscape was sufficient to show me, how widely different it was from any thing I had ever beheld. At night it blew a gale of wind, and heavy squalls from the mountains swept past us. It would have been a bad time out at sea, and we, as well as others, may call this Good Success Bay.

In the morning, the Captain sent a party to communicate with the Fuegians. When we came within hail, one of the four natives who were present advanced to receive us, and began to shout most vehemently, wishing to direct us where to land. When we were on shore the party looked rather alarmed, but continued talking and making gestures with great rapidity. It was without exception the most curious and interesting spectacle I had ever beheld. I could not have believed how wide was the difference, between savage and civilized man. It is greater than between a wild and domesticated animal, in as much as in man there is a greater power of improvement. The chief spokesman was old, and appeared to be the head of the family; the three others were powerful young men, about 6 feet high. The women and children had been sent away. These Fuegians are a very different race from the stunted miserable wretches further to the westward. They are much superior in person, and seem closely allied to the famous Patagonians of the Strait of Magellan. Their only garment consists of a mantle made of guanaco skin, with the wool outside; this they wear just thrown over their shoulders, as often leaving their persons exposed as covered. Their skin is of a dirty coppery red colour.

The old man had a fillet of white feathers tied round his head, which partly confined his black, coarse, and entangled hair. His face was crossed by two broad transverse bars; one painted bright red reached from ear to ear, and included the upper lip; the other, white like chalk, extended parallel and above the first, so that even his eyelids were thus coloured. Some of the other men were ornamented by streaks of black powder, made of charcoal. The party altogether closely resembled the devils which come on the stage in such plays as Der Freischutz.

Their very attitudes were abject, and the expression of their countenances distrustful, surprised, and startled. After we had presented them with some scarlet cloth, which they immediately tied round their necks, they became good friends. This was shown by the old man patting our breasts, and making a chuckling kind of noise, as people do when feeding chickens. I walked with the old man, and this demonstration of friendship was repeated several times; it was concluded by three hard slaps, which were given me on the breast and back at the same time. He then bared his bosom for me to return the compliment, which being done, he seemed highly pleased. The language of these people, according to our notions, scarcely deserves to be called articulate. Captain Cook has compared it to a man clearing his throat, but certainly no European ever cleared his throat with so many hoarse, guttural, and clicking sounds.

They are excellent mimics: as often as we coughed or yawned, or made any odd motion, they immediately Charles Darwin 32 imitated us. Some of our party began to squint and look awry; but one of the young Fuegians (whose whole face was painted black, excepting a white band across his eyes) succeeded in making far more hideous grimaces. They could repeat with perfect correctness, each word in any sentence we addressed them, and they remembered such words for some time. Yet we Europeans all know how difficult it is to distinguish apart the sounds in a foreign language. Which of us, for instance, could follow an American Indian through a sentence of more than three words? All savages appear to possess, to an uncommon degree, this power of mimicry. I was told almost in the same words, of the same ludicrous habits among the Caffres: the Australians, likewise, have long been notorious for being able to imitate and describe the gait of any man, so that he may be recognized. How can this faculty be explained? is it a consequence of the more practised habits of perception and keener senses, common to all men in a savage state, as compared to those long civilized?

When a song was struck up by our party, I thought the Fuegians would have fallen down with astonishment. With equal surprise they viewed our dancing; but one of the young men, when asked, had no objection to a little waltzing. Little accustomed to Europeans as they appeared to be, yet they knew, and dreaded our fire- arms; nothing would tempt them to take a gun in their hands. They begged for knives, calling them by the Spanish word ‘cuchilla’. They explained also what they wanted, by acting as if they had a piece of blubber in their mouth, and then pretending to cut instead of tear it.

It was interesting to watch the conduct of these people towards Jemmy Button (one of the Fuegians who had been taken, during the former voyage, to England): they immediately perceived the difference between him and the rest, and held much conversation between themselves on the subject. The old man addressed a long harangue to Jemmy, which it seems was to invite him to stay with them. But Jemmy understood very little of their language, and was, moreover, thoroughly ashamed of his countrymen. When York Minster (another of these men) came on shore, they noticed him in the same way, and told him he ought to shave; yet he had not twenty dwarf hairs on his face, whilst we all wore our untrimmed beards. They examined the colour of his skin, and compared it with ours. One of our arms being bared, they expressed the liveliest surprise and admiration at its whiteness. We thought that they mistook two or three of the officers, who were rather shorter and fairer (though adorned with large beards), for the ladies of our party. The tallest amongst the Fuegians was evidently much pleased at his height being noticed. When placed back to back with the tallest of the boat’s crew, he tried his best to edge on higher ground, and to stand on tiptoe. He opened his mouth to show his teeth, and turned his face for a side view; and all this was done with such alacrity, that I dare say he thought himself the handsomest man in Tierra del Fuego. After the first feeling on our part of grave astonishment was over, nothing could be more ludicrous or interesting than the odd mixture of surprise and imitation which these savages every moment exhibited.

The next day I attempted to penetrate some way into the country. Tierra del Fuego may be described as a mountainous country, partly submerged in the sea, so that deep islets and bays occupy the place where valleys should exist. The mountain sides (except on the exposed western coast) are covered from the water’s edge upwards by one great forest. The trees reach to an elevation of between 1,000 and 1,500 feet; and are succeeded by a band of peat, with minute alpine plants; and this again is succeeded by the line of perpetual snow, which, according to Captain King, in the Strait of Magellan descends to between 3,000 and 4,000 feet. To find an acre of level land in any part of the country is most rare. I recollect only one little flat near Port Famine, and another of rather larger extent near Goeree Road. In both these cases, and in all others, the surface was covered by a thick bed of swampy peat. Even within the forest the ground is concealed by a mass of slowly putrefying vegetable matter, which, from being soaked with water, yields to the foot.

Finding it nearly hopeless to push my way through the wood, I followed the course of a mountain torrent. At first, from the waterfalls and number of dead trees, I could hardly crawl along; but the bed of the stream soon became a little more open, from the floods having swept the broken and rocky banks; and was amply repaid by the grandeur of the scene. The gloomy depth of the ravine well accorded with the universal signs of violence. On every side were lying irregular masses of rock and up- torn trees; other trees, though still erect, were decayed to the heart and ready to fall. The entangled mass of the thriving and the fallen reminded me of the forests within the tropics; – yet there was a difference; for in these still solitudes, Death, instead of Life, seemed the predominant spirit. I followed the water- course till I came to a spot where a great slip had cleared a straight space down the mountain side. By this road I ascended to a considerable elevation, and obtained a good view of the surrounding woods. The trees all belong to one kind, the Fagus betuloides, for the number of the other species of beech, and of the Winter’s bark, is quite inconsiderable. This tree keeps its leaves throughout the year; but its foliage is of a peculiar brownish- green colour, with a tinge of yellow. As the whole landscape is thus coloured, it has a sombre, dull appearance; nor is it often enlivened by the rays of the sun.

Strait of Magellan

December 21st – The Beagle got under way: and on the succeeding day, favoured to an uncommon degree by a fine easterly breeze, we closed in with the Barnevelts, and, running past Cape Deceit with its stony peaks, about three o’clock doubled the weather beaten Cape Horn! The evening was calm and bright and means of judging of the distance, how the mountain appeared to rise in height.

The Fuegians twice came and plagued us. As there were many instruments, clothes, and men on shore, it was thought necessary to frighten them away. The first time, a few great guns were fired, when they were far distant. It was most ludicrous to watch through a glass the Indians, as often as the shot struck the water, take up stones, and as a bold defiance, throw them towards the ship, though about a mile and a half distant! A boat was then sent with orders to fire a few musket- shot wide of them. The Fuegians hid themselves behind the trees; and for every discharge of the musket they fired their arrows: all, however, fell short of the boat, and the officer as he pointed at them laughed. This made the Fuegians frantic with passion, and they shook their mantles in vain rage. At last seeing the balls cut and strike the trees, they ran away; and we were left in peace and quietness.

On a former occasion, when the Beagle was here in the month of February, I started one morning at four o’clock to ascend Mount Tarn, which is 2,600 feet high, and is the most elevated point in this immediate neighbourhood. We went in a boat to the foot of the mountain (but not to the best part), and then began our ascent. The forest commences at the line of high- water mark, and during the two first hours I gave over all hopes of reaching the summit. So thick was the wood, that it was necessary to have constant recourse to the compass; for every landmark, though in a mountainous country, was completely shut out. In the deep ravines, the death- like scene of desolation exceeded all description; outside it was blowing a gale, but in these hollows, not even a breath of wind stirred the leaves of the tallest trees. So gloomy, cold, and wet was every part, that not even the fungi, mosses, or ferns, could flourish. In the valleys it was scarcely possible to crawl along, they were so completely barricaded by the great mouldering trunks, which had fallen down in every direction. When passing over these natural bridges, one’s course was often arrested by sinking knee deep into the rotten wood; at other times, when attempting to lean against a firm tree, one was startled by finding a mass of decayed matter ready to fall at the slightest touch. We at last found ourselves among the stunted trees, and then soon reached the bare ridge, which conducted us to the summit. Here was a view characteristic of Tierra del Fuego; – irregular chains of hills, mottled with patches of snow, deep yellowish- green valleys, and arms of the sea intersecting the land in many directions. The strong wind was piercingly cold, and the atmosphere rather hazy, so that we did not stay long on the top of the mountain. Our descent was not quite so laborious as our ascent; for the weight of the body forced a passage, and all the slips and falls were in the right direction.

* * *

The perfect preservation of the Siberian animals, perhaps presented, till within a few years, one of the most difficult problems which geology ever attempted to solve. On the one hand it was granted, that the carcasses had not been drifted from any great distance by any tumultuous deluge, and on the other it was assumed as certain, that when the animals lived, the climate must have been so totally different, that the presence of ice in the vicinity was as incredible, as would be the freezing of the Ganges. Mr Lyell in his Principles of Geology has thrown the greatest light on this subject, by indicating the northerly course of the existing rivers with the probability that they formerly carried carcasses in the same direction; by showing (from Humboldt) how far the inhabitants of the hottest countries sometimes wander; by insisting on the caution necessary in judging of habits between animals of the same genus, when the species are not identical; and especially by bringing forward in the clearest manner the probable change from an insular to an extreme climate, as the consequence of the elevation of the land, of which proofs have lately been brought to light.

In a former part of this volume, I have endeavoured to prove, that as far as regards the quantity of food, there is no difficulty in supposing that these large quadrupeds inhabited sterile regions, producing but a scanty vegetation. With respect to temperature, the woolly covering both of the elephant and the rhinoceros seems at once to render it at least probable (although it has been argued that some animals living in the hottest regions are thickly clothed) that they were fitted for a cold climate. I suppose no reason can be assigned why, during a former epoch, when the pachydermata abounded over the greater part of the world, some species should not have been fitted for the northern regions, precisely as now happens with deer and several other animals. If, then, we believe that the climate of Siberia, anteriorly to the physical changes above alluded to, had some resemblance with that of the southern hemisphere at the present day – a circumstance which harmonizes well with other facts, as I think has been shown by the imaginary case, when we transported existing phenomena from one to the other hemisphere – the following conclusions may be deduced as probable: first, that the degree of cold formerly was not excessive; secondly, that snow did not for a long time together cover the ground (such not being the case at the extreme parts 55°– 56° of S. America); thirdly, that the vegetation partook of a more tropical character than it now does in the same latitudes; and lastly, that at but a short distance to the northward of the country thus circumstanced (even not so far as where Pallas found the entire rhinoceros), the soil might be perpetually congealed: so that if the carcass of any animal should once be buried a few feet beneath the surface, it would be preserved for centuries.

Both Humboldt and Lyell have remarked, that at the present day, the bodies of any animals, wandering beyond the line of perpetual congelation which extends as far south as 62°, if once embedded by any accident a few feet beneath the surface, would be preserved for an indefinite length of time: the same would happen with carcasses drifted by the rivers; and by such means the extinct mammalia may have been entombed. There is only one small step wanting, as it appears to me, and the whole problem would be solved with a degree of simplicity very striking, compared with the several theories first invented. From the account given by Mr Lyell of the Siberian plains, with their innumerable fossil bones, the relics of many successive generations, there can be little doubt that the beds were accumulated either in a shallow sea, or in an estuary. From the description given in Beechey’s voyage of Eschscholtz Bay, the same remark is applicable to the north- west coast of America: the formation there appears identical with the common littoral deposits recently elevated, which I have seen on the shores of the southern part of the same continent. It seems also well established, that the Siberian remains are only exposed where the rivers intersect the plain. With this fact, and the proofs of recent elevation, the whole case appears to be precisely similar to that of the Pampas: namely, that the carcasses were formerly floated into the sea, and the remains covered up in the deposits which were then accumulating. These beds have since been elevated; and as the rivers excavate their channels the entombed skeletons are exposed.

Here then, is the difficulty: how were the carcasses preserved at the bottom of the sea? I do not think it has been sufficiently noticed, that the preservation of the animal with its flesh was an occasional event, and not directly consequent on its position far northward. Cuvier refers to the voyage of Billing as showing that the bones of the elephant, buffalo, and rhinoceros, are nowhere so abundant as on the islands between the mouths of the Lena and Indigirska. It is even said that excepting some hills of rock, the whole is composed of sand, ice, and bones. These islands lie to the northward of the place where Adams found the mammoth with its flesh preserved, and even 10° north of the Wiljui, where the rhinoceros was discovered in a like condition. In the case of the bones we may suppose that the carcasses were drifted into a deeper sea, and there remaining at the bottom, the flesh decomposed. But in the second and more extraordinary case, where putrefaction seems to have been arrested, the body probably was soon covered up by deposits which were then accumulating. It may be asked, whether the mud a few feet deep, at the bottom of a shallow sea which is annually frozen, has a temperature higher than 32°? It must be remembered how intense a degree of cold is required to freeze salt water; and that the mud at some depth below the surface, would have a low mean temperature, precisely in the same manner as the subsoil on the land is frozen in countries which enjoy a short but hot summer. If this be possible, the entombment of these extinct quadrupeds is rendered very simple; and with regard to the conditions of their former existence, the principal difficulties have, I think, already been removed.

* * *

There is one marine production, which from its importance is worthy of a particular history. It is the kelp or Fucus giganteus of Solander. This plant grows on every rock from low- water mark to a great depth, both on the outer coast and within the channels. I believe, during the voyages of the Adventure and Beagle, not one rock near the surface was discovered, which was not buoyed by this floating weed. The good service it thus affords to vessels navigating near this stormy land is evident; and it certainly has saved many a one from being wrecked. I know few things more surprising than to see this plant growing and flourishing amidst those great breakers of the western ocean, which no mass of rock, let it be ever so hard, can long resist. The stem is round, slimy, and smooth, and seldom has a diameter of so much as an inch. A few taken together are sufficiently strong to support the weight of the large loose stones to which in the inland channels they grow attached; and some of these stones are so heavy, that when drawn to the surface they can scarcely be lifted into a boat by one person.

Captain Cook, in his second voyage, says, that at Kerguelen Land ‘some of this weed is of a most enormous length, though the stem is not much thicker than a man’s thumb. I have mentioned, that on some of the shoals upon which it grows, we did not strike ground with a line of 24 fathoms. The depth of water, therefore, must have been greater. And as this weed does not grow in a perpendicular direction, but makes a very acute angle with the bottom, and much of it afterwards spreads many fathoms on the surface of the sea, I am well warranted to say that some of it grows to the length of sixty fathoms and upwards.’ Certainly at the Falkland Islands, and about Tierra del Fuego, extensive beds frequently spring up from 10- and 15- fathom water. I do not suppose the stem of any other plant attains so great a length as 360 feet, as stated by Captain Cook. Its geographical range is very considerable; it is found from the extreme southern islets near Cape Horn, as far north, on the eastern coast (according to information given me by Mr Stokes), as lat. 43° – and on the western it was tolerably abundant, but far from luxuriant, at Chiloe, in lat. 42°. It may possibly extend a little further northward, but is soon succeeded by a different species. We thus have a range of 15° in latitude; and as Cook, who must have been well acquainted with the species, found it at Kerguelen Land, no less than 140° in longitude.

The number of living creatures of all orders, whose existence intimately depends on the kelp, is wonderful. A great volume might be written, describing the inhabitants of one of these beds of sea- weed. Almost every leaf, excepting those that float on the surface, is so thickly incrusted with coral- lines, as to be of a white colour. We find exquisitely- delicate structures, some inhabited by simple hydra- like polypi, others by more organized kinds, and beautiful compound Ascidiæ. On the flat surfaces of the leaves various patelliform shells, Trochi, uncovered molluscs, and some bivalves are attached. Innumerable crustacea frequent every part of the plant. On shaking the great entangled roots, a pile of small fish, shells, cuttle- fish, crabs of all orders, sea- eggs, star- fish, beautiful Holuthuriæ (some taking the external form of the nudibranch molluscs), Planariæ, and crawling nereidous animals of a multitude of forms, all fall out together. Often as I recurred to a branch of the kelp, I never failed to discover animals of new and curious structures. In Chiloe, where, as I have said, the kelp did not thrive very well, the numerous shells, coral- lines, and crustacea were absent; but there yet remained a few of the flustraceæ, and some compound Ascidiæ; the latter, however, were of different species from those in Tierra del Fuego. We here see the fucus possessing a wider range than the animals which use it as an abode.

I can only compare these great aquatic forests of the southern hemisphere with the terrestrial ones in the intertropical regions. Yet if the latter should be destroyed in any country, I do not believe nearly so many species of animals would perish, as, under similar circumstances, would happen with the kelp. Amidst the leaves of this plant numerous species of fish live, which nowhere else would find food or shelter; with their destruction the many cormorants, divers, and other fishing birds, the otters, seals, and porpoises, would soon perish also; and lastly, the Fuegian savage, the miserable lord of this miserable land, would redouble his cannibal feast, decrease in numbers, and perhaps cease to exist.

June 8th – We weighed anchor early in the morning, and left Port Famine. Captain FitzRoy determined to leave the Strait of Magellan by the Magdalen channel, which had not long been discovered. Our course lay due south, down that gloomy passage which I have before alluded to, as appearing to lead to another and worse world. The wind was fair, but the atmosphere was very thick; so that we missed much curious scenery. The dark ragged clouds were rapidly driven over the mountains, from their summits nearly to their bases. The glimpses which we caught through the dusky mass were highly interesting: jagged points, cones of snow, blue glaciers, strong outlines marked on a lurid sky, were seen at different distances and heights. In the midst of such scenery we anchored at Cape Turn, close to Mount Sarmiento, which was then hidden in the clouds. At the base of the lofty and almost perpendicular sides of our little cove, there was one deserted wigwam, and it alone reminded us that man sometimes wandered in these desolate regions. But it would be difficult to imagine a scene where he seemed to have less claims, or less authority. The inanimate works of nature – rock, ice, snow, wind, and water – all warring with each other, yet combined against man – here reigned in absolute sovereignty.

June 9th – In the morning we were delighted by seeing the veil of mist gradually rise from Sarmiento, and display it to our view. This mountain, which is one of the highest in Tierra del Fuego, has an elevation of 6,800 feet. Its base, for about an eighth of its total height, is clothed by dusky woods, and above this a field of snow extends to the summit. These vast piles of snow, which never melt, and seem destined to last as long as the world holds together, present a noble and even sublime spectacle. The outline of the mountain was admirably clear and defined. Owing to the abundance of light reflected from the white and glittering surface, no shadows are cast on any part; and those lines which intersect the sky can alone be distinguished: hence the mass stood out in the boldest relief. Several glaciers descended in a winding course, from the snow to the sea- coast: they may be likened to great frozen Niagaras; and perhaps these cataracts of blue ice are to the full as beautiful as the moving ones of water. By night we reached the western part of the channel; but the water was so deep that no anchorage could be found. We were in consequence obliged to stand off and on, in this narrow arm of the sea, during a pitch- dark night of fourteen hours long.

June 10th – In the morning we made the best of our way into the open Pacific. The Western coast generally consists of low, rounded, quite barren, hills of granite and greenstone. Sir John Narborough called one part South Desolation, because it is ‘so desolate a land to behold’; and well indeed might he say so. Outside the main islands there are numberless scattered rocks, on which the long swell of the open ocean incessantly rages. We passed out between the East and West Furies, and a little further northward there are so many breakers that the sea is called the Milky Way. One sight of such a coast is enough to make a landsman dream for a week about shipwreck, peril, and death; and with this sight, we bade farewell for ever to Tierra del Fuego.

掀开的面纱

/

第一章

我的末日就要来了。最近，我饱受心绞痛的折磨，医生告诉我，正常情况下，我的生命只剩下寥寥数月。除非，在被诅咒了拥有罕有的心智之外，我还不幸拥有了罕见的体质，不然我将在不久后摆脱这尘世生命的痛苦重担。不过要是我没能摆脱，要是我还可以活到大多数人渴望并且能够活到的那个岁数，我就能一探究竟，看看希望的落空是否会比预言的实现让人更感痛苦。因为，我已经预见到了我何时死亡，预见到了我生命最后时刻发生的每一件事。

从现在开始一个月后的那一天，也就是1850年9月20日那天，我将会坐在这把椅子上，就在这间书房里，在夜晚十点整，渴望着死亡，不断袭来的洞察和预见将我折磨得疲惫不堪，幻觉和希望都不再出现。我看着壁炉里一条蓝色火舌正在升起，我的灯即将燃烧殆尽，就在那一刻，我的胸口会迎来可怕的收缩。窒息感来临之前，我的时间只够伸手猛烈地拉铃。没有人会回应我的铃声。我知道为什么。我的两个仆人是一对情人，那时他们刚刚争吵完。我拉铃的两个小时前，女管家怒气冲冲地跑出房子，她要佩里以为她去投水自尽了。佩里最终警觉了，为了找她也离开了房子。年轻的洗碗女工在一条长凳上睡着了，她从来不回应铃声，铃声叫不醒她。窒息的感觉加重了，我的灯熄灭了，带来一股难闻的味道，我费尽全身力气又一次扑向了铃铛。我渴望生命，但却无人来救。我曾经渴望未知的世界，但那股渴望已经消散了。上帝啊，让我继续活在这已知的世界，让我继续被已知的世界折磨吧，我会心满意足。绞痛和窒息给我带来痛苦⸺土地、田野、鸦巢下铺着鹅卵石的小溪、雨后的新鲜气息、早晨透过卧室窗户的阳光，还有霜降时屋内温暖的壁炉，难道这些也要永远被黑暗吞噬吗？

黑暗，还是黑暗，没有痛苦，只有黑暗。而在黑暗中我一直在向前穿梭⸺我的思绪一直处在黑暗中，但感觉在向前持续移动……

在死亡降临前，我要用仅存的安宁和气力讲述我奇异的经历。我从未向任何人袒露过这一切，也从未对人们的同情心抱有太大期望。不过，死亡可能让世人在评价我们时带着几分同情、些许温柔和宽容⸺活着的人不会得到宽恕，活着的人不会得到迁就和尊重，对于活人的所有温情都像雨点一样消散在了无情的东风中。留给你的机会只有一个，遇到那心灵善良的人，你该摧残他；遇到那眼睛仍温情脉脉、小心翼翼地望着你的人，你该以冷若冰霜的眼神回敬他；耳朵是通向灵魂这座神龛深处的柔弱信使，要是遇到那耳朵还能听得下善意语句的人，你就该摆出一副冰冷的礼仪规范，说上几句暗藏讥讽的赞美，或者端着艳羡的冷漠态度拒他于千里之外；要是遇到一个头脑仍热情地维持正义、期盼着兄弟般感情的人，你该抓紧用你不怀好意的评判、琐碎的对比、看似无心的信口雌黄打击他。这样，他的心灵会逐渐麻木，直到“激烈的愤怒再也无法伤害心灵”[1]，眼睛再也不会流露满怀期待的神色，耳朵会听而不闻，头脑不再回应那些祈求，也不再思考。这样，你的话语才有了用武之地，你会记得并同情那些失败者付出的艰辛，你会尊敬那些已经完成的工作，你会原谅错误，你会心甘情愿地忘掉错误。

这些都是琐碎无用又幼稚的说辞，我为什么要思考这些？对我来说，这毫无意义，在我死后，我没有任何作品供人景仰；没有任何亲人会在我的墓前哭泣，懊悔在我生前给我造成的痛苦。我死后，恐怕只有我这一生的故事能在陌生人处换回一些同情，一些我生前从朋友处鲜少得到的同情。

和我后来不幸的人生相比，我的童年岁月还算过得不错，称得上幸福。那时的我和其他孩子一样，看不透未来。和那些孩子一样，我享受着当下时光的快乐，也享受着对未来无限憧憬的甜蜜。我那温柔的母亲还在我身边。即使是现在，岁月蹉跎，一想起她把我放在膝盖上温柔地抚摸我，我都可以朦胧地回忆起当时的感觉⸺她的双臂环抱着我，脸颊紧贴着我的脸颊。小时候，有段时间我患了眼疾，看不见东西，她就从早到晚地抱着我。母亲对我的爱无人能及，可她却过早地离开了我，还是孩子的我已感到生命被一股寒意侵蚀。和母亲去世前一样，我还是经常在马夫的照看下，骑着一匹白色的小马驹。可是，我上马时再也没有人热切地看着我，骑马回来时再也没有人等着拥抱我。其他孩子若是在七八岁时失去了母亲，他们的思念也许并不会像我这样强烈，因为他们生命中的其他乐趣还将继续，而我却是个异常敏感的孩子。我记得，我很容易被丁点儿声响弄得又焦虑又激动，马厩里马匹踏地板的回声、马夫们瓮声瓮气的说话声、父亲的马车一停到院子的拱门下就引来的阵阵犬吠声，以及提示午餐和晚餐的铃声，这些都会刺激到我。我父亲的房子毗邻一个有军营驻扎的乡村，军队操练时稳健的踏步声时而传来，让我颤抖着啜泣。可这声音一旦消失，我又盼望它再来。

我想，父亲大概认为我是个有些奇怪的孩子，所以不怎么喜欢我，尽管他完成一个父亲的责任时一丝不苟。就算如此，他也已经人到中年，是两个孩子的父亲。我的母亲是他的继室，他们结婚时父亲已经四十五岁了。他是一个坚定不移、从不屈服又极度有纪律的人，是一个从里到外地地道道的银行家；又是一个活跃的地主，渴望在全郡获得影响力。他一成不变，从不受天气的影响，从来没经历过忧郁，也不知道什么叫作兴高采烈。我很敬畏他，只要他在身边，我就会变得更加懦弱敏感。这恰恰让他相信，必须用不同于教育我兄长的那套常规方式教育我。我兄长是个高个子的年轻人，当时已经进入了伊顿公学。他将成为我父亲的代言人和继承人，当然，为了结交权贵他必须上伊顿公学和牛津大学。我父亲并不否认阅读拉丁讽刺作家或希腊剧作家的作品有助于获取贵族地位，不过，他其实并不怎么尊重这些“已故的贵族幽灵”。在读过波特翻译的埃斯库罗斯，粗略看过弗朗西斯译成英文的贺拉斯后，他觉得他自己已经完全有资格对这些作品评头论足了。他不屑于这些，他欣赏的是另一类事物，他最近涉足矿产投资，因此便更觉得科学教育才是对次子最有用的教育。特别是对我这样一个又害羞又敏感的男孩儿来说，我根本不适合去读弱肉强食的公立学校。莱瑟尔先生坚信这一点。莱瑟尔先生是一个戴眼镜的肥胖男人。一天，他肥胖的双手夹住我瘦小的头颅，带着科学研究的怀疑态度在我头上这里敲敲那里按按，随后，他用肥大的手指按住我的太阳穴把我推开，透过那副亮闪闪的眼镜打量着我。他额头紧锁，看来对这番审视并不满意，一边用拇指扫着我的眉毛一边对我父亲说：“他的不足之处是这里，先生⸺那里，还有这里。”他扶住我头颅的上半部分补充道：“但这里又过度了。缺陷部分一定要激发出来，而过度的部分要给予压制。”

我瑟瑟发抖，一部分在于我模模糊糊地感到自己被当作批判的对象了；一部分在于我为自己第一次的愤怒感到坐立难安，我憎恨这个戴眼镜的硕大男人，他随意地拉拽我的头颅，好像在讨价还价中试图廉价买下它。

我不清楚莱瑟尔先生和后来父亲用在我身上的那套教育体系到底有多大关系，但有一件事儿是肯定的，那就是私人教师、历史、自然科学、现代语言都是用来修补我先天不足的工具。由于我对机械一窍不通，他们就安排我整日和机器相处；我的思维中没有清晰的分类，他们就认为我需要系统地学习动物学和植物学。我渴望了解人类行为和人类情感，他们却把我的生活中塞满机械能量、元素和电子、磁力现象。如果是先天健全的男孩儿，带着他们运行正常的器官，定能从这些睿智教师的辅导中受益匪浅，他们将毫无疑问地对电磁现象滋生无限的兴趣，就像每个周四晚上老师努力想让我感受到的一样。事实上，对于他们所教授的科学知识，我依旧保持着相当的无知，其程度甚至可以匹敌被古典学院驱逐的最差的学生。暗地里，我偷偷地阅读普鲁塔克、莎士比亚和堂吉诃德，一边读一边任由我的思绪飘荡。我的教师告诉我，“一个受过教育的人与文盲的区别在于，他知道为什么水往低处流”。可我却无意成为这样一个受过教育的人，我喜欢流水，能够一连几个小时地观察它，听它从鹅卵石中蜿蜒流过的汩汩声，喜欢看它浇灌亮绿色的水草。我不想知道它流淌的原理，我所确信的是，如此美丽的事物背后一定有更深层次的原因。

还是不要再说这段往事了吧。我想我说的已足以证明，我的天性是敏感而不讲求实际的，我又是在这样一个对我天性不利的环境中成长，因此我不可能长成一个快乐健康的人。十六岁那年，我被送往日内瓦完成学业，这种改变为我带来了快乐。当我们从汝拉山上下来，第一次看到夕阳落在阿尔卑斯山脉的山顶，我觉得那里仿佛是天堂的入口。好似沉醉于甘甜的美酒中一般，那三年的时光在无尽的狂喜中度过，而大自然也向我展示了她百般的婀娜。也许你会以为，我如此年轻就能领略自然之美，我必定是个诗人。可惜，我的命运没有这般幸运。诗人会倾吐他的诗歌，而且他坚信他的诗歌会被那敏锐的耳朵采撷，得到灵魂的回应，迟早会在世间传诵。但是，敏感多情的诗人要是失去了声音，要是他的情感无法用语言表达出来，比如，阳光明媚的时候他在河岸看到水面波光粼粼之景只能默默流泪；或者，一旦有人说了几句难听的话、给了他一个坏脸色，他就寝食难安，内心的激情便无从释放，与人相处时，他便越发感到孤独。只有傍晚时分，行舟湖上，朝着中心泊去时，我的孤独感才有所减淡。那时，天空，闪着光辉的山峦，广阔的蓝色湖面，这一切景色将我环抱⸺自母亲过世，我就再也没能感受到这样的疼爱了。我会像让・雅克[2]一样，躺在小舟里，任凭它自由地漂荡。我看着天边褪去的霞光作别一座又一座的山巅，就像先知的烈火马车驶过，驶向光生出的地方。直到雪白的山顶变得灰暗，如同死尸，我才不得不起程返回，因为，我被看管得很严，他们不准许我晚上四处游荡。虽然在日内瓦求学的同龄人很多，但因为性情，大家在选择朋友时并不青睐我。不过，我还是结交了一个朋友，更让人想不到的是，他的志趣与我完全相反。我称呼他为查尔斯・麦尼埃，他的真实姓氏是一个后来颇有名气的英国姓，因为他拥有英国血统。他是个孤儿，在学医期间只能靠一点儿可怜的补贴过活，而他在医学上很有天赋。真是奇怪啊！我是个头脑糊涂、易受影响、不善观察、不求甚解又整日陷入沉思中的人，我居然会被这样一个对科学饱含激情的青年吸引。不过，我们之间的友谊并不是靠智力维系，这友谊的源泉能让愚钝的人和智慧的人结交，也能让异想天开的人和脚踏实地的人亲近，我们的友谊来源于共同的情感。查尔斯家境贫寒、相貌丑陋，只能招来日内瓦社会的嘲笑，被社交生活拒之门外。我看他和我一样被人孤立，当然，我们被孤立的原因不同，这使得我对他生出一种夹杂着同情的厌恶，受此驱使，我小心翼翼地接近他。可以这么说，在我们大相径庭的习惯差异所能允许的范围内，我们萌发了同志情谊。查尔斯很少休息，在他休息时，我们会一起爬萨莱沃山，或者一起乘船去沃韦，我迷迷糊糊地听他讲他正在进行的各种大胆的实验和发现。一边听他讲，我一边看沿途蓝色的水面、天空优美的浮云，一边听鸟儿婉转鸣叫、远方冰川融化之声。他很清楚，我听得三心二意，但他喜欢这样和我交谈，即便是狗啊、鸟啊爱我们，我们不也愿意向它们抒发自己的愿景和雄心吗？而我之所以说起这段友情，是因为这与我后面要讲的那段离奇、恐怖的经历有关。

我的这段相对幸福的时光因为一场严重的疾病中断了，我几乎回忆不起生病时的情形，只能隐隐约约记得当时的痛苦，父亲时不时地会来床边陪伴我。随后就是单调乏味的疗养期。随着体力慢慢恢复，我的生活也逐渐有些变化，渐渐地我可以远游。在我记得比较清楚的日子里，有一天，父亲坐在我身边的沙发上，对我说：“等你身体好点儿的时候，拉蒂默，我要带你跟我回家。这趟旅行会让你轻松愉快，这对你有好处。我会带你去蒂罗尔和奥地利，你会游历很多地方。我们的邻居菲尔莫尔一家会一起去，艾尔弗雷德将在巴塞尔和我们会合，我们会一起去维也纳，回来的时候路过布拉格……”

话还没说完，父亲就被叫走了，我的思绪停留在布拉格上。我有一种莫名其妙的感觉，一幅新颖、奇妙的图景展现在眼前：一座城市沐浴在阳光中，好像是几个世纪之前的夏日阳光仍在这里徘徊。这阳光已经陈旧了，它长年累月承受着夜晚露水的洗涤或突降云雨的冲荡；它照耀着一个布满灰尘、疲惫不堪又历经沧桑的伟大民族，这民族注定要活在陈旧的记忆中，如同那些被废黜、抛弃的国王，他们的金缕玉衣已经变成破衣烂衫。这城市看上去如此干渴，那宽阔的河水在我看来也如同一条金属块儿。沿着那座望不到尽头的桥，我从那些雕塑空洞的眼神下走过。这些雕塑已经发黑，他们穿着古老的衣服，戴着神圣的王冠，在我眼中，他们才是这座城市真正的居民和真正的主人，而那些熙熙攘攘、微不足道的男男女女，他们忙进忙出，其实只是暂时来叨扰这座城的游客。这些表情严肃的石头人，我想，他们是已经故去的古人的祖先，他们矗立在饱受风霜的建筑里拜谒宫廷。这些宫殿曾经繁华却已失色彩，它们的屋顶连成一条单调的天际线。这些雕塑在空气陈旧的教堂里疲惫地做礼拜，他们没有恐惧也没有希望，等待他们的只有衰老却永生的命运。在永恒的白日下，他们靠着刻板的习俗生活着，没有夜晚的休憩，亦无清晨的新生。

突然一阵金属碰撞的叮当声让我打了一个寒战，屋内的摆设重新出现在我的意识里，原来，皮埃尔开门给我药剂的时候一块火烙铁正好掉落，发出了那声响。我的心脏开始不规律地猛烈跳动，我让皮埃尔把药放在旁边，说我一会儿就喝。

留我只身一人的时候，我马上开始回想刚才是不是睡着了。这一切是不是梦境？我对一个陌生城市的幻境竟会如此清晰，此前我从未想象过这样一个城市，幻境却清晰到我能看见一盏星星样式的多彩灯在人行道上洒下了一块彩虹色的光斑。我从未看过关于布拉格的绘画，它在我头脑里只是个名字，我隐隐约约记得一些和它有关的历史事件，一些说不清的帝国辉煌和宗教战争。

我从未做过这样的梦，以往我总是受噩梦侵扰，其他梦的内容杂乱无章，梦到的也是寻常的事物，我常常为此感到不安。但我不相信刚刚我只是睡着了，我清楚地记得那幻境如何一步步降临到我身上，像是在模糊的视线中形成了新的图景，又好似太阳升起时掀开了清晨雾水形成的面纱，大地的景色逐渐清晰。在我开始意识到这幻境的时候，我同时也能感知到，皮埃尔告诉我父亲菲尔莫尔先生正在等他，随后我父亲迅速离开了房间。不，这不是梦，一种让我颤抖的狂喜使我想到，这难道是我体内的诗人本性苏醒了？迄今为止，这诗人的本性只是让我受多愁善感的折磨，如今，它终于要显现为即兴的创造力了吗？是啊，一定是这样，凭着诗人的本性，荷马看到了特洛伊的平原，但丁看到了死者的炼狱，弥尔顿看到了摔向地面的撒旦。难道是疾病给我的体质带来了喜人的变化，让我的神经变得更稳定，带走了体内愚钝的杂质？我读到过这类效果，至少在小说里读过。不，在真实的传记里我也曾读过，某些疾病会让头脑更稳定专注，有些疾病则会升华头脑的活力。诺瓦利斯不是随着肺结核的加重，感到他的灵感也越来越强了吗？

这个幸福的想法一直萦绕在我心头，我觉得我可以通过延伸自己的思维测试一下这种新的能力。幻境出现的时候，我父亲正说到我们要去布拉格。我全然不信，这幻境会是那城市的真实呈现。我相信，或者说我希望，那是我新解放的天才在瞬间描摹出的景象，其中的色彩则来自以往的记忆。如果我让思绪停留在另一座城市上，比如威尼斯，我对它的熟悉远胜过布拉格，也许同样的事情会再次发生。我集中精力将思绪交会在威尼斯上，我调动那些诗意的记忆来激发想象力，努力让自己感到身在威尼斯，如我此前想象身在布拉格一样。然而，没有用。我的头脑只是在为卡纳莱托的版画上色，它们就挂在家里我那间旧卧室的墙壁上。我脑海中形成的图像并不稳定，而我的头脑不停地找寻更生动的形象，我必须动用必要的手段有意识地努力才能看到形象或光影。这只是我毫无想象力的主动努力，我并没有全神贯注地进入这幅画中，所有的形象也没有不自觉地向我涌来，和半个小时前的那次经历完全不同。我有些灰心，但同时我也知道灵感总是断断续续到来的。

一连几天，我处在兴奋的渴望中，渴望着我的新天赋能再发生一次。我让思绪漂荡在知识的海洋中，希望它能找到某个对象将我沉睡的天才重新唤醒。但是，不，我的世界和从前一样灰暗，那一束神奇的光没有再来，尽管我怀着颤抖的渴望找寻着它。

每天，父亲都会陪我乘着车游览一段，散一段时间的步，并且随着我逐渐恢复，距离也越来越远。一天傍晚，他和我约好第二天中午十二点接我，我们可以一起去挑音乐盒和富裕的英国人在日内瓦常买的物品。他本就是十分守时的人，放在银行家里，他也算最守时的一个，为此，我总是紧紧张张地准备好，在约定的时间等着他。但让我意外的是，到了十二点一刻钟的时候他仍未出现。作为一个正在恢复期的病人，我本就无所事事，而为了支撑自己应对这趟外出，我更是刚刚饮下了一些补药，这使得我越发地不耐烦。

我实在没法坐着保持体力，就在屋里来回踱步，看着窗外的罗讷河从深蓝色的湖水中流出来，脑子里想的是各种可能绊住父亲和我会面的原因。

突然我感觉到父亲到了房子里，但并非独自一人，他身边有两个人。奇怪！我没有听见脚步声，没有看到门打开，但我确实看到了父亲。在他右手边是我们的邻居菲尔莫尔夫人，虽然已经五年没见，我还记得很清楚。她是一个普通的中年女性，身着丝绸和开司米料子的衣服。父亲左手边的女士还不满二十岁，身材高挑、纤细，身姿如柳条一般，一头华丽的金色长发编成俏皮的样式。对那苗条的身材、瘦小的脸庞、薄薄的嘴唇来说，这一头发髻形成的王冠可能过于沉重了。但这脸庞的表情却不是女孩子会有的青涩神情，她棱角分明，暗灰色的眼睛目光锐利、不停地转动，又满是挖苦人的神情。这双眼睛带着几分笑意好奇地打量着我，我感到一种痛苦，好似一股冷风刮伤了我。那暗绿色的裙子、暗绿色的袖子好像在她的淡金色头发旁围成一个边界，让我想到女水妖[3]，我脑子里满是德语诗歌，这个苍白、有着致命眼神的女人，穿着绿色的衣服，好像从长着莎草的冰冷河水中出生，是一条古老河流的女儿。

“啊，拉蒂默，你一定等我很久了……”父亲说。

在我听到这句话时，眼前所有的人都消失了，我面前除了那扇竖在门口的中国屏风外什么都没有。我感到寒冷，开始打战，只能向前跄踉几步栽进沙发里。这奇怪的新能力再次显现……但这究竟是不是一种能力？这难道不是一种病吗？一种间歇性的狂想症，让我的头脑陷入不健康的活跃状态，让我清醒的时光变得更加贫瘠？我的亲眼所见使我感到一种不真实的晕眩感，我痉挛般地扑向铃铛，好似那要挣脱噩梦的人。我摇了两次铃，皮埃尔一脸惊恐地赶来。

“先生，你不舒服吗？[4]”他焦虑不安地问。

“我不能再等了，皮埃尔。”我说。就像一个醉酒的人努力清醒一样，我用强调的语气尽力把话说得清楚：“我想父亲一定出事了，他一向守时。快跑去贝尔格酒店看看他在不在那儿。”

皮埃尔立刻走出房间，走时安慰着说了一句“好的，先生[5]”。在这简短清醒的对话后，我立刻感觉好了一些。为了进一步安抚自己，我走进和客厅相连的卧室，打开盛放古龙香水的箱子，取出一瓶香水，非常小心地取下软木塞，然后将这提神的液体擦在双手、额头和鼻翼下。我从这香气中得到一种新的喜悦，因为我是用缓慢、细致的动作得到的它，而不是什么奇怪的、突发的疯狂。我已经感到一种恐惧，那种无法适应简单人类生活的人才会有的恐惧。

我一边享受着香气，一边走回客厅。和我离开时不同的是，这时客厅里已有人在。在中国屏风前站着的是我父亲，他右手边是菲尔莫尔夫人，而左手边正是那纤瘦的金发女孩儿。女孩儿表情热切、眼神锐利地盯着我，带着几分笑意好奇地打量着我。

“啊，拉蒂默，你一定等我很久了……”父亲说。

我什么都听不见、什么都感觉不到了，直到我重新意识到自己低头躺在沙发上，皮埃尔和父亲在我身边。等我彻底恢复后，父亲走出房间，很快又折回来，说：“我去向女士们告知你的情况，拉蒂默。她们在隔壁屋里等着。今天我们要推迟采购活动了。”

一会儿他说：“那位年轻的女士是伯莎・格兰特，菲尔莫尔夫人的侄女，她是个孤儿。菲尔莫尔一家领养了她，他们住在一起。我们回家后她就是我们的邻居了，也许还能是更近一层的关系。我猜，她和艾尔弗雷德之间有些情愫，既然菲尔莫尔会像对待女儿一样为她提供一切，他们结合我会很高兴。我也是刚想到，你还不知道她和菲尔莫尔一家一起生活了。”

他没提我刚才见到她时晕倒的事儿，我也绝不会告诉他原因⸺我不愿意向任何人泄露原因，他们很可能把这当成可悲的怪癖，尤其不愿意告诉我父亲，他很可能以后会一直怀疑我精神不正常。

我不想再讲这些经历的细节了。我详细地描述了这两件事，因为这对我后来的人生有确定无疑、清晰可辨的影响。

这次经历之后，很快，我想就是在第二天，我意识到我那病态的敏感性进入了一个新阶段，在我和其他人那些慵懒琐碎的接触中还未曾遇到这种情况。那就是，我的头脑会被他人的大脑活动入侵，一个接一个，凡是我碰巧接触到的人无一例外。那些乏味的相识，比如菲尔莫尔夫人，他们游移不定、无关紧要的想法和情绪，会像一件跑调的乐器纠缠不休地发出怪音，或像一只被困住的昆虫一样弄出大噪声，强行压在我的意识上。不过，这让人不快的敏感只是偶尔发作，只要同伴的灵魂离开我，就能获得片刻安宁，那时，我疲惫的神经就会得到舒缓。如果不是我预见的语言和行动与他人的内心活动确有关联，我会认为这只是我过于活跃的想象力的又一表现。这强加于我的意识要是来自我不关心的普通人，只会让我疲惫不堪、心烦意乱。可一旦来自与我关系亲密的身边人，这意识会带给我强烈的痛苦与悲伤，如同我撕开他们的灵魂，看到那些理智的谈论、优雅的关切、机智的话语，还有善良的行为⸺所有这一切构成人性格的网络被一种显微视野撕开⸺我看到网络背后，那些无聊透顶的愚蠢，那些强忍不发的自我主义，那些幼稚、卑鄙、模糊又反复无常的记忆之间的混乱战争，那些好逸恶劳、没有常性的思绪。在这网络之上，人的语言和行为如叶片一般，而藏在叶片之下的是一个发酵堆。

在巴塞尔，兄长艾尔弗雷德和我们会合了，他如今是一个英俊自信的二十六岁男人了，和虚弱、敏感又无所事事的我形成鲜明对比。我知道，人们眼中的我拥有着半女性化的、魅影般的美色，日内瓦多如牛毛的肖像画家常常请我当模特，在一幅糅合了想象和虚构的日常生活画中，他们还按照我的样子画了一位已故的吟游诗人。可是，我厌恶我的外貌，只有把它当作是诗性天才的一种展现，才能让我与之妥协。可是，如今我也不再怀有这种幻想，我在自己的脸上只能看到一种病态身体的印记，我这种身体生来就只能被动地受罪⸺一个人要写作诗歌、接受崇高感受必须体魄健壮，过于羸弱的身体是无法承担这一重任的。艾尔弗雷德几乎从小就和我分离，他现在的性格和外形，在我看来尤为陌生，但他尽力对我显出友善的样子，好似一个好兄长。他是一个幽默而自信的人，并且展现出这类性格典型的浮于表面的善意，因此他几乎没有敌人，也从未受到他人的挑战。我知道，以我的性格，即使我们的欲望没有重合，我也还免不了要嫉妒他。或者，假使我是一个健康的人，慷慨自信，又有乐善好施的好品德，我也还是要嫉妒他的。因为，我们天生就在性格上互相排斥。几周来，他成为我憎恨的对象，看到他走进房间，尤其是听到他讲话，我就仿佛听到了金属的摩擦声一般，忍不住地想要磨牙。和其他人相比，我病态的意识更加强烈地专注于他的思想和情绪。他的骄傲自负，他的居高临下，他自以为是地认为伯莎爱他，还有他半是可怜半是轻蔑地对待我，这些都让我恼火气愤。我对这些情绪的感知，不是来自语调、言辞和微小动作，不是心思敏感、天性多疑的人的捕风捉影，而是直接、赤裸裸地感受到了这一切。

我们是敌人，我们的欲望相撞了，尽管他对此还一无所知。我还没有讲过和伯莎・格兰特熟识一些后，她对我造成的影响。之所以如此，主要在于，她是我接触的所有人中唯一的例外，她游离在我那不幸的洞察力天赋之外。关于伯莎我总是处在一种不确信的状态，我可以观察她的面部表情，思考表情的意义；我可以怀着真实的无知询问她对一些事物的看法；我可以听她讲话，带着希冀或恐惧找寻她的微笑。对我来说，她具有一种无法被看透命运的魅力。我说过，伯莎对我的影响主要源于她的这种例外，因为，抽象而言，对于一个羞怯、爱空想又情绪激动的年轻人而言，伯莎几乎能算得上最没有魅力的那一类女性。她头脑锐利，态度讥讽，缺乏想象力，过早地愤世嫉俗，对所有壮丽的场景都不为所动，始终保持批评态度。她喜欢肢解我钟爱的所有诗歌，对德国诗歌尤其轻蔑不屑，须知德国诗歌可是我那时的心头肉。当时，我还没办法弄清我对她是种什么样的感情。这不是一种普通的少年崇拜，因为她，包括她头发的颜色在内，她的一切都是我理想中美好女性的对立面。她无意追求崇高、实现美善，而这两点，即使是在我最迷恋她的时候，也始终是我最看重的品格。但是，一个人要是有着病态敏感的天性，又无时无刻不渴望得到他人的同情和支持，那么，她这样一个自私自利、缺乏热情的人就能如暴君般控制这个人。在独立自信的人看来，一个人的沉默不语可以为他的意见增值。要是能征服一个吹毛求疵、讽刺挖苦的批评家，他就会感到额外的胜利感。这也无怪，在一位充满热情又深陷自我怀疑的青年眼中，坚守内心秘密的女性之脸就会变成神龛，他会观察、守候着这张脸，就像这神龛里供奉的是掌握他命运的善良神明。那激情澎湃的年轻人无法想象，引得自己热血沸腾的那个人居然内心毫无波澜，在感情上麻木不仁。他想，的确，她的情绪可能有些虚弱，若隐若现，也不大活跃，但她一定是具备这些情绪的，它们可以随时被调动起来。有时，在幸福的妄想中他甚至认为，既然他看不到丝毫的情绪表现，也许她内在的情绪力量更为强大。这种效果，如我所言，在我身上激起了最强烈的感受，伯莎是我唯一无法探究其秘密的人，我对她少年的幻想才得以维持。毫无疑问，我对她的痴迷也有另一些因素，那微妙的身体吸引会欺骗我们，让我们对她们产生错误的心理预期，让那些画精灵的画家爱上与精灵大相径庭的凶悍、肥胖且满脸雀斑的女人。

伯莎对我的举动，可以说是鼓励了我所有的幻想，增加了我孩子气的激情，也让我越发地迷恋她的一颦一笑。如今我饱经沧桑、阅历无数之后再回看那段时间，我认为，第一次相见时她对我造成的强烈印象使我晕厥，这极大地满足了她的虚荣心和权力欲。最干瘪无聊的女性也愿意相信，会有人把她奉为一个抒发强烈诗性情感的对象；而伯莎本人毫无浪漫色彩的性格，也为她未婚夫的弟弟爱她爱到垂死、为她嫉妒得发狂这一情节增添了更多的色彩。

当时，我并不相信她真的打算嫁给我兄长，因为尽管他百般殷勤地待她，尽管他和父亲已决定促成这段良缘，但毕竟两人之间还没有公开地谈及婚嫁，还没有明确地对外宣布。伯莎习惯性地和我的兄长打情骂俏，接受他的殷勤，这一举动透露出她知道他的心意。但是，她最微妙的表情与言辞⸺女性的一些无可指摘的小细节，却让我认为，其实她暗地里在取笑他，她认为他和我一样，也是一个花花公子，她以令其扫兴为乐。当着我兄长的面，她会公开地爱抚我，仿佛我过于年轻、过于虚弱，根本不会被看成一位情人，这正符合兄长眼中我的形象。但我相信，每当她用玩笑的态度一边轻轻拍着我的卷发一边取笑我的引语，她的内心一定为她在我身上所激起的波澜感到快乐。只有当着朋友们的面她才会这样抚摸我，我们二人独处时，她反倒会与我离得远些。她还会时不时地抓住机会，在语言和行动上刺激我，让我愚蠢又怯懦地期待着，她对我怀有胜于兄长的感情。她为何不听从心意呢？和我兄长比，我的条件没有那么优越，不过，我也有一笔财富，比她年轻不到一岁，何况，她也能够继承财产，并且很快就将进入可以自己做选择的年龄。

我时而充满希望，时而充满恐惧，我被她如此控制，在她身边的每一天都是甜蜜的折磨。她干下的一件事尤其让我为她发狂。我们在维也纳的那段时间恰逢她二十岁生日，她非常喜欢首饰，我们大家都竭力在这座日耳曼巴黎城的珠宝商铺挑选珠宝，作为她的生日礼物。我准备的礼物自然不是最昂贵的，礼物是一枚蛋白石戒指。蛋白石是我最钟爱的宝石，它如同有灵魂一般，会害羞脸红，也会变得苍白。在把礼物送给伯莎时，我这样向她解释着，并且还告诉她蛋白石象征着诗人的天性，会随着天光的变化和女人眼波的流转而起起伏伏。傍晚时，她着装典雅，招摇地穿戴上所有生日礼物，却唯独没有戴我赠予她的那份礼物。我满眼热切地盯着她的手指，却找不到那块蛋白石。那天晚上我没有机会问她，到了第二天，我看她早餐后独自坐在窗边，就对她说：“你不屑于戴我那可怜兮兮的蛋白石。我本该记得，你是看不起诗人天性的。我本该送你珊瑚或者绿松石的，或者其他什么不透明、不会变化的石头，那就好了。”“我看不起？”她一边答道，一边从胸口拉出那条她常戴在脖子上的细细的金链，项链的尾端挂着我送她的戒指。“说实在的，它有点儿弄疼我了，”她带着她常有的暧昧微笑说，“我把它戴在了那么隐秘的地方，不过，既然你诗人的天性如此愚钝，竟然希望我把它戴在外面，我可不受这份罪了。”

她把戒指从项链上取下，戴在手指上，仍旧挂着那种微笑。我顿时感到血涌上我的脸颊，想恳求她照原样戴它，可是一句话也讲不出来。

这件事彻底愚弄了我。两天来，只要伯莎不在，我就把自己锁在屋里反复回味这个让我痴迷的场景，回味它隐含的各种意义。

这里我要提一句，两个月来，我经历的快乐和痛苦是如此强烈、如此新奇，我感觉好像过了漫长的一生。这段时间，我病态地参与他人的头脑活动，持续地受此折磨，一会儿是我的父亲，一会儿是我兄长，一会儿是菲尔莫尔夫人或是她的丈夫，一会儿又是我们的德国向导，他们的意识流涌向我，如同无法摆脱的耳鸣声。不过，我自己的冲动和思想是不受这些干扰的。这就好像我的听力得到超自然力量的加强，别人感觉寂静无声，在我听来却是震耳欲聋。我被迫卷入他人的灵魂，这给我带来的疲惫和恶心只有一种办法可以消除，那就是我对伯莎的无知，还有我对她日渐增长的激情⸺我对她的无知极大地助长了这激情，抑或是，这激情就源于我对她的无知。在可怕的已知沙漠中，她是我神秘的绿洲。我从不让自己的病态显露出来，也不会说反常的话、做反常的事，只有一次例外，那时我对兄长怀着尤其强烈的敌意，我聪明地预见到他准备好打算说的话，先他一步说了出来。有时，他说话会装腔作势地停顿一下，他刚说到第二个词就停下来，我对他既不耐烦又很嫉妒，就顺口说出他后面的话，好像我们两人都提前背好了词。转眼间，他的脸色就变了，看上去十分震惊，也很懊恼。我刚说完话就感到了警觉，这话出现在这个情境中绝非理所当然，不可能随意猜到，我唯恐对他语言的预测会暴露我是一个特殊的人，一个看似安静却被恶魔附体的人，这样的人会让所有人惊恐、避之不及，尤其是伯莎。不过，和往常一样，我还是高估了我的言行对他人的影响，所有人都把我的打断视为一次粗俗无礼的行为，看在我神经脆弱的面子上原谅了我。

对现实世界附加的意识几乎时时刻刻纠缠着我，不过，和伯莎第一次见面时的那种清晰的预见却没有再发生过，与此同时，我急不可耐地想知道我对布拉格的预见是否真实。在我送出蛋白石戒指之后不久，我们再一次游览了曾多次造访的利希滕山宫殿。我一向不能连续地欣赏多幅绘画，因为绘画，只要是有力量的绘画，一两幅作品就会耗尽我的精力，使我无法继续思考。这天早晨，我一直在欣赏乔尔乔内的那幅画，画中女人长着可怕的眼睛，人们说这是卢克雷齐娅・波吉亚的画像。我驻足在画作前，慢慢地欣赏它。画像中那张面孔狡黠、无情得过于真实，这让我着迷。突然，一种奇特而有害的感受向我袭来，好像长久以来我吸入了致命的毒气，毒气就要发作。也许当时若不是大家决定离开，我根本就不会从那张画像前抽身。艾尔弗雷德和菲尔莫尔先生为一幅肖像画打了赌，大家决定去贝尔维迪尔画廊看看究竟谁胜谁负。我迷迷糊糊地跟着大家，对周身的一切没有了知觉，直到大家都走去画廊，我就不再继续跟着了⸺我不愿再看画了。我走向大阳台，大家商量好，他们两人解决矛盾的时候其他人可以在花园里散步。我坐在这里小憩，对周围花园的意识已经模糊了，远处是城市和绿色的山丘。为了躲避走来的哨兵，我起身走到开阔的石头路上，想到花园的边上坐一坐。正当我走上沙砾小路的时候，我感到一只手臂挽着我的手臂，一只纤细小手轻轻搂着我的腰。同时，一种叫人痴醉的麻木感席卷我的全身，就像我在卢克雷齐娅・波吉亚的注视下所产生的那种感受的延续，或者说这正是那种感受的高潮。花园、夏日的天空，我对伯莎的手臂挽着我手臂的意识，所有这一切都消失了，我好像一下子掉入了黑暗，从中逐渐升起一个微小的火光，我感觉，我身处家中的书房，正坐在父亲的皮椅上。有我熟悉的壁炉⸺旁边是喜欢看柴火燃烧的狗们⸺黑色大理石烟囱中间是白色大理石徽章，徽章中心描画的是垂死的克利奥佩特拉。强烈而无望的痛苦压迫着我的灵魂，这时火光更明亮了些，是伯莎持着一柄蜡烛走近我⸺伯莎，我的妻子，有着一双残酷冷漠的眼睛，戴着绿色的宝石，白色的礼服裙子也镶着绿色的边，她头脑里每一个憎恨的想法都呈现在我面前：“疯子，白痴！你怎么不自杀呢？……”那一刻我如同身在地狱。我看到她的灵魂毫无怜悯心，满是赤裸裸的恶俗和尖酸刻薄的仇恨，也感到这灵魂如空气般包裹着我，而我不得不呼吸这样的空气。为什么她手里拿着蜡烛，站在我面前，用那冷酷而轻蔑的眼睛盯着我看？而她胸前那闪闪发光的蛇，像一个似曾相识的魔鬼。我周身颤抖，我鄙视这个女人赤裸的灵魂、刻薄的思想。但我在她面前感到无力，滴血的心脏似乎被她紧紧攥着，她仿佛要一直攥着这心脏，直到它流尽最后一滴鲜血。她是我的妻子，可我们憎恨着彼此。渐渐地，壁炉、昏暗的藏书室、蜡烛的光亮都消失了，它们都淹没在背景的光亮中，留在视网膜上的黑色图像只有那条钻石眼睛的绿蛇。随后，我感到自己的眼睑在颤抖，白昼的光重新打亮我，我看到了花园，我听到了说话声，我坐在贝尔维迪尔的台阶上，我的朋友们就在身边。

这次丑陋的预见扰得我心绪不宁，我一连生病了几天，让我们在维也纳多待了些时日。这次场景不断重现，让我惊恐万分，而且所有微小的细节也跟着不断重现，好像它们已经烙印在我的记忆里。然而，人类心灵的疯狂就在于它受短暂欲望的驱使，一想到伯莎就要属于我，我就感到一种疯狂的、地狱般的快乐，因为她第一次出现在我面前的那个预见已成现实，这让我确信，我对未来的可怕预见并非我病态头脑的游戏，与外在现实没有联系。只有一件事可能挑战我那可怕的预见力，那就是我对布拉格的预见是错误的，而布拉格就是我们下一站行程要去的城市，我对此十分期待。

直到我恢复了此前对伯莎的痴迷，我才重新与她接触。我害怕我会在她心里读到那个成熟的伯莎，那个作为我妻子的伯莎的想法。伯莎，这个年轻的女子，她的内心对我来说仍是秘密⸺我会在她的抚摸下颤抖，她在我身边我就着迷，我渴望能确认她对我的爱。在干渴的感受面前，毒药也变得不足为惧了。不，我和以前一样嫉妒我的兄长，和以前一样对他那种居高临下的做事方式感到不快，我的自尊心、我病态的敏感性和以前一样，对任何冒犯行为都无可救药地畏缩惧怕，即使是一粒灰尘掉入眼睛也会畏缩惧怕。未来，不过是一个想法，即使对未来的预见让我颤抖，和当下感情的力量⸺我对伯莎的爱，我对兄长的厌恶和嫉妒相比，也不足道。

老故事说，人们把自己卖给了古老的诱惑者撒旦，用血签订了契约，便冲向那杯满足他们灵魂饥渴的酒。他们认为后果只会发生在遥远的将来。这种激情野蛮而强烈，并不因为一个黑暗的影子要从此跟随在他们身边而怯懦分毫。通向智慧的道路没有捷径，没有已经铺好的路，几百年来我们有无数的创造发明，但直到今天，我们的灵魂仍须走在满是荆棘的荒野之地，必须孤独地踩在这样的土地上，脚上鲜血淋漓，哭泣着喊着求救，正如我们的先辈所艰难探索的那样。

我头脑里琢磨着如何才能战胜我的情敌⸺我的兄长，我还是那么胆小，不知道伯莎真实的感受，不敢贸然采取行动，让她主动说明心意。我想，如果我对布拉格的预见是真的，我就会对伯莎对我的感情有更多的自信。然而，我又怕预见是真的！我仔细观察她的言辞、表情。她的抚摸是我的福音，但在这瘦弱的伯莎身后始终站着那个丰满些的伯莎，她有严苛的眼神、冷酷的嘴唇，我看透她赤裸裸的自私灵魂，她不再是那个迷人的秘密，而是一个看得清清楚楚的事实，这事实不断压迫着我的眼界。读到此处的读者，你难道不同情我吗？你难道想象不出，在我体内有两种意识同时存在，如同两条平行流淌的河流，永远不会融汇在一起，不会披上同一个色彩？不过，你一定理解，预见与激情相撞会产生的那种不祥感受，我的预见就如同这不祥预感一般，只是更为强烈而转变为了一种恐惧。你也一定理解，和冲动相比，思想是多么无力，一旦将预见储存为记忆，它们也就化为思想，如影子一般苍白无力，可我的手却由那些鲜活的、我所爱的人紧握着。

在后来的日子里，我怀着悔恨想，如果当初我预见的内容丰富些，或者预见到的是别的事物⸺如果当初我的预见没有那么丑陋，它毒化了激情却不足以杀死激情，又或者除了我所见的，我能预见到我和兄长生前最后一次相见的情景，一种柔和的力量就会改变我对他的感情⸺骄傲和憎恨就会转化为怜悯，我对他隐藏的罪恶也会减少。不过，这只是我们人类聊以自慰的东西。我们试图相信，我们内在的自我本可以轻易融化，只是自身知识的浅薄才会妨碍我们的慷慨、我们的敬畏、我们的虔诚，妨碍我们对同伴施以同情。一旦我们终结了自我主义，我们就会变得温柔，变得愿意为他人奉献。我身上的自我主义是以这种方式终结的，我对胜利的苦苦追求是由另一个人的失败促成的，这胜利来得突然，让我打冷战，因为它是死神冰冷的手带来的。

我们到达布拉格的时候正值夜晚时分，我很高兴，这意味着几个小时里我们都看不清这座城市，那个决定我命运的可怕时刻就会迟些到来。由于我们在布拉格不会久留，要很快赶去德累斯顿，大家提议第二天一早出发浏览一下城市全貌，赶在暑气上升前去看一些特别重要的景点，因为当时正值八月，天气又热又干。不过，到了那天早晨，女士们梳洗得很迟，我父亲压着火，尽量表现得客客气气，大家还是能看出他这份不满，直到上午晚些时候我们才上了马车。走进犹太人区的时候，我的心情略感快慰。我们原计划参观那古老的犹太会堂，它位于城市中一个平整、封闭的地方，我原以为大家会在这里一直待到又累又热无法游览的时候，那样我们就会匆匆返回，就会错过看沿途街道的景色。这样，我就又拥有一天的悬念⸺对一个充满恐惧的灵魂来说，只有悬念能带来一些慰藉的希望。不过，当我站在这座犹太会堂那些黑色带穹棱的拱顶下时，圣灯七柄瘦弱的蜡烛照出犹太会堂微弱的轮廓，我们的犹太导游伸手拿起律法书，用古老的语言读给我们听⸺我感到一阵颤抖，这座奇怪的建筑及其微弱的灯，这座中世纪犹太教幸存下来的有些凋敝的古迹，都与我之前的预见有着相同的特征。那些有点儿变黑的、布满尘土的基督教圣人像立在高大的穹顶之下，被硕大的蜡烛点亮，它们在人们心中激起一种带有宽慰的轻蔑，又带着这种轻蔑看向更加枯竭、地狱般的人间。

如我所料，我们一离开犹太人区，年长的人就要回酒店。但现在，和预想的不同，我没有为此高兴，相反，我有一种压倒一切的冲动要赶去看那座桥，立刻终结我一直想要推延的悬念。我异常坚定地告诉大家，我要下马车一个人走走，他们不必带我先回去。我父亲认为，这不过是我那“诗人胡闹”的又一例证，他反对我独自一人在暑天散步，这会伤害我的身体。见我坚持，他生气地说，我尽可以由着性子无理取闹，但施密特（我们的向导）必须跟着我。我同意这个安排，和施密特出发去看那座桥。我正穿过一座雄伟壮观的古老大门的拱道，这拱道直通那座桥，突然被一种颤抖附身，正午的炎炎烈日之下我感到一股冰冷。但我继续前行，我在找寻某样东西，一个能唤回那次预见景象的某样东西。就是它⸺一盏星星样式的多彩灯在人行道上洒下一块块彩虹色的光斑。

第二章

秋日结束之前，庄园里山毛榉的棕色树叶仍繁茂地挂在树梢上，兄长和伯莎订婚了，大家都觉得，来年春天早些时候他们会举行婚礼。除了在布拉格的那座桥上的一瞬间我确定伯莎有一天会成为我的妻子，其余时刻，我体质中的胆小多疑仍然使我不敢行动，我反复练习爱的表白，却一直说不出口。我内心深处的矛盾仍旧存在，我既渴求伯莎能亲口吐露对我的爱，又害怕她的蔑视和拒绝会像酸一样腐蚀我。即便对遥远的未来有十足的把握，又有什么用呢？我颤抖于当下的眼神，我饥渴于当下的快乐，我受制于当下的恐惧。就这样，日子一天天过去了：我目睹了伯莎的订婚，听人们谈论着她的婚事。仿佛我身处一个清醒的噩梦中，我知道这个梦会消失，可我像被他人扼住喉咙一般无法呼吸。

我经常和伯莎在一起，她带着几分戏谑对我屈尊降贵，我们在一起也不会招致兄长的嫉妒。我不在她身边时，白天的时光都用来游荡、散步或远足，或者把自己和那些并没有在读的书关在一起⸺书已经无法吸引我的注意力了。我的自我意识已经到达无以复加的强度，我的情绪会上演戏剧，强迫进入我的思想，对痛苦的思考⸺而不是痛苦本身⸺令我落泪。我为自己命运的悲壮感到哀伤沉痛，这命运精心设计好如何让我痛苦，却没理清怎么让我快乐，对我来说，未来的罪恶剥夺了我此时此刻的欢愉，未来的美好却不能安抚我此时此刻的渴求与恐惧。在这苦行中，真正的诗人会感受到咏诵大量诗句带来的甜美，也会为他的种种悲伤塑造意象，但我却只是沉默地忍受着。

我如此醉生梦死地度日，却没有任何人来责备我，我知道父亲是怎么看我的：“那孩子终究一事无成，他会在无关紧要的事儿上浪费大把青春，靠着留给他的一点儿收入生活，我是不会操心为他谋一个职业的。”

十一月初的一个和煦的早晨，碰巧我站在门廊外轻抚那条懒散的老狗恺撒。这是一条老得几乎要瞎的纽芬兰狗，是唯一一条亲近我的狗⸺狗一般都会绕开我，到身边更快乐的人们那里摇尾乞怜。这时，马夫把兄长那匹狩猎时骑的马牵来。兄长也来到门口，他容光焕发、胸膛宽厚、自信十足，他自我感觉真是一个不错的人，他本可以靠着他的本钱更傲慢无礼地对待我们的。

“拉蒂默，老伙计，”他带着几分同情和热忱对我说，“真遗憾啊，你不经常带着猎狗跑一跑！对情绪低落的人来说，这可是世上最好的事儿！”

“情绪低落！”看着他走远，我愤怒地想，“这就是你这种粗俗狭隘的人会用的词儿，用来描述你理解不了的东西，你和你的马一样蠢。对你们这样的人而言，世上的好事便是心甘情愿的无聊、心智健康的自私以及伪装成好脾气的自满，而这些就是你们通向幸福的关键。”

很快我就想到，我比他更自私，只不过我的自私会带来痛苦，不会带来享受。但是，我恼怒地洞察到艾尔弗雷德那自负的灵魂，他没有怀疑也没有恐惧，没有未满足的渴望，亦无多愁善感导致的折磨，这些却构成了我生活的网络，这割断了我与他所有的感情纽带。这个男人无须怜悯，无须爱，他感受不到这些高尚的力量，如同岩石感受不到晶莹露水的轻抚。他不会遇到什么不幸的事情，要是他没有和伯莎结婚，也是因为他找到了更舒服的生活。

离我们的大门不足半里远就是菲尔莫尔先生的房子，每次我一得知兄长去了别处，就跑去看伯莎是否在家。那天晚些时候我走去那里。非常凑巧她独自一人在家，难得我们一起到开阔的场地上散步，而她平时则鲜少踏足整齐的碎石子路之外的地方。我记得，十一月份低沉的阳光照在她金色的头发上，在我眼里她如同一个美丽的精灵，她轻快地边走边跳，和平时一样和我开玩笑，有时我听得很高兴，有时我听得很难过，这就是伯莎那谜一样的内在自我显露给我的样子。今天，难过的情绪占了上风，刚刚和兄长分开时他那颐指气使的劲儿让我嫉妒、憎恨。突然，我打断她，几乎用一种粗暴的态度对她说：“伯莎，你怎么可以爱艾尔弗雷德？”这话吓了她一跳。

她惊讶地看了我一会儿，很快恢复了淡淡的微笑，讥讽地回答：“为什么你会觉得我爱他？”

“你怎么能这么问，伯莎？”

“怎么？你的聪明才智告诉你我必须爱我未来的丈夫？那可是世上最难过的事。我可能会和他争吵，我可能会为他充满嫉妒，我可能会把家务弄得一团糟。轻微而默不作声的蔑视能让生活优雅许多。”

“伯莎，这不是你真实的感受。你为什么以欺骗我为乐，编造这愤世嫉俗的说辞？”

“我不需要费这个劲儿撒谎来骗你，我的小塔索[6]（这是她取笑我时经常叫的名字）。欺骗一个诗人的最好办法是告诉他实话。”

她正十分大胆地测试这警句的真实性，有那么一瞬间，我预见的影子⸺那个我已经洞悉其灵魂的伯莎⸺出现在我和这个光彩照人的女孩儿之间，这嬉笑精灵的感情对我仍是个谜。我想我可能身体发抖了，或者用什么别的方式泄露了我这一瞬间的恐惧。

“塔索！”她说着，抓住我的手臂，看着我的脸，“你真的开始觉察出我是一个铁石心肠的女孩儿了吗？我想，你连半个诗人都不配当，你居然会相信我说的是实话。”

游荡在我们之间的那个影子离开了。面前的这个女孩儿纤细的手指握着我，她精灵般有魅力的脸庞望着我的脸庞⸺我想，她正对我流露出一种此前从未公开承认的兴趣⸺这个呼吸温暖的人又一次占据了我的感官和想象力，她犹如一段仙人的乐章，刚刚有那么一瞬，这乐章被汹涌的海浪声盖过，如今这乐章又回来了。这一瞬间甘之若饴，我仿佛是一个青年人，做了中年人的梦，醒来发现自己仍是青年人一样。我忘记了一切，只记得我的激情，我眼含热泪地说：“伯莎，你能在我们新婚时爱我吗？哪怕你的爱只是那么一会儿，我也会高兴的。”

她十分震惊，放开我的手离开了我，这让我马上意识到自己的古怪和罪恶的轻率。

“原谅我，”等我恢复了说话能力后，我马上说，“我不知道我在说什么。”

“啊，塔索疯狂的症状又开始了，我明白了，”她平静地答道⸺她比我恢复得快，“让他回家吧，让他头脑变得清醒吧。我必须回家了，太阳要落山了。”

我离开了她，对自己满是懊恼。如果她细想我的失言，可能认为我的精神状态不正常，这是我最怕的一种怀疑。除此之外，我为刚才明目张胆的卑鄙行径感到羞愧，我居然对兄长的未婚妻说出这样的话。我缓慢地游荡回家，没有从大门的门房走，而是通过一扇小门走进庄园。我走近房子的时候看到一个人全速从马厩跑出来穿过庄园。家里难道出事了吗？不，可能只是我父亲又蛮横地做了什么安排。尽管如此，我没有什么明确的目的，还是加快了脚步，很快我就到家了。我就不描述家里发生的事情了。我的兄长去世了⸺他从马上摔下来，当场死于脑震荡。

我走进他躺着的屋子，父亲坐在他身边，脸上是沉痛的绝望。自从我们回家后，我一直躲避着父亲，我们的天性存在着巨大差异，对他内心世界的窥视会给我带来持续的痛苦。但是眼下，我走近他，悲伤地站在他身边，一句话也没说，我感到一种全新的因素把我们融为一体，我们以前从未如此亲近。我的父亲在这巧取豪夺的金钱世界属于那种最成功的人士，他从未体验过多愁善感的痛苦，也不曾忍受疾病。他所经历过的最大的痛苦就是他第一位妻子的死亡。不过，他随后很快与我母亲结婚，据那时年幼的我的观察，小时候母亲去世后一周，他就恢复如常了。但眼下，终于，他也感到了悲痛⸺人老年时的悲剧尤其痛苦，骄傲与希望有多狭隘、有多单调，骄傲与希望的毁灭就会带来多大的打击。他的儿子马上就要结婚了，下次选举时还很有可能当选区代表。这样一个儿子本身就是他每年购买土地、壮大宅院的最大动力。要是没有个动力，失去了目的，年复一年做着同样的事就是苦差。也许，年迈时世俗中的悲剧要比青年时代失落的激情所带来的悲剧要更加痛苦。

我看到父亲心中的孤寂，对他产生了深切的同情，这引发了一种全新的感情。这段感情不断地成长壮大，尽管在兄长去世后的一两个月里他用一种怪异的憎恨表情看待我，也不曾阻碍我对他感情的日渐深厚。若不是因为我对他的同情软化了我⸺这是我第一次体会到深刻的同情⸺我就会被他的态度刺伤。他把长子的继承权移交给了我，仿佛忍受着命运的强迫，命运强迫他必须把我当作一个重要的人来照顾，这让他感到受辱不悦。他不是出于自愿，而是出于责任，开始为我忧虑。死亡空出了一个位子，让一个被父母忽视的孩子得到了垂爱，想必所有拥有类似经历的孩子都能理解我此时的处境。

出于同情我对他也很有耐心，这使得我处处遵从他的意愿，逐渐地赢得了他的青睐。虽然我比兄长的性格懦弱些，但他开始努力让我尽量填补兄长的位置并以此为乐。而逐渐地，他也开始接受我成为伯莎的丈夫这一不断浮现的可能，他甚至想让我和他的儿媳伯莎同他一起生活，这是他不曾为我兄长考虑过的。我对父亲的温柔感情使得这段时光成为自我童年时代以来最快乐的时间。这也是最后的几个月里，我得以保留了对伯莎爱的甜美幻觉，我渴望，我怀疑，我希冀她能爱我。自我兄长去世后，她意识到了什么新的可能，和我保持着距离。同样，我也被一种双重的约束限制着，一方面我要小心处置跟兄长有关的记忆，另一方面我担忧她会怎么看待我说过的那些唐突话。但是，我们各自的缄默竖立起的额外屏障，反而让我更为她神魂颠倒⸺无论人的内在如何贫瘠，只要这面纱足够厚实。我们的灵魂需要一些隐秘、不确定的东西来维持怀疑、维持希望、维持努力，这些就是生命的氧气。如果今天以后的整个未来都在我们面前展开，全人类的兴趣就会凝聚在明天到来之前的这几个小时，我们会拼命追逐这最后一个清晨、最后一个下午；我们会勇猛地冲进交易所做最后一次投机，以把握住最后一次胜利或最后一次失望；我们会在预言到来前拥有大量的政治先知，预测仅存的二十四小时中的一次危机或一次和平。想象一下，对人类头脑来说，如果一切命题都不证自明，只有一个例外，唯有等到夏日终结才能弄清这个命题，那么在等待的这段时间里，这唯一的命题就会成为所有疑问、所有假说、所有辩论的中心。艺术与哲学、文学与科学，都会如蜜蜂一般围绕这个命题，这命题包裹着如甘甜蜂蜜般的不确定性，而鉴于落日时分他们的快乐就要终结，他们对这一命题便更加热切。我们的动机、我们的精神活动不会因这一命题未来的虚无而休止，只要我们的心脏还在跳动，只要我们的肌肉还能感受刺激，这种精神活动就会延续。

伯莎，这纤瘦、浅色头发的女孩儿，在这一刻，她的思想和情绪对我而言都还是谜。对我这能看透身边人的头脑、疲惫不堪的人来说，她是那唯一有吸引力的“今日”，是日落之前都能保持神秘的“假想命题”，是我天性中所有的坚信和怀疑唯一而狭窄的出口，我的信赖和猜忌纷纷涌向她。

她使我相信她是爱我的。她没有改变之前打趣的语气和那半开玩笑、高人一等的态度，却能弄得我神魂颠倒，让我以为她离不开我，只要我不在身边她就寝食难安，我心甘情愿地臣服于她这戏谑的暴君。一个女人竟能如此轻易地迷惑我们！只要话说一半，来一次出人意料的沉默，甚至轻而易举地演一出无理取闹，就能让我们像服用了大麻一样飘飘然。除了微妙的、不易察觉的种种迹象外，她还为我编织出了一个幻想，那就是，一直以来在潜意识里她爱我胜于爱艾尔弗雷德。不过，像我兄长这样闯荡世界的男人的青睐，对于她这样一个无知又焦虑敏感的年轻女性而言，有着巨大的吸引力。她优雅地自嘲她的虚荣和野心。除了我兄长自身的优点，我现在占有了他一切的优势，而即使我曾经在预见这一刻时怀有忧愁，又有什么关系呢？在我们甜美的幻觉中，我们不也没有忘记真实的残酷吗？就好像看着美妙的光影时，我们也没有忘记它们是由华而不实的玻璃碎屑发出的。

艾尔弗雷德去世十八个月后，四月一个寒冷萧瑟的早晨我们结婚了。那天既有冰雹也有阳光，伯莎穿着白色丝绸的衣裙，上面有着淡绿色边饰，她的头发和脸庞略显苍白，整个人看上去如同清晨的仙子。我父亲比他预想的还要高兴：他确信，婚礼会把我的性格最终改造成他想要的样子，让我学会务实，变得通人情，这样才能在心智正常的社会中立足。伯莎的世故圆滑、敏捷机智颇得他的欢心，他确信，我一定会受她约束，变成她想要的样子，因为我只有二十一岁，疯狂地爱着她。可怜的父亲！他的这些愿望仅仅维持到我们婚后一年，当时我们的感情还没有完全消散，而父亲在这时中风，也不会饱受失望之苦。

随后发生的故事我要快些讲了，不能如之前那般描述我的内心经验了。我们要像人们熟识后那样，只谈论外部发生了什么，内在的感受和情绪只留待推测。

我们回家后，每日宾客盈门、迎来送往，家里举办了许多奢华的晚宴，我们新置办的用具光鲜亮丽，引得邻居们十分艳羡。我父亲一直隐藏着他日益增长的财富，直到我的婚礼期间才展现出来。熟人们尽可以自由地品评，我这个继承人、新郎官身材过于弱不禁风。这样的日子使我精疲力竭，人们的虚情假意和陈词滥调我都得忍受两遍，内心世界和外在世界各自经历一遍，若不是我仍沉浸在初恋的甜美醉意中，这些事情都会令我抓狂。一对新郎和新娘，被象征财富的种种奢华包裹，整日在社交生活中忙碌，抓住仅有的独处时间仓促爱抚。他们如此为未来的婚姻生活做准备，如同即将进入修道院的新人在最后一刻花天酒地⸺体验着现在与未来极大的反差。

在这门庭若市令人兴奋的几个月中，伯莎的内在自我仍旧隐藏在我的洞察之外，我仍旧只能通过她的言谈举止推测她的思想，我仍旧十分好奇我的言语、行为是否取悦她，仍旧渴望听她讲一句亲密的话，仍旧夸张地解读她微笑背后的深意。不过，我已经觉察出她对我的态度变了。有时候，她的态度真是傲慢无礼、冰冷僵硬，如同我们婚礼那天上午穿透阳光的冰雹，她的寒冷刺骨伤透了我的心，这种变化只能从她巧妙地回避与我单独散步、单独共进晚餐中体会出来，而这些原本都是我所期盼的。这些深深地伤害了我，我的心灵从未遭受过如此打击，我预感到快乐的生活即将结束了。不过，我仍旧依靠着伯莎，渴望享受幸福的最后一缕光辉。尽管这光辉就要永远地消逝了，我仍旧渴望着、找寻着夕阳那因为降临的夜晚而更显魅力的余晖。

我记得，我怎么能忘呢？依赖与希望彻底摒弃我的那个时刻，伯莎对我日渐疏远。这原本造成了我的痛苦，在那一刻看来，却变成了快乐，如一个肢体瘫痪的人留恋最后一次感到疼痛一般。这一刻发生在父亲的最后一次病痛结束之后。父亲最后一次生病时，我们不得不远离社交生活，只剩下彼此相互依偎。一切都发生在父亲去世的那天傍晚。那天晚上，一直遮蔽伯莎灵魂的面纱第一次被掀开了⸺在我身边的所有人中，唯有这面纱被赋予了神秘、怀疑和期盼的可能性。也许，自我爱她以来，那天是第一次，我对她的爱恋被另外一种更深邃的感情冲淡了。父亲去世时，我一直守候在那张床前：我目睹了他的灵魂最后一次颤抖地回顾他一生挥霍的财富，我紧握住他的手让他最后一次体会到爱。当我们体会到了那极致的痛苦时，我们个人的恋爱又算些什么呢？而当我们再次从死亡面前走开，在我们的体验中，我们与每一个生者的关系就变成了整个自然和人类整体命运的一部分。

我抱着这种想法，走去伯莎的起居室找她。她背对着门，身体前倾靠在沙发椅上，从沙发椅的后面能看到她浓密的淡黄色卷发垂肩，衬出她纤细的脖子。我记得，我转身关门的一刹那，一股寒意侵袭了我，我开始颤抖，模模糊糊地感到我遭人怨恨、深陷孤独，这感受虽然模糊却很强烈，好像一种预兆。我知道那一刻我是什么神情，因为，伯莎抬起冷酷的灰色眼睛望着我时，我洞见到她如何看我：在她眼中，我是一个可怜的幽灵预见者，青天白日里我被鬼魂缠身，树叶纹丝不动时一阵阴风却让我战栗不止，我对人们寻常渴望的事物一概没有兴趣，却热切地追求那月光。我们面对面僵持着，审判着对方。可怕的光明终于降临到我身上，在这光明下我清楚地看到，遮蔽着她灵魂的那一团黑暗之后并没有一处田园风景，只有一堵空虚无聊的墙。那以后，在越发令人厌恶的岁月中，我彻底看清这个女人狭隘的灵魂，看清那些卑微的小诡计、无聊的小脾气。曾经，我愿意相信，这些都只是忸怩的多愁善感，是智慧和潜在的情感发生冲突时的表现。我看到，少女的那几许轻柔飘浮的虚荣心已转变为女人的伎俩，转变为精心设计的卖弄风情、诡计多端的自私自利。我看到，少女的厌恶和反感转变为女性的残忍憎恨，仅仅为了自己发脾气而给别人施加痛苦。

伯莎，按她自己的感受来说，也吃到了幻想破灭的苦头。她本以为，疯狂的诗人激情会让我成为她的奴隶，这样，作为她的奴隶我会按照她的心意办事。以她最为浅薄、缺乏想象力的本性，她不知道，多愁善感的人并非性格软弱。她本以为，我的无能会将我置于她的股掌之中，却发现我并不轻易顺从她。我们的位置调过来了。结婚前，她完全控制了我的想象力，那是因为她对我是个谜，我看不透她，我造出一种思想安在她身上当成是她的，并为此颤抖癫狂。现如今，她的灵魂一览无余，我被迫知道了她隐秘的动机，知道她说话办事前的所有小伎俩，除了让我感到寒心、厌恶外，她对我无能为力。她无能为力，是因为她没有逼我就范的筹码。我没有野心在世俗中争得上游，无意于在社交生活中左右逢源，她那狭隘的头脑能想象到的所有诱惑我都无动于衷，因此，我究竟为什么而活，她根本想不出。

有这样一个丈夫，她真是可怜，全世界都这么想。一个像伯莎这样典雅、美妙的女人，她在清晨时对唤醒她的仆人报以微笑，在舞会上展现身姿风采，能够机敏地应答⸺这一点在外人看来是女人智慧的表现，她获得了所有人的同情。她的丈夫看上去病恹恹的，不务正业，一些人甚至揣测我精神错乱。甚至家里的仆人都向她投以尊重和怜悯。我们之间从来不争吵，我们的疏远、厌恶只藏在彼此心里。如果女主人经常出门，看上去不喜欢与男主人相处，这对于一个可怜人来说不是很正常吗？男主人是个怪人。我对仆人一向善良、公正，不过，他们对我有点儿畏惧，有点儿轻蔑地可怜我，因为，他们这个阶层的男男女女对人缺乏独立的判断，易受其他人所持观念的影响，而他们用经验分辨人的性格。他们看待人就像看待硬币，认为那些像流通货币一样被人们广泛称赞的人即是更好的个体。

一段时间后，我几乎从不干涉伯莎的生活习惯，可伯莎还是强烈地憎恨我。可能是我不自觉地泄露了什么，她开始怀疑我具有看穿人的病态能力⸺至少每隔一段时间我能神奇地看穿她的思想和意图⸺她开始惧怕我，时不时地，不是惧怕我就是蔑视我。她一直考虑如何摆脱我这梦魇，如何与我彻底斩断联系。我曾像一个白痴一般被她看不起，如今却像审判长一样让她恐惧，她恨我。很长一段时间里，她希望，我那可怜的性情有一天会逼我自杀。不过，我的天性是不会让我自杀的。我深信，我受不可见的力量控制，无法靠自己的力量求得解脱。我对自己的命运是完全被动的。我唯一的欲望已经耗尽，再没有冲动凌驾于理性之上了。因此，我从没想过要彻底和她分居，因为那样做就是把我们的疏远弄得世人皆知。我为什么要改弦更张呢？我眼下的痛苦就是我曾经强烈意愿的后果。一个仍有欲望要满足的人会寻求改变，可我已没有了欲望。不过，我和伯莎还是分离得越来越远。对于富人而言，在婚姻内分开生活并不是一件难事。

我的几句话就描述了我们几年来的生活。仇恨与罪恶缓慢却丑陋地积累出那么多苦难，最后居然囊括在一句话中！人们就是靠着这简短的一句话，总结评价彼此的人生。他们把同伴的经历浓缩，用干练的词句下了审判，这么做能让他们感到自己是多么智慧、多么善良，用几个精挑细选的谓语动词就说出了那些困扰他们的诱惑。一个人倘若从未体会过冰冷的失望，从未感受过头脑和心灵的悸动，没有时而惊恐不安、时而虚妄自负，不知何为后悔、何为绝望，才会一笔带过七年的蹉跎岁月。我们只是死记硬背下词语，并不熟谙词语的内涵，唯有经历过血的洗礼才能真的理解它们，把它们写入我们的神经。

不过，我要加快说完我的故事了。对那一点就通的人，我应该说得简洁些；对那永远也理解不了其中道理的人，我也该说得简洁些。

我父亲去世几年后，一月的一个傍晚，我在藏书室里挨着壁炉坐着，壁炉里的火光有些暗淡，我坐在父亲的那把皮椅上，这时伯莎出现在门口，手持一柄蜡烛，走向我。我认得她穿的这件礼服裙子，壁炉上的蜡烛光洒在她白色的裙子和绿色的珠宝首饰上，壁炉上的圆形装饰画内是垂死的克利奥佩特拉。外出前她为什么来找我呢？我从未在藏书室见过她，几个月来这是我的地盘。为什么她要拿着那柄蜡烛站在我面前，眼睛冷酷轻蔑地紧盯着我？她胸前那只闪耀的珠宝蛇如熟悉的魔鬼。有那么一刻，我觉得眼前的景象印证了我在维也纳的预见，它代表了我命运中的一个可怕危机，但在伯莎的头脑中我什么都没看见，她站在我面前，对坐在面前痛苦不堪的我投以最大的鄙视：“白痴，蠢货，你怎么不自杀呢？……”这就是她的想法。最后，她的想法回到她要办的事情上。她用语言把这些事项说出来。她要说的明显是件小事，与我的预见和紧张情绪完全不相称，滑稽可笑得令人扫兴。

“我雇了一个新女佣。弗莱彻要结婚了，她要我来找你把莫尔顿的酒馆和农场给她丈夫。我也愿意如此。你现在就得答应，她明天一早就动身，快着点儿吧，我还得走呢。”

“很好，你答应她吧，”我无所谓地说。伯莎马上离开了藏书室。

我总是怕见新人，更怕见一个俗气、无知又琐碎的人，他的精神活动会消耗我的洞见，弄得我疲惫不堪。我尤其怕见这个新女仆，宣布她来的时机很特殊，我不禁把她和我的命运联系起来：我隐隐地害怕她会和我的人生戏剧有关，某种令人作呕的预见会让我将她视作邪恶的天才。最终，我不可避免地见到了她，隐隐的恐惧变为确定无疑的厌恶。这个阿切尔夫人，她是一个高个子、体型瘦长的黑眼睛女人，长着一张足够俊朗的脸，在她粗糙坚硬的秉性之上增加了一种令人作呕、明目张胆、自以为是的媚态。这足以让我躲着她，更何况她总是鄙视地琢磨我。我很少见到她，但我知道她很快成为她女主人的心腹。八九个月之后，我开始意识到，伯莎的头脑里对这个女人有一种混合着恐惧与依恋的复杂感情，这种感情与她梳妆室里那些烛光摇曳、难以名状的场景有关，与伯莎内室里那些翻箱倒柜的事情有关。我和我妻子的见面越发简短，而且很少能够单独见面，因此我无法更确切地知道她到底在想些什么。我们对过去的回忆因为思维的快速运动而变得简短，有时，这些回忆如此失真，与外部现实毫无相似性，就像形态各异的东方字母让人根本难以联想起它们所代表的物体。

此外，过去的一年多，我的头脑发生了一种越发明显的变化。我对周围人思想的洞察逐渐变得不清楚，断断续续的，那些拥堵在我头脑中的双重意识也与我和接触到的周围的人变得无关了。我体内一切属于自己的部分都在慢慢走向死亡，因此，我也在逐渐失去能感受到个人激情和他人感情投影的感官。我虽从洞察人心的疲惫活动中解脱出来，但却越发能预测外在世界的发展了。这种感受就好像我与人类同伴的关系逐渐僵死，我与那无生命的世界的关系越发亲密一样。我的不幸逐渐平息，从悲壮的激情走向日常无聊的痛苦。与此相对，我越是远离人群，就越是频繁、生动地看到我曾经对布拉格的预见⸺怪异的城市；铺满沙子的平原；庞大的古迹；午夜天空中异常明亮的星辰；连绵的山脉；午后阳光穿过郁郁葱葱的树冠，在野草丛生的幽静处洒下一块块光斑。我置身于这些景色之中，在所有景色中有一样东西比其他任何东西都更重要，它是一样不可知又不值得怜悯的东西。不断的痛苦已经将我体内的宗教信仰消解了，对于最可悲的人而言，对于既无法爱人也得不到爱的人而言，没有任何宗教信仰的可能，我不可能崇拜什么，除非是崇拜邪恶。除此之外，不断闪现的是我对死亡的预见，疼痛、窒息、最后一搏时的情景不断闪现，我徒劳地想挽回生命。

到了第七年年底，我完全失去了洞察的能力，除了我自己的意识之外，再也不会病态地认知他人的意识了，再也不会被迫侵犯他人的内心世界，我转而沉浸在自己孤独的未来中。伯莎意识到我变了。出乎我的意料，她最近好像一直找机会与我相处，我们之间滋生出一种新的关系，可以冷淡地说说话，这是那些彼此礼貌相待却不可能挽回感情的夫妻常有的姿态。我疲惫地接受了这种关系，不想仔细探究她这么做的动机究竟是什么。不过，我还是忍不住感到她的举止仪态、面部表情都透露出一种胜利、兴奋的感情，这种感情难以言表，不过能让人感到她对什么事情充满期待，或者说她在充满希冀地等待着什么。我最为满意的是她的内在自我又一次遮蔽起来，有一次我几乎要欢喜地陶醉了，我低落的时候回了她的话却没说中她的所思所想，这泄露出我完全不知道她刚刚在说什么。有一天我犯了这样的错，我清楚地记得她的眼神和微笑，她说：“我原以为你长了透视眼，你为此很刻薄地对待其他长了透视眼的人，想要独占这能力，但现在我知道你比任何人都更愚蠢。”

我什么都没说。我突然想到，她近来对我的搅扰可能是想测验我是否能看透她的秘密，但我立刻停止了想这事，我对她的动机、行动毫不关心，她想找什么乐子都可以，我无意去干涉她。我灵魂的深处对人仍有怜悯，伯莎是个活生生的人，她也可能被什么痛苦缠身。

就在那段时间发生了一件改变我沉闷生活的事，给了我一种新的乐趣，而我原以为我不会在生活中找到任何乐趣了。查尔斯・麦尼埃要来看我了，他写信说工作过于繁重，要来英国放松，他想见我。麦尼埃在欧洲有了名气，不过，他给我的信说了许多我们早年的事儿，他感激我的同情。他能记得这些，这和他高尚的性格分不开，我也感到他的到来会让我暂时重新回到旧时那快乐的时光。

他来了，我们又开始两人单独远游。不过，没有山脉、冰川和广阔的蓝色湖泊了，我们只能在山坡、池塘和人造园林中游玩，我们能走多远走多远。时光改变了我们，把我们塑造成完全不同的样子！麦尼埃如今是社会上显赫的人物，高贵的夫人们会对他曲意逢迎，那些假意自夸对脑科学感兴趣的贵族会与他结交。我很清楚，我的变化让他震惊，他十分巧妙地强忍住，不探究我的身体情况和生活境况，而是用迷人的社交能力让我们的重逢欢欣愉悦。伯莎很惊讶，这位宾客会出人意料地有魅力，她原以为他只是名气大些罢了，于是使尽浑身解数卖弄她的风情和才华。显然，她成功赢得了他的仰慕，麦尼埃对她殷勤周到，赞美之词溢于言表。他的到来对我十分有益，尤其是我们又能一起单独地散步远足，他向我倾诉他的职业生涯。不止一次，他向我提到疾病对心理的影响，我突然想到，如果他住的时间够长，我很可能向他讲述我命运的秘密。难道他的科学就没有给我的解药吗？难道对我这种情况，他那博学洽闻的头脑就不会藏着某种理解和同情吗？不过，这种想法只是偶然闪现，在成为一种愿望前已经消失了。我惧怕让另外一个人知道我的秘密，我有一种不理性的本能，这本能要我用隐瞒这层外衣把自己裹得严严实实。看透他人的秘密后，我更觉得需要保守好自己的秘密。

麦尼埃的拜访接近尾声时发生了一件事，在我们家引起了不小的骚动，主要是这件事给伯莎很大的冲击。伯莎是个一向沉着冷静的人，她看上去不会有女性的焦虑不安，甚至她憎恨别人都是有度的，不会伤及身体。这件事就是她的女仆阿切尔夫人突然生了重病。这里我需要说一件事，在麦尼埃到访前不久发生了一件事，我注意到伯莎和这个女佣之间产生了一些不快，很可能在她们拜访一个远房亲戚时争吵了，当时这个佣人陪着她的女主人。我偶然听到阿切尔对伯莎傲慢无礼地说话，那语气在我看来应当立刻辞退她。但是伯莎没有辞退她，反而默默地忍受这个女人发脾气造成的不便。更令我惊讶的是，她的疾病反而使得伯莎对她更加地关切，伯莎夜以继日地守候在她床边，她不允许任何人照料她。正巧，我们的家庭医生外出度假，这让麦尼埃的到来更受欢迎。他接手了病人，并且，对这一病例展现出了正常职业反应之外的热情。那天，在看望过病人后，他陷入了沉思。我对他说：“这病例非常特别吗，麦尼埃？”

“不，”他回答，“她得的是腹膜炎，是致命的，和我诊治过的许多人情况差不多。但是，我要告诉你我在想什么。我想拿这个女人做一次实验，如果你允许的话。我不会伤害她，不会让她痛苦，我会等到她完全失去知觉的时候做实验。我想在她心脏停止跳动几分钟后，把血输入到她的动脉，看看有什么效果。这个实验我已经在患了同样病症的动物身上做了一次又一次，结果十分令人震惊，我想在人类身上尝试。我带着必要的管子，装在我的箱子里，其他的设备都可以很快准备。我会用自己的血，从我的手臂上取出来。我确定这个女人不会活过今晚，我要你答应做我的实验助手。我没办法自己完成，但在乡下医生里找一个助手可能不合适。这件事可能被说得粗鄙荒唐，弄得沸沸扬扬到处传播。”

“你和我的妻子说过这事了吗？”我说，“她对这个女人看起来有一种特殊的感情，这是她最喜爱的女仆。”

“实话告诉你，”麦尼埃说，“我不想让她知道这件事。女人在这些事上是说不通的，何况，到时候这个女仆身体上可能会产生一些令人惊讶的反应。你和我要一起熬夜了，得时刻准备好。一旦出现某些症状我会带你进去，时机成熟的时候我们必须把其他所有人赶出房间。”

我不必再讲我们对这件事的对话了。他很详尽地说明了细节，克服了我对这些事的反感，让我对他实验的结果怀着一种敬畏、好奇的复杂心理。

我们准备好了一切，他指示我如何当一个助手。他没有告诉伯莎，他十分确定阿切尔熬不过这个晚上，他努力劝说她让病人自己好好休息一个晚上。但她很倔强，预感到死亡已经临近，她以为麦尼埃是为了保护她的神经让她离开。她拒绝离开病房。麦尼埃和我一起在藏书室等着，他不断地去病房，回来告诉我病情发展如他所料。有一次他对我说：“你知道这女人为什么令她的女主人心怀不满吗？女主人待她这么好。”

“我想她生病前，她们之间有什么误会。你为什么问这个？”

“因为在我过去观察的五六个小时里，我猜，她没有恢复的希望了。有一种奇怪的动机推着她要说什么，不过疼痛和虚弱让她说不出话。她的眼睛里有一种可怕的神情，她一直用那种眼神看着她的主人。而这种病的患者往往到最后一刻都保持着头脑清醒。”

“这女人会有恶毒的想法，我一点儿都不惊讶。”我说，“对她，我一向不信任也不喜欢，但她有办法赢得她主人的欢心。”这之后，他沉默了，看着壁炉里的火陷入沉思，随后起身又上楼去了。这次比平时待的时间久一些，他回来的时候，悄悄对我说：“现在来吧。”

我随他进入那间死神徘徊的屋子。我进屋的时候，在床四周的黑色幔布的映衬下，伯莎苍白的脸色缓和了一些。看我进来，她连忙身子向前，随后一脸愤怒、迷惑地看着麦尼埃。他一边抬起手示意安静，一边紧紧盯着这垂死的女人，测量她的脉搏。这张脸苍白瘦削、毛骨悚然，额头挂着冰冷的汗珠，眼睑下垂几乎盖住了她大而黑的眼睛。一两分钟后，麦尼埃走向床的另一侧伯莎站的地方，用一贯温柔礼貌的语气请求她离开病人，交由我们照顾，一切都会为病人处理好，她如今已经不可能感受到周围人的温存了。伯莎在犹豫，显然她愿意相信他的保证，愿意听从他的安排。她看着那张可怕的、垂死的脸，好像要读出某种信息证实麦尼埃的保证。有那么一刻已经下垂的眼睑又抬了起来，好像，这双眼睛正看着伯莎，不过眼神茫然而空洞。伯莎全身战栗了一下，她又回到病人的枕边，巧妙地暗示她不会离开屋子。

眼睑再也没有抬起来。我看着伯莎，她正看着垂死之人的脸。她身着一件昂贵的睡衣，一顶蕾丝帽半遮着金色的头发，穿着这身衣服的她一如既往地优雅，宛如现代贵族生活画像中的人。我问我自己，为何我曾经会认为这样一个女人也是由母亲所生、拥有童年记忆、能够感受痛苦、需要人宠爱呢？那一刻，她的面貌表情异常地尖刻，她的眼睛异常地冷酷、焦虑，她看上去像一个残忍的神明，这个女仆和死亡的赛跑则是她的一场精神盛宴。而当女仆咽下最后一口气，当死亡的黑色头纱已经在这女人身上完全落下时，从伯莎尖刻的面容后闪耀出一丝光芒。伯莎和这个女人之间到底有什么秘密呢？我把眼睛从她身上转开，生怕我恢复了洞悉的能力，那样我就会被迫得知这两个没有爱意的女人到底在想什么。我感到，伯莎期待着死亡会守住她的秘密，我感谢上天，这秘密对我仍是个谜。

麦尼埃轻声说：“她死了。”他把胳膊伸向伯莎，她顺从地走出了屋子。

我想，是她命令了两个女随从到屋子来，让原来那个年轻的随从离开了。她们进来的时候，麦尼埃已经切开了枕头上那条瘦长、僵硬的脖子的动脉，我赶走了随从，让她们在远处等着我们摇铃，我说，医生要做个手术，他不确定病人是否死亡。在随后的二十分钟里我忘记了一切，只记得麦尼埃和让他专注的实验，我想，他的感官已经隔离了一切与实验无关的声音和图像。我的任务，首先是保持人工呼吸，直到完成输血。不过很快麦尼埃接替了我。我能看到生命神奇又缓慢地回来了，胸口开始起伏，吸气越来越强烈，眼睑在颤抖，灵魂好像也回来了。人工呼吸停止后，呼吸仍在继续，嘴唇开始运动。

就在那时，我听到门把手转动了。我猜，伯莎从那些被支走的女人那里听说了什么，可能她隐约感到了恐惧，因为，她神色警觉地进来。她走近床脚，发出了一声哀鸣。

死去女人的眼睛大睁着，眼看着她，她认出了她，带着仇恨地认出了她。突然一股强力让伯莎以为已经永远静止的手指向了她。那张憔悴的脸动了，喘着粗气的声音急切地说⸺

“你计划毒杀你的丈夫……毒药放在黑色橱柜里……我为你弄到的……你嘲笑我，在背地里说我的坏话，让别人厌恶我……因为你嫉妒……你知道错了吗……现在？”

嘴唇仍在小声说着什么，但是已经听不出声音了。很快，什么声音都没有了，只有微小的动作：火焰跃升了起来，又更快地熄灭了。这可怜女人的心中满是憎恨和报复；生命的灵魂弹拨了一下和弦，就一去不复返了。上帝啊！这就是复活吗……就是为了醒来倾倒那未被平息的欲望，让双唇发泄未能说出的诅咒，让肌肉完成犯了一半的罪恶吗？

伯莎脸色苍白地站在床脚边，浑身颤抖、无能为力、无计可施，像狡猾野兽的藏身之处被迅猛的火焰围困了一般。麦尼埃也瘫在那里动不了，对他来说，那一刻生命不再是一个科学问题。而对我来说，这一幕和我生命里发生的其他事情基调一样，恐惧与我常相伴，而这一刻新的启示也不过是旧有的疼痛在新的场景中重新出现。

那以后伯莎和我分居了，她住在她自己的宅院里，掌管着我们一半的财富，我则游荡在海外，直到现在，我来到德文郡居住，等待死亡。伯莎接受人们的怜悯和仰慕；我能举出什么来反对这个有魅力的女人呢？除我以外所有人都喜欢和她相处，没有人看到那间屋子里发生的场景，除了麦尼埃，而麦尼埃答应我他活着就不会说出那个秘密。

有那么一两次，我疲于奔波了，驻足在一个喜爱的地方。我的心灵奔向男人、女人和孩子们，他们的面孔日渐熟悉起来，但我担心旧时的洞察力会回来，又急忙离开。我一直奔走，一直活在这种未知的存在之中，这种未知已经向我揭晓，但我却让它隐藏在天地之间那移动的幕布后。直到最后，疾病抓住了我，迫使我留在此处休息，迫使我依靠我的仆人。然后，洞察力的诅咒⸺我的双重意识回来了，而且再也没有离开过我。我知道仆人们所有狭隘的思想、他们微弱的尊敬和他们将要耗尽的怜悯。

今天是1850年9月20日。我知道我刚刚写下的这个日期，这串数字如同一个熟识很久的碑文。我无数次在书桌的这一页纸上见到它们，在我最后死亡前的挣扎开始的时候。

（1859）

（张欣  译）

[1] 原文为拉丁语ubi saeva indignatio ulterius cor lacerare nequit，来自英国作家斯威夫特墓碑上的诗。——原文注

[2] 指的是让・雅克・卢梭。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明之外，均为译者注。）

[3] 女水妖，格林童话中的形象。

[4] 原文为法语。

[5] 原文为法语。

[6] 塔索，意大利诗人。

女作家写的蠢故事[7]

/

女作家写的蠢故事内容丰富，风格多样。按照愚蠢的不同特质，它包含了浅薄空洞型、单调涣散型、一片虔诚型、迂腐卖弄型等多种文风。然而，所有这些展示女性愚昧的作品中，有一个分支流派数量最为庞大，我们暂且管它叫女帽类小说[8]。此类蠢故事往往是这样开始的：女主角是一位继承人或颇有家产的贵族夫人，与她交往甚密的几位情人包括一位桀骜不驯的准男爵，一位和善亲切的公爵，以及一位魅力四射的侯爵家骄子；牧师或诗人追求者在远处为她叹着气；当然，她身后还跟着一群各式各样的仰慕者，书里只是轻描淡写地带过。通常来说，这位女主角的眼睛闪耀着美丽的光泽，头脑机智非凡；她的鼻子挺拔，就像她的品性那样端庄；她有着宛如女低音的嗓子，思维敏捷；她穿戴讲究，笃信宗教。跳舞时，她宛如曼妙的西尔芙精灵；读起书来更是了不得，能读懂原版的《圣经》[9]。另外一种女主角拥有所有这些美好品质，只不过她不是继承人，也没有万贯家财，但她总是有跻身上流社会的机缘，总是能毫无疏漏地在众多追求者中挑选出最优秀的结婚对象，并最终成为大家眼中正直不阿、极具传统家庭观念的贤良淑女。放荡男人面对她机智的言语常常无力还击，只好保持沉默，甚至因为她辞藻华丽的谴责而开始深深地自省；诚然，这些女主角都爱长篇大论、滔滔不绝，她们退回到自己卧室的那一刻便是她们高谈阔论的开始。人们能从她文章的字里行间看出她的伶牙俐齿，从她的谈吐中感受到她的诙谐和巧思。人们都知道她思想深刻洞察万物，能够看透浅薄哲学家提出的理论，而她那绝妙的直觉就像钟表，只需有人按下启动，便能自然而然地运行，参透万物。事实上，男人在她身边只是扮演了跑龙套的戏份。然而时不时地，你又能从书中某些暗示里感受到男女主人公之间的暧昧关系，这让你又欣慰了几分，重新确认了男人在现实世界中的重要作用。不过，在该女主角领衔主演的这部漫长人生影片中，男人存在的最终目的也只不过是扮演了女主角的护送者而已。男人们或是在舞会上看见她的身姿而目眩神迷，或是在某次花展上被她迷住，或是在一次骑行中被她高贵的驭马术所征服，或是在教堂瞥见她庄重又甜美的姿态。总之，她给人的感觉、她展现出来的才智以及她带有蕾丝花边的衣饰都全方位地符合了男性心中理想的女神形象。尽管如此，在故事的开头女主角也总是会错误地嫁给一个邪恶的准男爵，丈夫的阴谋诡计让她饱受情感折磨。但是，即使是死神也在心中为我们完美的女主角保留着柔情，一定会在恰当的时候出面，用死亡解决她的困境。可怜的男爵一定会在某次决斗中战死，躺在床上的他奄奄一息，请求妻子一定要再嫁给自己最爱的人，就当作是对将死的自己的一种恩赐，并且已经自作主张给她的情人派送了信件。在情节进展到这一步之前，我们也跟随高贵、可爱、有才的女主角一起体验了她之前诸多的糟糕时光。不过，我们最终也能获得满足感，毕竟看到她还是能够掩面在精致的刺绣镶边手绢中哭泣；能够晕倒在价值连城的高档坐垫上；乘着马车匆忙赶来，她也依旧容光焕发；因高烧剃去了头发，大病痊愈后，女主角的秀发也只会更加丰盈。

在淑女小说家笔下，有且仅有这高贵而时尚的社会，这倒是让我们免去了一个极为严重的担忧。我们曾经猜测，淑女小说家们都是穷困潦倒的女人，她们写作小说的原因与她们去应聘家庭女教师一样⸺她们实在找不到别的“女性化”生存之道了。基于这样的假设，我们即使发现小说语句啰唆、情节离奇，也会因为心中的同情而原谅这些瑕疵，就像看到盲人售卖的粗糙针垫和睡帽⸺我们会告诉自己，这些物品虽有缺陷，但是我们所付的钱却能解救那些穷苦女性。我们想象着那些寂寞的单身女性为了生存而苦苦写作，妻子们为了偿还丈夫的债务、女儿们为了给生病的父亲买件礼物而孜孜不倦地辛勤生产着“作品”，仿佛在进行某种伟大的英雄主义行动。在这样的印象下，我们对于淑女小说的评价就比较含蓄了：她的小说有语病，但她的写作动机却无可指责；她的想象力平庸无奇，但她坚持不懈的精神令人感动。似乎，我们因作者的困境而原谅了她们写的白痴故事，因为眼泪而相信了那些废话。但事实并不是这样！我们的这种想法以及类似冠冕堂皇的观点都被新的发现所否定了。女作家的这些小说是在完全不同于我们想象的状态下写出来的。这些女作家出行都坐马车，只透过车窗和卖东西的小贩交谈；她们视工人阶级为自己的附属物；她们觉得五百英镑的年薪简直少得可怜；贝尔格莱维亚区和“豪华大别墅”的一切才是真实的生活；而男性若不是一位有身份地位的政治家，或者至少是个拥有大片土地的地主，那她们甚至连看都不愿看一眼。很显然，她们是坐在优雅的闺房里，用紫罗兰颜色的墨水和红宝石笔尖的钢笔写作的人；她们对出版商的评价完全不在乎，她们一点儿都不穷困潦倒，拮据的是她们的脑容量。她们所描绘的上流社会的确惟妙惟肖，令人羡慕，但同时，她们的文字却流露出对其他阶层的陌生。如果我们把她们对贵族老爷、太太的描绘称为不准确，那她们对文人、商贩和农民的描述简直就是荒谬了，但她们的聪明才智还是秉持着公平的原则，以同样的离谱描绘着她们确实听过、看过和未曾听过、看过的东西。

我们认为，应该很少有女性根本不曾见过五岁以下的小孩，但是最近有一部自称“源自真人真事”的女帽类小说《补偿》（Compensation）中，却有一个才四岁半的小女孩在以奥西恩风格[10]的口吻说话：

“我太开心了，亲爱的外婆！我遇到了一个如此令人心旷神怡的人，他就像所有美好的事物——像芬芳的花朵，像从本洛蒙德山上看到的景致——噢！不！比这还要美。我一想到他、见到他就感觉非常非常幸福。他唱歌时就像妈妈那样温柔。他的前额如同远方的大海一般，”小女孩手指向蔚蓝的地中海继续说道，“没有边际；又像温暖的夏夜里，我抬头仰望天空时最爱的那一丛星星……不要这样看着我啊，你现在的额头就像是被阳光照射、被风吹皱了的罗蒙湖面，我最喜欢平静湖面上的阳光了……就像现在，天上飘着些深色云朵，阳光冲破云层，瞬间就给旁边的丛林和紫色的岩石镀上了金色，它们倒映在湖面上，显得那么美丽。

文中的神童小女孩完全展现了一个成人在醉酒后才有的滔滔不绝，此时，就算我们被告知她是一个死而复生的人，生来就拥有一长段的记忆，我们也不会惊讶。故事一次次地告诉我们，文中的小女孩就是这样一个富有创造力并且自认为是天才的神童，而且她足够幸运，遇上了一个同样“最具独创性”的令她倾心的天才爱人。

按照书中所写，这位神童的爱人虽然与她“在权势和才智”上都惊人地相似，但“在宗教信仰和发育上”却更胜一筹。她把他当作自己的“‘挚爱’（Agape）⸺一个她从希腊文《圣经》中读到并一直喜爱的词。得益于她对学习语言的超常天赋，她用原版语言阅读了所有宗教经典”。当然，希腊语和希伯来语对于女主角来说易如反掌，要她讲梵语也不过是小菜一碟。事实上，除了说不好英语，她能准确无误地用其他任何语言交流。她不仅会跳波尔卡舞，还通晓数国语言，她简直就是一位穿着裙子的外交家。可怜的男人们！你们有几个看得懂希伯来文，你们恐怕和博林布鲁克一样，在“大致了解了一点儿那门语言，熟悉了由那门语言写成的重要作品的名称”后，就会开始吹嘘；而你们着迷的那些女人，却可以用每一种闪族语言在心里说你们的坏话呢。然而，我们都知道这样一个道理，故事中的女主角常常还拥有一个“美丽而小巧的脑袋”，也许正是这种对服装和仪态的关注启发了她们的早慧。因此，我们可以猜想，对于女主角而言，学习东方语言就如蝴蝶轻啜花蜜那样轻巧，更不用说学习和她们母语相近的其他欧洲语言了。另外，女主角的博学一定深不可测，虽然作者的头脑倒是能够一眼望到底。

在另外一本女帽类小说《劳拉・盖伊》（Laura Gay）中，女主角并不精通希腊语和希伯来语，但她对拉丁古典文学的熟稔弥补了这一缺点⸺她熟读“亲爱的老维吉尔”、“优雅的贺拉斯”、“仁慈的西塞罗”，以及“令人愉悦的李维”，各种经典烂熟于心。旁征博引拉丁经典对劳拉而言是如此理所当然的一件事，在与一群形形色色的男女出去野餐时，她心想：“我从来不知道高贵如男性也会在这件事情上产生嫉妒。”书中继续写道：“若在场的多数人是理智且高贵的绅士，他们必定不会对这种引用产生嫉妒感；但在场的若都是温德姆小姐和雷德福先生这种普通之流，那么就必须得牺牲一下自己引用的天性了。”但我想，无论是高贵的少数男性，还是无知又愚蠢的大多数人，都愿意谈话中少一些这种无聊又毫无关联的引用。在男女混合的聚会场所，有教养的男性和女性都很少谈论拉丁名著，他们即使熟读“仁慈的西塞罗”，即便是“令人愉悦的李维”几欲脱口而出，也能在平常的谈话交流中控制自己的学识。然而，对于书中的盖伊小姐来说，用西塞罗的拉丁经典讲话几乎是她最平易近人的交流方式了。一次在帕拉丁山上，她对一众观光客做出了如下脉络清晰、内容全面而丰富的评论：

真理只能是完全客观的，因为即使在宗教经典中，当真理偶尔通过主观方式被展现时，它都会多多少少沾染了些迷信的色彩；而在罗马天主教的教条中，这种无知、利益、古老偶像崇拜造成的偏见以及权威，都逐渐堆积在了真理之上，并把罗马天主教变成了一场拥有众多信徒的迷信。而又有多少人，能够拥有等量的热情、勇气和智慧去剖开这堆积在真相之上的垃圾，在一团废墟中找到藏身其中的珍珠呢。

如果仔细想想，我们或许见过很多比劳拉・盖伊更加清新脱俗、思维深刻的女性，但是肯定没遇见过如此不合时宜发表长篇大论的。有一位刚刚爱上她的贵族牧师正是因为听了以上那一段深沉的评论，开始有些怀疑她是不是个独立思考的女性，担心不好把控。但是他想错了！当劳拉难过时，贵族牧师温柔地想“唤起她平时忘却了的记忆，一个她在痛苦时分力量和慰藉的储藏地，而这个储藏地，除非我们也被生活的苦难狠狠压榨，否则，也是同样会被我们所遗忘的”。我们在文中读到，她确实找到了这个神圣的储藏地，连同她的茶壶一起找到的。在《劳拉・盖伊》的珠光宝气、香车鬓影之外，的确还存在着一些正统的风味，但是这种正统却被她“仁慈的西塞罗”“热爱分析的性格”所破坏了。

相比之下，《补偿》一书更具教条主义风格，但是其中堆砌了更多势利世俗以及荒诞的插曲，以迎合虔诚但轻浮的读者的喜好。书中的女主角琳达比劳拉・盖伊更深思、更聪敏，她已经出入了社交场合，因此也有更多、地位更显赫的情人；书中还引入了各种邪恶但令人着迷的女人⸺甚至包括一个法国悍妇；作者不遗余力地为小说创作各种引人入胜的故事，其桥段堪比最为悖德伦理故事。事实上，这本书就是一个大杂烩：有舞会、有苏格兰人的预言、罗杰斯先生的早餐、意大利强盗、临终时的皈依、聪明绝顶的女作家、意大利情人、毒杀老妇人，而这些情节描写又被佐以对“信仰和人类未来”的讨论，因“最为新颖的思想”而更具风味。书中的女作家苏珊・巴顿小姐是个天才，她提起笔“写小说时一挥而就”，而即使她已经拒绝了多桩好婚事，即使年纪大到已经足够当琳达的母亲（因为她曾拒绝了琳达的父亲），但她最终该是能够与一位年轻的伯爵喜结良缘，情定这位女主角曾拒绝过的情人。

当然，天才和道德高尚这两种品质只有在财富可观的人身上才不显得乏味；同样，虔诚，有时候为了显得有必要[11]，也必须融入“社会”，在最好的圈子里展示才能合乎礼仪。

《阶级与美女》（Rank and Beauty）是一本更加浅薄、宗教色彩相对较弱的女帽类小说。书中是这样写我们的女主角的：“即使她出身卑微，如果她继承了她父亲的风骨、她母亲的美貌，具有符合她年龄的奔放与热情，这些特质将最终升华成敢爱敢恨的勇气，她的后代会觉得这些是他们能够得到的最好的财富。”这位青春热血的年轻女士在读父亲的报纸时爱上了首相先生。通过头版新闻和“议会辩论概要”，首相先生在温德姆小姐的想象中就已经闪耀特异如一颗明星，然而这颗星星对于身居乡村无足轻重的温德姆小姐而言，自是可望而不可即的。但是，温德姆小姐迅速凭借自己的力量成为乌姆弗拉维尔女爵，当她搬进春日公园的豪宅之时，她的美貌和成就惊艳了世人，而正如你所想，她不久就将会碰到她的爱慕对象[12]了。可能“首相”一词总让你想起满脸皱纹、一身赘肉的六十多岁的老头儿，但是请赶紧摆脱这种印象吧，鲁伯特・康威勋爵“在他几乎还是青年时就被委以重任，处理全人类最为紧要的事务”，而他也符合我们的女主角在阅读了头版新闻和议会辩论概要后所产生的每一则幻想：

门又打开了，鲁伯特·康威走了进来。伊夫琳小姐抬头看了一眼，这一眼就足够了！他完全没让她失望。这一眼似乎就像是她之前一直盯着一幅画看，而现在画中人竟然从画中走了出来的感觉。他身姿挺拔，气度非凡，像凡·戴克画中的人物，像一位骑士——他高尚的骑士祖先们，和她幻想中的他形容相似的骑士们，曾在遥远的古时和乌姆弗拉维尔家族在远方的战场上并肩作战，讨伐异教徒。这些都是真实的吗？

当然不是。

渐渐地，书中越来越明显地展示，首相先生对她动心了。这发生在乌姆弗拉维尔小姐在温莎堡觐见女王的时候⸺

这是她在王宫的最后一晚了，骑马回来后，温德姆先生带着她和一群伙伴到围墙顶上看风景。她倚在城墙上，站在高处向下俯瞰风景，鲁伯特正在她身边。她感叹道：“这风景真是无与伦比的美丽啊！”

“是很美！要是没有到这高处来就离开了应该会很遗憾！这次旅行觉得高兴吗？”

“简直令人陶醉！为女王而生，为女王而死，为女王尽忠！”

“哈！”他大声应道，情感突然激昂，脸上灵光一现，仿佛终遇知音。

这种“脸上灵光一现”为第三卷末尾他们最终结婚埋下了伏笔，但是在那美满的结局之前，勒特雷尔・威彻利先生恶毒的诡计在二人之间造成了许多复杂的误会。这位威彻利先生是一位天才诗人，在各方面都是个非凡的角色。他不仅是浪漫的诗人，潇洒的浪子，还是个愤世嫉俗的才子。他对乌姆弗拉维尔女士的极端爱慕穷尽了他辛辣的口才，使得他在谈话中显得极为愚笨。当她拒绝了他，这位先生竟然冲进灌木林在泥里打滚，并且开始了最为邪恶和煞费苦心的报复历程。他伪装成一位冒牌医师，并且成为家庭医生，他相信伊夫琳总有一天会生病，会召唤他需要他的照料。最终，他的计划泡汤，他写了一封长信跟她道别，信中洋溢着他的满腹才华：

噢，亲爱的小姐，当你沉浸在美好和喜悦中时，你能否想起，给你写信的我，这痛苦的灵魂？当你镀金的游轮在宽阔繁华的世界里顺流而下，你能否透过世界上最甜蜜的音乐——你的颂歌——听到来自远方的，我的叹息？

总之，虽然故事浅薄空洞，但是和其他两部小说比较起来，大家还是更喜欢这本《阶级与美女》。作者写的对话更加自然生动；她对于自己的无知十分坦诚，没有卖弄学问；我们只需要简单地相信女主角的惊人智慧，而不用被迫阅读她在谈话中对怀疑论者与哲学家的驳斥、她对宇宙谜题的解答。

女帽类小说的作者们在写作措辞上都十分雷同。在她们的小说中，总有一位女士或者绅士反派像见血封喉树般阴险毒辣；爱人总有着富有男子气概的胸膛，大脑总是可以联想起许许多多；内心却总是空虚寂寞；所有的活动都别有目的；所有的伙伴都可以托付性命；所有的童年都将伴随终身；每一次西沉的太阳都被比作将军白头，每一次霁晴都是雨水被收纳进了太阳光辉的胸膛；所有人都视生命为一则伤感的恩惠；而人人也都在对话中使用阿尔比恩[13]和斯科舍[14]这种名称。这些人物的道德评价也惊人地相似，例如“所有人，无论贫富，都会被不好的榜样所影响，这是个令人忧伤的事实”；“读者在任何一本不起眼的书中都能获取有用的信息”；“邪恶总是能打着美德的幌子横行”；“本性中的美好和高尚一定存在着，并且能够被赏识，因为小说写得再喧嚣浮夸，也没那么容易欺骗熟读何为人性的读者”；以及“我们只有被伤害过，才能学会原谅”等等。毫无疑问，这些评论在有一部分读者看来是犀利、辛辣的。我们常常看到一些读者手握铅笔一遍又一遍地在书上做标注，他们用精致的手写体在一旁写道：“太对了”，表达对勇敢直言的淑女作家坚定的赞成，并且加上许多的感叹号表示强调。这些小说对话的语言特点在于使用很多具有独创性的倒装句，并且刻意避免日常生活中的平凡用语。愤怒的年轻人这样惊呼：“就是这样，我认为！”；再听听晚餐前半小时，一位年轻女士和她的邻居谈论她第一次读莎士比亚的经历：“我偷偷溜进公园里，坐在绿色的树冠下，兴高采烈地阅读着这位如同魔术大师般的人所写的带给人无限惊喜的书页。”但是此类女帽类小说家最显著的贡献在于她们的哲学思考。例如《劳拉・盖伊》的女作者让女主和男主最终结婚，她进一步升华了他们的结合：“那些眼睛长期盯着物质，看不见人类身上其他方面的怀疑论者们，如果能够全心全意地投入到这样一场极乐中去，就会发现一个人的灵魂和肉体源自不同的起源，其本质也是不一样的。”淑女小说家似乎能看到除却物质层面的其他内容，她们不局限于观察现象，而是偶尔能透过现象洞察本体；自然，她们就比其他任何人更能反驳那些富有盛名的怀疑论者。不过，坚持人的灵魂和肉体是一致的这一怀疑论学派，我们倒也很少听说。

在淑女作家所写的愚蠢小说中，还有一种“神谕体”最令人惋惜叹气，这类小说致力于阐释作者自己的宗教观点、哲学见解和道德观念。类似于那种把愚蠢的言论和行为视为对上帝旨意的传达的迷信，在女性中似乎还广泛流传着这样一种认知，她们认为最无知、最缺乏常识的人却最能传达神的启示。通过她们的写作来判断，总有那么一些女作家认为，对科学和生活的完全无知，是认识复杂的道德及理论难题的最好途径。显然，她们解决类似难题的秘诀都像这样：准备一个女性角色空空的头脑，往里填充对哲学和文学零零碎碎的一知半解，佐以社会僵化而错误的认识把这颗头脑烘焙成型，淑女作家不时地把这颗头脑端上桌来暗示这其中的智慧，并在某些尴尬而不必要的时刻，用她们水平有限的英语把这其中的思想传达出来，装在盘中供读者享用。你很少能碰见一个“神谕体”的淑女小说家会质疑她自己对神学问题的判断能力，她从不会怀疑自己，自认为能极精确地分辨出不同教派间的善恶；她们能准确地指出人类何以堕落到了如今的境地，并且对所有哲学家表示遗憾，因为他们不曾有机会向她请教。当真正伟大的作家谦逊地将自己的经历写进小说，展示人和物最本真的样子时，神谕体女作家就会认为这种写作辜负了他们的才能：“他们并没有解决什么重大问题啊”⸺于是乎她时刻准备着，通过讲述一个爱情故事来弥补所谓的伟大作家们的缺陷，通过富裕家庭的女士先生们经历上流社会特有的种种磨难，来传达一整套关于生命的理论和对于神学的完整指南；这故事对基督教独特的见解能使自然神论者、皮由兹[15]以及极端新教徒都晕头转向，这种新的理论被浓缩进字里行间，在三百三十页的书页中铺展开来。你会觉得，这些小说中的先生和女士们，与你曾经碰到过的人完全不一样。因为，在通常情况下，一个女作家描写她同胞和真实生活的能力，与她谈论上帝的能力成反比；而她把读者导向精神世界的方法则是向他们展现出一幅完全不符合实际的现实生活的图景。

《一个谜团：来自乌尔克里庄园档案中的一页》（The Enigma：A Leaf from the Chronicles of Wolchorley House，后文简称《谜团》）是我们能见到的最典型的“神谕体”小说。书中“谜团”的困难程度无异于解释邪恶的存在，而要解答这一谜团，也正需要我们淑女作家才有的超凡的才智。作者已经在小说的第一页提出了难题，答案也欲隐欲现。留着乌黑头发、生机勃勃的年轻女士说：“生命就是一团难以解开的谜团”；而顶着褐色头发的另一位温柔女士，对着自己正在临摹的圣母像说：“那儿似乎曾有解决这一难题的方法”。这种小说的风格的虚无缥缈自然适应了它目的的崇高，我们必须承认，有些段落我们可能花了很长时间研究却仍然不懂，即使作者加入了斜体小字的解说，或许，我们必须等到智力进一步开发才能理解书中的内容吧。书中写了一位年轻的模范牧师欧内斯特，无论在什么情况下，他都能使人们回到正轨，“在全社会都变得渎神后，他开始不赞成交易类型的婚姻”，在某个晚上，“睡眠没有造访他神圣的心灵，其中汹涌着聚集而混杂的悲伤和喜悦”，以及“他不能容忍任何为交易而写成的人类文章，无论它是何种类型，被认为拥有何种价值，无论是出于尊敬抑或是阶级需要写作，他正直的灵魂都对之深恶痛绝，自欺欺人者的最后结论对于他来说只是一个神圣的谎言，因为他们‘生活在一出虚无的演出中，欺骗别人并且被人欺骗’，而他觉得自己的护经匣以及衣服上夸张的下摆并不只是一种社交摆设”。（所有的特殊字体处理都是文章中原有的，我们希望它们能帮助读者进一步理解。）文中另一位莱昂内尔先生是个模范老绅士，“他除了不散漫不颓废，人们对中世纪人物的典型印象似乎在他身上都得到了体现，将人们团结在一起的正是一种英雄主义纽带。原始信仰和真理的色彩镌刻在普通人的内心，随着法律准则的出现和积累，融入到更加广泛的兄弟情谊中，并且互相依赖，越来越臻于完美”。是的，看了这句话，你一定明白这些色彩是如何铭刻在心中，又是怎样融合成一道情谊之桥⸺显然这是一条彩虹⸺准则的出现和积累又是如何使得这座情谊之桥越来越完美。看到这里，如果你还需要进一步认识莱昂内尔先生，我们会告诉你，他的灵魂深处，“浮漾在他灵魂周围的气氛里、隐藏在他灵魂原始的脉搏中，有一种比任何科学思想都能想象到的更为极致的善与真的结合。当他在封信时，“瞧！这位好人胸膛中跳动着一颗充满真与善的心，如同他装满爱意的双眼，充盈着对祖先的崇敬和自豪，似乎在凝视着家族那清晰的箴言——忠诚[16]”。

淑女作家也用同样崇高的风格剔除了生活中所有琐碎事物中的庸俗。普通人可能会说休息室的桌上摆着一本莎士比亚，可是《谜团》的女作者决心迂回地表现自己的文采，会这样描述桌上的书：“那人类思想和情感的宝库，用这样一个小小的名字‘莎士比亚’引导着人类的心灵。”又比如，一位夜巡人看到某扇窗户里的灯比平常亮久了一些，感慨这些熬夜的人为何傻到有机会早睡却不珍惜；但是，作者唯恐这些事实对于我们来说太过平淡无奇，于是采用了如下这种引人注目且形而上学的方式呈现在我们面前：“他惊叹——人们在思考他人的问题时总会站在旁观者的角度，因此（尽管他们不赞成这种错误）他们也会在脑海中错误地假想——要是他自己，他一定会表现得大为不同，他一定会满怀欣喜地珍惜在房间内根本没有被当回事所得来的休息。”一位普通侍从，他小腿粗壮，说话漏风，现在正开门去迎客，作者立即抓住了这样一个机会开始描写，他是“众多被宠坏了的奴仆中的一员，就像是中了该隐一样的诅咒⸺成为了世间的‘流浪者’，他把个人的财富和花销作为衡量人类的标尺……噢！英格兰！所有的这些都是你病态文明的错误启发而已！”我们听说过来自卡明博士[17]和罗伯特・欧文[18]的错误启发，从皮由兹到招魂者的误导，但是之前我们还从未听说过哪种错误启发能从文明的细枝末节，从仆人每日照料的绒毛粉末般的小事中产生。

正如生活中平常的事件被提升为了令人激动的紧急时刻，小说中身着伞裙和中国式长袖[19]的小姐们行事方式也颇具血腥闹剧女主角的风采。《谜团》中的珀西太太是一位肤浅且虚荣的妇人，她希望自己的儿子贺勒斯能娶一位富有的女继承人：褐色头发的格蕾斯；然而，和所有类似的儿子角色一样，贺勒斯爱的却是女继承人的表妹：黑头发的凯特，即便她没有任何财产；此外，格蕾斯对贺勒斯本来也没有展现出任何好感。在这种情景设定下，儿子一般要么阴沉忧郁，要么脾气暴躁，母亲则时而强势主动时而尖刻易怒，而那位没有财产的灰姑娘常常夜不能寐、以泪洗面。我们已经习惯了这些套路，就像我们已经习惯了月食，不会再在无月的夜晚大声号叫敲击作响。然而，即使是遍历故事如我们，对于书中珀西太太这位处在时尚“前沿”的夫人在这种情况下的反应，也不得不大感惊讶。有一天，珀西太太碰巧看到自己的儿子贺勒斯和格蕾斯在窗前谈话，距离远到根本听不见他们在谈什么，而且众所周知，即使贺勒斯向她求婚，高贵的庄园继承人格蕾斯小姐根本没有任何理由会接受，但是珀西太太就直冲冲地奔了过去，紧紧抱住他们俩，她的脸色因为激动和兴奋而泛红，说道：“幸福的一幕终于上演了啊！那我现在是不是能叫你格蕾斯，我的格蕾斯，贺勒斯的格蕾斯！我亲爱的孩子们！”贺勒斯连忙解释，指出这只是一个误会，自己已经和凯特订了婚，于是，我们就看到了以下场景和画面：

她（珀西太太）听到这个消息后，眼睛充满怒火，声音提到了前所未有的高度——

她用嘶哑和愤怒的语气吼道：“你这个不肖子！”她双拳紧握继续说：“你自食苦果吧！低下你的头，让一位母亲的……”

“不要再骂了！”此刻，从身后传来一句低低的反驳声。这一声就像是上天派来的天使，打断了珀西太太恶毒的语言；反正她是被吓住了，停止了讲话。

而与此同时，贺勒斯正双手捂脸，悲伤地跪在母亲的脚边。

母亲的那些可怕语言很过分，已深深刺伤了他，就像是挥之不去的魔咒，将一直留存在他的心间。那一声反驳是谁说的？是他真正的守护神发话了！

站在珀西太太身后的人正是凯特，她脸色苍白，站得笔直，全身笼罩着死寂一般的镇定——她是当下唯一一个冷静的人了，她抑扬顿挫地缓慢地讲着，语气中充满悲愤和哀伤，一字一句都像是敲在人心上。

“他是做了他的决定，但是我并没有接受！所以，你不能，你也没有权利诅咒他！我现在，”此时，凯特抬起又大又黑的双眼，那眸子里闪烁着柔和的光，这也是第一次，这热情的双眸被痛苦所点亮。她伸出一只手向天起誓，“在这里对天发誓，即使以幸福为饵，以悲伤相逼，如果没有贺勒斯母亲的同意和祝福，我绝不答应贺勒斯·乌尔克里先生的求婚！”

在此处，以及在整篇小说中，作者有意营造一种混杂、迷惑，而这也正是蠢故事的典型特征。《谜团》的故事本是关于一群现代“沙龙社团”的贵族年轻人，他们跳着波尔卡舞，谈论着皮由兹运动；但同时，故事里又混杂了各种各样的角色、突发事件以及行为礼仪，像是混杂了各种不同类型爱情小说的片段。书中写了一个爱尔兰竖琴家，“宛如古时眉目如画的吟游诗人”，他来到这个普通的英国小村庄，在教堂主日学校举办的茶点庆祝会上惊艳出场。另外有一个疯狂的吉卜赛人，她穿戴着鲜红的斗篷，爱唱浪漫的歌曲，在她临终的时候还揭露了一个秘密：年轻的模范牧师欧内斯特是凯特的哥哥。而这一秘密又由一个矮小、吝啬的商人做证，这个商人爱诅咒陌生人并且对着他们发出邪恶的笑声。作者还写了一位极其正直的爱尔兰人巴尼，他通过比对一份文件的落款日期和签名的日期证实了它是一份假文件，尽管在此之前这份文件已经通过了法庭的审核并且已经生效。谈到莱昂内尔先生的住所，那是一个古老家族留下来的乡村别墅，我们猜想，这也使得女作者的想象力就此开始跳跃到城堡和城墙，“听啊，守卫吹响了号角”，据普利斯曼・X回忆，居民夜里都住在内屋卧室；一开始，外面的风很微弱，接着风渐渐变大，把香柏的枝杈吹到了草地上，于是女作者开始了中世纪式的描述：“旗面随着声音而展开，扬起它守卫的翅膀，猫头鹰受到惊吓后在常春藤丛中用翅膀拍动着她；而苍天正透过它的‘阿尔格斯之眼[20]’俯瞰着这个世界⸺

掌管无声旋律的神。

噢，听吧！守卫塔的钟敲了两声，楼下回荡着报时人‘凌晨两点’的回音。”

《谜团》中的故事就是如此混搭，就像我们在观赏一幅完全源自小朋友想象力的画：右边画着一处时髦的别墅，中间却是两个穿着盔甲的骑士在搏斗，而左边竟然画着一只咧着嘴的老虎在丛林中趴着，这些没有联系的事物被混在了一起仅仅是因为作者觉得它们各自很有特色，或者真正的原因是她在其他的画中见过这些场景，所以全部拿来据为己用。

然而，这种做作的中世纪写作风格，比起女作家的神谕体写作而言，也根本不算什么。她的神谕体内容谈论“本我”[21]“主观”“客观”，并且明确地划定了基督教真理的边界⸺“右侧过量，左侧不足”，对于所有不符合这一真理的人物，作者都会用居高临下的语气介绍他们。书中通过清晰的字体变化告诉我们一位名叫茵西奎林的小姐“在这个会幕时代，功能，而非形式——作为灵魂不可避免的外在表现——微弱地吸引着她”。另一位福音派的美嘉女士，过度热衷于讲述她探访病危女性的经历，并总是高谈阔论描述她们灵魂的状况；她告诉我们，那位模范牧师“并不反对人们在表层之下，主观上想着善良，而客观上追求真实的利益”。当她说到句中的变化字体的词时，我们可以想象着她加重了音调，并且略微点了点下巴。我们在这里就不引用她别的神谕教条式段落，因为她谈及的内容太过严肃，不适宜在这里讨论。

对于《谜团》这本显然源自作者大量阅读和思考的小说而言，我们说它“愚蠢”似乎太不合适。不过，“愚蠢”这个评论的确是经过我们深思熟虑才给出的。如果我们早已认识到，接受大量的教育并不能成就一个智慧的男人，那么我们也更应该认识到，接受过一定程度的教育也不意味着是一个智慧的女性。在女性所有的愚蠢中，影响最为恶劣的形式莫过于文学，因为它固化了人们对提高女性教育水平的偏见。当男人看到淑女们耗费光阴谈论礼帽和舞会礼服时，看到姑娘们为了爱情时而傻笑、时而神伤时，或是看到中年妇女热衷于说长道短而管不好自家孩子时，他们禁不住感叹：“上帝啊！让女孩们多读些书吧！让她们的头脑里多些有价值的东西，让她们更有事可干好吗？！”但是，当他们与一位神谕体女作家谈论几个小时，或者读了一会儿她的书之后，男人们又会这样说：“算了吧，当女人有了学识，看看她们是怎么利用这些学识的！她的知识仅仅停留在一种外在的习得，而没有被内化为自身的文化；她没有更多地思考、接触事实，从而学会谦逊、朴素地使用自己的知识；她心怀激动感受着新获取的知识，好像脑袋里装了一面镜子，时不时地看向里面沉浸在自己的‘才华’里；她形而上学的问题破坏了人们品尝松饼的胃口；她无懈可击的知识在晚宴上“挫败”了男人；她抓住舞会的机会为我们讲授物质和意识关系中的关键点。然后，再看看她写的东西！她错把模糊当深邃，将夸张的言辞看作文采，把矫揉造作等同于创造力；她在这一页还在炫耀自己的学识，眼睛却瞟向下一页，对着第三页做鬼脸，却又在第四页里歇斯底里。她肯定是读过很多伟大的男性作家的作品，以及少许伟大的女性作家的作品，但是她根本就不能分辨他们的风格和自己的风格，就像一个约克郡人分不清自己的口音和伦敦音的区别，而大言不惭正是她天生的风格。天哪！所以，一般来说，女人的资质还是像贫瘠且脆弱的土壤，经受不住什么耕种，只能生长出最微不足道的作物。”

诚然，仅根据表面观察和片面推断就得出这一结论的男人也并不是最明智的人；但我们在此不是要反驳他们的观点⸺我们只是指出，有很大一部分自觉标榜为知识女性代表的人确实不自觉地助推了这种观点。如果一个男人和一位真正有修养的女人交谈过，真正有修养是指那种真正吸收了学识而不是被学识所淹没的女人，那么他就不会得出以上观点了。一个真正有修养的女人，和真正有修养的男人一样，能更加公正地认识自身和自己的观点，她朴素地展示自己的学识，且不让人感到冒犯。她不会拿知识当垫脚的高台，扬扬自得地以为站在这里便可以一览人类和事物的全貌；但她会把知识当作一个观察点，由此可对自己形成正确的评价。她不会动不动就口喷诗句或引证西塞罗，这种沉默并不是担心男性的嫉妒而做出的牺牲，相反，她认为这种展现自己记忆力和拉丁语的方式并无意义也不甚优雅。她写书不是为了让哲学家困惑，或许正因为她能写出让哲学家感到愉悦的书，在谈话中，她是最不难缠的对象，因为她了解你，而又不强加给你你并不了解她的印象。她不是在教化你，而是在给你赞同⸺这才是有教养的最高境界。

比起小众的神谕体小说（被少数高教会派[22]和超验基督徒推崇），还有一种数量比较庞大的愚蠢小说我们叫作“白色圣领体”[23]，之所以叫这个名字，因为牧师脖子上佩戴的白色硬领能展示出福音派[24]的思想氛围和虔诚基调。这类小说就像是页数更多的宗教宣传册，为低教会派年轻女士提供的有蜜饯风味的药品；流行小说的福音派替代，就如人们把五月集会当作是歌剧的替代。我们认为，即使是贵格教派[25]的小朋友，在童年时也会沉迷于玩具娃娃，不过他们玩的娃娃穿的不是俗气的亮片薄纱裙，而是身着褐色长袍，头戴煤斗形的软帽。出于同样的原因，我们也认为爱情故事对于任何一位年轻女子而言都是不可或缺的，除非这位女子来自婚姻内也没有任何性交的基督教协基会。因此，福音派的年轻女士们拥有福音派爱情故事，这样的爱情经过各种磨难之后，因为重生和赎罪而变得神圣起来。这种小说不同于神谕体小说，就像低教会派女教徒不同于高教会派女教徒一样：她们不那么傲慢，却更加无知，句法更多错误，故事更加通俗。

福音派文学的主角一般都是年轻的牧师，从中产阶级的观点来看，牧师衣服上的亚麻带对年轻女士具有双重的吸引力，就如同一位军人的肩章在他的上级和下属心中激起的两种感受的混合。这类福音派小说的男主角无一例外地都是一个忧国忧民的年轻牧师，市井的老妇们对他可能是不屑一顾，但是她们年轻的女儿们“却再也不能忘怀他的布道”，轻易就被他获取芳心；温柔的一瞥总发生在讲道坛的阶梯上，而不是在话剧包厢里；二人间的亲密交谈时常引用圣经，而不是文学类诗集；他对女主角感情的怀疑常常还发展为对她灵魂的担忧。这位牧师的背景总是很好，要么是出身于上流社会，要么家庭富裕、衣着得体⸺其实，福音派小说也具备其他类别小说的愚蠢之处，作者在前一页还在跟你讲赎罪，下一页又开始描写贵族的礼仪和他们的高谈阔论了。作者所描绘的上流社会只不过是她的福音派想象力的奇怪彰显罢了；但是在众多“白色圣领”小说类别中有一点是值得称赞的真实⸺万年不变的男主角，传福音的年轻牧师，通常是极为枯燥乏味的。

最近刚巧有一本这种类型的小说面世：《古老的灰教堂》（Old Grey Church）。这本书完全平淡无味；在她笔下，每一个对象都被以同样的笔墨，平淡地描述；我们毫无头绪她的这些经验到底是来自生命的哪一个年龄阶段，但是，从她俗气的风格特点来看，她交往的人群主要还是那些行为举止没有被传统所蹂躏规训的男男女女，这本能成为她写作小说的一大优势，但她也并没有成功地将它发挥出来。而对于福音派作家而言，如果她都仅仅只关注着权贵阶层，讲述着他们的故事，这一点则显得更加不可原谅。真正的福音派故事就应当存在于中低产阶级，这个阶层中存在着很多优质的素材，前提是你得有一双善于发现的眼睛并且能用文字重现这些剧情。而福音派的观点不正是更多地关注世界上的弱势群体吗？为什么我们的福音派女作家就不能在这些大多数普通人的故事中展现她们的宗教观点呢？这些“大多数”普通人没钱买马车，“更别说是镶黄铜的轻便型双轮马车了”，甚至在家吃饭的时候连银制的刀叉都用不起，而且女作家们蹩脚的英语在他们看来却是极其通顺的。我们为什么不能描绘一下英国工人阶层的宗教生活，就像斯托夫人描绘的黑人宗教生活那样，一定也会很有意思。然而，事实上是，这些虔敬的女作家却还是拿一些虚伪的故事恶心我们，这些故事令我们想到刚刚皈依的世俗妇女：虽然她还是那么喜欢晚宴，但是她不再宴请花花公子而是邀请牧师；她虽仍旧沉迷于服饰，但她挑选颜色和图案的品位却变得严肃和清醒；她的言语依旧琐碎，但琐碎的言论中却充斥着福音而不是小道传闻。在《古老的灰教堂》一书中，我们同样能看到与流行小说一致的滑稽片段，各种品性不端却魅力无边的准男爵也是不会缺席的。有必要引用小说中的一段话来证明，这种出身高贵的人与斯桂尔斯小姐是相配的。这类谈话中充斥着大量字体上的变化和显而易见的暗讽。在一个夜晚，年轻的尤斯塔斯牧师为了能和勒欣顿小姐单独谈话，于是带着她去参观罗马斗兽场遗址。准男爵对此很嫉妒，于是就有了以下这段对勒欣顿的气话：

毫无疑问，勒欣顿和他在一起是十分安全的，因为他有尤斯塔斯教皇一世般的神圣指引。

他会给勒欣顿小姐说教，告诉她很多年前，就在这里，在罗马斗兽场，邪恶的异教徒放出凶猛的野兽袭击我们的门徒保罗——噢，不！顺便说一句，我觉得我错了，那并不是门徒保罗，也并不是在罗马斗兽场。但是内容的真假没关系，他依旧可以布道，从这些离谱的故事讲到那些堕落的异教徒，描述他们不恰当的行为，并且以这样的训词结尾：“醒来吧！不要和他们同流合污”——而且我确定，勒欣顿小姐，你十分虔诚地遵守了当晚的禁令，因为我们自从到达聚会就没有看见你。可是，大家都公认今晚是个快乐且有趣的聚会，而且我们都十分感激格雷先生关于举办这个聚会的提议，既然他是如此重要的一位活动向导，我希望他可以想出其他同样令所有人都愉快的事情来。

这种口水话以及这种口水叙述就像一幅糟糕的画，什么都没呈现出来，也没能暗示作者的用意。但是毫无疑问的是我们和蔼可亲的女作者认为这是一本极具教育意义的小说，虔诚的基督徒妈妈肯定会把这本书塞到她们女儿的手中。但一切都只是相对的，我们可能会遇到这样的美国素食者，他们平常只吃干粮，如果他们想要刺激下胃口，便会想法子找点“湿粮”来刺激刺激。所以，我们权可以把《古老的灰教堂》看作福音派小说圈子里口味独特的一味菜品，或许有的人读起来还是会觉得富有趣味和冲击力呢。

然而，可能最不具有可读性的蠢故事要数“现代仿古类”[26]小说了。这类小说给读者讲述雅尼和佯庇[27]的家庭生活、亚述王西拿基立[28]的个人感情经历或是银匠迪米特里厄斯的内心挣扎和最终皈依。其实别的大多数蠢故事至少能够博得读者一笑，但是现代仿古类简直就是给人完全呆板和沉重的感觉，其沉闷的愚昧让人禁不住呻吟。文学女性们常常自顾自地揽下一桩仅能由世界上最杰出的天才完成的任务，这无疑是对她们不自量力的最好证明。重现过去最好的办法只能是尽可能地模仿接近——而通过这种方式，我们也或多或少地把时代精神注入到了古典形式中⸺

时代精神是什么？

那就是做自我精神的主宰，

由此映射出的时代精神[29]。

我们承认有些天才对过去任何一个时期都了如指掌，他们可以通过丰富的想象力弥补“人类历史之声”里缺失的音符，并且将这些碎片重构成一个整体，从而把久远的过去呈现在欣赏能力贫乏的我们面前。这种天才的想象力十分稀有，因为它不仅要求有准确和翔实的知识，而且需要极其鲜活的创造力。然而，现代仿古类女性作家总有一些适得其反的写作技巧来暴露她们平庸的资质：她们借用古人的名字，把多愁善感用在罗马修女和埃及公主身上，并且借用大量犹太主教和希腊哲学家之口说出她们自己的修辞论证。这种极度愚昧的小说最近有《亚多尼雅：犹太人驱逐史》（Adonijah, a Tale of the Jewish Dispersion，后文简称《亚多尼雅》），它和其他小说组成了一系列“结合了品味、幽默和合理原则”的故事。我们猜想《亚多尼雅》展现的是合理的原则，而品味和幽默可能只在其余几本中得以体现。小说的封面上说此书故事的情节“非同寻常地有趣”，而且前言结尾这样写道：“如果你对被驱逐的以色列人和朱迪亚人感兴趣，本书会向你提供相关重大历史事件的信息并带来别样的阅读体验。”既然书中所谓的“重大历史事件”并未详细说明，因此有很多深奥的意义我们根本读不懂；然而要说被驱逐的以色列人和朱迪亚人这段历史，任何一个爱读书的学生丫头知道的都比这本小说中提供的信息要多。至于《亚多尼雅》中的爱情故事可以算是最低能的了，然而我们假定它尚且具有一定的教育意义，一是因为小说的男主角是个犹太俘虏，女主角是个罗马修女，他俩以及他们的朋友在经过“促进犹太人改变信仰协会”最简单、最快速的感化之后都皈依了基督教；二是因为作者为了让小说看起来比较复古，于是并不是用普通语来写，而采用了夸张的书面语言，例如“尼罗大帝毋庸置疑拥有天下最杰出的头脑”“这一贵族气数将尽”“他忠贞不渝的床笫伴侣”“啊！对维斯塔灶神起誓！”“罗马人，尔等听着！”等。本册书的封面上有众多名人推荐和介绍，有一句来自辛克莱小姐⸺“理性、智慧、虔诚的人都会坦坦荡荡地选择读这本充满想象力的小说”，据此读者可以愉快地推理，无论是多贝尼医生、米勒先生还是莫里斯先生，都是公开地阅读《亚多尼雅》，而不是将其偷偷地藏在沙发垫子底下或者在桌子下断断续续地读。

俗语说：“如果自己的脑袋都是黄油做的，就别去当面包师。”变通一下也可以说，如果没有准备好接受后果，女士们就不要投身于写作事业。我们意识到，我们的评论与别的评论者的语气完全不同。那些评论者常年怀着相似的感情，就像一位月嫂一样，对着一位又一位女性小说家说我们对你的作品“欣然致敬”。我们同样也意识到，我们所批评的那些女作家已经习惯了别人对她们的夸奖：小说的措辞十分考究，描写的生活十分生动，人物性格刻画突出，风格令人着迷，而且人物的精神高尚。但是如果她们怨恨我们直白的言论，我们则建议这些女作家应该好好审视一下她们的称颂者对其他作家吝啬的表扬和吹毛求疵的批评，因为这些作家的作品，正是在不久的将来可能成为经典的那一部分。一位女性作家的作品一旦受到了适度的赞扬和严厉的批评，则证明她的天赋或是影响力得到了认可。若是用一支温度计来度量女性的才华，那么，如果这位女作家的才华本身为零，那么媒体夸奖她作品的热度可能达到沸点；若是她的才华算得上平庸，外界的称赞则能达到酷暑的温度；但倘若是她才华横溢，外界的评论热情却会降到冰点。哈丽雅特・马蒂诺[30]、柯勒・贝尔[31]以及加斯克尔夫人和男性一样，得到了骑士般的待遇。如果哪个评论家真正承认女性作者在文学中的地位，那么从原则上来说，他一定得是个中立者，并且不对文学女性的作品有特殊偏好。因为如果你曾大量且不带偏见地阅读过女性所著的文学作品，你就会发现这些作品中最大的缺陷不仅仅是智性上的不足，更是一种与文学造诣息息相关的道德品质的缺失⸺女性作者常常容易忽略耐心刻苦伏案写作的重要性，不了解出版作品所带来的责任，难以欣赏写作艺术的神圣性。在女性大部分的著作中，由于缺乏高标准的约束而存在着大量愚昧的拼接或是拙劣的模仿，其实一丁点的自我批评就能使其原形毕露；但是，就好像听歌的人若不能正确给出评价，唱歌的人就会跑调一样；倘若是听歌的人有那么一些音乐细胞，就会让唱歌的人闭上嘴。单纯地想让文字变成出版物的虚荣心似乎鼓舞了很多女性，她们错误地认为只要会写作就好像高人一等了，可是写出来的作品却充满智力和道德的退化，毫无用处，她们就是没有这一点自知之明。在这样的前提下，我们认为女性的平均智力被大部分女性文学作品所错误地代表了；极少数写作水平很高的女作家远远超出普通水平，当然，还有多数女作家的写作能力远远低于平均水平。因此，严厉的书评肩负着一项十分具有骑士精神的任务，即剥夺女性作者的虚假威望，制止她们具有迷惑性的吸引力，并且劝阻那些资质平庸的女性⸺就不要写小说了⸺这是她们作为女性对文坛能做的唯一贡献了。

女性不经任何特殊资格证明就成为作家，其根源在于社会上的其他职业长期将女性拒之门外。看来，社会真是个十恶不赦的存在，小到有毒的咸菜，大到槽糕的文学，社会都应当对这些有害身体的物品负责。然而，社会，就像“物质”、女王陛下的政府或者其他崇高的抽象概念一样褒贬参半。如果有一个女性是为了生计而写作，那么必定有三个女性是为了名利而写作；而为了生计工作又是如此圣洁，让所有烂俗的女性小说显得与它格格不入。虽然俗语说“一切劳动必有收益”，但是我们认为女性作家的这些蠢故事并非劳动的成果，而只是一种庸庸碌碌的游手好闲。

幸运的是，我们并不需要去论证、去证明在小说这个领域，女性就不如男性。我们可以轻而易举地列出一长串已去世和健在的女性小说家名字，她们不仅仅写作优秀的小说，有的作品还能被认为是顶级的，这些作品也具有女性小说宝贵的特征，区别男性的天性和阅历。即使没有受到完整的教育，女性仍然不会被挡在写小说的门外，而其他艺术形式则没有如此简单的入门原则。就好像在任何形态下都十分美丽的水晶石，小说能以多种方式呈现，而仍然保持其魅力，只要我们在写作小说时诚恳地观察，保持幽默及热情。可是，正是因为写小说的门槛太低，才使得很多能力不够的女性也加入了写作的队伍。女性若是琴技不佳，则很难蒙混过关，假装自己富有音乐才华，因为在弹奏的过程中她需要克服实际的困难，而这也让她成了一个合格的演奏家。在一定程度上，任何一种讲求绝对技巧的艺术，都会自动抵制能力不足引发的愚蠢行为。然而，在小说写作中，即使你能力不够，也没有什么外在的条件来约束你，也不会阻碍你把愚昧的能力当作写作天赋。于是我们一次又一次地见证了拉封丹寓言中驴子的故事：它将鼻孔对准长笛，发现竟然奏出了声音，于是它激动地大叫：“我！我能吹笛子了！”在最后，我们把这个寓言故事谨献给那些想加入“写蠢故事的女作家”行列的女性读者，你们还是好自为之吧。

（石伟东、孙平华  译）

[7]《女作家写的蠢故事》是艾略特于1856年写给《威斯敏斯特评论》（Westminster Review）的一篇论文。

[8] 女帽类小说（mind-and-millinery species），作者借用英国女士们十分喜爱的帽子，暗讽女作家的作品虽然样式纷繁、精巧别致，但基本上虚有其表、华而不实。

[9] 用希伯来文和希腊文写的《圣经》。

[10] 奥西恩风格（Ossianic fashion）是指十分夸张的口吻，类似现在的琼瑶体。

[11] 原文为法语。

[12] 原文为法语。

[13] 阿尔比恩（Albion），英格兰或大不列颠的雅称。

[14] 斯科舍（Scotia），苏格兰的名字来源于拉丁语Scotia。

[15] 皮由兹运动（Puseyism），又称牛津运动，或书册派运动，19世纪中期由英国牛津大学部分教授发动的宗教复兴运动。该运动主张恢复教会昔日的权威和早期的传统，保留罗马天主教的礼仪。运动领导者纽曼、凯布勒、皮由兹等人发表了一系列书册或论文，为这些主张做了理论说明或论证。

[16] 原文为法语。

[17] 约翰・卡明，苏格兰教会牧师，曾在伦敦考文特花园的教堂讲经，本文作者乔治・艾略特曾反对过他推翻天主教的思想。

[18] 罗伯特・欧文（Robert Owen，1771-1858），英国的空想社会主义者、企业家、慈善家。代表作品有《新社会观》《新道德世界书》。

[19] 原文为法语。

[20] 阿尔格斯之眼（Argus eyes）。阿尔格斯是希腊神话中的百眼巨人。

[21] 原文为德语。

[22] 高教会派（High Churchmen），基督教新教圣公会派别之一。专指英格兰教会和英国国教会中的信徒，追随皮由兹运动。与“低教会派”对立。

[23] 白色圣领体（white neck-cloth），源自牧师的穿着，牧师一般穿黑色长袍，脖子上戴着白色硬领，习惯上被称作罗马领，牧师在不穿长衫的时候也会把罗马领戴在普通的衬衫上，白色的罗马领就成了他们身份的标签。

[24] 福音派（Evangelical），这一词始于16世纪，当时的宗教改革者以此名称呼表明反对罗马天主教的立场，凡接受基督教新教信仰的人都被称为福音派。福音派重视《圣经》权威和学术研究，较罗马天主教更注重直接与上帝建立信约而不通过耶稣以外的任何人作中保，因此更加恪守传统教义。

[25] 贵格会（Quaker），基督教新教的一个教派，又称教友派或者公谊会。该派成立于17世纪，创始人为乔治・福克斯，因一名早期领袖的号诫“听到上帝的话而发抖”而得名Quaker，中文意译为“震颤者”（tremble），音译贵格会。该派反对任何形式的战争和暴力，不尊敬任何人也不要求别人尊敬自己，不起誓，主张任何人之间要像兄弟一样，主张和平主义和宗教自由。

[26] 现代仿古类小说的作者一般是胡乱设定某个历史场景作为故事背景，然后完全不考据，便将自己想写的东西套进该历史时代。

[27] 雅尼和佯庇（Jannes and Jambres），埃及国的术士，是法老用来与摩西斗法的。

[28] 西拿基立（Sennacherib），古亚述国的国王，公元前704年至前681年在位。

[29] 出自歌德的《浮士德》。原文为德语。

[30] 英国社会理论家，被视为第一位女性社会学家。

[31] 夏洛蒂・勃朗特在发表《简・爱》的时候所用的笔名。

时髦婚姻[1]

/

去车站的路上，威廉突然失望地想起，自己没给孩子们带任何东西。可怜的孩子们！他们向来不依不饶，跑出来迎接他时，总是一样的话：“爸爸，你给我带什么啦？”他什么也没带，又不得不去火车站给他们买些糖果了。但之前的四个周六，他带的都是糖果。上周看见拿出来的又是一样的旧盒子，孩子们的脸都垮了下来。

帕迪说：“我之……之前就拿到过有红丝带的盒子了。”

约翰尼说：“我总是拿到粉色的。我讨厌粉色。”

那威廉该怎么办？这事似乎并不容易解决。从前，他可以叫辆出租车，去体面的玩具店，用五分钟为他们选点儿东西。但现在，他们已经有俄国玩具、法国玩具、塞尔维亚玩具，还有天知道哪儿来的玩具。一年多以前，伊莎贝尔就把老驴和机车之类的玩具拆烂了。因为，它们实在太“多愁善感”，“无益于培养孩子对形状的感知”。

“这点非常重要，”焕然一新的伊莎贝尔解释道，“小孩应该一开始就喜爱正确的东西，这样，今后才能节省不少时间。说真的，可怜的孩子如果得从小盯着这些可怕的东西，长大后多半会要求大人把自己送进皇家艺术学院吧。”

听她的口气，似乎对任何人来说，去皇家艺术学院一游，都肯定会立刻丧命……

“呃，我不知道，”威廉缓慢地说，“我像他们那么大时，常常拥着一块打了个结的旧毛巾入睡。”

焕然一新的伊莎贝尔看着他，眯起眼睛，微张着嘴。

“亲爱的威廉！我相信，你的确干得出这种事！”她换了种方式，哈哈大笑着说。

不过，还是只能买糖果吧。威廉郁闷地想着，在兜里摸索零钱，付出租车费。他见过孩子们传递盒子分享——他们都是相当慷慨的小孩。然而伊莎贝尔珍视的朋友们则一点儿也不客气……

水果怎么样？威廉在车站里的一个水果摊前徘徊。给每人买个甜瓜如何？总不会甜瓜都得分着吃吧？或者给帕迪买个菠萝，给约翰尼买个甜瓜？孩子们进餐时，伊莎贝尔的那些朋友几乎不可能溜进儿童室。尽管如此，威廉还是边买甜瓜，边厌恶地想象着：伊莎贝尔认识的某个年轻诗人肯定会找理由顺走一块儿，躲在儿童房门后吃。

他拎着两个笨重的包，大步朝他的那趟车走去。月台上很拥挤，列车已经进站。车门砰砰地开了又关，机车发出一声响亮的轰鸣，让匆忙来去的人们一脸茫然。威廉径直走向头等座的吸烟室，放好行李箱和包，从内袋掏出一大沓报纸，一屁股坐进角落，读了起来。

“再者，我们的客户还是很积极的……我们倾向于重新考虑……倘若……”啊，那样就好多了。威廉把扁塌的头发往后梳，腿伸过车厢地板。心中那种熟悉的啃噬感平息了。“至于我们的决定……”他拿出一支蓝色铅笔，慢慢在一段话下画线。

两个男人上车，经过他身边，朝较远的一个角落走去。一个年轻人把高尔夫球杆放在架子上，坐到他对面。列车轻轻一晃，启动了。威廉抬眼一瞥，看到炎热而明亮的车站渐行渐远。一个满脸通红的女孩追着车厢跑，一边挥手一边大喊，透着某种紧张又几近绝望的意味。“歇斯底里！”威廉没精打采地想。随后，他看见一个工人站在月台尽头，冲经过的列车咧嘴而笑，那张黑脸上满是油污。威廉想：“肮脏的生活！”然后，他便继续看起报纸来。

等再抬起头，窗外已是一片又一片田野，牲畜躲在幽暗的树下。一条宽阔的河流映入眼帘，光着身子的小孩在浅滩上泼水玩。随后，这一幕也溜走了。天空亮得苍白，一只鸟在高处滑翔，仿佛宝石上的一粒微尘。

“我们已经审查过客户的信函……”最后一句在他脑海中回荡，“我们已经审查过……”威廉把那句话读了一遍又一遍，还是徒劳无益。它似乎断在中间，田野、天空、飞翔的鸟、河水，一切都在说：“伊莎贝尔。”每周六下午，都会上演同样的场景。去见伊莎贝尔的途中，他总会展开无数想象：她在车站上，站得离其他人稍微远了一些。她坐在外面敞着门的出租车里，她在花园门边，她走过干枯的草坪，她站在门口，或门厅里。

她清透温柔的声音说：“是威廉啊。”“你好，威廉！”或“威廉来了呀！”他会碰触她冰冰的手和凉凉的脸颊。

多么精致又清凉的伊莎贝尔啊！还是个小男孩时，他就很喜欢跑进刚刚下过雨的花园，摇晃头顶的玫瑰花丛。伊莎贝尔就是那玫瑰花丛，花瓣柔软，闪闪发亮，清透凉爽。他仍是那个小男孩，如今却不再跑进花园，也不会欢笑着摇晃花丛。胸中又升起那种钝钝的、持续不断的啃噬感。他收回双腿，把报纸扔到一边，闭上了眼。

“那是什么，伊莎贝尔？是什么？”他柔声问道。他们在新房子的卧室里，伊莎贝尔坐在梳妆台前的一张彩绘凳上，台面上堆满了黑色和绿色的小盒子。

“什么是什么，威廉？”她倾身向前，漂亮的浅色头发垂到脸上。

“啊，你知道！”站在陌生房间的中央，他觉得自己也像个陌生人。伊莎贝尔飞快地转过身面向他。

“噢，威廉！”她拿起梳子，哀求地大声说，“求你了！求你别这么一本正经、满脸悲痛的样子。你说的话、露出的表情或给出的暗示，总是在控诉我变了。就因为我开始结识志趣相投的人，出去得勤了些，真正开始热爱每样东西，你就表现得我好似——”伊莎贝尔把头发甩到身后，笑了，“好似扼杀了我们的爱情之类的。真是太荒谬！”她咬着唇，“而且，这太疯狂了，威廉。甚至这座新房子和你硬塞给我的那些仆人，也太疯狂。”

“伊莎贝尔！”

“没错，没错，从某种程度上来说，这些都是事实。”伊莎贝尔飞快地说，“你认为它们是坏兆头。噢，我知道你是这么认为的，我能感觉到！”她轻声说，“每次你上楼来，我都能感觉到。但我们不能在那个逼仄的小窝里生活了，威廉。至少现实一点儿吧！唉，孩子们待在那儿，甚至没有足够的活动空间。”

对，这话没错。每天早晨，他从卧室回来，都发现伊莎贝尔和孩子们待在后面的客厅里，不是在骑着铺在沙发后背上的豹皮，就是把伊莎贝尔的桌子当柜台，玩着商店游戏。要么，就是帕迪坐在壁炉前的地毯上，把铜质的小火铲当成船桨，划船试图逃命；与此同时，约翰尼则拿着火钳射杀海盗。每天晚上，都得把他们一个接一个地背上狭窄的楼梯，送到又胖又老的保姆那儿去。

没错，他想，那的确是座逼仄的小房子。一座有蓝色窗帘的小白房子，窗台上的花盆箱里种着矮牵牛花。威廉会在门口跟朋友们打招呼：“瞧见我们的矮牵牛花了吗？非常适合伦敦，不是吗？”

但最愚蠢、最不可思议的是：他压根没想到伊莎贝尔竟然不像自己一样开心。天哪，多蠢呀！在那些日子里，他一点儿也不知道，她其实非常讨厌那座不方便的小房子，并认为那个胖保姆在宠坏孩子们。她十分孤独，渴望结识新朋友，接触新的音乐和画作之类的东西。他们要是没去参加莫伊拉·莫里森工作室的聚会；要是离开时，莫伊拉·莫里森没说“自私的男人，我要拯救你的妻子，她就像是高雅小巧的缇坦妮雅[2]”；如果伊莎贝尔没有跟莫伊拉去巴黎……如果……如果……

列车停在另一站——贝汀福德到了。天哪！还有十分钟他就要到站了。威廉把报纸塞回内袋。对面的年轻人早就不见了，这会儿，另外两个也下了车。傍晚的阳光照在身着棉裙的女人和光着脚丫、微微有些晒黑的孩子身上，同时也照耀着一朵柔软光洁的黄花：花儿粗糙的叶片四处蔓延，已经爬上一片石壁。微风拂过窗口，带来大海的味道。威廉想：伊莎贝尔这周末也还是和同一群人一起吗？

他想起从前一家四口去度假的日子。为了照顾小孩，他们还带上了一个名叫罗丝的农场小姑娘。伊莎贝尔穿紧身运动套衫，头发编成辫子，看起来就跟十四岁一样。天哪！当时，他的鼻子被晒到脱皮！他们吃得真多，睡得也多，双腿交缠着，睡在那么大一张羽毛褥子上……想到伊莎贝尔若是知道自己的这番多愁善感会有多惊恐，威廉不由得冷冷一笑。

“喂，威廉！”她果然在车站，正如他料想的那样，站得稍微离其他人远一些。威廉的心怦怦直跳——她是一个人。

“哎，伊莎贝尔！”威廉盯着她，觉得她看起来真漂亮。他得说点儿什么，“你真好看。”

“是吗？”伊莎贝尔说，“我倒不怎么觉得。快点，你那趟讨厌的列车晚点。出租车都在外面等着啦。”经过检票员身边时，她把手轻轻放在他胳膊上，“我们都来接你了，”她说，“不过，得去糖果店接博比·凯恩，我们把他留在那儿了。”

“哦！”威廉说。目前，他也只能说出这么多了。

等候的出租车开着灯。炫目的强光中，比尔·亨特和丹尼斯·格林伸开四肢摊在一边，帽子歪扣在脸上。另一边，莫伊拉·莫里森戴着顶活像巨大草莓的软帽，上蹿下跳。

“没有冰！没有冰！没有冰！”她快活地叫道。

丹尼斯附和的声音从帽子下传来：“只有鱼贩子那里能搞到冰。”

比尔·亨特冒出头，补充道：“里头还有一整条鱼呢。”

“噢，真讨厌！”伊莎贝尔哀号道。她跟威廉解释，说等待期间，几人如何如何满城找冰，“就是从黄油开始，一切都走起了下坡路。”

“我们将来得用黄油给自己行涂油礼了。”丹尼斯说，“威廉，愿汝之头，不会缺少油膏。”

“嗨，”威廉说，“我们怎么坐？我最好还是坐司机旁边吧。”

“不，博比·凯恩坐司机旁边，”伊莎贝尔说，“你坐莫伊拉和我中间。”出租车启动了，“那些神秘包裹里装的什么？”

“被砍——下——的人头！”比尔·亨特边说，边在帽子下瑟瑟发抖。

“噢，是水果！”伊莎贝尔听起来很高兴，“明智的威廉！一个甜瓜和一个菠萝，真是太棒啦！”

“别，等一会儿，”威廉笑着说。不过，他其实很紧张，“这是我给孩子们买的。”

“噢，亲爱的！”伊莎贝尔哈哈大笑，伸手挽住他的胳膊，“不行，如果吃掉这些，他们肯定会痛苦得打滚。”她拍拍他的手，“下次你给他们带点儿别的。我拒绝与我的菠萝分开！”

“无情的伊莎贝尔！快让我闻闻它的味儿！”莫伊拉说，一把抱住威廉，哀哀地唤了声“噢！”，草莓女帽朝前掉下去，让她的声音也变得模糊不清。

“一位爱上了菠萝的夫人。”丹尼斯说。出租车停在一家带条纹遮帘的小店前。博比·凯恩抱着满怀小包裹走出来。

“真希望这些都不错，我是按颜色挑的。有些圆圆的东西看起来棒极了。瞧瞧这牛轧糖！”他欣喜若狂地嚷道，“快瞧瞧！优雅得跟芭蕾舞似的！”

可就在这时，店员走了出来。“噢！我忘了！这些都还没付钱。”博比说，一副挺害怕的样子。伊莎贝尔给了店员一张钞票，博比又喜笑颜开起来，“你好，威廉！我坐司机旁边。”于是，一身白衣，光着脑袋的他把袖子卷到肩膀上，一下子跳进座位，大喊道：“前进[3]！”

茶点后，趁其他人去游泳，威廉留下来跟孩子们讲和。不过，约翰尼和帕迪已经睡着了，天光那玫瑰般的红色渐暗，蝙蝠也已经出洞，游泳的人们尚未归来。威廉溜达到楼下时，女仆正拿着一盏灯穿过门厅。他跟着她进了客厅。客厅很长，漆成了黄色。威廉对面的墙上有人画了个比真人还大的年轻人：那人颤着双腿，正向一位年轻女士献上一朵大眼菊。那女人一只胳膊很短，另一只却又细又长。椅子和沙发上挂了很多黑色的布条，上面溅满了碎鸡蛋似的痕迹。无论往哪儿看，似乎都能看到装满烟蒂的烟灰缸。威廉在其中的一张扶手椅里坐下。如今，即便伸手探向身侧，似乎也不会从这个“诺亚方舟”上触碰到一只三条腿的羊、少了一边犄角的牛抑或是肥鸽子；只可能是再捞起一本看起来满是污秽诗歌的平装小书……他想起内袋里的那沓报纸，但饥饿和疲惫让他无心去读。门开了，声音从厨房传出。仆人们旁若无人地说着话，仿佛整座房子里只有他们。突然，传来一阵刺耳的大笑，接着是同样大声的嘘，仆人们终于想起他也在。威廉起身，经过落地窗，走进花园。站在阴影里，他听见去游泳的几人走上沙土路，他们的说话声打破了沉寂。

“我想，得靠莫伊拉耍耍小聪明啦。”

莫伊拉哀叹一声。

“我们周末应该搞台能放《群山少女》的留声机。”

“噢，不！噢，不！”伊莎贝尔嚷道，“那对威廉不公平。伙计们，对他好点儿！他就待到明天傍晚。”

“把他交给我吧，”博比·凯恩大声说，“我特别擅长照顾人。”

门开了又关。威廉走上阳台，几人看见了他。“你好啊，威廉！”博比·凯恩甩着毛巾，在干枯的草坪上跳跃、踮着脚尖旋转，“威廉，你没来真遗憾。那水真是棒极啦！之后我们又去了一家小酒吧，喝黑刺李金酒。”

其他人都走到房子跟前。“喂，伊莎贝尔，”博比大声说，“我今晚穿尼金斯基裙怎么样？”

“不，”伊莎贝尔说，“没人需要盛装打扮。我们快饿死啦。威廉也饿了。来吧，朋友们[4]，去吃沙丁鱼。”

“沙丁鱼是我找到的！”莫伊拉高举着一个盒子，冲进门厅。

“一位拿着盒沙丁鱼的夫人。”丹尼斯严肃地说。

“威廉，伦敦怎么样？”比尔·亨特问。他正在拔一瓶威士忌的软木塞。

“噢，伦敦没多大变化。”威廉回答。

“美好的老伦敦。”博比边戳沙丁鱼，边十分真诚地说。

但不一会儿，大家便把威廉抛到了脑后。莫伊拉·莫里森开始琢磨一个人的腿在水下到底是什么颜色。

“我的是最浅、最浅的蘑菇色。”

比尔和丹尼斯只顾大口大口地狼吞虎咽。伊莎贝尔替大家斟满酒杯、更换盘子、寻找火柴，笑得非常开心。有一次，她说：“比尔，我真心希望你能把它画下来。”

“把什么画下来？”比尔大声问，满嘴都是面包。

“我们呀，”伊莎贝尔说，“围坐一桌的样子。再过二十年来看，一定非常迷人。”

比尔眯起眼，边嚼东西边粗鲁地说：“灯光不对，太黄了。”说完，他便继续大吃起来。可就是这副样子，伊莎贝尔似乎也很着迷。

但晚饭后，大家累得除了打哈欠，其他什么也没做。等天色足够晚，他们便上床睡觉了……

第二天下午，威廉直到等出租车时，才得以跟伊莎贝尔独处。他把行李箱搬进门厅，伊莎贝尔离开其他人，走到他面前。她俯身提起行李箱。“真够沉的呀！”她有些尴尬地笑了笑，“我来拿吧！我帮你提到门口。”

“不用了，怎么能让你提呢？”威廉说，“怎么也不该你来提，快给我。”

“噢，请让我提吧，”伊莎贝尔说，“我想提，真的。”两人默默地朝前走，威廉觉得这会儿没什么好说的。

“到啦。”伊莎贝尔洋洋得意地说，放下手提箱，焦急地望向沙土路，“这次我似乎都没怎么见到你。”她喘着气说，“真是太短了，不是吗？我觉得你才刚来。下次——”出租车开进了视野，“希望伦敦的那些人能好好照顾你。抱歉孩子们整天都在外面，但那是尼尔小姐早就安排好的。他们肯定会特别遗憾没有见到你。可怜的威廉，这就要回伦敦了。”出租车掉了个头，“再见！”她匆匆吻了他一下，便离开了。

田野、树木和篱笆不断闪过。他们摇摇晃晃地穿过空旷晦暗的小镇，开上车站所在的陡坡。列车已经进站。威廉径直走向头等座的吸烟室，一屁股坐进角落。不过，这次他没去管那些报纸。他交叠双臂，用以抵抗那钝钝的、持续不断的啃噬感，开始在脑中给伊莎贝尔写信。

和往常一样，邮件又晚了。他们坐在屋外彩色阳伞下的长椅里。只有博比·凯恩躺在伊莎贝尔脚边的草坪上。空气沉闷又压抑，这天就如一面低垂的旗帜，丧失了活力。

“你们觉得，天堂里会有周一吗？”博比孩子气地问道。

丹尼斯嘀咕道：“天堂就是漫长的周一。”

但伊莎贝尔忍不住琢磨：昨天晚饭大家吃的鲑鱼到底去哪儿了。她本想午餐吃蛋黄酱鱼，可现在……

莫伊拉已经睡着。睡觉是她的最新发现。“真是太棒了。只需闭上眼睛就行。无比美妙。”

当面色红润的邮差骑着三轮车，沿沙土路有节奏地驶来时，让人觉得那车把手真该变成船桨。

比尔·亨特放下书。“信来了。”他殷勤地说。然而，没心肝的邮差，噢，多恶毒的世界呀！只有一封信，一封厚厚的、寄给伊莎贝尔的信。此外连份报纸都没有。

“只有威廉会给我写信。”伊莎贝尔悲伤地说。

“威廉……这么快？”

“他是把结婚证书作为委婉的提醒，寄回来了吧。”

“每个人都有结婚证书吗？我还以为只有仆人们才有。”

“一页又一页！瞧瞧她！一位读信的夫人。”丹尼斯说。

亲爱的、珍爱的伊莎贝尔。威廉的信写了一页又一页。伊莎贝尔读着读着，惊讶渐渐变成窒息。到底是什么引得威廉……这封信可太奇特了……是什么让他……她觉得困惑，也越来越激动，甚至感到害怕。威廉就是这样，不是吗？真荒谬，这当然很荒谬，太可笑了。“哈哈哈！噢，天哪！”她在干什么呀？伊莎贝尔猛地靠回到椅子上，哈哈大笑，一直笑到不得不停下来为止。

“快，告诉我们。”其他人说，“你一定要告诉我们。”

“我正准备说呢。”伊莎贝尔咯咯笑着说。她坐直身子，拿起信，冲他们挥了挥，“快过来，”她说，“听着，它棒极了，是封情书！”

“一封情书！多棒呀！”亲爱的伊莎贝尔。可她刚开始，就被他们的笑声打断了。

“继续，伊莎贝尔，它非常完美。”

“简直是最了不起的发现。”

“噢，伊莎贝尔，一定要念下去！”

上帝保佑，亲爱的，你追求快乐时，我应该成了你的累赘吧。

“噢！噢！噢！”

“嘘！嘘！嘘！”

伊莎贝尔继续念着。等她念完，所有人都几近疯狂：博比在草地上滚来滚去，几乎啜泣起来。

“你一定得让我把它原封不动地写进新书，整篇都要写进去，”丹尼斯坚定地说，“我可以给它整整一章。”

“噢，伊莎贝尔，”莫伊拉呻吟道，“他把你搂在怀中那段，真是妙极了。”

“我一直以为，离婚案子里提到的这种信件都是瞎编的。但在这封信面前，它们简直都显得苍白无力啦。”

“给我。让我瞧瞧，我亲自读一读。”博比·凯恩说。

然而，让他们吃惊的是，伊莎贝尔把信揉成了一团。她不再大笑，反而飞快地瞥了一眼所有人，显得非常疲惫。“不，现在还不行，现在还不行。”她结结巴巴地说。

没等他们反应过来，她已经穿过门厅冲进屋子，爬上楼梯，回到自己的卧室。她坐在床边。“真恶毒、真可憎、太糟糕、太粗鲁了。”伊莎贝尔嘟囔道。她用指关节按了按眼睛，前后晃动着身子。然后，她又看见了他们，但并非四个，更像是四十个，在她读威廉来信时，伸出双手，一脸讥讽、嘲笑和奚落。噢，她做了件多么令人憎恶的事！她怎么能做这种事！上帝保佑，亲爱的，你追求快乐时，我应该成了你的累赘吧。威廉！伊莎贝尔把脸埋进枕头。可她觉得，甚至沉重的卧室都知道，她是一个多么肤浅、虚荣的无用之人……

这时，楼下花园传来呼喊声。

“伊莎贝尔，我们要去游泳了。快来！”

“威廉之妻，快来呀！”

“走之前再叫她一次，再叫一次！”

伊莎贝尔坐起身。就是现在，现在她必须做出决定。是跟他们去，还是留在这儿给威廉写信？应该做哪样？“我得做决定了。”噢，但怎么可能还有任何疑问？她当然要留在这儿写信。

“缇坦妮雅！”莫伊拉尖声叫道。

“伊莎——贝尔？”

不，这事太难了。“我……我要跟他们去，待会儿再给威廉写信吧。另外找时间写。待会儿。现在不写。不过，我肯定会写的。”伊莎贝尔匆匆想。

于是，她用自己那焕然一新的方式，哈哈大笑着跑下楼去。

[1]Marriage à-la-mode作为本篇的题目，源自威廉·贺加斯（英国著名画家、版画家、讽刺画家和欧洲连环漫画的先驱）一组以讽刺为主旨的油画的名字。油画主要探讨了关于婚姻与道德、爱情与金钱的关系。——编者注

[2]Titania，最早出现于古罗马诗人奥维德的《变形记》中，作为女神戴安娜的别称，后出现于莎士比亚的《仲夏夜之梦》，以妖精王后的身份登场。此名多被文学创作所沿用，代表美丽的女性。——编者注

[3]原文为意大利语。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明之外，均为译者注。）

[4]原文为法语。

布里尔小姐

/

蓝天上铺散着金色，大片的光斑落在市政公园，像白葡萄酒溅在地上。虽然天气这么好，布里尔小姐还是很高兴戴上了毛皮围脖。尽管空气里一丝风也没有，但一张开嘴，便能感觉到淡淡的凉意——好似啜饮冰水前，会感觉到的那种凉意。而且，天上时不时就不知从哪儿飘下来一片树叶。布里尔小姐抬起手，摸了摸毛皮围脖。多可爱的小东西呀！再次摸到它的感觉真棒。这天下午，她才从盒子里把它拿出来，抖掉防蛀粉，好好地刷了一番，让那双昏暗的小眼睛重新焕发出生气。那双忧伤的小眼睛仿佛在问：“我怎么了？”噢，又看到那双眼睛从红鸭绒垫中冲自己眨动，真是太甜美了！但那个用某种黑色材料做的鼻子，却不怎么牢固了。一定是不知怎的，被撞了一下。没关系，到时候……等非修补不可的时候，用一点儿黑色封蜡就行……小淘气鬼！没错，她真觉得这东西是个小淘气鬼。它正在她左耳旁咬自己的尾巴呢。她可以把它取下来，放在膝上抚摸。她感觉双手和胳膊一阵刺痛，但她想多半是走路的缘故。呼吸间，某种轻柔伤感——不，不能说伤感——是某种柔和的东西，似乎在胸中游走。

今天下午出来的人，比上周日多得多。乐队的声音也更大、更欢快。因为，演出季开始了。虽然一年到头，每周日乐队都会演奏，但非演出季期间，乐音绝对跟现在不同。那时，乐队仿佛只演奏给自家人听。也就是说，没有外人在场的情况下，它才不在乎到底演奏得如何。指挥似乎也换了件新外套，不是吗？布里尔小姐非常肯定，那衣服就是新的。指挥脚擦着地面，挥舞着双臂，活像一只即将打鸣的大公鸡。乐队成员坐在绿色的圆形乐池里，鼓着腮帮，目光炯炯地瞪着乐谱。听，现在开始了柔和清亮的一段——真美呀！一小串明亮欢快的调子。布里尔小姐觉得，这段肯定还会再奏一次。果不其然。她扬起头，笑了。

只有两个人跟她分享“专座”：一个是穿天鹅绒外套、双手紧紧攥着根大雕花手杖的和善老头；还有一个是坐得笔直、绣花围裙上放了团毛线的大个子老太太。他们都不说话。真扫兴！因为布里尔小姐向来期望交谈。她觉得，自己真的已经成为这方面的专家：坐在交谈的人们中间，若无其事地偷听，融入他们的生活，哪怕只是一会儿也行。

她斜瞥了一眼那对老人。或许，他们很快就会离开。上周日也不像平常一样有趣。那天，旁边是个英国人和他的妻子。男的戴了顶非常难看的巴拿马帽，女的则穿了双带扣长筒靴。其间她一直在不停地说该戴眼镜，说尽管知道需要眼镜，但不管买哪种，肯定都会摔碎，也多半戴不了多久，所以买了也不会有什么好处。男人始终都很有耐心，提出各种建议：金边的、镜腿弯曲，能挂在耳朵上的，或鼻梁架内侧带小衬垫的。不，任何一款都无法让她满意。“眼镜总会从我鼻子上滑下去！”布里尔小姐真想使劲摇她几下。

那对老人仍像雕塑一样坐在长凳上。没关系，总有人群可以观察。花坛和乐队所在的圆形乐池前，一对对情侣和三五成群的人来来往往，或驻足交谈，或互相问候，要么就是从老乞丐手中买一把花。乞丐行乞的浅盘固定在栏杆上。小孩嬉笑着，在人群中蹿来蹿去。小男孩脖子上系着大大的丝绸领结，法国洋娃娃般的小女孩们则穿着天鹅绒和蕾丝衣服。有时，一个蹒跚学步的小家伙突然从树下摇摇摆摆地走出来，又突然停住脚步，瞪着眼睛，啪的一声坐到地上，直到娇小的妈妈迈开大步，如小母鸡般冲出来，骂骂咧咧地去救他。其他人则坐在长凳或绿椅上，一个又一个周日过去，几乎总是老样子。布里尔小姐常常发现，差不多所有人都有些可笑之处。他们古怪、沉默，几乎都是老人。那副凝望着某处的神情，仿佛他们刚从某个幽暗的小房间出来，或者……甚至刚从壁橱里出来。

圆形乐池后，纤长的树枝叶低垂。透过那些黄叶，能看到一线大海。海的后面是蓝色的天幕，隐约透着金光的云朵飘散其上。

当当当，嘀嗒！嘀嗒！嗒嘀嗒嘀嗒！乐队开始演奏。

两位红衣女郎走过，迎向两个穿蓝军装的小伙。四人欢笑着，凑成对儿，手挽手地走了。两个戴着滑稽草帽的农妇牵着漂亮的烟灰色毛驴，神色凝重地走了过去。一个面色苍白、神情冰冷的修女匆匆而过。一位漂亮女士走来，掉了一束紫罗兰，一个小男孩追上去，把花捡起来递给她。她接过花，却又扔掉了，仿佛它们已经被下了毒。天哪！布里尔小姐真不知道该不该欣赏这种行为！这时，在她面前，一位戴白鼬皮无檐帽的女士跟一位穿灰衣的绅士碰了头。绅士个头很高，行为拘谨，面色庄严。而那位夫人戴的白鼬皮无檐帽，是她在头发曾经金黄时买的。现在，她的头发、脸，甚至眼睛，一切都跟那顶破旧的白鼬皮帽一样，变成了灰色。她抬起戴着干净手套的手，轻轻拍了下嘴唇。如今，那只手也变成细小的黄爪了。噢，见到他，她真高兴，简直太高兴了！她就知道下午会碰上他。她绘声绘色地讲述自己去过哪儿，每一处都讲，这儿，那儿，还有沿着海边走的情景。今天天气可真不错啊，对吧？或许，他不这样认为？……可他摇摇头，点燃一支烟，慢悠悠地朝她的脸深深喷了一大口。而在她说着笑着时，他就把火柴棒一弹，继续朝前走了。只剩下戴白鼬皮无檐帽的夫人。她的笑容比任何时候都灿烂，但即便乐队，似乎也知道她是什么感觉，乐音变得更加轻柔舒缓。只有大鼓一遍又一遍地敲出：“狠心的人！狠心的人！”她要怎么做？接下来会发生什么？然而，布里尔小姐正在纳闷时，戴白鼬皮无檐帽的夫人已经抬起手，仿佛见到了什么更有趣的人；就这样，她脚步轻快地走开了。乐音再次改变，变得前所未有地快，也更活泼了。跟布里尔小姐同坐的那对老人站起身，大步离开了。那长胡子老头真好笑，虽走得一瘸一拐，却正好和上节拍，还差点儿被并排走来的四个女孩撞倒。

噢，这一切真迷人！她好享受呀！她喜欢坐在这儿，观察周遭的一切！多像一出戏剧。这就是一出戏剧。谁能相信后面的天空不是画出来的？但直到一只棕色小狗隆重地快步跑来，接着又如“剧场”小狗，一只仿佛被下了药的小家伙般，慢悠悠地跑开，布里尔小姐才恍然大悟，到底是什么让这一切如此激动人心——他们都在舞台上。他们不仅是观众，不但在看戏，也在演戏。即便她，也扮演了其中的一个角色，每周日都来。毫无疑问，她要是没来，肯定会有人注意到。终究，她也是剧中的一员。真奇怪，以前怎么没注意到这点？难怪她每周都要同一时间从家里出发——演出不能迟到啊！难怪跟她的英国小孩们讲起自己周日下午如何度过时，她会生出那般古怪又羞涩的感觉。难怪呀！布里尔小姐差点儿大笑出声。她在舞台上。她想起自己每周都花四个下午，给一位躺在花园里的病弱老绅士读报。她已经相当习惯那颗躺在棉枕上的虚弱脑袋、那双凹陷的眼睛、张开的嘴和高挺清癯的鼻子。他如果死了，她或许好几个星期都不会注意到，也不会在意。但突然间，他知道是个女演员在给自己读报。“女演员！”苍老的头抬起，年迈的眼中两点光芒闪动，“你是——一个女演员吗？”布里尔小姐抚平报纸，仿佛那是她的台词本。然后，她温柔地说：“嗯，我当女演员已经很久啦。”

乐队已经停了一会儿，此刻又开始演奏，声音听上去温暖、和煦，却透着一丝凉意——那是什么呢？不是忧伤，不，不是忧伤，而是某种让人想放声歌唱的东西。调子越来越高，越来越高，灯亮了。布里尔小姐觉得，下一刻，所有人，整个剧团，都会开始歌唱。年轻人、欢笑着的同行之人会首先唱起来，男士们勇敢坚定的声音也会加入其中。然后，她，她也会，以及其他坐在长椅上的人，都会以伴唱的形式加入。那声音低低的，几乎没有高低起伏，那么美……那么动人……布里尔小姐热泪盈眶，微笑着看向剧团的其他成员。是的，我们理解，我们明白。她这么想着——尽管她并不知道大家究竟明白了什么。

就在这时，一个姑娘和一个小伙子走过来，坐在刚才那对老人的位置上。他们穿得很漂亮，显然正在热恋中。当然，这就是男女主人公。他们刚刚走下男方父亲的游艇。布里尔小姐仍在无声地歌唱，也仍挂着颤抖的笑容，准备倾听他们的谈话。

“不，现在不行，”姑娘说，“别在这儿，我不行。”

“为什么不行？因为那边那个愚蠢的老家伙吗？”小伙问，“她干吗到这儿来？谁会想让她来啊？这愚蠢的老太太干吗不留在家里？”

“她的毛……毛皮围脖真滑稽，”女孩咯咯笑着说，“简直像条炸牙鳕。”

“嘿，赶紧滚吧！”小伙子气鼓鼓地嘀咕道，然后又说，“告诉我吧，亲爱的小——”

“不，这儿不行。”女孩接着说，“现在还不行。”

回家的路上，她通常会在面包店买一片蜂蜜蛋糕，作为周日对自己的特别款待。有时，这片面包里会有一颗杏仁，有时没有。有或没有，差别可大了。这样一颗杏仁，就像带回家的一份小礼物、一个惊喜，是某种完全有可能不出现的东西。有杏仁的周日，她都会匆匆赶回家，精力充沛地划燃火柴，烧好茶水。

今天，她却没去面包店，反而爬上楼梯，走进又黑又小的房间——一个壁橱一般的房间。她坐在红鸭绒垫上，坐了很长时间。放毛皮围脖的盒子就在床上。她飞快地解下围脖，看也没看，就放进盒里。然而，关上盖子时，她觉得，自己听见什么东西在哭。

陌生人

/

码头上的那一小群人觉得，它似乎永远都不会动了。它静静地躺在涟漪阵阵的灰色水面，那般庞大，一动不动。一圈烟雾在它上空缭绕不去，一大群海鸥尖叫着，冲向船尾排出的厨房残渣。你只能看见船上的人们走来走去，像一群苍蝇围着灰色桌布上的菜肴上下飞动。其他苍蝇则聚集在栏杆边。下层甲板闪过一道白光，可能是厨师或女服务员的围裙。某位乘客像一只黑色小蜘蛛，顺着梯子，飞快地朝驾驶台走去。

人群前方，有个看上去很壮实的中年男子。他穿着不凡，一身灰色大衣，围着灰色丝绸围巾，戴着厚厚的手套和深色软帽。他转着一把折叠起来的雨伞，大踏步地走来走去。看起来，他似乎是码头上这一小群人的首领，起到了将众人聚集起来的作用，效果介乎牧羊犬和牧羊人之间。

但他多傻啊，真是个大傻瓜，居然没有带望远镜！而且，这一群人里，竟然找不出一副望远镜。

“真奇怪，斯科特先生，我们竟然谁都没想到要带副望远镜。原本可以激起一点儿船上的反应，想办法给他们点儿信号也行啊。说‘别迟疑，请靠岸，当地人并无恶意’或者‘大伙正在欢迎你们。全部赦免！’怎样？呃？”

哈蒙德先生急切地瞥了一眼，眼神虽然十分紧张，却也非常友善、充满信任。他的眼神扫过码头上的每一个人，甚至包括懒懒靠在舷梯上的那几个老伙计。他们知道，每个人都知道，哈蒙德太太也在那艘船上。他如此激动，以至于从未怀疑：这个惊人的事实对码头上的每个人也意义非凡。这个事实温暖了他的心，让他更贴近他们。他断定，他们就是一群体面的人。舷梯旁那几个老伙计也是善良、可靠的人。天哪，那是怎样的胸膛啊！他挺起胸膛，把戴着厚手套的双手插进衣兜，踮着脚跟来回晃悠。

“是啊，过去的十个月，我太太一直待在欧洲。我们的大女儿去年结婚，她去探望她。当时，我亲自把她送到克劳福德这么远的地方。所以，我想，我最好还是到这儿来接她回去。嗯，是啊，没错。”精明的灰眸再次眯起，焦急又快速地搜寻那艘一动不动的班轮。他的大衣又没扣扣子。那块细小的奶油黄色的怀表再次被掏出来。他第二十次……第五十次……第一百次地计算起来。

“让我想想……医生的汽艇两点十五分出发。现在刚好四点二十八分。那就是说，医生已经离开两小时十三分钟了。两小时又十三分钟呀！哟嗬！”他发出一声类似口哨的奇怪嘘声，啪地再次合上表盖，“但我认为，如果发生了什么事，应该会告诉我们的。你说对吗，加文先生。”

“噢，是呀，哈蒙德先生！我不觉得有什么……有什么值得担心的，”加文先生说着，在鞋跟上敲熄了烟斗，“与此同时——”

“的确如此！一点儿没错！”哈蒙德先生大声说，“真烦人！”他快速地走来走去，又在斯科特夫妇和加文先生间停了下来，“而且，天色越来越黑了。”他挥舞着那把折叠起来的伞，仿佛黄昏至少可以礼貌地回避一下。然而，暮色仍旧缓缓降临，如一块污渍，在水面缓缓晕开。小琼·斯科特拉了拉妈妈的手。

“我要喝茶，妈妈！”她哭喊道。

“我就知道你要喝茶了，”哈蒙德先生说，“我看，所有女士都想喝茶了吧。”他友善、热切、几近慈悲的一瞥再次扫过众人。他想知道，珍妮是否正在那边客轮的交谊厅喝最后一杯茶。尽管希望如此，但他知道她不会。以她的性格，她不会离开甲板。那样的话，船上的服务员或许会给她送去一杯。不管怎样，他要是在那儿，一定设法亲自给她弄一杯。一时间，他仿佛已经上了甲板，站在她身边，以自己特有的方式俯视她，伸出小手握住杯子，喝着船上最后一杯茶……但此时此刻，他却在这儿。天知道那个该死的船长要在水中徘徊到什么时候。他又转过身，前前后后地走来走去。他一直走到出租车停车场，确定自己的车夫还在，才猛一转身，走回人群中。那些人在一箱箱的香蕉下挤作一团。小琼·斯科特仍吵着要喝茶。可怜的小家伙！他希望他身上揣了一块巧克力。

“过来，琼！”他说，“想举高高吗？”他温柔又轻巧地举起小女孩，放在一个高一些的木桶上。抱起她，把她扶稳的过程，竟奇妙地让他轻松了不少。

“坐稳啦！”他说，伸出一只胳膊稳住她。

“噢，不用担心琼，哈蒙德先生！”斯科特太太说。

“没关系，斯科特太太，一点儿也不麻烦。我很乐意。琼是我的小伙伴，是吗，琼？”

“嗯，哈蒙德先生。”琼边说边伸出手指，在他帽檐的凹陷处游走。

她却突然抓住他的耳朵，大声叫着：“看，哈蒙德先生！它动了！看，它进港了！”

天哪！真的动了。终于动了！它慢慢地、慢慢地掉转头。水面上远远传来铃声，一大股蒸汽冲入空中。海鸥拍打着翅膀，如一张张白纸屑般飞了起来。那低沉的震动究竟是来自引擎的轰鸣，还是他的心，哈蒙德先生已经说不清。不管那是什么，他都得鼓起勇气，才能承受住。这时，老船长——如今的港务长约翰逊先生胳膊下夹着个皮公文包，沿着码头大步走来。

“琼没事的，”斯科特先生说，“我来扶住她。”他来得正是时候。哈蒙德先生彻底忘了琼，快步冲上前，去迎接约翰逊老船长。

“呀，船长！”紧张又热切的声音再次响起，“你终于对我们开恩了呀。”

“哈蒙德先生，怪我可没用，”约翰逊老船长喘着气，盯着班轮说，“哈蒙德太太在船上，是吧？”

“是啊，是啊！”哈蒙德说。他始终站在港务长身边，“哈蒙德太太在那儿。哈——喽！我们现在不用等太久啦！”

巨大的班轮，在船上的叮零零响个不停的电话声中，在水拍击船体的海浪声中，重重地向他们压过来。船头劈开幽暗的水面，海水在两侧卷起大片大片的白色浪花。哈蒙德和港务长始终站在众人前头。哈蒙德摘下帽子，目光在甲板上来回搜寻——那儿挤满乘客。他挥舞着帽子，朝着对面大声呼喊“哈——喽！”，他转过身来，放声大笑，对着约翰逊老船长说着——不，什么也没说。

“看见她了吗？”港务长问。

“不，还没。冷静——等一等！”突然，在两个傻大个中间——“喂，走开，别挡道！”他用雨伞示意。然后，他看见一只手举了起来——那是一只戴着白手套的手，正在挥舞一块手帕。又过了一会儿……谢天谢地，谢天谢地！她在那儿！那就是珍妮，是哈蒙德太太，没错，是她，就是她！正站在栏杆边，微笑点头，挥舞着她的手帕。

“呀，那是头等舱——头等舱！哎呀呀！”他肯定地跺了跺脚，闪电般抽出雪茄盒，递给约翰逊老船长，“船长，来根雪茄！相当不错呢！来两根！给！”他把所有雪茄都塞进港务长的烟盒，“我旅馆还有几盒。”

“谢谢，哈蒙德先生！”约翰逊老船长喘着气说。

哈蒙德把烟盒塞回去，虽然手抖个不停，他还是稳住了自己。他可以看向珍妮了！她就在那儿，倚在栏杆上，边跟一位女士说话，边看着他，随时准备迎接他。看着水面上的鸿沟合拢，他突然觉得站在那样巨大的船上，她显得多么娇小。他的心一阵绞痛，差点儿喊出声来。如此娇小的她，竟千里迢迢地独自来回！不过，她就是这样的人。这样才像她。她的勇气就像——此刻，船员已经上前，他们和乘客告别，降低栏杆，放下舷梯。

岸上的声音和船上的声音响起，互相问候。

“一切还好吗？”

“一切都好！”

“妈妈怎么样？”

“好多了！”

“你好，珍妮！”

“你好，埃米莉姨妈！”

“旅途还愉快吧？”

“棒极了！”

“现在用不了多久啦！”

“现在快了。”

引擎停了。船身缓缓靠近码头侧边。

“让一让，让一让，让一让！”码头工人扛着沉重的舷梯，飞快地跑了过来。哈蒙德示意珍妮待在原地。老港务长走上前，他跟在后面，完全忽略了“女士优先”之类的废话。

“您先请，船长！”他亲切地大声说道。然后，紧跟在老人身后，他顺着舷梯，大步跨上甲板，径直奔向珍妮，将她紧紧揽入怀中。

“呀，呀，呀！嗯，是呀！我们终于见面了！”他结结巴巴地念叨着，到头来也只说得出这些话了。珍妮抬起头。用她冷淡细弱的声音，这世界上于他唯一的声响，对他说：“呀，亲爱的！你等很久了吧？”

不，没多久。或者说，不管等多久都没关系。反正，现在也等到你啦。但问题是，他还让一辆马车等在码头。她准备好出发了吗？行李到了吗？如果都准备好了，他们可以直接带着她的随身行李先走，剩下的行李丢到明天再说。他低头看向她，她仰头看他，脸上仍是熟悉的微笑。她还跟从前一样，一点儿也没变，完全是他熟悉的样子。她把小手放到他衣袖上。

“约翰，孩子们怎么样？”她问。

（去他的孩子们！）“好极了。好得不能再好了。”

“他们没给我写信吗？”

“写了，写了，当然写了！我把信留在旅馆了，你待会儿再细看吧。”

“我们不能这么快就走，”她说，“我还得跟几个人道别……最后跟船长道别。”见他沉下脸来，她了然地轻轻拧了他胳膊一把，“船长要是从驾驶台出来，希望你好好感谢人家，把你妻子照顾得如此周到。”好吧，他已经接到她。如果她想再等十分钟……他让步后，她立刻就被包围了。似乎整个头等舱的人，都想跟珍妮道别。

“再见，哈蒙德太太！我可盼着你下次来悉尼做客哦！”

“亲爱的哈蒙德太太！你不会忘了给我写信，是吧？”

“噢，哈蒙德太太，少了你，真不知道这艘船会怎么样！”

显而易见，她是船上最受欢迎的女人。她也一如既往地接受了这一切，沉着冷静，丝毫不乱。这就是小小的珍妮，真真切切的珍妮——掀开面纱，站在那里。哈蒙德从未注意过妻子的穿着。他觉得，她无论穿什么都一样。今天，他却注意到她穿了一身黑“套装”——他们是这么叫的吧？领口和袖口有白色褶边，他想，那些多半叫“饰边”。这期间，珍妮已经领着他转了一圈。

“约翰，亲爱的！”她接着说，“我来给你介绍一下……”

最后，他们终于逃离。她领着他一路去了自己的包厢。跟着珍妮走在这些她如此熟悉，他却非常陌生的走廊上，又跟着她挑开绿门帘，踏进她的舱房，感觉真快活呀。可是——真讨厌！女乘务员正蹲在地上滚地毯。

“这是最后一块了，哈蒙德太太。”女乘务员边说，边站起身，扯下袖口。

他又被介绍了一遍。珍妮和女乘务员没入过道。他听见耳语声。他想，她估计在结小费。他坐在条纹沙发上，摘掉帽子。那些是她随身带的小地毯，看起来都跟新的一样。她的所有行李都干净整洁。标签上是她清晰漂亮的小字“约翰·哈蒙德太太”。

“约翰·哈蒙德太太！”他长长地舒了口气，双臂交叉，满足地往后靠去。终于不再紧张。他觉得，自己可以永远这么坐下去，在摆脱了心上那种可怕的拉扯感之后，如释重负地叹息。危险已经过去。就是这感觉。他们又踏上了陆地。

可就在这时，珍妮的头从屋角探进来。

“亲爱的，我想去跟医生道个别，你不会介意吧？”

哈蒙德一下子跳起来。“我跟你一起去。”

“不，不，”她说，“不用麻烦。我想自己去，用不了多久。”

他还没来得及回答，她已经走了。他有点儿想追上去，但还是坐了回来。

她真的去不了多久吗？现在几点了？他掏出怀表，却什么也没看进去。珍妮这举动很奇怪，不是吗？干吗不让女乘务员代为告别呢？干吗非要自己追着船上的医生跑？就算事情要紧，她也可以从旅馆寄张便条过去。要紧？这是说——这是说她在旅途中病了？她是不是有事瞒着他？原来如此！他抓起帽子，决定立马去找那家伙。要不惜一切代价，逼问出真相！他觉得，自己刚才应该已经注意到什么了，她太冷静、太沉着。从一开始——

门帘响动。珍妮回来了。他立马站了起来。

“珍妮，你在途中病了？是吗！”

“病了？”她轻飘飘的声音嘲笑着他。她跨过地毯，走到他跟前，伸手碰着他的胸口，抬头看向他。

“亲爱的，”她说，“别吓我，我当然没生病。你为何会这么想？我看起来不健康吗？”

但哈蒙德并未看她。只要感觉到她在看自己，他就觉得没什么可担忧的。她在这儿料理事情。没关系。一切正常。

她的手轻轻按在他身上，感觉那般平静。他也把手放上去，将她的手握在自己心口。她说：“站着别动。我想看看你。我还没好好看过你呢。你的胡子刮得真漂亮，看起来——更年轻了。明显瘦了不少！单身汉生活很适合你呀。”

“很适合我！”他充满爱意地感叹道，又紧紧拥住她。一如既往，他再次觉得自己搂住了某样永远也不会属于自己的东西。她太脆弱、太珍贵，一旦放手，就会飞走。

“看在上帝的分儿上，我们赶紧出发去旅馆吧。这样，咱俩才能单独在一起呀！”他用力摇铃，叫人快点儿来看行李。

她挽着他的胳膊，跟他一起走过码头。他又可以让她挽着自己了。跟着珍妮上车，感觉都不一样了。他用红黄条纹的毯子把两人裹住，催促车夫加快速度，因为他们都还没喝茶。再也不用过没茶喝，或者得自己给自己倒茶喝的日子了。她回来了。他转向她，紧紧握着她的手，温柔地打趣，仍是面对她才会用的那种“特别”声音：“回家很开心吧，亲爱的？”她笑了，没有费心回答，而是在马车行驶到更明亮的街后，轻轻推开了他的手。

“我们已经订下旅馆最好的房间。”他说，“用别的房间敷衍我可不行。我已经叫女服务员送了一小盆火进去，以免你觉得冷。她是个殷勤的好姑娘。我想，既然已经到这儿，不必急着明天回家，可以花一天时间四处转转，后天早晨再走。你觉得怎么样？没必要太赶，对吧？孩子们很快就能见到你……我想，花一天时间观光，也算是在一趟旅程后好好休息一下。对吧，珍妮？”

“你买后天的车票了吗？”她问。

“应该买了吧！”他解开大衣扣子，取出鼓鼓囊囊的随身笔记本，“在这儿！我订了去索尔兹伯里的头等车厢。这儿写着呢——‘约翰·哈蒙德夫妇’。我想，咱们应该坐得舒服些，不要让别人来打扰，不是吗？还是你想在这儿多待几天……”

“噢，不！”珍妮飞快地说，“千万别！就后天走吧。孩子们——”

可是，他们抵达旅馆了。经理原本站在灯火通明的门廊，这会儿也走下来迎接他们。一个搬运工从门厅跑出来，替他们拎箱子。

“呀，哈蒙德先生，哈蒙德太太终于到啦！”

经理亲自领着他们穿过门厅，并按了电梯的铃。哈蒙德知道，几个生意伙伴正在门厅的小桌上餐前小酌。可他不想被打断，所以目不斜视。他们爱怎么想就怎么想好了。如果无法理解，那只能说他们是傻瓜。他走出电梯，打开房间门，护送珍妮进去。门关上了。现在，终于只剩他俩。他打开灯。窗帘已经拉上，炉火燃得正旺。他把帽子扔到那张巨大的床上，朝她走去。

然而——难以置信！他们竟然又被打断。这次，是搬运工送行李来了。他跑了两趟，其间并未关门。那家伙从牙缝里吹着口哨，慢悠悠地穿过走廊。哈蒙德在房间里来回踱步，扯掉手套，又扯掉围巾。最后，他一把将大衣扔到床边。

那蠢货终于走了。门咔哒一声关上。这下，只剩他俩独处了。哈蒙德说：“珍妮，这些该死的家伙，让我觉得似乎永远也无法再拥有你了一样。”他双眼晶亮，目光热切地俯视着她：“我们就在上面吃晚饭吧。如果下去餐厅，肯定会被打扰。而且，那儿的音乐也很讨厌，（昨晚他还盛赞餐厅里的音乐，报以十分响亮的掌声！）想聊聊天都不行。就待楼上，在炉火前吃点什么吧。现在吃下午茶太晚，我订点儿晚餐，好吗？你觉得这主意怎么样？”

“点吧，亲爱的！”珍妮说，“你离开期间……孩子们的信……”

“噢，等会儿看也行。”哈蒙德说。

“那就得等到我们吃完饭，”珍妮说，“我想，首先有空——”

“噢，我不用下楼！”哈蒙德解释道，“按铃就能点菜……你也不想我走开，对吧？”

珍妮摇摇头，笑了。

“可你在想别的事。你在担心。”哈蒙德说，“什么事？过来，坐在这儿。过来坐我腿上，到炉火前待着。”

“我得先取下帽子。”说完，珍妮便朝梳妆台走去，“啊呀！”她轻呼一声。

“怎么了？”

“没什么，亲爱的。我就是找到了孩子们的信。没关系。等会儿再看吧。现在不着急！”她转向他，把攥在手里的信塞进带褶边的衬衫，突然快活地大声说道，“噢，这个梳妆台真是你喜欢的类型！”

“何以见得？它怎么了？”哈蒙德问。

“如果它哪天也开始不断地漂泊，我定要喊它‘约翰！’”珍妮哈哈大笑，盯着一大瓶生发水、柳条筐里的古龙水、两把毛刷、一打粉红带子捆起来的新领圈，“这就是你全部的行李？”

“别管我的行李啦！”哈蒙德说。但尽管如此，他还是喜欢被珍妮取笑，“我们聊聊吧，坐下来好好聊。告诉我——”珍妮坐到他腿上，他往后一靠，把她拉进那张又深又丑的椅子，“珍妮，告诉我，回来真的让你很高兴。”

“嗯，亲爱的，我很高兴。”她说。

可正如抱着她时觉得她仿佛要飞走一般，哈蒙德从来不知道——始终无法确定，她是否跟自己一样高兴。他怎么知道？他真的会有知道的那天吗？这种渴望、这种不知怎的，类似饥饿的痛感，这种就想让珍妮成为自己的一部分，再也无法逃开的感觉，真的会一直伴随着他吗？他想抹掉所有人、所有事，真希望此时此刻已经关了灯。那样，或许就能将她拉得更近些。此时此刻，孩子们的信在她的衬衫里窸窣作响，真恨不得把它们扔进火里。

“珍妮。”他轻声唤道。

“嗯，亲爱的？”她躺在他胸口，却感觉那么轻、那么遥远。两人的呼吸一起一伏，十分同步。

“珍妮！”

“怎么了？”

“转过来，对着我。”他轻声说，额头缓缓变得绯红，“珍妮，吻我！你吻吻我！”

她的唇坚定而轻柔地落到他唇上前，他似乎感到片刻停顿。对他来说，这短短的一刻已经长得足以成为一种折磨。她像往常那样吻他，可这个吻——该如何形容呢？这个吻进一步确定了他们正在说的话，犹如签订了合同一般。可那不是他想要的，完全不是他心心念念之物。他突然觉得万分疲惫。

“如果你知道，”他睁开眼睛，说，“今天这种等待……是何等滋味。我还以为，船永远不会开进来了。我们不得不一直在那儿徘徊。什么事让你们耽误了那么久？”

她没回答，也没看他，而是盯着炉火。火苗急匆匆地、急匆匆地从煤块间冲出来，摇曳、闪烁，然后坠落。

“你没睡着吧，睡着了吗？”哈蒙德上上下下地摇晃着她，说道。

“没有，”她回答，接着又说，“别这样，亲爱的。我没睡着，事实上，我在思考。”她说，“昨晚，有个乘客死了。一个男人。我们就是被这事耽误了。得把他带回来呀——我的意思是说，没有对他进行海葬。所以，船上的医生和岸上的医生当然都会——”

“什么病？”哈蒙德不自在地问。他讨厌听到死亡，讨厌发生这样的事。这事……听起来真有点儿怪，仿佛他和珍妮在去旅馆的途中遇到一场葬礼似的。

“噢，一点儿都不会传染！”珍妮说，声音几不可闻，“是心脏病。”她顿了顿，接着说，“可怜的人！还相当年轻！”她看着火苗亮起又坠落，“他死在了我怀里。”

这打击如此突然，哈蒙德差点儿晕过去。他无法动弹，不能呼吸，觉得全身的力量正在流逝，流进那张深色的大椅子里。这张深色大椅紧紧抓住他、攥着他，强迫他接受这个事实。

“什么？”他低沉地说，“你说什么？”

“最后相当平静，”那细小的声音说，“他只是——”哈蒙德看见她举起一只温柔的手，“静静地呼吸，直到生命终结。”她的手垂了下去。

“还……还有谁在那儿？”哈蒙德艰难地问出了口。

“没有人。只有我跟他在一起。”

噢，天哪，她在说什么！她对他做了什么！这会杀了他！可是，她仍一刻不停地讲着：“我发现情况有异，派乘务员去叫医生，医生却来得太迟。不管怎样，他本来也做不了什么。”

“可——为什么是你，怎么是你？”哈蒙德呻吟着。

听到他的声音，珍妮飞快地转过头，在他脸上迅速搜寻起来。

“你不会介意吧，约翰，你介意吗？”她问，“你不会——这跟你我无关啊。”

他设法冲她露出某种笑容，设法结结巴巴地说：“不——继——继续说！我想让你告诉我。”

“可是，约翰，亲爱的——”

“告诉我，珍妮！”

“没什么可说的啊，”她纳闷，“他就是头等舱的一位乘客。我见他上船时就病得厉害……但到昨天那时之前，他看起来都好多了。下午，他的病突然剧烈发作。我想，是因为即将抵岸的兴奋……或紧张吧。那之后，他就再没恢复过来。”

“可女乘务员为什么——”

“噢，天哪，女乘务员！”珍妮说，“那他会作何感想？况且……也或许还想留点遗言给……”

“他没留吗？”哈蒙德嘟囔道，“难道他没说什么？”

“没有，亲爱的，一个字也没说！”她轻轻摇摇头，“我陪着他的时候，他都太虚弱……虚弱得连一根手指头都动不了……”

珍妮沉默了。可她说过的话，虽然那般轻柔、那般冰冷，却仿佛始终在空中徘徊，如雪花般落到他胸口。

火已经烧红，尖锐地响了一声后，垮了下去。房间渐渐变冷。凉意爬上他的胳膊。这个房间很大，好似无边无际，还闪闪发光，填满了他的整个世界。这儿有一张挂着帘子的大床。随意丢弃的大衣仿佛一个正在祈祷的无头人，横亘在床上。行李就在那儿，随时可以再次出发。去往任何地方，抛进火车，运上轮船，去哪儿都行。

“他太虚弱……虚弱得连一根手指头都动不了……”他却死在珍妮的怀里。她——这么多年，她……她从没有……一次都没有……

不，他不能这么想。想这些会发疯的。不，他无法面对这种事，无法忍受，完全无法忍受！

这时，珍妮伸出手指，碰到他的领带，把边缘捏到一起。

“你没有……对不起我不该告诉你的，亲爱的约翰？这事没让你难过吧？它没有破坏我们的夜晚，我们独处的时光吧？”

但此时此刻，他只能藏起脸。他把脸埋进她的胸口，伸手抱住了她。

破坏了他们的夜晚！破坏了他们独处的时光！他们再也没有独处的时光了。

The Stranger

It seemed to the little crowd on the wharf that she was never going to move again. There she lay, immense, motionless on the grey crinkled water, a loop of smoke above her, an immense flock of gulls screaming and diving after the galley droppings at the stern. You could just see little couples parading – little flies walking up and down the dish on the grey crinkled tablecloth. Other flies clustered and swarmed at the edge. Now there was a gleam of white on the lower deck – the cook's apron or the stewardess perhaps. Now a tiny black spider raced up the ladder on to the bridge.

In the front of the crowd a strong- looking, middle- aged man, dressed very well, very snugly in a grey overcoat, grey silk scarf, thick gloves and dark felt hat, marched up and down, twirling his folded umbrella. He seemed to be the leader of the little crowd on the wharf and at the same time to keep them together. He was something between the sheep- dog and the shepherd.

But what a fool – what a fool he had been not to bring any glasses! There wasn't a pair of glasses between the whole lot of them.

‘Curious thing, Mr Scott, that none of us thought of glasses. We might have been able to stir 'em up a bit. We might have managed a little signalling. Don't hesitate to land. Natives harmless. Or: A welcome awaits you. All is forgiven. What? Eh?'

Mr Hammond's quick, eager glance, so nervous and yet so friendly and confiding, took in everybody on the wharf, roped in even those old chaps lounging against the gangways. They knew, every man- jack of them, that Mrs Hammond was on that boat, and he was so tremendously excited it never entered his head not to believe that this marvellous fact meant something to them too. It warmed his heart towards them. They were, he decided, as decent a crowd of people – those old chaps over by the gangways, too – fine, solid old chaps. What chests – by Jove! And he squared his own, plunged his thick- gloved hands into his pockets, rocked from heel to toe.

‘Yes, my wife's been in Europe for the last ten months. On a visit to our eldest girl, who was married last year. I brought her up here, as far as Crawford, myself. So I thought I'd better come and fetch her back. Yes, yes, yes.' The shrewd grey eyes narrowed again and searched anxiously, quickly, the motionless liner. Again his overcoat was unbuttoned. Out came the thin, butter- yellow watch again, and for the twentieth – fiftieth – hundredth time he made the calculation.

‘Let me see, now. It was two fifteen when the doctor's launch went off. Two fifteen. It is now exactly twenty- eight minutes past four. That is to say, the doctor's been gone two hours and thirteen minutes. Two hours and thirteen minutes! Whee- ooh!' He gave a queer little half- whistle and snapped his watch to again. ‘But I think we should have been told if there was anything up – don't you, Mr Gaven?'

‘Oh, yes, Mr Hammond! I don't think there's anything to – anything to worry about,' said Mr Gaven, knocking out his pipe against the heel of his shoe. ‘At the same time –'

‘Quite so! Quite so!' cried Mr Hammond. ‘Dashed annoying!' He paced quickly up and down and came back again to his stand between Mr and Mrs Scott and Mr Gaven. ‘It's getting quite dark, too,' and he waved his folded umbrella as though the dusk at least might have had the decency to keep off for a bit. But the dusk came slowly, spreading like a slow stain over the water. Little Jean Scott dragged at her mother's hand.

‘I wan' my tea, mammy!' she wailed.

‘I expect you do,' said Mr Hammond. ‘I expect all these ladies want their tea.' And his kind, flushed, almost pitiful glance roped them all in again. He wondered whether Janey was having a final cup of tea in the saloon out there. He hoped so; he thought not. It would be just like her not to leave the deck. In that case perhaps the deck steward would bring her up a cup. If he'd been there he'd have got it for her – somehow. And for a moment he was on deck, standing over her, watching her little hand fold round the cup in the way she had, while she drank the only cup of tea to be got on board ... But now he was back here, and the Lord only knew when that cursed Captain would stop hanging about in the stream. He took another turn, up and down, up and down. He walked as far as the cab- stand to make sure his driver hadn't disappeared; back he swerved again to the little flock huddled in the shelter of the banana crates. Little Jean Scott was still wanting her tea. Poor little beggar! He wished he had a bit of chocolate on him.

‘Here, Jean!' he said. ‘Like a lift up?' And easily, gently, he swung the little girl on to a higher barrel. The movement of holding her, steadying her, relieved him wonderfully, lightened his heart.

‘Hold on,' he said, keeping an arm round her.

‘Oh, don't worry about Jean, Mr Hammond!' said Mrs Scott.

‘That's all right, Mrs Scott. No trouble. It's a pleasure. Jean's a little pal of mine, aren't you, Jean?'

‘Yes, Mr Hammond,' said Jean, and she ran her finger down the dent of his felt hat.

But suddenly she caught him by the ear and gave a loud scream. ‘ Lo- ok, Mr Hammond! She's moving! Look, she's coming in!'

By Jove! So she was. At last! She was slowly, slowly turning round. A bell sounded far over the water and a great spout of steam gushed into the air. The gulls rose; they fluttered away like bits of white paper. And whether that deep throbbing was her engines or his heart Mr Hammond couldn't say. He had to nerve himself to bear it, whatever it was. At that moment old Captain Johnson, the harbour- master, came striding down the wharf, a leather portfolio under his arm.

‘Jean'll be all right,' said Mr Scott. ‘I'll hold her.' He was just in time. Mr Hammond had forgotten about Jean. He sprang away to greet old Captain Johnson.

‘Well, Captain,' the eager, nervous voice rang out again, ‘you've taken pity on us at last.'

‘It's no good blaming me, Mr Hammond,' wheezed old Captain Johnson, staring at the liner. ‘You got Mrs Hammond on board, ain't yer?'

‘Yes, yes!' said Hammond, and he kept by the harbour- master's side. ‘Mrs Hammond's there. Hul- lo! We shan't be long now!'

With her telephone ring- ringing, the thrum of her screw filling the air, the big liner bore down on them, cutting sharp through the dark water so that big white shavings curled to either side. Hammond and the harbour- master kept in front of the rest. Hammond took off his hat; he raked the decks – they were crammed with passengers; he waved his hat and bawled a loud, strange ‘ Hul- lo!' across the water, and then turned round and burst out laughing and said something – nothing – to old Captain Johnson.

‘Seen her?' asked the harbour- master.

‘No, not yet. Steady – wait a bit!' And suddenly, between two great clumsy idiots – ‘Get out of the way there!' he signed with his umbrella – he saw a hand raised ... hite glove shaking a handkerchief. Another moment, and – thank God, thank God! – there she was. There was Janey. There was Mrs Hammond, yes, yes, yes – standing by the rail and smiling and nodding and waving her handkerchief.

‘Well, that's first class – first class! Well, well, well!' He positively stamped. Like lightning he drew out his cigar- case and offered it to old Captain Johnson. ‘Have a cigar, Captain! They're pretty good. Have a couple! Here' – and he pressed all the cigars in the case on the harbour- master – ‘I've a couple of boxes up at the hotel.'

‘Thenks, Mr Hammond!' wheezed old Captain Johnson.

Hammond stuffed the cigar- case back. His hands were shaking, but he'd got hold of himself again. He was able to face Janey. There she was, leaning on the rail, talking to some woman and at the same time watching him, ready for him. It struck him, as the gulf of water closed, how small she looked on that huge ship. His heart was wrung with such a spasm that he could have cried out. How little she looked to have come all that long way and back by herself! Just like her, though. Just like Janey. She had the courage of ... nd now the crew had come forward and parted the passengers; they had lowered the rails for the gangways.

The voices on shore and the voices on board flew to greet each other.

‘All well?'

‘All well.'

‘How's mother?'

‘Much better.'

‘Hullo, Jean!'

‘Hillo, Aun' Emily!'

‘Had a good voyage?'

‘Splendid!'

‘Shan't be long now!'

‘Not long now.'

The engines stopped. Slowly she edged to the wharf- side.

‘Make way there – make way – make way!' And the wharf hands brought the heavy gangways along at a sweeping run. Hammond signed to Janey to stay where she was. The old harbour- master stepped forward; he followed. As to ‘ladies first,' or any rot like that, it never entered his head.

‘After you, Captain!' he cried genially. And, treading on the old man's heels, he strode up the gangway on to the deck in a bee- line to Janey, and Janey was clasped in his arms.

‘Well, well, well! Yes, yes! Here we are at last!' he stammered. It was all he could say. And Janey emerged, and her cool little voice – the only voice in the world for him – said,

‘Well, darling! Have you been waiting long?'

No; not long. Or, at any rate, it didn't matter. It was over now. But the point was, he had a cab waiting at the end of the wharf. Was she ready to go off? Was her luggage ready? In that case they could cut off sharp with her cabin luggage and let the rest go hang until tomorrow. He bent over her and she looked up with her familiar half- smile. She was just the same. Not a day changed. Just as he'd always known her. She laid her small hand on his sleeve.

‘How are the children, John?' she asked.

(Hang the children!) ‘Perfectly well. Never better in their lives.'

‘Haven't they sent me letters?'

‘Yes, yes – of course! I've left them at the hotel for you to digest later on.'

‘We can't go quite so fast,' said she. ‘I've got people to say goodbye to – and then there's the Captain.' As his face fell she gave his arm a small understanding squeeze. ‘If the Captain comes off the bridge I want you to thank him for having looked after your wife so beautifully.' Well, he'd got her. If she wanted another ten minutes – As he gave way she was surrounded. The whole first- class seemed to want to say goodbye to Janey.

‘Goodbye, dear Mrs Hammond! And next time you're in Sydney I'll expect you.'

‘Darling Mrs Hammond! You won't forget to write to me, will you?'

‘Well, Mrs Hammond, what this boat would have been without you!'

It was as plain as a pikestaff that she was by far the most popular woman on board. And she took it all – just as usual. Absolutely composed. Just her little self – just Janey all over; standing there with her v thrown back. Hammond never noticed what his wife had on. It was all the same to him whatever she wore. But today he did notice that she wore a black ‘costume' – didn't they call it? – with white frills, trimmings he supposed they were, at the neck and sleeves. All this while Janey handed him round.

‘John, dear!' And then: ‘I want to introduce you to –'

Finally they did escape, and she led the way to her state- room. To follow Janey down the passage that she knew so well – that was so strange to him; to part the green curtains after her and to step into the cabin that had been hers gave him exquisite happiness. But – confound it! – the stewardess was there on the floor, strapping up the rugs.

‘That's the last, Mrs Hammond,' said the stewardess, rising and pulling down her cuffs.

He was introduced again, and then Janey and the stewardess disappeared into the passage. He heard whisperings. She was getting the tipping business over, he supposed. He sat down on the striped sofa and took his hat off. There were the rugs she had taken with her; they looked good as new. All her luggage looked fresh, perfect. The labels were written in her beautiful little clear hand – ‘Mrs John Hammond.'

‘Mrs John Hammond!' He gave a long sigh of content and leaned back, crossing his arms. The strain was over. He felt he could have sat there for ever sighing his relief – the relief at being rid of that horrible tug, pull, grip on his heart. The danger was over. That was the feeling. They were on dry land again.

But at that moment Janey's head came round the corner.

‘Darling – do you mind? I just want to go and say goodbye to the doctor.'

Hammond started up. ‘I'll come with you.'

‘No, no!' she said. ‘Don't bother. I'd rather not. I'll not be a minute.'

And before he could answer she was gone. He had half a mind to run after her; but instead he sat down again.

Would she really not be long? What was the time now? Out came the watch; he stared at nothing. That was rather queer of Janey, wasn't it? Why couldn't she have told the stewardess to say goodbye for her? Why did she have to go chasing after the ship's doctor? She could have sent a note from the hotel even if the affair had been urgent. Urgent? Did it – could it mean that she had been ill on the voyage – she was keeping something from him? That was it! He seized his hat. He was going off to find that fellow and to wring the truth out of him at all costs. He thought he'd noticed just something. She was just a touch too calm – too steady. From the very first moment –

The curtains rang. Janey was back. He jumped to his feet.

‘Janey, have you been ill on this voyage? You have!'

‘Ill?' Her airy little voice mocked him. She stepped over the rugs, came up close, touched his breast, and looked up at him.

‘Darling,' she said, ‘don't frighten me. Of course I haven't! Whatever makes you think I have? Do I look ill?'

But Hammond didn't see her. He only felt that she was looking at him and that there was no need to worry about anything. She was here to look after things. It was all right. Everything was.

The gentle pressure of her hand was so calming that he put his over hers to hold it there. And she said:

‘Stand still. I want to look at you. I haven't seen you yet. You've had your beard beautifully trimmed, and you look – younger, I think, and decidedly thinner! Bachelor life agrees with you.'

‘Agrees with me!' He groaned for love and caught her close again. And again, as always, he had the feeling he was holding something that never was quite his – his. Something too delicate, too precious, that would fly away once he let go.

‘For God's sake let's get off to the hotel so that we can be by ourselves!' And he rang the bell hard for some one to look sharp with the luggage.

Walking down the wharf together she took his arm. He had her on his arm again. And the difference it made to get into the cab after Janey – to throw the red- and- yellow striped blanket round them both – to tell the driver to hurry because neither of them had had any tea. No more going without his tea or pouring out his own. She was back. He turned to her, squeezed her hand, and said gently, teasingly, in the ‘special' voice he had for her: ‘Glad to be home again, dearie?' She smiled; she didn't even bother to answer, but gently she drew his hand away as they came to the brighter streets.

‘We've got the best room in the hotel,' he said. ‘I wouldn't be put off with another. And I asked the chambermaid to put in a bit of a fire in case you felt chilly. She's a nice, attentive girl. And I thought now we were here we wouldn't bother to go home tomorrow, but spend the day looking round and leave the morning after. Does that suit you? There's no hurry, is there? The children will have you soon enough ... I thought a day's sightseeing might make a nice break in your journey – eh, Janey?'

‘Have you taken the tickets for the day after?' she asked.

‘I should think I have!' He unbuttoned his overcoat and took out his bulging pocket- book. ‘Here we are! I reserved a first- class carriage to Salisbury. There it is – "Mr and Mrs John Hammond." I thought we might as well do ourselves comfortably, and we don't want other people butting in, do we? But if you'd like to stop here a bit longer –?'

‘Oh, no!' said Janey quickly. ‘Not for the world! The day after tomorrow, then. And the children –'

But they had reached the hotel. The manager was standing in the broad, brilliantly- lighted porch. He came down to greet them. A porter ran from the hall for their boxes.

‘Well, Mr Arnold, here's Mrs Hammond at last!'

The manager led them through the hall himself and pressed the elevator- bell. Hammond knew there were business pals of his sitting at the little hall tables having a drink before dinner. But he wasn't going to risk interruption; he looked neither to the right nor the left. They could think what they pleased. If they didn't understand, the more fools they – and he stepped out of the lift, unlocked the door of their room, and shepherded Janey in. The door shut. Now, at last, they were alone together. He turned up the light. The curtains were drawn; the fire blazed. He flung his hat on to the huge bed and went towards her.

But – would you believe it! – again they were interrupted. This time it was the porter with the luggage. He made two journeys of it, leaving the door open in between, taking his time, whistling through his teeth in the corridor. Hammond paced up and down the room, tearing off his gloves, tearing off his scarf. Finally he flung his overcoat on the bedside.

At last the fool was gone. The door clicked. Now they were alone. Said Hammond: ‘I feel I'll never have you to myself again. These cursed people! Janey' – and he bent his flushed, eager gaze upon her – ‘let's have dinner up here. If we go down to the restaurant we'll be interrupted, and then there's the confounded music' (the music he'd praised so highly, applauded so loudly last night!). ‘We shan't be able to hear each other speak. Let's have something up here in front of the fire. It's too late for tea. I'll order a little supper, shall I? How does the idea strike you?'

‘Do, darling!' said Janey. ‘And while you're away – the children's letters –'

‘Oh, later on will do!' said Hammond.

‘But then we'd get it over,' said Janey. ‘And I'd first have time to –'

‘Oh, I needn't go down!' explained Hammond. ‘I'll just ring and give the order ... you don't want to send me away, do you?'

Janey shook her head and smiled.

‘But you're thinking of something else. You're worrying about something,' said Hammond. ‘What is it? Come and sit here – come and sit on my knee before the fire.'

‘I'll just unpin my hat,' said Janey, and she went over to the dressing- table. ‘ A- ah!' She gave a little cry.

‘What is it?'

‘Nothing, darling. I've just found the children's letters. That's all right! They will keep. No hurry now!' She turned to him, clasping them. She tucked them into her frilled blouse. She cried quickly, gaily: ‘Oh, how typical this dressing- table is of you!'

‘Why? What's the matter with it?' said Hammond.

‘If it were floating in eternity I should say "John!" ' laughed Janey, staring at the big bottle of hair tonic, the wicker bottle of eau- de- Cologne, the two hairbrushes, and a dozen new collars tied with pink tape. ‘Is this all your luggage?'

‘Hang my luggage!' said Hammond; but all the same he liked being laughed at by Janey. ‘Let's talk. Let's get down to things. Tell me' – and as Janey perched on his knees he leaned back and drew her into the deep, ugly chair – ‘tell me you're really glad to be back, Janey.'

‘Yes, darling, I am glad,' she said.

But just as when he embraced her he felt she would fly away, so Hammond never knew – never knew for dead certain that she was as glad as he was. How could he know? Would he ever know? Would he always have this craving – this pang like hunger somehow, to make Janey so much part of him that there wasn't any of her to escape? He wanted to blot out everybody, everything. He wished now he'd turned off the light. That might have brought her nearer. And now those letters from the children rustled in her blouse. He could have chucked them into the fire.

‘Janey,' he whispered.

‘Yes, dear?' She lay on his breast, but so lightly, so remotely. Their breathing rose and fell together.

‘Janey!'

‘What is it?'

‘Turn to me,' he whispered. A slow, deep flush flowed into his forehead. ‘Kiss me, Janey! You kiss me!'

It seemed to him there was a tiny pause – but long enough for him to suffer torture – before her lips touched his, firmly, lightly – kissing them as she always kissed him, as though the kiss – how could he describe it? – confirmed what they were saying, signed the contract. But that wasn't what he wanted; that wasn't at all what he thirsted for. He felt suddenly horribly tired.

‘If you knew,' he said, opening his eyes, ‘what it's been like – waiting today. I thought the boat never would come in. There we were, hanging about. What kept you so long?'

She made no answer. She was looking away from him at the fire. The flames hurried – hurried over the coals, flickered, fell.

‘Not asleep, are you?' said Hammond, and he jumped her up and down.

‘No,' she said. And then: ‘Don't do that, dear. No, I was thinking. As a matter of fact,' she said, ‘one of the passengers died last night ... an. That's what held us up. We brought him in ... ean, he wasn't buried at sea. So, of course, the ship's doctor and the shore doctor –'

‘What was it?' asked Hammond uneasily. He hated to hear of death. He hated this to have happened. It was, in some queer way, as though he and Janey had met a funeral on their way to the hotel.

‘Oh, it wasn't anything in the least infectious!' said Janey. She was speaking scarcely above her breath. ‘It was heart.' A pause. ‘Poor fellow!' she said. ‘Quite young.' And she watched the fire flicker and fall. ‘He died in my arms,' said Janey.

The blow was so sudden that Hammond thought he would faint. He couldn't move; he couldn't breathe. He felt all his strength flowing – flowing into the big dark chair, and the big dark chair held him fast, gripped him, forced him to bear it.

‘What?' he said dully. ‘What's that you say?'

‘The end was quite peaceful,' said the small voice. ‘He just' – and Hammond saw her lift her gentle hand – ‘breathed his life away at the end.' And her hand fell.

‘Who – else was there?' Hammond managed to ask.

‘Nobody. I was alone with him.'

Ah, my God, what was she saying! What was she doing to him! This would kill him! And all the while she spoke:

‘I saw the change coming and I sent the steward for the doctor, but the doctor was too late. He couldn't have done anything, anyway.'

‘But – why you, why you?' moaned Hammond.

At that Janey turned quickly, quickly searched his face.

‘You don't mind, John, do you?' she asked. ‘You don't – It's nothing to do with you and me.'

Somehow or other he managed to shake some sort of smile at her. Somehow or other he stammered: ‘No – go – on, go on! I want you to tell me.'

‘But, John darling. –'

‘Tell me, Janey!'

‘There's nothing to tell,' she said, wondering. ‘He was one of the first- class passengers. I saw he was very ill when he came on board ... But he seemed to be so much better until yesterday. He had a severe attack in the afternoon – excitement – nervousness, I think, about arriving. And after that he never recovered.'

‘But why didn't the stewardess –'

‘Oh, my dear – the stewardess!' said Janey. ‘What would he have felt? And besides ... he might have wanted to leave a message ... to –'

‘Didn't he?' muttered Hammond. ‘Didn't he say anything?'

‘No, darling, not a word!' She shook her head softly. ‘All the time I was with him he was too weak ... he was too weak even to move a finger ... '

Janey was silent. But her words, so light, so soft, so chill, seemed to hover in the air, to rain into his breast like snow.

The fire had gone red. Now it fell in with a sharp sound and the room was colder. Cold crept up his arms. The room was huge, immense, glittering. It filled his whole world. There was the great blind bed, with his coat flung across it like some headless man saying his prayers. There was the luggage, ready to be carried away again, anywhere, tossed into trains, carted on to boats.

... . He was too weak. He was too weak to move a finger.' And yet he died in Janey's arms. She – who'd never – never once in all these years – never on one single solitary occasion –

No; he mustn't think of it. Madness lay in thinking of it. No, he wouldn't face it. He couldn't stand it. It was too much to bear!

And now Janey touched his tie with her fingers. She pinched the edges of the tie together.

‘You're not – sorry I told you, John darling? It hasn't made you sad? It hasn't spoilt our evening – our being alone together?'

But at that he had to hide his face. He put his face into her bosom and his arms enfolded her.

Spoilt their evening! Spoilt their being alone together! They would never be alone together again.

1.“是下午一点，大人！”

/

因为部长是一个大胖子，且有中风的可能，因此，在通报一桩针对他的严重预谋犯罪的时候，警务处长小心翼翼，以避免引起不必要的激动而导致危险情况发生。看到部长听到他这消息还算平静，甚至还面带微笑，他便又进一步汇报了一些细节：犯罪预计在明天白天部长出发进宫觐见时实施；几个恐怖分子下午一点会持枪弹埋伏在大门口等他出现，但这伙人已经被奸细出卖。目前正密切监视其动向，在这里将会把他们一网打尽。

“等一下，”部长觉得奇怪，“他们从哪儿得到消息说我要在下午一点出门？我自己都是两天前才知道要去觐见！”

警务处长也满是困惑地双手一摊：

“是下午一点，大人。”

部长摇了摇头，不知道是觉得奇怪，还是对警方周密的部署表示赞赏，他肥厚的红嘴唇上浮起一丝忧郁的微笑，这笑容一直停留在脸上。为了不干涉警方接下来的工作，他很快就收拾好了东西，带着妻子和两个孩子一同离开了宅邸。他们借住到一位殷勤好客的皇亲府上，空留一座明天暴徒会聚集的危险房子。

在灯火通明的皇亲家里，熟识的客人们彬彬有礼，不断向部长致意，微笑着表示出他们对此事的愤慨，部长感到了愉悦的亢奋——就仿佛他已经得到或者就要被授予一枚不期而至的硕大勋章。但在客人均已离开，灯火已息的子夜时分，街灯透过镜子般的玻璃反射到天花板上，光怪陆离的影子愈显周围的寂然，这位高官睡在满是绘画和雕像的陌生房子里，形影相吊，自己无事也无聊，不安的思绪便泛滥开来，觉得门闩、警卫和墙壁都不可靠。他睡在冷清、寂寞的别人卧室里，难以抑制的恐惧袭上心头。

他有严重的肾病，一旦过于激动，脸、手和脚就会出现水肿，使他看起来更加肥胖和臃肿。此时，他浑身肥胖的肉犹如小山一般沉甸甸地压在弹簧床上，他满怀着一个病人的郁闷，感觉着这张肿得面目全非的脸，并且一直在不停地想别人给自己预备的残酷结局。他接二连三地回想起不久前发生的恐怖事件，都是往显贵们身上扔炸弹，有的还是比他级别还高的大臣。他们被炸得血肉横飞，脑浆迸出并飞溅到肮脏的砖墙上，连牙齿都炸脱落了。由于这些接二连三的回忆，他觉得这瘫在床上的肥胖病躯已经不是自己的了，似乎已经遭受了炸弹的袭击；他觉得，肩膀上的双臂已经被炸离躯干，牙齿都迸出牙床，脑浆也迸得星星点点到处都是，双腿僵直伸着，脚趾朝上，跟一具死尸一样。为了显示自己还活着，并非一具死尸，他使劲翻身，大声喘气，咳嗽几声，用力压得弹簧床吱嘎作响，不停地把被子弄出窸窸窣窣的声音。为了显示自己还活得很好，根本没死，离死还大老远呢，他在寂静无人的卧室里用低沉的嗓音大喊：

“好样的！好样的！好样的！”

他这是在夸赞密探、警察和卫兵们，他们保卫着他的生命安全，那么及时、那么巧妙地提前告知了他有关暗杀的情报。但是，在他晃动着身体、称赞安保人员并撇着嘴巴勉强挤出笑容嘲讽不走运的恐怖分子时，他仍然不相信自己会获救，不相信生命猝然离去只是假设。别人想要杀死他，尽管那只是想法、只是预谋，但仿佛死亡已经站在这屋子里，在歹徒没有抓到前、在他们手上的炸弹没有被夺下来之前，在他们没有被关进坚固的大牢之前，死亡会一直盘踞此地不会离开。瞧，死亡就站在那个角落里，没有走，也不会走掉——它就像一个服从命令的哨兵，绝不会擅离岗位。

“是下午一点，大人。”这句话以不同语调在他的脑海中时起时落：一会儿是幸灾乐祸的嘲笑，一会儿是怒气冲冲的大叫，一会儿是固执的警告和死板的重复。就好像卧室里摆上了几百台上足了发条的唱机，它们一台接一台地以白痴才有的那种勤奋的傻劲儿，叫喊着预先灌制的这句话：

“是下午一点，大人。”

明天的这个“下午一点”，不久前还和其他钟点没有任何区别，无非就是表盘上的指针沿着刻度盘平缓移动而表示的一个时刻而已，而现在它突然就变成了必然会应验的一个凶兆，它跳出了刻度盘，单独存在，身子竖直，像一根巨大的黑色界标，把全部生活一分为二。仿佛在它之前或者在它之后，世界上从未存在过其他的钟点，只有它这一个钟点，可以放肆和自命不凡地拥有特别存在的权利。

“怎么？你想干什么？”部长气呼呼地小声问。

所有唱机一起大声吼叫：

“是下午一点，大人。”而且，好像屋角的那根黑色界标还冷笑着给他鞠了一个躬。

部长咬牙撑着从床上坐了起来，手掌捂着脸，在这个该死的夜晚，他是不能睡着觉了。

他用肿胀得厉害的手掌捂着脸，特别清晰地想象着一幅画面，即明天早晨他一起床，什么也不知道，就喝上了咖啡，什么也不知道，就在门厅里穿上了外衣。无论是他，还是递给他大衣的看门人，还是给他端咖啡的听差都不知道即将发生的事，他们一干人完全没有料到喝咖啡、穿大衣这等事情都毫无意义，因为就只过了几秒钟，大衣，他的身体，喝进肚里的咖啡，都会被炸弹毁灭、被死神带走。瞧，这个看门人正在打开玻璃大门……他长得可爱、善良又和气，这位长着一双宝蓝色眼睛的士兵，胸前佩戴着一大排军功章，他亲手打开了那扇恐怖的大门，因为他对即将发生的事情一无所知。所有人都微笑着，因为所有人都对即将发生的事情一无所知。

“啊！”他突然大叫一声，把两个手掌从脸上放了下来。他面前是一片黑暗，他紧张地盯着这片黑暗，慢慢地伸出手，摸索到电灯开关，把灯拧亮。然后他站起来，也不穿鞋，光着脚走过地毯，在陌生卧室里走了一圈，找到了壁灯开关，也拧开了壁灯。屋子里亮了，看起来很舒适，只有乱糟糟的床铺摊着一堆被子直拖到地上，表明某种恐惧还未走远。

部长就这样穿着睡衣，胡子也因刚才的辗转反侧而弄得乱蓬蓬的，他的双眼满是愤怒，那模样跟任何一个因失眠和气喘而大动肝火的老头儿毫无二致。好像人们为他准备的死亡把他剥得一丝不挂一样，一下子就失去了原先举手投足间的器宇轩昂和威风凛凛——让人很难相信，现在这样一个人会拥有那样大的权力，这样一个普普通通的人的躯体竟会死得这么惨，会在威力惊人的炸弹的爆炸声中和火光中血肉横飞。他没有穿好衣服，也感觉不到冷，就坐到离自己最近的一把扶手椅上，手捻着蓬乱的胡子，直愣愣盯着别人家的雕花天花板，陷入了无边的沉思中。

原来是这么回事！原来令他这么害怕、这么激动不安的是这个原因！原来是这个原因令死亡盘踞在屋角不肯离去，也不能离去！

“一群蠢货！”他轻蔑地狠狠骂道。

“一群蠢货！”他把头转向门口，又大声地骂了一句，让那些被骂的人听见好了。就在刚才他还称赞那些家伙呢，现在他骂他们为了多余的献殷勤而把密谋行刺的事详细地汇报给他。

“当然就是这么回事啦！”他的思路突然变得顺畅了，“就是他们告诉我暗杀的事了，我知道了，现在才这么害怕，要是我什么都不知道，我不就能安稳地喝咖啡了吗？当然了，喝了咖啡后死神还会来——但难道我这么怕死吗？对，我有肾病，总有一天会死，但什么也不知道的话就不会这么害怕。这帮蠢货非要说，是下午一点，大人。这帮蠢货还以为我听了会高兴，高兴什么呀，倒把死神弄墙角来了，还怎么都轰不走。它不走，是因为我一直在想它。其实可怕的不是死亡本身，而是你知道自己的死期，如果一个人要是准确无误地知道自己的死亡日期和时辰，那他就完全没法儿活了。而这帮蠢货却提前告知说：‘是下午一点，大人！’”

这么一想，他心情立刻轻松愉快了，好像是有谁说他长生不老了一样。他重新觉得自己在那帮蠢货中间是一个强大又聪明的人，不像他们那样毫无意义地窥探未来的秘密，他陷入了饱经沧桑的老人和病后余生之人的那类思绪中，即什么都不知道最好。不要让任何有生命的东西，包括任何人、任何禽兽知道自己的死亡日期和时辰。前不久他病了一场，医生说，他快要死了，应当安排一下后事，他根本不相信，这不也活下来了。年轻时候也有过类似事情：他曾误入歧途，想以自杀结束自己生命。他准备了一把左轮手枪，连遗书都写好了，甚至自杀时间就定在下午一点——但就在最后那一刻，不知为什么他突然改变主意了。总是这样，总是在最后的时刻会有突如其来的、意想不到的情况出现，正因为如此，谁也不能轻易断言自己什么时候会死。

“是下午一点，大人”，那些蠢货讨好地来告知他，是因为死亡的威胁会被排除，然而，他却因为知道了可能的死亡时间而惊恐不已。完全有可能，他某一天会被人杀死，但不会是明天——明天不会发生这一幕、明天不会发生这一幕——要是这样，他就能像一个长生不老的人一样放心上床去睡觉了。可是，这帮蠢货，他们不知道，他们推翻了一个多么伟大的铁律，当他们说出了那句白痴一样的呓语“是下午一点，大人”的时候，他们捅下了一个多大的娄子。

“不，不是下午一点，大人，不知道是什么时候。不知道是什么时候。你说什么？”

“没说什么，”黑暗中有个声音回答，“没说什么。”

“不，你说了。”

“没说什么，小事一桩。我说的是：明天，下午一点。”

顿时一种猝不及防的极度惊恐掠过心头，他明白了，只要这个该死的、跳出了表盘的时辰不过去，他就绝无任何美梦可做了，也不会有什么安宁，更谈不上什么高兴。只要那桩任何有生命的东西都不该提前知道的事还在墙角暗影幢幢，那就足以让人看不见一丝光亮，永远处于恐怖的黑暗中。死亡的恐惧一旦袭来，就会弥漫全身，渗入骨髓，令人失魂落魄，寝食难安。

此刻他害怕的已经不是明天的那些杀人犯了，他们连同他周围数不清的，充满敌意的人和事混在一起，被他忘却了。现在需要担心的是某些遽然来临的和不可避免发生的事情：中风、心力衰竭、某根纤细的血管栓塞溢血导致动脉破裂，就像紧紧绷在肿胀粗大手指上的手套突然绽裂开了一样。

他开始担心自己又短又肥的脖子，看自己肿胀且汗津津的短手指，觉得自己的手难看得要命。如果说，刚才他还在黑暗中不停地翻身以便不像个死尸，那么现在，在明晃晃的、充满冷淡敌意的灯光下，他倒害怕得一动也不敢动了——连按铃叫人给拿支香烟都不敢了。他的神经处于极度紧张之中。每根神经都像是一根金属导线，上方弯曲成一个小脑袋，脑袋上的眼睛惊恐万分地凸鼓出来，口不出声，气喘吁吁，但呼吸不到一点儿空气。

突然间，在天花板布满灰尘和蜘蛛网的昏暗之处，铃声骤然响起。电铃盒里的金属舌片在恐惧氛围中痉挛般地敲击盒壁，停了一小会儿，接着又开始可怕地持续不断地颤动着敲击起来。这是部长大人在他住的卧室里按的电铃。

外面开始有人忙乱地奔跑。各处的枝形吊灯和墙上的壁灯都打开了几盏——照明足够了，但还不是灯火通明，阴影随之投射下来。一时间，天花板上、角落里，都布满了拉得长长的影子，它们闪闪缩缩地掠过每一处隆起的家具，紧贴到墙壁上去。真弄不明白，这些数不清的无声而丑陋的阴影、这些无声无息的幽灵一样的东西，在未开灯前到底所居何处呢。

有人用战战兢兢的声音说了句话，然后就打电话叫医生了：部长病情危笃，已经昏迷，部长的夫人也被请了过来。

2.判处绞刑

/

结果和警方预料的一样。在部长家大门口，四个恐怖分子，三男一女携带定时炸弹和手枪一出现就被当场逮捕，第五个也在租住房子里被抓获，就是这个秘密住所的女主人。在这里还起获了不少的炸药、半成品炸弹和武器。所有嫌疑犯都很年轻：男犯中最大的二十八岁，女犯中最小那个是十九岁。就在关押他们的监狱进行了审判，在那个残酷的年代，这种事总是迅速而草率。

五个人在法庭上都很镇定，面容肃穆，十分沉静，他们对法官的蔑视是如此之深，以至于没有人愿意用不必要的微笑或假装的喜悦来强调他们的勇气。他们的镇定自如隔绝了法庭上其他人凶狠的、充满敌意的目光，使自己的心灵和临死前的痛苦不被任何人窥探到。有时他们拒绝回答问题，有时回答——但都很简短、直白、准确，就好像不是在回答法官的提问，而是在回应统计师要求填写的某种特殊表格一样。有三个人，一个女的和两个男的，说出了自己的真实姓名，另外两个人则拒绝招供自己的真名实姓，所以法官最后也不知道他们姓甚名谁。他们对法庭上所进行的一切都抱有一种病人或者身临大事之人才有的好奇心，既心不在焉又思绪潮涌。如果法庭上有人讲了一句比较有趣的话，那他们就会张望一下，认真听进去，随即就会继续以沉思状回到自己的思绪中。

离法官最近的位置坐着那位报出了自己真实姓名的年轻人——谢尔盖・戈洛温，他是退伍上校的儿子，自己也曾是军官。他还相当年轻，头发浅黄，宽肩膀，身体强壮结实，以至于无论是监禁还是即将来临的死刑都未能抹去他脸颊上的红晕和蓝眼睛里孩子般天真的幸福表情。他一直不停地抚弄自己那两撇小胡子——他对自己的小胡子还不太习惯呢，同时眯着双眼，一直盯着窗外看。

时值暮冬，在暴风雪和阴冷天气交替的时段，春天早已经别奏先声，有时一天都会是阳光灿烂的日子，有时这种好天气也就仅有一小时，但即使短暂，它生机勃勃的气息也令街道上的麻雀快活得发疯，路上行人也十分沉醉。此刻，窗户上落满了去夏以来不曾擦拭的灰尘，透过上端的玻璃可以看到出奇的美丽：乍一看，天空似薄雾朦胧，可往远处看的话，天空开始变蓝，而且越远越蓝、越晶莹、越辽阔。正因为天空并不是全然的一览无余，所以，在透明青烟般的云霭中，它就显得像你爱上的姑娘一样，含羞而立，楚楚动人。谢尔盖・戈洛温仰望着这一小片晴空，轻抚着小胡子，左右变换着眯缝着双眼，若有所思。有那么一小会儿，他甚至弹拨起手指来，高兴而天真地做了一个鬼脸——但环顾了一下四周，刚才高兴的表情就消失得无影无踪了，就像上去一脚踩灭了一点儿火星。几乎就是在瞬间，他的脸色由鲜红变得煞白，露出了死灰色。他从头上狠狠地拔下一根又细又软的头发，用两根没有血色的手指紧紧拈着。但，生命和春天的喜悦是更强大的——只过了几分钟，他那天真无邪的脸庞又恢复了原来生机勃勃的天真表情，他又开始仰望天空了。

同时仰望天空的还有那个不肯供出自己真名实姓的姑娘，她化名叫穆夏。这是一个比戈洛温还年轻的姑娘，有着白皙的皮肤，举止老成持重，一双黑眼睛直率而骄傲。但她那细嫩的脖子和少女的手臂，以及浑身上下同样不可捉摸的青春活力，还有古典乐器般令人惊叹的纯净悦耳的嗓音，都说明着她的年龄。她肤色很白，但不是那种死尸般的惨白，而是一种特别热烈的洁白，就好比是一个人体内燃烧着熊熊烈火，身体发出透明的光亮，像法国的塞夫勒瓷器一样。她几乎一动也不动地坐着，只是偶尔难以察觉地用手指抚摸一下右手中指上深凹的一小圈，这是不久前刚摘下戒指所留的痕迹。她仰望天空时毫无温情，也没有陷入某种愉快的回忆之中，她之所以只望着那里，完全是因为在整个肮脏的监狱法庭里，唯有这一小块蓝色的天空是美丽、干净和真实的——她的眼睛里什么表情也没有。

法官们可怜谢尔盖・戈洛温，却讨厌这姑娘。

穆夏身旁的男子也一动不动地坐着，双手夹在膝盖中间，他也没有报出真名实姓，他的化名是维尔纳。如果假设一个人的脸可以像道大门一样，关紧时可以密不透风的话，那么现在这个无名氏的脸就像是一道关严的大门，还有铁将军把门。他一直盯着脚下肮脏的地板，谁也猜不透他是平静还是一直在激动，是在想心事还是在倾听法庭上密探的陈词。他个子不高，容貌清秀而高贵。一副温文尔雅的长相令人很容易想到南方月夜海边婆娑柏树的身影，但同时，他又会使人觉察到一种巨大的沉着冷静的力量，浑身散发出不可战胜的坚强、冷静和刚毅的英雄气概。他彬彬有礼地回答问题，总是简明扼要，并微微欠身向前，他有一种震撼人心的力量。如果说，囚衣穿在别人身上多少有那么一点儿荒唐的话——这根本不是人穿的——穿在他身上则完全不一样了。从恐怖分子身上搜到了武器和定时炸弹，但在维尔纳的身上只搜到了一把黑色手枪，法官据此就认定他是首犯，对他的态度相当恭敬，规规矩矩地公事公办。

在维尔纳之后受审的是瓦西里・卡希林，他呢，浑身上下充满了难以克制的死亡恐惧，并且无望地竭力控制着自己，不想在法官面前流露出自己的恐惧。从一大早把他们这些人提审到法庭上来时，他就开始心跳加速喘不上气来，他的额头上一直冷汗不断，手上也浸透了冷汗，身上的冷汗更是已经湿透了衬衫，使他难以动弹。他正在以非凡的力量竭力控制手指不哆嗦，抑制说话的声音，让它更坚定、明确，让自己的眼神显得镇静。他看不清自己周围的东西，法官的问话像是从雾霭中穿过似的缥缈，他尽力回答得大声而坚决。但一回答完毕，他就忘记了法官的问话，也忘了自己回答的内容，重新回到与恐惧的默默搏斗中。死亡在他的身上表现得如此明显，以至于法官都刻意不去看他，也很难确定他的年龄，就像无法确定一具死尸的准确年龄一样。根据身份证，他才二十三岁。维尔纳几次用手触碰他的膝盖，他总是回答同一个词：

“没事儿。”

瓦西里・卡希林最怕自己会突然大喊大叫起来，没有话语——而是像野兽一样嚎叫。那时他就会轻轻地碰一下身旁的维尔纳，而这位连眼睛也没抬一下，低声回答：

“没事儿的，瓦夏[1]。很快就结束了。”

一直在为同伴们担惊受怕的是第五位恐怖分子，用她那充满母爱的眼神不住地望着所有同道，她叫丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克。她还没有生过孩子，同谢尔盖・戈洛温一样，年轻的脸蛋绯红，可她却像是这些人的母亲一样：微笑里、眼神中、害怕的表情里，满是关切，满是慈爱。她对法庭视若无睹，就好像与己毫不相干，只是在倾听同伴们对质询的回答：声音是否颤抖、是否过于害怕、是否需要喝水。

在瓦夏受审时，她难过得不敢看他，只是悄悄地捏自己的胖手指。而在穆夏和维尔纳受审时，她就骄傲地钦佩不已地注视着他们，脸色严肃专注，不时地向谢尔盖・戈洛温报以微笑。

“可爱的孩子，正在仰望这天空呢。看吧，看吧，可爱的小鸽子，”她就这样心里想着戈洛温，“哎呀，瓦夏呀？我的天哪，他怎么会这样子呢？我的天哪……我能拿他怎么办呢？说什么呢？说了会更糟糕：万一他哭起来可如何是好呢？”

就像日光潋滟的池塘，能够映射出所有流云的倒影一样，她那丰腴、可爱、善良的脸上反映出另外四个人情感的瞬息万变，思虑的上下浮动。她完全将自己也在受审，将被判处绞刑的这些事置于一边，连想都不去想，漠然处之。就是在她的家里搜查出来的武器和炸药，而且，说起来也奇怪——正是她开枪拒捕并打伤了一个密探。

审讯在八点钟结束，天已经完全黑下来了。穆夏和谢尔盖眼前的蓝色天空暗淡了，但不像夏天天空那样，红霞尽染，笑意迭出，而是渐渐暗下来，渐渐发灰，又突然变成了一副寒冷的冬夜模样。戈洛温叹了一口气，伸了伸腰，又看了两眼窗外，外面已经是漆黑夜色。他抚弄着小胡子，以一种小孩般的好奇心打量起法庭和荷枪的法警，对着丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克微笑了一下。穆夏呢，在天空变暗后，就将目光转到角落里，不是看地下，而是观察被供暖的气流冲压得不停摇曳的一张蜘蛛网，目不转睛直到宣判。

宣判后，被告们就和辩护律师告别，竭力回避律师们因无能为力而深感歉意的怜悯目光，被告们也在门口碰头简单交谈了几句。

“没事的，瓦夏。一切很快都会结束的。”维尔纳说道。

“是啊，老弟，我没事的。”卡希林大声回答，嗓音坚决甚至还挺愉快。

确实，他的脸已经泛起红晕，不再像一具死尸了。

“见他妈的鬼去吧！这帮浑蛋竟敢判我们绞刑。”戈洛温毫无顾忌地大骂起来。

“这是早就应该预料到的。”维尔纳倒是平静。

“明天宣布终审判决，这以后我们就会关押在一起了。”科瓦利丘克安慰大家，“直到行刑前，我们都将在一起。”

穆夏一直没有说话。后来她挺直身体，果断地走到最前面去了。

[1] 瓦西里的小名。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明之外，均为译者注。）

3.“不该绞死我”

/

在审讯恐怖分子的半个月前，在同一个地方的军事法庭，由另一批法官，把一个名叫伊万・扬松的农民判处了绞刑。

这个扬松原本是一个富裕农场主家里的长工，同所有孤苦伶仃的穷雇工没什么区别。他是爱沙尼亚人，出生在维森别格，长大后四处漂泊，从一个农场到另一个农场，靠打短工过活，几年之后来到了首都附近。他俄语说得不行，但雇他的主人却是一个名叫拉扎列夫的俄罗斯人，住处附近没有爱沙尼亚人，所以两年多的时间里，他几乎没怎么说过话。看来，他也是一个不怎么爱说话的人，不仅对人不爱说话，而且对牲口也吝于开口：他就默然无声地饮马、套马，整天无精打采地、慢腾腾地在马棚周围挪着小碎步，要是马都腻烦了他的沉默寡言、跳起来尥蹶子的时候，他就扬起长鞭子默默地、狠狠地抽打它。他一旦打起牲口来就毫不手软，残忍、凶狠、冷酷，而且这种事要是发生在他正好喝得酩酊大醉的时候，那就会下死手猛抽牲口。那时，就是在正屋都能听到呼呼的鞭子声和因剧痛而跺得凌乱的马蹄子声。因为扬松打马，雇主曾打过他，但什么也改变不了，扬松依然故我，无奈只好随他去了。每个月扬松都会大醉那么一两回，通常都是在他送雇主去车站后。那个车站比较大，有一家餐馆，把雇主送到后，他就赶车到离车站半俄里[2]远的地方，把马和雪橇赶进远离路边的雪地里，雪橇和马斜倒在雪堆中，等着火车开走。雪橇歪在路边，而马陷进齐肚子深的雪里，支棱着腿，不时地抻长脖子来舔几口松软的浮雪，而扬松就歪躺在雪橇上，好像是在打盹儿。他头上扣着一顶破皮帽子，上面的毛快掉光了，帽耳没有系好，像猎犬的两只耳朵一般向下耷拉着，冻得通红的小鼻子下淌着湿漉漉的鼻涕。

紧接着，扬松便返回车站的餐馆，喝个大醉而归。

从车站回到农场总共有十俄里路，他简直是策马疾驰。由于不停地被鞭打，马惊恐地扬起四蹄飞奔，扬松连缰绳也不握，雪橇忽左忽右，老是撞上路旁的界碑，人也处于随时要飞出去的危险中。但扬松不以为意，似唱非唱地哼唧着某种爱沙尼亚小曲儿，既不连贯也不清晰。有的路段里扬松就不唱了，而是咬紧牙关，一声不响，怀着一种莫名的痛苦、愤怒和亢奋，瞎子一般抽打着马向前飞奔，看不见迎面走过来的人，看见了也不管，拐弯和下坡时也不放慢疯狂飞驰的速度。在野蛮的驾驶中，他没轧着别人，自己也没摔死——这真是不可思议。

很早就应该把他解雇，就像他在别的地方被撵走一样，但他要的工钱便宜，别的雇工也好不到哪儿去，所以他在这里干了两年。扬松的生活里没有什么大事。有一次他收到一封信，是用爱沙尼亚文写的，可他一个大字不识，别人也不懂爱沙尼亚文，所以这封信一直没读过。扬松弄不懂这封信给他带来了家乡的什么消息，就像没开化的野蛮人那样，冷漠地把信扔到粪堆里去了。扬松试着对厨娘献过殷勤，看得出来，他想女人了，但没得手，只招来了粗暴的拒绝和一顿奚落：嫌他个子小，身子骨弱，还一脸雀斑，说他总是睡眼惺忪的小绿眼睛浑浊得啥也看不清。扬松对这次碰钉子倒不大在乎，后来也就不再去纠缠厨娘了。

扬松虽然不怎么说话，却时刻在倾听着什么。他听白雪覆盖在荒凉的田野上的动静，听白雪覆盖着的鼓得像坟包一样的粪堆的动静，听着柔和的蓝色的远方的动静，听着风声掠过电线杆，听人们的谈话声。田野和电线杆子能告诉他什么，只有他一个人知道，而人们的谈话则令人不安，充斥着凶杀、抢劫和纵火等流言。有一天夜里，他听到邻村小教堂的钟声像小铃铛一样叮当地响个不停，接着火焰就冲上了天：原来不知从哪里来了一伙人抢劫了一家富户，打死了主人和他的妻子，把他们家放火烧了。

于是这边农场里的人也都惶惶不安起来：不仅是在夜里，就是白天也把狗放出来看家，夜里主人枪不离身。他本来想把一支旧的单筒猎枪交到扬松手上以备不时之需，但扬松掂了掂枪，摇了摇头，不知为什么拒绝了。主人不明白他为什么不要，就骂了他一顿，而扬松拒绝的原因，是他认为自己那把芬兰刀比这生锈了的旧家伙好使多了。

“我拿它只会把自己打死。”扬松还是用他那睡眼惺忪的目光望着主人说。

主人只好无可奈何地挥了挥手：“伊万，你这家伙真是个傻瓜蛋。跟这样的雇工过日子也真糟心。”

就是这个连枪都不相信的伊万・扬松在一个冬天的夜晚，在另一个雇工被派到车站去的时候，犯下了一桩集持刀抢劫、凶杀和强奸的极其复杂的刑事罪。他倒是做得干脆利落：先是把厨娘反锁在厨房，然后装出一副睡眼惺忪、困倦已极的样子，走到男主人背后，特别迅速地在背上猛戳了两刀，男主人立刻失去了知觉，倒在了地上，女主人方寸大乱，尖叫不已，扬松龇牙咧嘴地举着刀开始翻箱倒柜。出乎了他自己的预料，在找到钱后，就像是突然发现了团团乱转的女主人一样，他猛地扑向女主人，想要强奸她。但是因为他把刀子放到一旁了，女主人力气比他大，反倒差点把他掐死。这时昏倒在地的男主人醒过来了，厨娘也抄了炉钩子开始拼命地砸厨房的门，扬松就跑到外面去了。过了一小时，正当扬松蹲在仓房角落里一根接一根地划火柴意欲纵火时，他被当场抓住。

过了几天，男主人因伤口感染破伤风死了，而扬松和其他一批抢劫犯、杀人犯一起受审，并且被判处绞刑。在法庭上他还是依然故我的样子：又瘦又小，满脸雀斑，永远睡眼惺忪，好像完全不明白所发生事情的严重性，所以也满不在乎：扑闪着白睫毛，傻呆呆地张望着从没来过的庄严大堂，用粗糙、僵直的手指抠着鼻屎。只有每逢礼拜天在教堂见过他的人才知道，他也多少拾掇了一下：脖子上围了一条脏兮兮的红围巾，头发用水抿了抿；用水抿到的头发黑且平整，没有抿到的头发就稀稀拉拉地翘着，就像冰雹砸过的地里面仅剩的几根麦秸杆。

当宣布判决结果为绞刑的时候，扬松突然激动起来。他的脸涨得通红，来来回回地撕扯红围巾，就像围巾勒得他上不来气一样。然后他又无措地挥舞着双手，用手指头指着那个刚才宣读判决的法官，对没有宣读判决的另一个法官说：

“她说，她要把我绞死。”

“‘她’是谁？”刚读完判决的法官用浑厚的低音问道。

法庭上所有人都笑了，有人低头笑，有人用卷宗掩住嘴，而扬松伸出食指对着问话的法官，生气地说：

“就是你！”

“啊？”

扬松又把目光投向另一个竭力忍住笑的法官，他觉得这个人是他的朋友，和判决毫不相干，就对着这个人又说了一遍：

“她说的，要绞死我。不该绞死我。”

“把被告带下去。”

可扬松还是明确地、大声地重复了一遍：

“不该绞死我。”

他那想装成庄重的样子和他的愤怒小脸、伸得僵直的手指更显其愚不可言，以至于连押送他的士兵都忍不住违反了规则，小声对他说：

“唉，你这小伙儿，真是个傻瓜！”

“不该绞死我。”扬松固执地重复着。

“要是我有幸去吊死你，保管教你连腿都来不及蹬一下。”

“好了好了，少说两句！”另一个押送士兵生气地嚷嚷起来。但他自己也憋不住说，“谁让你当强盗了！你这傻瓜，你没弄死人吗？现在只能给你上绞索了。”

“你说，会赦免他吗？”第一个押送士兵有点儿可怜扬松了。

“怎么可能！怎么会赦免这种人呢……算了，说太多了。”

这时候扬松倒不说话了。他又被押回坐了一个多月的牢房，他对这间牢房已经习惯了，就像习惯所有事情一样：习惯挨打、习惯喝酒、习惯白雪覆盖的田野、习惯那上面满是圆圆坟包一样的粪堆。现在看到自己的床、自己的栅栏小窗和送来的囚饭——从早上起他还粒米未进，他甚至感到有点儿快乐。只有刚才在法庭上发生的一幕让他不太高兴，但他不懂得应该怎么去想，也不会去思考这些。至于用绞刑把人吊死，他完全不能想象。

尽管扬松被判处绞刑，但像他这样的犯人很多，他都算不上是监狱里的要犯，因此别人跟他谈话都没什么禁忌，也不会像对那些未定死罪的犯人一样有敌意。大家好像没有把他的死当成一回事。看守得知已经对他进行了判决，就用教训的口气跟他说话：

“怎么样？老弟，到底还是给你判了绞刑吧！”

“那啥时候绞死我呢？”扬松半信半疑地问人家。

看守想了一下。

“老弟呀，这你可得等等呢。怎么也得凑成一批才行。哪能光为你一个人行刑，况且你又是个糊涂蛋，哪里值得兴师动众。这种事可需要场面。”

“到底啥时候呢？”扬松固执地问。

对光为他一个人连个绞刑都不能办理这说法，扬松没感到屈辱，他也不相信这种说法有道理，而且，认定这只是一个拖延刑期的借口，最后应该会取消对他的判决。他立刻高兴起来：那个既模糊又可怕的时刻，那个想都不能想的时刻被推得远远的了，就像任何一种死法一样，变得神秘而不用去想了。

“老问啥时候，啥时候！”看守生气了，这是个古板、阴郁的老头子，“这可不是绞死一条狗，拉到棚子外面，找绳子一勒就得了。傻蛋，你就巴不得像狗一样报销掉吧！”

“我可不愿意那样！”扬松做了一个鬼脸，挺高兴地说，“这是她说的，应该把我绞死，我可不愿意！”

可能这是有生以来第一次，扬松大笑起来，笑声怪里怪气，愚蠢至极，但却相当快活和高兴。就像一只大鹅在“嘎——嘎——嘎”地叫着。看守吃惊地望着他，然后严厉地皱起了眉头：在他看来，一个被判处了绞刑的人开心大笑是荒唐的，是对监狱和死刑的极大不敬，把监狱和死刑都变成荒诞不经的事情了。于是，出现了那么一个瞬间，一个很短的瞬间，这个在监狱里度过了全部人生的老看守，这个默认监狱法则为自然法则的老看守，突然就觉得这里像是一个疯人院，而且，他，这个看守，才是这里的头号老疯子。

“呸，你这死鬼！”他吐了口唾沫，“干吗张牙舞爪地号叫，这又不是酒馆！”

“我可不愿意死啊！嘎——嘎——嘎！”扬松大笑不已。

“你这魔鬼！”看守一边骂，一边画着十字。

其实这个长了一张松弛小脸的人最不像魔鬼了，但是在他的嘎嘎怪笑声中有某种对监狱的牢固性和神圣性危害不已的东西。他再这么笑下去，这监狱的烂墙就会坍塌，潮湿的铁栅栏就会脱落，看守就会自动把囚犯送出大铁门……“先生们，请去城里溜达一圈吧，你们有人想去乡下兜个风吗？”真是个魔鬼呀！

但这会儿扬松已经不再笑了，只是恶魔一般地眯着眼睛。

“瞧，难怪会这样！”看守没有再威胁他，转身走了，一边走还一边回头看他。

整个晚上扬松都很平静、愉快。他自言自语、反复说他已经说过的话，“我不该被绞死”。在他看来，这句话是令人信服的、有智慧的、不容辩驳的，根本不值得去担心任何事了。他早就忘了自己犯罪这件事了，只是有时会遗憾没能强奸成女主人。不过，这事也很快就被忘得一干二净了。

每天早上扬松都要问，什么时候把他绞死；每天早上看守都没好气地回答：“你这魔鬼，别急，老实等着吧！”

由于天天都重复这个对话，由于每天的开始、经过和结束与寻常的日子毫无两样，扬松就更加确信，不会有把他绞死这个事了。他很快就忘记了法庭上的判决，开始整天在床上大睡特睡，迷迷糊糊地做着白日梦，梦到荒凉的有粪堆的田野覆盖着白雪，梦到火车站前的酒馆，还有许许多多更遥远更开心的事情。监狱里伙食尚可，很快，就几天的工夫，他就胖了，看上去气色不错。

“要是搁到现在，她说不定会爱上我呢，”他想起了女主人，“现在我胖了，不比主人差啥。”

只是他太想喝伏特加了，就想猛喝猛喝然后赶着马飞奔。

当一批恐怖分子被逮捕的消息传到监狱后，看守再回答扬松的问题就相当粗野并且完全出乎扬松的意料了：

“这下可快了。”

看守一字一顿地、居高临下地说：

“这下可快了。我觉得，也就一个星期的事儿啦。”

扬松的脸立刻就白了，两只浑浊的眼睛目光呆滞，一副失神的样子，他问道：

“你开玩笑吧？”

“你不是都等不及了吗，还开啥玩笑。我们这里可不兴开这种玩笑。你喜欢开玩笑，我们可不兴开玩笑。”看守一本正经地说完就走了。

一天下来扬松就瘦脱了人形。入狱这一段时间以来他胖了，皮肤光滑了，现在突然间有了很多皱纹，有的地方皮肤也下垂了。眼睛更浑浊了，行动起来呆板迟缓，好像动一动头部，动一动手指，迈一迈步子，都成了相当复杂的需要深思熟虑的头等大事。夜里，他躺在床上，合不上眼睛，直到早上仍然睡眼惺忪地睁着。

“啊哈！”看守早上一看到他就得意地说，“我说得对吧，老弟，这可不是小酒馆。”

看守这得意仿佛就像是一个学者再次验证了自己的实验结果一样，他从头到脚再次认真仔细地打量了犯人一番：现在一切都进入正轨了。魔鬼的报应来了，监狱和死刑的正当性再度确立，为了表示宽容，这老看守探问起犯人：

“有没有想会见的什么人呢？”

“为什么要会见？”

“嗨，告别呀。比如见一见母亲或者兄弟。”

“不应该绞死我，”扬松小声说，乜斜着眼睛看了看守一眼，“我可不想被绞死。”

看守看了看他，啥也没说，挥了挥手走掉了。

傍晚，扬松的心情平静一些了。这一天相当平常，冬天的天空里云雾缭绕，走廊里仍然充斥着脚步声和例行公事的谈话声，酸白菜汤像以往一样散发出怪味，这一天太平常，以至于扬松又停止相信面临死刑这回事了。但一到了夜里，扬松又开始害怕了。从前他觉得夜里就是黑暗而已，上床睡觉就行了。但现在他却感到夜晚有一种既神秘又令人恐惧的本质。为了不去相信面临的死亡，就需要听到和看到周围寻常的东西：比如脚步声、谈话声、光亮、酸白菜汤，而现在一切都不同寻常，这种寂静、这种黑暗，这本身就已经是死亡了。

而且夜越是深沉，恐惧就越是强烈。扬松像原始人或者小孩子一样天真，总是认为一切都是人力可为的，他特别想对太阳大叫一声：你快天亮吧！他心里恳求、哀告太阳快点升起来，但黑夜还在大地上拖延自己那黑暗的时刻，没有什么力量能够阻止它的蔓延。扬松笨拙的大脑第一次意识到了这个不可能，他感到了巨大的恐惧。尽管他还不敢明确地这样想，但他已经感到面临的死亡不可避免了，他的一只将死的脚已经踏上了断头台的第一级台阶。

白天的到来又安慰了他，他不去想死亡的事了，可一到夜晚，他又怕得要死，就这样，直到行刑的前三天夜里，他终于意识到和感觉到，死亡是不可避免的了，再过三天，一过黎明，太阳一升起来，他就要被绞死了。

他从未想过死亡这回事，也不知道死亡是咋回事——但现在他明确地感觉到、看到、触摸到了，死亡正在走进他的牢房，正在用手摩挲他。为了逃命，他在牢房里拼命跑了起来。

可是，牢房相当狭小，四个角落都不是直角，而是钝角，他就总是好像被推到屋子中央一样，无处可藏。门是上了锁的。天又亮了。有好几次他用身体去撞墙壁，又一次撞到了门上——那声音喑哑又空洞。后来不知又撞到了哪里，他就脸朝下跌倒了，顿时感到被死神抓住了。他趴在地上，肚子紧紧地贴在地上，一边使劲把脸往又黑又脏的沥青地面里藏，一边惊骇地号叫起来。他就趴在那里拼命地号哭，直到有人进来。大家把他拖起来，放到床上，劈头给他浇上凉水，可是扬松仍然紧闭双眼，一直不敢睁开。刚睁开一只眼，看到空荡荡有光亮的角落或者是看到了一只空靴子，他就又大声号叫起来。

但是，凉水开始起作用了。再加上看守就是那个老头子，为了让他清醒过来，照他头上就敲了几下子。于是，活人才有的感觉赶跑了死神，扬松睁开了眼睛，剩下来的后半夜他也就昏头涨脑地睡过去了。他仰着脸，大张着嘴，忽高忽低地打着很响的呼噜。微微张着的眼睛的缝隙中不见瞳孔，只有眼白，特别像死人的眼睛。

自这以后，无论是白天还是黑夜，无论是脚步声还是谈话声，无论是酸白菜汤味还是别的，都让他感到无所不在的恐怖，把他逼进了一种无可比拟的原始人状态中。他贫乏的思想力使其无法连接两种对立的矛盾概念：一种是普通的白天，散发着酸白菜汤的气味，一种是再过那么一两天他必须去死。他什么也不想，甚至也不去算时间，只是惊恐地默默站在这一对矛盾面前，任凭这矛盾把他的脑子分成两半。他脸色变白了，但没有失去血色，也没有潮红，就是一副平静的样子。但不吃什么饭了，也不睡觉了，整夜都缩着双腿，坐在凳子上，或者悄无声息地东张西望，在牢房里环视左右地走来走去。

看到他变成这副样子，从牢房的监视小窗往里面看的看守们都兴味索然，不再注意他了。这是死囚正常的状态，据看守说——当然啦，他本人也从来没有这方面的经验——一头牲口在被人用斧子劈开头部进行宰杀前都是这副样子。

“现在他已经吓傻了，从现在起一直到死他什么感觉也都没有了。”看守用有经验者的眼光盯着他，喊他，“喂！伊万，你听得到我在叫你吗？啊，伊万？”

“不应该绞死我。”扬松无精打采，答非所问地说了这么一句，下颌又耷拉下来，没声了。

“你要是不杀人就不会绞死你了。”监狱长不忘教训他，虽然这人很年轻，但胸前却佩戴着勋章，很神气，“你杀了人，还想不上绞架啊。”

“想杀人不偿命？真是蠢到家了，还挺狡猾。”

“我不想被绞死。”扬松说。

“你不想就不想呗，亲爱的，咋想是你自己的事，”监狱长冷酷地说，“最好少说点蠢话，处理一下自己的财物。不管怎么说，总还有点什么要收拾的吧。”

“他啥也没有。他只有一件衬衫外加一条裤衩，还有一顶破皮帽子。就是个败家子！”

时间就这样过去了，已经到了星期四。这天午夜十二点钟，许多人拥进了扬松的牢房，其中一个戴肩章的人开口说道：“喂，收拾东西，该上路了。”

扬松的动作还是那么慢慢腾腾、无精打采，把他所有的衣服都穿上了，围上了那条脏兮兮的红围巾。戴肩章的先生抽着烟，一边看着他穿衣服，一边对身旁的人说：

“今天天儿不错，很暖和。完全到了春天了。”

扬松仍然一副睡眼惺忪的样子，他像睡着了一样，动作迟缓，看守就朝他吼叫：

“喂，快点，你睡着了吗！”

“我不想死。”他有气无力地说。

这些人抓住他的肩膀，架着他就走了，他耸着双肩，顺从地挪动着脚步。进到院子里后，一股潮湿空气袭来，他鼻子下边又湿漉漉的了。虽然是在半夜里，冰雪解冻得更快，附近有水滴不断落下来，滴在石头上，声音清晰可闻。卫兵们先是弯腰进入暗黑的囚车里，佩刀发出叮当的响声，扬松等着上车，懒洋洋地用手指去蹭鼻子下边滑溜溜的鼻涕，还拉了拉没有系好的围巾。

[2] 1俄里约等于1千米。——编者注

4.我们，奥勒尔省人

/

也是在同一个地方军事法庭，同一批法官还审理了另一个案子，将一名奥勒尔省叶列茨县的农民判处了绞刑。他叫米哈伊尔・戈卢别茨，他是鞑靼人，有个外号叫米什卡・茨冈诺克。经查明，他最后一次作案是打死三人和持枪抢劫，而他的黑暗过去简直是一个谜团。有迹象表明，他曾经卷入了一系列抢劫和杀人案，一看他就是一个杀人放火、酗酒滋事的惯犯。他倒坦诚，直截了当地管自己叫强盗，对那些明明就是打劫却还时髦地打着“杀富济贫”旗号的土匪不屑一顾。他的最后一次犯罪，由于铁证如山无法抵赖，他也就痛快地承认了所有细节，但一问到他过去的行径，他就龇着牙吹口哨：

“都是些没影儿的事！”

当审讯人员步步紧逼的时候，茨冈诺克就会摆出一本正经的样子，大言不惭：

“我们所有奥勒尔省的人都是提着头闯荡出来的爷们儿，”他慢条斯理，不卑不亢地说，“奥勒尔人和科罗马人是头号的窃贼。卡拉乔夫人和里文人让所有小偷甘拜下风。叶列茨人呢，那就是各路小偷的鼻祖。这还有什么弄不明白的呢！”

他就是因为长相和窃贼的好手法才被叫茨冈诺克[3]。他身材瘦小，顶着一头黑得出奇的密发，脸上是鞑靼人特有的高颧骨，两块烧伤的黄疤痕像是装饰物。眼睛像是马眼睛一样总是翻着眼白，显出一副急不可耐的样子。他看人的时候目光停留时间很短，但毫无顾忌，充满好奇心，他看任何东西都像是把那东西的某一部分弄走了，把它变成了另外一件东西一样。他要是看一眼香烟，香烟就仿佛被别人放在嘴唇之间抽过一样，谁也不愿意再拿起来抽了。在他的身体里好像有某种永不安宁的东西，一会儿像火一样需要藏匿起来，一会儿像一捆向四处迸发火星的柴捆。倒也是，他口渴的时候，像一匹马一样，能喝好几桶水呢。

对法庭上向他提出的问题，他都跳起来，回答得简洁、坚决，很配合的样子：

“是的！”

有时候他还会强调一下：

“是的，没错！”

法庭上一提到别的案子，他就会出乎意料地站起来请求审判长：

“请让我吹个口哨再说！”

“这又是为什么？”庭长惊讶地问。

“他们不是招供说，是我给同伙打了暗号嘛，那就来一下，很好玩。”

庭长也有点儿疑惑，就同意了。茨冈诺克立刻将左右手各两根手指一起放进嘴里，双眼暴凸。死气沉沉的审判大厅里响起了野蛮的、真正强盗才有的呼哨声，这一声呼哨能立刻让马后腿直立、人脸失色。这是人之将死的哀愁，这是杀人者野蛮的狂喜，这是恐怖的警告，这是呼号，这是阴雨之夜的黑暗，这是孤独。这声尖锐的、非人非兽的号叫里包含着一切。

庭长大叫一声，抬手制止了茨冈诺克，他也就顺从地停下来了。这时他像一个刚刚唱完拿手咏叹调的演员一样，坐下来，开始用衣服擦那四根湿漉漉的手指，还颇为自得地环顾审判大厅里别人的反应。

“真是强盗！”一个法官揉着耳朵说道。

但另一个法官却笑着，不以为意，他眼睛和茨冈诺克的鞑靼人眼睛一样，却留着俄式的大胡子，一直越过茨冈诺克的头部，出神望着厅堂的高处。

“确实挺有趣。”

就这样，法官们冷静地、毫无怜悯之心地、深觉良心无愧地判了茨冈诺克死刑。

“判得好！”法官刚一读完判决书，茨冈诺克就说，“在旷野摆上一副绞刑架，判得好！”

说完，就转过身，对押解他的士兵来了一句：

“喂，窝囊废，咱们走吧。枪可抓紧点——小心我把它夺下来！”

士兵大气不敢出，提心吊胆地看着他，和同伴交换了一下眼色，手放在扳机上。另一个士兵也同样戒备起来。回监狱这一路上，两个士兵简直不是在走路，而是如履薄冰，穿云踏雾。他们全神贯注地监视犯人，丝毫感觉不到他们脚下踩的土地，既忘了时间，也忘了自己。

和扬松一样，米什卡・茨冈诺克死刑前也不得不在监狱度过十七天。这十七天对他来说，快得就像是一天——因为他想的都是怎么越狱逃跑，怎么自由自在，怎么活着。茨冈诺克天性不安宁，现在被禁锢在高墙之内，坐在铁栅栏里，在不见天日的小窗下幽闭，使他愤懑不已，怒火中烧，像一块煤被扔在了旺火上。像极了喝醉了酒的时刻，许许多多迷乱的想法和鲜明的印象混合在一起，像不可遏制的旋风，忽明忽暗地从心底刮过，汇聚成一个念头——越狱逃跑，出去自在，好好活着。茨冈诺克有时候一连几小时，都像一匹马那样抻长脖子，翕动着鼻孔闻来嗅去——他觉得空气里有一股大麻的味道，有失火时的呛人的烟味，还有刺鼻的煳味；有时候，他像陀螺一样在牢房里打转，快速地用手摸一摸墙壁，敲几下，用目光打量和估测天花板和栅栏，想着把这些一股脑儿锯断。在监视孔里一直监视他的士兵，看他一刻不得安宁地折腾，有好几次威胁他说再不老实要开枪了。茨冈诺克可不害怕，总是反唇相讥。事情之所以没闹大，到头来相安无事，就是因为这种拌嘴很快能变成普通庄稼汉们满嘴脏话却并不伤人的常见阵势，为这种事就开枪既荒谬又没必要。

夜里茨冈诺克睡得很沉，几乎都不翻身，就保持一个不变的姿势，但也算睡姿生动，犹如一根暂时不动的弹簧。但只要一起床，他就立即开始满屋子打转，思来想去，摸来摸去。他的双手又干又热，但心里却不时生出凉意，就像胸口被塞进去了一块硬冰块，把他激得浑身上下打冷战。原本就皮肤黝黑的茨冈诺克现在更黑了，身上出现了铸铁才有的青黑色。现在他有了一个奇怪的习惯：就像吃了特别多的甜腻食物一样，他不停地舔嘴唇，吧嗒嘴，吐唾沫，总是一口就啐到地上。说话也不连贯起来，想法接二连三，舌头跟不上趟儿了。

有一次，白天的时候，监狱长在卫兵的陪同下进到了他的囚室。见到满地吐得脏乱不堪，就板着脸说：

“瞧你把这里吐得这么脏！”

茨冈诺克立刻反唇相讥：

“你这头肥猪把地球都弄脏了，我还没有骂你呢。你钻到这里来干吗？”

监狱长依然板着脸，提出让他当刽子手。茨冈诺克龇着牙，哈哈大笑起来。

“嗯哼，找不到人了？太好玩了！你们判绞刑，判绞刑，哈哈！脖子在、绳子有，没人帮你们吊起来。我的天啊，太好玩了！”

“你干了就能活命。”

“哼，那还用你说。我成了死人还哪能帮你绞死别人。你这傻瓜，净瞎说！”

“你怎么想的？对你来说，现在干什么不都一样吗？”

“你们这里怎么把人绞死？大概就悄悄弄死拉倒吧。”

“才不是，还奏乐呢。”监狱长没好气地说。

“还真是头蠢猪。当然，应当奏乐。那就来吧。”茨冈诺克开始唱一支雄壮的曲子。

“那么，亲爱的，你答应了？”监狱长说，“爽快点说吧。”

茨冈诺克龇了龇牙，说道：

“瞧把你急的！你下次来时，我再告诉你吧。”

在茨冈诺克许许多多迷乱的想法和鲜明的印象混合的大脑中，终于出现了一个新想法：当个穿大红袍子的刽子手也挺不错的呀。在他的头脑中越来越清晰地闪现出一个人头攒动的广场，断头台已经高高竖起，他，茨冈诺克，身穿大红袍子，手执一柄大斧子，逍遥地在周围踱步。太阳照射着人们的脑袋，日光在铮亮的大斧子上闪烁，一切都令人心满意足，连那个就要被砍头的家伙都在微笑。人群之后有许多的四轮大车和马脸——那是从乡下进城的庄稼汉在看热闹，远处就是田野。

“呸！”茨冈诺克抿了抿嘴唇，把满口唾沫啐到地上。

突然间，就像是有人把他的皮帽子一把拉到嘴边一样，他感到又黑又闷，那块不化的冰又开始让他浑身打起冷战。

监狱长又来过两次，茨冈诺克也总是龇着牙说：

“瞧把你急的。下次来再说。”

终于有一天，看守对着监视小窗，匆匆地对他大声喊道：

“你错过了大好机会了，装腔的家伙！人家找到别人了！”

“那去你妈的吧！你自己去绞吧。”茨冈诺克回骂了一句，也就断了当刽子手的念想。

后来，离行刑时间越近，茨冈诺克的脑子就越乱，那些迷乱想法和鲜明印象令他难以忍受。他已经不想走来走去了，他想就叉开双腿，停止活动。但脑子里的想法就像极速流淌的激流一样推动着他，他抓不住任何东西，眼前的一切都在动态地流淌。他也开始睡不好觉了，总是做梦。这些梦就犹如乡下涂满色彩的短木头，既清晰又沉重，这些梦境比他的思想转换得还快。这已经不是一股激流，而是从万丈高山上倾泻而下的瀑布，掠过整个万花筒般的世界。在没被逮捕前，茨冈诺克蓄着相当时髦的小胡子，入狱后，却长出了又黑又硬的络腮胡子，这使他看上去特别吓人，好像是一个疯子。有的时候，他也确实疯疯癫癫地在牢房里转圈，一副神志不清的样子，但即使这样，茨冈诺克也不忘去摸摸粗糙的泥灰墙。当然喝起水来还是像马一样狂饮。

有一天，已是黄昏时分，茨冈诺克趴在牢房的地上，像狼一样地哀嚎起来，声音令人胆寒。他特别起劲地嚎叫，就像在干一件必须完成的大事。他先是提一口气，然后慢慢地把这种特别发颤的嚎叫持续下来，他一边嚎叫，一边眯着眼睛调整气息。那来自嗓子眼的颤声似乎是精心设计出来的：他不是在胡乱地叫喊，而是仔细地发出这野兽嚎哭的每个声调，令其有说不出的恐怖和哀伤。

后来，嚎哭突然停下了，他就趴在地上也没动弹，沉默了有几分钟。蓦然间，他对着地面慢声细语地喃喃起来：

“老兄们哪，亲爱的老兄们……可怜可怜我吧……老兄们！可爱的老兄们哪！”

而且就好像要倾听一下效果如何一样，每说一个词，就停顿一下。

后来，他就跳起来了——脏话连篇地骂了整整一个钟头，气都不喘一下。

“你们这帮浑蛋，都他妈的给我滚！”他两眼充血，大声咆哮，“绞死就绞死，别他妈的这样拖着……哼，你们都他妈的是浑蛋……”

看守他的士兵吓得够呛，脸色发白，又难过又害怕，就用枪戳牢门，无助地往里喊话：

“我要开枪了！天哪，再喊我真开枪了！你听见了没有！”

但是他不敢开枪，除非发生真正的暴动，是不允许对判死刑的犯人开枪的。茨冈诺克咬牙切齿地痛骂着，唾沫星子横飞——他的大脑被放在荒谬的生与死的尖锐的分界线上，像一块风干的泥巴，被分割得七零八落。

当夜幕降临时，许多人来到牢房，准备押他去行刑。这时他好像活过来了，又忙碌起来。他觉得嘴里更腥甜了，唾沫越来越多，但面颊变得红润了，眼睛里又出现了以前那种狡黠的神情。穿好衣服后，他就问提刑官：

“那么，是谁来绞死我呢？是个新手吗？手脚不利索可不行。”

“这事可不用你来操心。”提刑官面无表情地说。

“大人，我怎么能不操心呢，要被绞死的是我，而不是您。您别心疼，可得往绞索上多抹点肥皂哇。”

“行了，行了，你可别说话了。”

“不然的话，所有的肥皂都得被他贪了，”茨冈诺克指着监狱长说，“你看他肥头大耳的。”

“住嘴！”

“这下不心疼肥皂了吧！”

茨冈诺克哈哈大笑起来，但嘴里更甜了，突然就觉得腿部很奇怪地僵硬了。尽管如此，走到院子里时，他还是大声地喊了一嗓子：

“快把孟加拉伯爵的马车赶过来，接我上阵！”

[3] 即茨冈人（吉卜赛人）的意思。

5.吻一下就行——别说话

/

对五名恐怖分子的终审判决在宣判当天就获得核准。虽然没有通知被告行刑的时间，但按照惯例，他们也知道，当天夜里，或最迟第二天夜里，他们就会被绞死。当他们被告知，第二天，也就是周四可以会见亲属的时候，他们明白了，绞刑将在星期五的黎明时分进行。

丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克没什么近亲，远亲都住在偏僻的小俄罗斯[4]，也未必知道她受审和即将被处以绞刑的事；穆夏和维尔纳连自己的真名实姓都不说，当然也就更不会通知哪些亲属前来；只有谢尔盖・戈洛温和瓦西里・卡希林有可以会见的亲属。然而，他们两个一想到这次会面，就感到十分害怕，特别伤心难过，但还是不能狠下心来拒绝见自家老人最后一面，与他们做最后的道别，最后的拥吻。

谢尔盖・戈洛温为即将到来的会见痛苦不已。他很爱自己的父母亲，就在不久前还和他们朝夕相处，而现在却害怕见他们——天知道事情是怎样走到这一步的。绞刑本身不寻常且荒谬，会使人受到惊吓且失去理智，但只是想象它，就要来得容易些，它也就不见得有那么可怕，但与亲属会见的几分钟是短暂且混沌的，是完全超出时间，超出生活本身。看什么、想什么、说什么，人类的大脑无法想象这一切。平常最普通的也最常见的动作——拉起父亲的手，亲吻，说一句“你好哇，父亲”——在这个时刻简直是不可思议的荒唐行为，是极不人道和虚伪做作的表现了。

丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克以为判决后他们会被关在一起，实则不然，他们都被单独关押了。整个上午，直到十一点父母到来前，谢尔盖・戈洛温都在单人牢房里烦躁不安地走来走去，把小胡子揪得一缕缕，皱着眉头自言自语。有时会猛地站住，深深地吸上一口气，就像一个在深海里潜水的人需要换气一样。然而，他是一个十分健康的人，年轻的生命包含精力，即使这一刻心灵饱受折磨，他的脸颊仍是红润的，一双淡蓝色的眼睛仍然是明亮和纯洁的。

会见的过程比谢尔盖想象的要好得多。

最先走进会见室的是谢尔盖的父亲，尼古拉・谢尔盖耶维奇・戈洛温，他是一位已退休的上校。他浑身上下皆白，脸，胡子，头发，手，都是雪白的，就像穿衣服的雪人一样。他还穿着制服，是旧的，但熨烫得很平整，散发出汽油味，双肩上佩戴着肩章。父亲坚定、庄重、步履矫健地走进来。他把白皙但干瘦的手伸出来，声音洪亮地说：

“你好哇，谢尔盖！”

母亲迈着碎步子跟着进来，特别不自然地微笑着。但也握了儿子的手，同样大声说：

“你好，谢廖扎[5]！”

母亲吻了吻儿子的嘴唇，就默默地坐了下来。出乎谢尔盖预料，母亲既没有悲伤地扑上来拥抱，也没有撕心裂肺地大哭大叫，更没有什么可怕的举动，只是那么亲了一下就默默地坐下了。甚至还用那双哆嗦的双手整理了一下穿的黑色丝绸连衣裙。

谢尔盖根本不知道，昨天一整夜，上校把自己关在书房里，苦思冥想才确定了这么个仪式。“我们在这最后的时刻，不应该增加儿子的精神痛苦，而是要尽量减轻他的心理负担。”上校定下了这个方案，并仔细斟酌了明天交谈时可能说的每句话、每个动作。但有时弄混了或者漏说了想说的某一句，上校就倒在书房一角的长沙发上伤心地啜泣好一会儿。第二天一大早，他就向老伴讲了一遍，在会见中应该注意哪些举止。

“最要紧的在于一开始，吻一下就行——别说话！”他教了老伴儿一遍，“然后，过一会儿你再说话，但吻儿子的时候，先别说话。不要在吻了后立刻说话，明白了吗？否则会很不得体。”

“我明白的，尼古拉・谢尔盖耶维奇。”老伴儿哭着回答他。

“而且你一定不要哭。千万不能哭哇！老太婆，你要是一哭，就等于要了他的命啊！”

“那你自己不是也在哭吗？”

“这不陪你哭吗！见面时不要哭，听见了吗？”

“好的，尼古拉・谢尔盖耶维奇。”

上校本来想着在马车上他再叮嘱一遍老伴儿，但自己却忘记了。就这样，他们一路沉默着，两个白发苍苍的老人，弯腰驼背地想着心事，而身外的整个城市都在喧嚣着，一片祥和气氛。时值谢肉节[6]，街上熙熙攘攘，人来人往。

三口人都坐下了。上校以惯常的姿势，左手按住制服的前襟，准备说话。谢尔盖刚一坐下，抬眼看到对面母亲那张满是皱纹的脸，立即又站起来了。

“坐下吧，谢廖扎。”母亲恳求他。

“你坐下，谢尔盖。”父亲也附和母亲道。

大家都默不作声。母亲不自然地微笑了一下。

“我们一直在努力营救你，谢廖扎。”

“好妈妈，那不可能了……”

上校坚决地说：

“这是我们应该做的，谢尔盖，这样你会知道，父母不会抛下你。”

又是一阵沉默。三个人都害怕说话，仿佛话一到嘴边就会失去该有的意义，而变成死亡的同义词了。谢尔盖瞥了一眼父亲身上穿的旧制服干干净净，仍旧散发出汽油味，心想：“现在他也没有勤务兵了，肯定是他自己熨烫干净的。怎么以前我从没有发现他能做这种事？大概，一早起来就干这事了。”所以下意识地，突然他就开口了：

“妹妹怎么样？她还好吗？”

“尼诺奇卡到现在还什么也不知道呢。”母亲赶紧接上话。

但上校严厉地制止了这个话头：

“为什么撒谎？小姑娘都在报纸上读到了这个消息。要让谢尔盖知道，所有的亲人，在这种时候……也都挂念着……”

他说不下去了，就立刻停住了。母亲的脸立时皱成一团，悲苦地颤动起来，泪水瞬间也流了下来。她失神地瞪着双眼，呼吸越来越急促，声音也提高了。

“谢……谢廖……谢……”她重复着单音，哆嗦着嘴唇怎么也张不开口了。

“好妈妈！”

上校朝前走了一步，他全身，包括制服上的饰物、脸上的皱纹，都在颤抖，他自己都未必知道，他的脸有多么惨白，他以一种绝望的镇定对妻子说：

“别说话！不要折磨他！不要折磨！不要折磨！他都要死了！不要折磨！”

妻子吓得不再作声了，而他却还紧握着拳头，一字一句地说：

“不要折磨！”

然后，后退了一步，把胸口紧攥着的手放下，竭力以一副镇静的样子，翕动着两片惨白的嘴唇，大声地问儿子：

“什么时候？”

“明天早上。”儿子也咬着惨白的双唇回答。

母亲眼睛朝下，努着嘴，仿佛什么也没听见。就这样努着嘴，后来，脱口说了一句既简单又和儿子那句一样奇怪的话：

“尼诺奇卡让我代她吻你一下，谢廖扎。”

“你也代我吻她。”谢尔盖回答道。

“好的。还有赫斯托夫一家都问你好。”

“哪个赫斯托夫家？啊，知道了。”

上校打断了他们：

“好了，该走了。起来吧，他母亲，走吧。”

两个人一起把瘫软无力的母亲扶起来了。

“告别吧！”上校命令道，“画个十字给儿子祝福。”

她照做了。但是，在画十字和吻儿子这会儿，她又摇着头，语无伦次地说道：

“不是的，不该这样。不对呀，不该这样。叫我今后怎么办？我该怎么说？不对，不该这样。”

“再见，谢尔盖！”父亲说。

两个人用力地握手并互相亲吻了一下。

“你……”谢尔盖欲说什么。

“什么？”父亲问不成句了。

“不是的，不该这样。不对呀，不该这样。我该怎么说？”母亲一直摇着头，执拗地重复着。她已经又坐下了，全身不住地抖。

“你……”谢尔盖又开口道。

突然间，谢尔盖像小孩子一样，皱着眉头，眼里全是泪水。他站得很近，就透过眼帘的泪珠，看到父亲惨白的脸上也挂满了泪水。

“你，父亲，你是个好人。”

“你这孩子！说这些干什么呀！”上校惊诧不已。

就这样猛然地，他瘫倒在儿子的肩上。本来他比谢尔盖个头高，现在却变矮了，哽咽着把他那干枯蓬乱的头靠在儿子肩膀上。两个人互相亲吻起来，谢尔盖亲吻的是父亲乱蓬蓬的白发，而父亲则亲吻着儿子的囚服。

“那我呢？”突然一个特别大的声音响了起来。

他们就转过头，发现母亲昂头站着，气愤地，甚至有点恨恨地望着他俩。

“你怎么啦？母亲？”

“我怎么啦？”她摇着头，任性地说，“你们男人倒亲上了，啊？那我呢？我呢？”

“好妈妈！”谢尔盖就转身扑向了母亲怀抱。

此情此景无须任何，也没有任何语言能够传达。

上校最后说的是：

“谢廖扎，祝你慷慨赴死！要像一个军官那样无畏！”

他们就这样走了。最终只能走了。就在刚才还站在这里，说着话——突然就走了。母亲刚刚就坐在这里，父亲站在那里——突然间就都走了。回到牢房的谢尔盖，倒在床上，脸朝里，不让看守士兵发现他一直在哭。哭累了就面带泪痕地沉睡过去了。

来看望瓦西里・卡希林的只有母亲一人——他的父亲是一名富商，不愿意来。瓦西里将母亲迎进来后，就一直在地上踱步，尽管天气暖和，甚至有点儿热，但他一直冷得直打战。他们的交谈既简短又令人心情沉重。

“妈妈，您其实不该来的。这只能让您和我难受呀。”

“瓦夏，怎么这样说！你为何要干出这种事呢！天哪！”

老太太大声哭了起来，不时用羊毛头巾边来擦拭眼泪。瓦西里和几个兄弟经常对什么都不懂的母亲大喊大叫，养成了习惯，所以现在，他就停住了脚步，打着寒战，生气地大叫起来：

“又来了！我早就知道会这样！妈妈，你啥也不懂！啥也不懂还非要说！”

“行了，行了。好吧，不说。你怎么啦，冷吗？”

“是冷……”瓦西里打断了她，又开始踱步，不高兴地看着妈妈。

“是不是感冒了？”

“哎呀，妈妈，都这时候了，还什么感不感冒……”

他绝望地挥了挥手。老太太本来想说“家里的老头子让我周一就开始做馅儿饼”，但被儿子的话吓到，赶紧改口说：

“我和你爸说了，怎么说也是自己儿子，去看一眼，就当宽恕了。他不干哪，这个倔老头子！”

“见他的鬼去吧！对我来说他算什么父亲！他一辈子都是个恶棍，现在也是。”

“瓦夏呀！不能这样说自己父亲呀！”老太太责备儿子。

“就要说他！”

“他可是你亲生父亲！”

“我才不认他。”

这一幕没什么亲情也相当荒唐。死亡近在眼前，但说的都是空洞无聊的小事，说出来的话就像脚下踩着空的核桃壳一样，毫无意义。整个一生中，瓦西里和自己的亲人都不能互相理解，就像他们之间有一堵墙那样厚的隔阂，所以现在，在死亡即将来临的时刻，他伤心、郁闷地几乎要哭出声了，他蛮横地瞪着一双小眼睛，冲着母亲大喊大叫：

“我都要被绞死了，你懂不懂！绞死！懂没懂？要被绞死了！”

“你要是没去惹这些人，能这样吗……”老太太也喊道。

“天哪！这话说的！简直连禽兽都不如了！我还是你们儿子吗？”

他大哭起来，一屁股坐在了墙角。老太太也坐在自己这一头哭。就是在这一刻，两个无助的人也无法互相交融爱的情感，也无法对抗即将到来的死亡的恐怖。他们各自冰冷冷地孤独地哭着，心里没有感到一点儿温暖。母亲哭着抢白儿子：

“你倒是说说，我还是不是你的母亲，你就知道说我。这些天我头发都愁白了，变成老太婆了。你还是说我、埋怨我！”

“哎呀，好了，好了，妈妈，原谅我吧。你该走了，代我亲吻兄弟们。”

“难道我不是你母亲？难道我不难过吗？”

老太太终于走了。她伤心不已地哭着走了，不停地用头巾一角擦着眼泪，但她泪眼模糊，根本看不清路。离开监狱越远，她的眼泪就越是灼热。她想返回监狱去，但是却糊里糊涂地在这座自己出生、长大乃至老去的城市里迷了路。她误入了一个只有几棵枯树的小破公园，坐到融有雪水的长凳上。如梦方醒地意识到：明天儿子要被绞死了。

老太太一下子跳起来，想跑出去，可突如其来的头晕使她滑倒了。小路上冰雪交融，特别滑，老太太怎么也爬不起来。先是用胳膊肘支着，又双腿跪下，结果又摔了个仰面朝天。黑头巾从头上滑落，露出沾满污泥的后脑勺。她忽然觉得，这是在给儿子娶亲的婚礼上，她在喝酒，而且已经完全喝醉了。

“我不能再喝了。快别倒了，我不能再喝了！”她一边不停地说，一边摇晃着头。她在冰雪泥泞的路面上爬，而大家还在给她斟酒，所有人都来斟酒。

由于喝多了蜂蜜酒，吃了太多的好东西，看跳舞也看累了，她的心痛了起来。而大家也还一个劲儿地给她倒酒。所有人都来倒酒。

[4] 指乌克兰。

[5] 谢尔盖的小名。——编者注

[6] 又称“送冬节”，俄罗斯族的传统节日。在东正教大斋期即将到来之前的一周尽情吃肉喝酒，“谢肉节”也因此而得名。——编者注

6.时间在流逝

/

被宣判的恐怖分子都被关押在一座城堡里，那里的钟楼上有一座年代久远的自鸣钟。每隔十五分钟、半小时，以及一小时，一种单调且凄凉的钟声就回荡在高空，像是南迁的候鸟离开时那既遥远又悲伤的鸣叫声。白天，这古怪又悲伤的音乐湮没在城市的喧嚣声里，无闻于监狱外人来人往的街巷中。电车驶过，叮当作响，马车驶来，蹄声嘚嘚，汽车行驶在不平的路上，老远就开始鸣笛，尤其是正赶上过谢肉节的时候，农民们陆续从郊外赶车过来，他们那些小马驹的脖子上都挂着铛铛作响的小铃铛。四处人声鼎沸，开心过节的人多少都有点儿微醺，大声喧哗着。早春里融化的雪水滴答不停，街道的积水被踩得啪啪作响，街心公园里突然变绿的树木好像也在那里拔节歌唱。海上吹来阵阵湿润温暖的劲风，似乎用眼睛就可以看到它们卷着一团团的水汽飞舞向前，向无垠的自由的远方飘飞而去。

入夜，街道上沉寂下来了，瓦数颇大的街灯闪耀着孤寂光线。于是，这座极大的监狱连同它那平滑的外墙就陷入了毫无光亮、毫无声响的一片黑暗和寂静之中，它盘踞于此，黑暗将它和生机一片、流动不息的城市截然分割开来。只有这时，自鸣钟的报时声才清晰可闻，那与尘世完全格格不入的缓慢而悲伤的旋律开始不断地响起和湮灭。当它再度响起的时候，就不像是准确报时，而是以前的回声，悲伤迟缓，中断了一小会儿，再度响起。就像是大颗透明的玻璃珠子，从高处落入刻有时间标记的金属刻度盘里。犹如南迁的鸟儿在啼鸣。

关押在单身牢房里的犯人，无论白天还是黑夜，能听到的只有这个报时钟的声音。这种声响穿透了牢狱的屋顶和厚厚的石墙，打破了寂静，泯然消失，然后再悄然而至。有时候，犯人们忘了这声响，以至于充耳不闻；有时候，却又受不了牢房里的寂然无声，焦急地盼着有个声响，希望它一声接一声地响下去。这座监狱是用来关押重刑犯的，这里的狱规特别严厉、冷酷和死板，跟这城堡钝厚的墙角是一个样子的。若要说到这种冷酷之中还有什么宽容的话，那就无疑是死一般的无边寂静了，它庄严不已，能衬托出衣物的窸窣声和人轻微的呼吸声。

就是在这种庄严的与世隔绝的寂静中，在悲伤的钟声里，在流逝的时光中，五个人，两女三男，在等待着黑夜的降临、黎明的到来，等待着死刑的临近。他们每个人都按各自的方式有所准备。

7.死亡是不存在的

/

丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克生来就只关心别人，从不想着自己，即使到了现在也是如此，她仍在为别人难过，为别人而倍加痛苦。她越是对面临的死亡毫无痛苦之感，就越能感受到死亡对谢尔盖・戈洛温，对穆夏，对其他人来说，有多么地残忍，至于她自己，则仿佛和死亡毫无关系一样。

在法庭上，她不得不表现得异常坚定，但就像是一种补偿一样，回到牢房，她能一连哭上好几个小时，就像那些饱受苦痛的老年妇女和充满同情心的少女一样大放悲声。她一想到，谢尔盖可能弄不到烟抽，维尔纳可能喝不到习以为常的浓茶，而这些事都发生在他们行将赴死的时候，这就让她更加难过，可能，这比死刑本身更让她痛不欲生。死刑——这已经是某种不可避免之事了，是一件不值得再去想的身外之事了，而一个坐牢的人，在死刑之前弄不到一根烟抽抽的话，简直是不可忍受的。她逐一回忆起他们共同生活时的种种细节，一想到谢尔盖即将和父母见面的情形，她惊骇得几乎无法呼吸。

她特别怜惜穆夏。她早就觉得，穆夏爱上了维尔纳，尽管实际上并非如此，她还是希望他们两个人最终会幸福美满。入狱前，穆夏手上戴着一枚银戒指，上面刻有骷髅头，下面交叉着两根骨头和一顶环绕着的受难荆冠[7]，这是必然遭难的象征，丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克经常揪心地看着这枚戒指，经常半真半假地请求穆夏别戴了。

“把它送给我吧。”她请求穆夏。

“不，丹涅琪卡[8]，我不送给你。你手指上会戴上另一枚戒指的。”

不知为什么，大家都一致认定，她很快会嫁人，这使她生气，她可不想要什么丈夫。现在一想起和穆夏说的那些半真半假的玩笑，想到穆夏现在真的要蒙难牺牲了，她心头就涌上一种母性的怜悯，不禁失声痛哭起来。只有听到钟鸣声，她才会抬起满是泪痕的脸，倾听起来，心里想着牢房里的那几个人，想他们是如何忍受这近似于死亡一般沉重的固执的呼号声。

可在这个时候穆夏却感到很幸福。

她背着双手，不紧不慢地在牢房里踱步，囚服穿在她身上，让她看上去完全像一个男人，像一个穿了别人衣服的半大小子那样奇怪。囚服的袖子太长，她卷起了袖子，这样她那细瘦得像小孩子似的胳膊，麻秆一样露在袖筒外，像一茎单花插在粗陋、肮脏的水罐里。细嫩的白脖子被粗硬的囚服摩擦得生疼，她总不时地拉一拉领口，轻轻地摩挲一下红肿发痒部位的皮肤。

穆夏踱来踱去——她在想象中向众人表白自己的心迹，激动得涨红了脸。她想表白的是：她是一个渺小的年轻姑娘，所做的事情很少，完全不是什么英雄，配不上这种光荣和美好的死法，在她之前，只有英雄和真正的受难者才有资格被判绞刑。她坚信，人们都是善良的，富有同情心的，有爱的，她认为现在大家都在为她的遭遇而激动不安，为她难过痛心，惋惜不已，当然，她也感到羞愧不已，脸都红了。就是，她怎么能担得起死在绞刑架上的荣誉呢。

在最后一次会面时，她向自己的辩护人要求给她弄些毒药来，但突然间醒悟过来了：如果他和其他人认为她出于卖弄或者怯懦呢？如果本来想谦逊地不引人注目地死去却招来更大轰动，怎么办？所以，她说完就赶紧改口：

“算了，其实，也用不上。”

此时，她只想一件事：要向人们讲清楚并证明给他们看，她不是英雄，死亡根本不可怕，大家不用可怜她，也不用为她操心。要给大家解释，她完全没有想过作为一个年轻姑娘会这样去死，没想到，因为她会引起这样大的轰动，这完全不是她的错。

作为一个被控有罪的人，穆夏也想找一个理由，证明她的牺牲是物有所值，提升自己牺牲的意义，她这样想道：

“当然，像我这样的年纪很轻的姑娘是应该活很久的。可是……”

她的青春时代和生活就像是晴空万里的太阳所遇到的烛光，微不足道，暗淡不已，应该是伟大的、辉煌的东升之旭日照亮了她这颗平庸的头脑。她本人哪能配得上这英雄般的荣耀呢。

但，也许她心里一直有一种特别的东西——无限的爱、无限的建功立业的决心、无限的自我献身精神也配得上这种荣耀？毕竟她没有做到她想做的一切，就将被绞死在神圣的殿堂之外的祭坛上，这不是她的错。

可是，事情如果是这样的，即一个人的价值不在于他做成了什么，而在于他想做什么的话，那么……那么，她是有资格得到这顶受难者的荆冠的。

“真是这样吗？”穆夏羞愧地想着，“我真的有资格吗？我真的有资格让人们为我哭泣和难受吗？就为我这样一个年纪轻轻微不足道的女孩子？”

想到这里，她浑身充满喜悦之情。毫不怀疑、毫无迟疑地，她就这样进入了一个自由的国度，她合理地被接纳为圣人——那些自古以来经历了火刑柱、酷刑和死刑的升天者的行列中的一员。他们的面前是清明的世界，充满了宁静无边的、流光溢彩的幸福。她已经完全从尘世飞升至包含了真理和生命的神秘的太阳国度，沐浴在其熠熠华光之中。

“这就已经是死了。死有什么了不得的呢？”穆夏怡然自得地想着。

要是全世界的学者、哲学家和刽子手在这个时候都能汇聚到穆夏的牢房里面来，在她的面前摆上书籍、手术刀、斧子和绞索，开始向她证明，死亡是存在的，人是会死的，也能够被打死，永生不死是不可能的，那么，他们的话肯定会让她吃惊的。她明明是没有死的，怎么还会死呢？现在谈论死亡已经毫无意义了，谈论不死也同样丧失了意义，因为她现在的状态是虽死犹生，虽生犹死，还有什么可谈的呢？

要是这时候，有人把装殓着她腐烂尸体的棺材抬进她的牢房，让整个牢房臭气熏天，并且对她说：

“快看吧，这就是你！”

她会看一眼就回答：

“不，这不是我。”

要是人们向她证明，这散发着腐臭味的尸体就是她的话——就是她！穆夏也准会笑着回答：

“不是。你们认为这是我，但这可不是。我是正在和你们说话的人哪，这怎么可能是我呢？”

“但是你就要死了，就要变成这个样子了。”

“不，我是不会死的。”

“会把你绞死的。你看，绞索就在这里。”

“他们会绞死我，但我不会死。我已经获得了永生，怎么还有死呢？”

于是，学者、哲学家和刽子手都认输了，他们颤抖着说：

“不要碰这个地方，这个地方是一块神圣之地。”

穆夏还幻想了些什么呢？她想了很多——对她来说，死亡还没有割断她的生命之线，这根线还在平静缓慢地缠绕着她。她想到了自己的同志们，想到了那些为他们即将被绞死而痛苦不堪的远方的同志，也想到了和自己同赴断头台的同伴们。最让她吃惊的是瓦西里竟然会怕得要命——从前他可是很勇敢的，还老是拿死亡开玩笑。就在星期二的早晨，同志们一起往瓦西里的腰上捆绑爆破炸弹，预计会在几小时之后，连同他们一起炸死，丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克紧张得双手一直在颤抖，只好让她退到一旁去，而瓦西里就在这个时候还开玩笑，像小丑一样耍活宝呢，他那满不在乎的样子使维尔纳不得不严肃地提醒他：

“可不能拿死亡当儿戏呢。”

为什么他现在害怕起来了呢？这种莫名的害怕对穆夏来说太难以理解了，所以她很快就不再去想瓦西里了，不愿再去探究他害怕的原因。这会儿，她突然非常想见谢尔盖・戈洛温，想和他谈笑风生。她还特别强烈地想见到维尔纳，想说服他某一件事呢。于是，她想象着，维尔纳和她正在并肩行走的情景，他的步伐均匀，稳当，每走一步鞋都陷在泥土里，而自己正在滔滔不绝地跟他说话呢：

“不，维尔纳，亲爱的，你行刺的行动成功与否，都无所谓，根本是不值一提的。你是一个聪明人，但是，你只是把行刺当成是下棋，你吃掉了一个棋子，然后再吃掉另一个，就赢了这盘棋。维尔纳，这里最重要的事情是我们一心赴死。你明白吗？你知道那些老爷们儿在想什么吗？他们认为没有比死更可怕的事情了。他们自己想出来了死亡这档子事。他们自己害怕死亡，也拿死亡吓唬我们。我甚至想这样去死：一个人站到一个团的士兵面前，举起勃朗宁手枪向他们开火。我只有一个人，他们却有上千人，我可能连一个都不会打死的。这件事的重要性在于，他们有几千人，人多势众。当几千人要打死一个人的时候，那么，胜利的是这一个人。这是真理，维尔纳，亲爱的。”

这样一个观点是如此清晰，以至于她不想再进一步论证了，可能现在维尔纳自己也明白了。也许，她并不愿意让她的思想只停留在这件事情上——她的思绪就像是轻盈翱翔的小鸟，瞭望着广袤的地平线，巡视着整个四通八达的空间，享受着其间所有的深奥、所有的喜悦、所有的亲切和温柔。钟声不间断地鸣响着，不时地打破清冷的寂静，她的思绪与这个和谐、悠长而美好的声响融汇在一起，也在她的头脑中开始鸣响，那些轻盈的小鸟形象都变成了音乐。穆夏仿佛在暗夜里驾着马车，沿着宽阔平坦的大道驶向某地，坐垫上柔软的弹簧上下颤动，铃铛一路高歌响个不停。所有的激动和不安都烟消云散了，倦怠的身体也仿佛在黑暗中融化，懒洋洋的思绪平静地创造出了一系列的形象，她就陶醉在这些形象的绚烂的色彩和安宁的形态之中。穆夏还想到了不久以前被处以绞刑的三位同志，回想起他们开朗的脸庞，以前见到他们时的喜悦——甚至比与他们生前的见面更觉亲切。就像一个人早上就高兴地想着，晚上要到自己朋友家去，想着怎样向朋友问好，怎样笑眯眯地跨进门去。

穆夏走得已经很累了。她小心翼翼地躺倒在床上，继续微合双眼，继续自己的幻想和憧憬。钟声不间断地鸣响着，不时地打破清冷的寂静，就在这鸣响的波段中，一群欢乐地歌唱的形象在游动。穆夏想：

“难道这就是死吗？我的天哪，死亡真是太美了！也许，这是生吧？我不知道，我不知道。我再看一看，再听一听……”

已经很久了，从被捕的第一天起，穆夏就开始幻听。她的耳朵对音乐很敏感，由于寂静这个听觉就更敏锐了。监狱中声音原本不多，走廊看守的脚步声、钟声、风过屋顶的簌簌声、路灯的晃动声对她来说构成了完整的乐章。一开始，穆夏害怕这些声响，病态般地极力避免去听它们，后来，她明白了，她自己很健康，也没有什么病，所以开始平静地沉浸在这些声响中了。

现在，她突然清楚无误地听到了军乐声。她惊讶地睁开了双眼，抬起头——窗外依然黑夜沉沉，报时的钟声在鸣响。“又是钟声在响啊！”这样想着就平静地又合上了双眼。可是，刚合上眼皮，军乐声又响了。她清楚地听到，从大楼的右侧拐角处，整整一个团的士兵正在从窗户旁走过去。脚步整齐划一地按着“一——二！一——二！”的口令跺在上了冰的硬地上，甚至还能听到皮鞋吱吱的声音，其中夹杂着有人突然脚下一滑，又赶紧跟上大家步伐的忙乱声。音乐越来越近了：这是一首从未听过的乐曲，但是非常洪亮，是一首异常欢乐的节日进行曲。看样子，监狱里有什么庆典仪式吧。

军乐队正好走到窗下了，整个牢房里充满了节奏明快的、和谐激昂的乐曲声。一个大铜号明显是吹跑调了，没跟上整个乐队的节拍，一会儿超前，一会儿落后——穆夏就像看到了吹号的士兵那紧张地调整节奏时的面部表情，直想笑。

乐队和音乐声都渐渐走远了。听不见“一——二！一——二！”的口令声和脚步声了。远远地听着那军乐声更觉悠扬和激昂。大铜号又跑了一两次调，后来就什么也听不见了。只有钟楼上传来的缓慢而悲伤的钟声勉强打破了再度降临的寂静。

“都走了。”穆夏怀着淡淡的哀愁想道。她还对那远去的乐曲声有点儿不舍，那军乐声听上去那么欢乐，还滑稽可笑，她甚至舍不得那个走远的使劲吹大铜号的士兵，那些大头皮鞋吱吱的声音。他们是完全另外一些人，不同于她想用勃朗宁手枪打死的那些人。

“啊，回来吧！”她温柔地恳求。那些幻像又回来了。它们向她俯下身子，像透明的云彩一样围绕着她，托着她直上云霄，那里鸟儿们盘旋着，啼鸣着，就像是天庭里的传令使者。它们上下翻飞，左右盘旋，像传令使者那样口吐莲花。它们的鸣叫声是对她的欢迎，也是向远处宣布她的到来。它们挥动着宽阔的翅膀，能接住黑暗，也能托起光明。它们前凸的胸脯划破了空气，以一片蓝色之光映照出地面上的城市。穆夏的心跳越来越均匀，呼吸也越来越平静和安宁。她睡着了。脸色苍白，略显疲倦，眼睛下方的眼袋已经很明显，少女的手臂纤细而瘦弱，嘴唇上还挂着微笑。明天，太阳升起的时候，这张人脸就会变成丑陋的死人脸，脑子就会浸泡在黏稠的黑血之中，眼球会突出眼眶，但今天，她睡得很安静，面带微笑，就睡在自己伟大的永生中。

穆夏睡着了。

监狱生活有自己的那一套，这种生活死气沉沉，毫无目的，却又是十分警觉的，它本身对人来说，就是一种永恒的不安。有的地方，犯人在走动；有的地方，看守们窃窃私语；有的地方，武器叮当作响。似乎有人在竭力呼喊，又仿佛并没有人叫喊——只不过是寂静引起的幻听而已。

这时门上的监视孔无声无息地被打开了——黑洞的小口里出现了一张黢黑的、胡子拉碴的脸。这个人瞪大了眼睛惊奇地看了穆夏好一会儿，然后又像出现时一样，无声地消失不见了。

报时钟铛铛地鸣响着——缓慢而悲伤。这疲倦的钟声犹如正在深更半夜爬向一座高山一般，越爬越艰难，越爬越沉重吃力。突然，钟声断掉了，就像从半山间滑脱下来，呻吟着一路向下而来，重新艰难地爬回自己黑暗的钟楼里。

有的地方，犯人在走动；有的地方，守卫们窃窃私语，有人把马套在黑黢黢没点上车灯的马车上了。

[7] 荆冠是基督教徒纪念耶稣苦难的标记。——编者注

[8] 丹妮雅的昵称。

8.有死，也有生

/

谢尔盖・戈洛温从未想到过死，这仿佛就像是别人的事，与他自己毫不相干，无须去想一样。他是一个强壮、健康、快乐的小伙子，生就一副安然且活泼的脾气，一切与生活有害和无益的思想及类似感觉在他身上都不会停留，会很快消失殆尽。在他的身上，任何割开的小口子及针孔，都会很快愈合，所有伤心难过的事情他都很少外露，他很快就会整理好心情。无论做什么事，他都会以这种安然且活泼的认真劲儿来做：一切都是兴致勃勃地做，一切都认真地做，一切都需要做到更好，娱乐消遣如此，照相如此，学骑自行车如此，准备恐怖暗杀行动也如此。

他也确实一切都做得很好：划船很会掌舵，射击特别有准头，对待友情敦厚，对待爱情忠贞，对别人的“保证”抱以诚信的态度。自己人都笑话他，说如果一个一望即知的密探，或者一个明显是间谍的人赌咒发誓说，他不是密探，谢尔盖也会相信人家，与人家同志般地握手。他只有一个缺点：认为自己唱歌好听，但是实际上，他一点儿乐感也没有，他唱歌难听得要命，一唱就跑调，唱革命歌曲也是如此。大家要是笑话他的歌声，他还觉得委屈呢。

“要么你们全是叫驴，要么只有我是一头叫驴。”他较真儿了，特别委屈地说。大家也较真儿了，考虑了一下，一起坚定地表态：

“从听到的嗓音来看，只有你是一头叫驴。”

但因为这个缺点，他更招大家的喜欢，因为有时候和相当不错的人交往，比起所谓优点，人们更喜欢他的缺点。

他就因为不怕死，所以根本就不去想死亡这回事，在那个致命的早晨，在离开丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克家的时候，只有他一个人像往常一样，胃口奇好地吃着早餐，喝了两杯兑了牛奶的浓茶，吃了一个大面包，五个戈比才能买一个呢。然后，忧心忡忡地看了一眼维尔纳根本没动的面包，说：

“你怎么不吃呢？吃吧，吃了才有劲儿呢。”

“吃不下。”

“那我可吃了，行不？”

“嗯，吃吧，谢尔盖，你的胃口真好。”

谢尔盖顾不上说话，一口吞下面包，一边嚼，一边呜啦呜啦跑着调，又唱上了：

“在我们的头上敌人的仇恨在飘荡……”

被捕后，他有点儿沮丧——任务完成得不好，失败了。但他是这样想的：“现在已经有了另外一件事，需要做得更好——那就是去死。”他又振奋起来。所以，看起来很奇怪，被押到古堡监狱的第二天早上，他就开始做体操了，那体操是一个叫穆勒的德国人发明的，编排十分合理，谢尔盖相当喜欢这套体操。他脱光衣服，做完了整套规定的十八个动作，这让不安监视着他的看守大为惊奇。看得出来，发现看守在监视他的时候，谢尔盖特别高兴，就像他是一个穆勒体操理念的宣传者一样。尽管也知道得不到回应，他还是对着门上监视孔里的那只眼睛说道：

“老弟，这套体操可好呢。你们团里要是引进这体操就好了。”他觉得，看守肯定以为他是个疯子，所以为了不吓到看守，他说得恳切又温和。

他是逐渐地感到对死亡的恐惧的，而且这种感觉具有阵发性的特点，就像是有人从下面抓住了他的心脏，用拳头使劲地往上面击打。比起恐惧害怕，他更能感觉到心痛。然后这种感觉会消失——但过几小时之后，又会重新出现，每一次再出现，都会比先前那一阵的感觉更持久，也更强烈。他就这样开始明显地感觉到某种说不清道不明但又巨大且难以忍受的恐惧。

“难道我害怕了吗？”谢尔盖吃惊地想道，“这可真是太愚蠢了！”

不是他害怕了，而是他的肉体害怕了，无论是做德国人穆勒发明的体操，还是用冷水擦洗身体，他那年轻、强壮、精力充沛的躯体是任何细微的东西也无法隐瞒住的。每次冷水浴后，他越是感到强壮、精力充沛，就越能感受到那瞬间出现的恐惧是多么地剧烈，多么地不可忍受。也正是每当早晨来临，当他感受到浑身元气满满、精力充沛的时候，在睡了一个好觉、做了早操的时候，这种刺心的、对他来说十分陌生的恐惧感就出现了。他发现了这一情况，不由得想道：

“谢尔盖老弟，这可太愚蠢了。为了死得轻松一点儿，应该弱化它，不应该强化它呀。太愚蠢了吧！”

所以，他停止了做操，也不再用冷水擦拭身体，他还向卫兵解释，为这套体操说好话：

“你别看我不再做操了。老弟，这套体操是相当好的东西呢。就是对被判了绞刑的人已经不太适合了，对别的其他人呢，是非常有好处的。”

不做那些令身体知觉常新的事情之后，果然感觉轻松了一些。他又尝试着减少进食量，以便进一步让身体弱下来，但是，这可不太容易做到，尽管牢房里缺乏新鲜空气，他也不再做操耗费体力，但胃口仍然好得出奇，他总是把送来的东西全部吃得精光。后来他开始尝试其他办法：在开始吃饭前，他就把一半的饭菜倒进马桶。这倒是挺有效果。其后他的症状就只剩下无精打采、昏昏欲睡了。

“我要让你尝尝我的厉害！”他警告自己的身体，却忧心忡忡地用手摩挲日渐无力且变软的肌肉。

但是身体很快就适应了这一变化，死亡的恐惧再度出现了。确实，不那么强烈，也不那么难以忍受了，但是更缠磨人，更让人恶心，总是让人想要呕吐。“可能这是死刑拖得太久的缘故，”谢尔盖想，“要是在死刑执行之前一直都是睡着的状态就好了。”于是，他就尽可能地尽情地睡觉。一开始嘛，效果不错，但是后来，也许是睡多了，也许是由于别的原因，他开始失眠。这一失眠，想的就更多，那些想法既强烈又敏锐，使得他更加留恋起生命来了。

“难道我还怕这个魔鬼不成？”他想的是死亡，“我是舍不得生命啊。生命是那么美好的东西，管他悲观主义者说什么呢。如果把一个悲观主义者送上绞刑架呢？哎呀，就是生命太可惜了，太可惜了呀。我为什么不停地长胡子呢？以前一直不长，怎么也不长，却这时候突然长成大胡子了。这是为什么呢？”

他面色忧郁地摇了摇头，心情沉重地长长地叹息了几声。接着沉默了一会儿，然后又开始长时间地、沉重地叹息，再接下来还是沉默不语——之后重新开始更长时间的、更沉重的叹息。

就这样，直到庭审之前，直到和父母亲那次可怕的见面之前，他都是在唉声叹气中度过的。当他在牢房中醒来，清楚地意识到生命就要终结，再过毫无意义的几小时，死亡就会到来的时候，他开始感到恐惧了。他觉得就像是有人把他的一切都拿走了，不仅是扒光了他的衣服，而且还挪走了太阳、空气、声响、亮光，以至于他的行为和语言都丧失殆尽了。还没有死呢，但是命已经没了，还有的只是一种新的东西，一种令人震惊的、难以理解的东西，这种东西既不能说没有意义，也不好说其有什么意义，但，这是一种深奥的、神秘的、非人的东西，想弄明白它是不可能的。

“呸，真是见鬼了！”谢尔盖备受折磨又十分疑惑，“这到底是怎么回事呢？我到底是在什么地方呀？我……怎么变成这样子了呢？”

他开始饶有兴致地认真打量起自己了，先是看脚上那双大号的囚靴，再看鼓鼓囊囊的肚子，囚服被撑得贴在肚皮上面。然后一边在牢房里穿行，一边张开双手，继续观察自己，就像是一个刚穿上一件下摆过长的新连衣裙的女人一样。因为谢尔盖不停地摆动脑袋，所以很快就转得头晕目眩了。不知道为什么，他感到十分恐惧，因为这个不停地转来转去的人就是他，谢尔盖・戈洛温，而且这个人很快就会死了。一切都变得那么奇怪，不可思议了。

他尝试着在牢房里走动——连走路也变得奇怪了。他又坐下——坐着也变得奇怪了。他又试着去喝了一口水——喝水也变得奇怪，水就莫名其妙地被吞下去了。手里还拿着杯子——拿着杯子的手指更奇怪了，还在微微地颤抖。想到这里，他被呛着了，咳嗽起来，一边咳嗽，一边想：“多奇怪呀，我怎么还咳嗽？”

“我这是怎么了呢，难道是疯了吗！”谢尔盖想到这里，浑身都凉了，“真是见鬼了，判了个绞刑还不够惨吗！”

他抬手擦了擦额头的汗水，但觉得擦汗这个动作也令他奇怪不已。因此，他屏住呼吸，几乎感觉过了有好几小时，就那么呆若木鸡地一动不动，什么都不去想，大气也不喘一口，没有任何的动作——因为任何想法都会是不理智的，任何动作都会使他陷入疯狂。时间已经不复存在了，时间已经进入到空间之中，变成一座透明的真空广场，巨大而广阔，所有的土地、所有的生物都聚集于此，一切都尽收眼底，一切都能一眼望到头，只因到了最后的断头路——那就是死亡。令他备受折磨的，不是能够一眼就看见死亡，而是一下子同时看到生与死。自古以来，遮住了生死真相的大幕一直紧闭着，现在这层幕布被一只亵渎神明的大手打开了，生与死就不再是秘密了——但是，它们仍是混沌不明的，不可理喻的，就像用晦涩难懂的语言描绘的真理一样。在他那人类的头脑中还没有一种概念来解释这景象，他所使用的人类语言也不足以表达他的所思所见。他只会说“我感到害怕”这样的话——因为在他心里或者头脑中还没有，也不可能有哪一句话或哪一个概念，比这句话更能够契合他现在的非人状态和所见景象。一个人，或者说，像他这样的人，要是不能脱离于人类的理智、经验和情感的范畴，即使是见到了上帝本人，也理解不了上帝的含义，尽管知道这就是那个叫上帝的人，却会因为难以理解的巨大痛苦而浑身战栗不已。

“现在还是让穆勒出场吧！”谢尔盖忽然特别自信地大叫了一声，摇了摇头。他像一个正常人常有的情况一样，毫无预料地转变了心情，愉快且发自内心地大笑起来。“啊呀，你呀，穆勒！哎呀，你这个亲爱的穆勒老兄！啊呀，你这个德国妙人啊！好穆勒，到头来呀——最终你是对的，我呢，就是一头愚蠢的驴呀。”

他又特别快地在牢房里走了几趟，在监视孔监视他的看守又一次大吃一惊——谢尔盖飞快地把衣服脱了个精光，高高兴兴且十分卖力地做着全套十八个体操动作。他不断伸展自己年轻却已经消瘦了的身体，下蹲、吸气、呼气、踮起脚、踢腿、摆臂。每完成一个动作，他都满意地说：

“就这么做！这才是真正的体操，穆勒老兄！”

谢尔盖的脸颊变得通红了，令人舒服的热汗大滴大滴地渗出皮肤，心脏也跳得有力而且相当平稳。

“问题在于，穆勒，”谢尔盖挺起胸膛，皮肤下面的条条肋骨清晰可见，“问题在于，穆勒，还有第十九节体操——它的动作为保持不动，笔直地将脖子吊起来。这一节称为绞刑。你明白吗，穆勒？抓住一个活人——比方说吧，抓住了谢尔盖・戈洛温，把他像一个洋娃娃裹在襁褓里一样绑起来，然后用绳子吊住脖子，吊死拉倒。穆勒啊，这事儿是很愚蠢，但是毫无办法了，不得不如此了。”

他向右边做体侧运动，并且重复了一遍说：

“不得不如此了，穆勒老兄。”

9.可怕的孤独

/

此刻，在同样的钟声里，在远离谢尔盖和穆夏的几间空牢房之外，不幸的瓦西里・卡希林感受到了沉重的孤独，仿佛宇宙间只剩下了他一个人，正在恐怖和忧伤中挨过他生命的最后时光。

瓦西里・卡希林大汗淋漓，衬衫湿答答地粘在身上，原本卷曲的头发现在都松垮地粘在头皮上，他像一个患了剧烈牙疼的人，浑身痉挛着，无可忍受地在牢房里走过来踱过去。他一会儿坐下，一会儿又跑开，一会儿把头抵住墙，一会儿又直愣愣地眼睛盯着某处不动——就好像要找一种医牙疼的药一样。他入狱后容貌大变，以至于他仿佛有过两张不同的脸，一张从前的脸，年轻却杳然无迹；取代这张脸的是一张新的脸孔，它苍老难看、憔悴不已。

对死亡的恐惧猝然到来，而且一下子就把他紧紧地攫住，他再也无法挣脱了。决定行动的那天早晨，他还毫无畏惧地走向死亡，还轻松地调侃死亡，而到了晚上，在被关进单人牢房之后，极度的恐惧像大浪一样席卷身心，彻底吞没了他。当他还凭借自己的自由意志，去面对危险和死亡的时候，在他还能用自己的双手去解决问题的时候，无论死亡看起来有多么可怕，他都可以轻松地，甚至乐观地对待，这是因为，以前他感觉自己是无限自由的，是无比勇敢的，是信念坚定的，是大胆无畏的，是毫不怯懦的，即使害怕什么，也像小老太太满脸细小的皱纹一样，无迹可寻，毫不显眼。当炸弹被绑在他腰上的时候，他自己仿佛也变成了一颗炸弹，就像头脑中嵌入了烈性炸药的冷酷理智，赋予了他致命的可怕能量。每当走在街道上，跻身于熙熙攘攘的人流中，看到街巷里凡夫俗子们只关心自己的事情，谨小慎微地躲避着马车和电车，他就更觉得自己是一个不同凡响的人，完全来自不知何为死亡、何谓害怕的神秘国度。

可是，剧烈反转的变化骤然来临，荒唐至极。人们偏要押送他去那个他本人不情愿去的地方。他已经不能够选择待在什么地方，而是被人押着关进石头牢房，像什么东西一样，扔进去锁起来。他已经不能像所有自由人一样选择生或者是死，他必定会无可避免地要被杀死。只是一瞬间，他这位原先为自由意志、生命和力量的化身，就立刻变成了待宰的牲畜，变成了无声无息的东西，变成了可以被任意摆布、随意烧毁和随便折损的任何东西。他现在无论说什么，都没有人愿意倾听他说的话。而如果他敢喊叫起来，那么，就会有人来用抹布塞住他的嘴，无论他挪不挪动他的双腿，反正人们是要把他押走去绞死的。他反抗也好，挣扎也罢，躺在地上撒泼打滚也是一样的——人们照样还会制服他，拖他起来，捆绑他，把他反绑押至绞刑架下。完成这种机械性杀人事务的，是和他一样的人，而这就使得他们看上去好像有一种完全不同于常人的凶狠样子，既像是一种故意变形的幽灵，又像是装上了发条的机械玩偶——他们抓人、逮人、押送人、吊死人，顺着脚把人拉下来。他们割断绳索之后，就把尸首装车运走，扔到乱坟岗上一埋了事。

从入狱的第一天起，对他来说，人们和生活都变成了不可思议的满是幽灵和机械玩偶的可怕世界。他恐惧得几乎发疯，竭力想象人们长了舌头，应该是会说话，但却说不出来——好像全是哑巴一样；他又竭力回忆人们之间有过的谈话，他们在交际时说过的有含义的句子，结果也是徒劳。人们的嘴都张着，发出了某种声音，后来就四散开来，只能看见脚在移动，其他什么也看不见、听不见。

如果深夜里一个人孤零零地被留在房子里，他就会感到屋子里的东西都活了过来，能四处走动，凌驾于孤独的人之上，获得了无限的权力。这些东西——桌子、椅子、写字台和沙发可能会突然来审判他。他会喊叫，会四处奔突，会寻求帮助。但是，这些东西——桌子、椅子、写字台和沙发会用它们才懂的语言和方式来商量。然后这些东西——桌子、椅子、写字台就下令立刻把人绞死。其他的东西嘛，就只能冷眼旁观。

在被判处绞刑以后，瓦西里・卡希林觉得一切都变成了玩偶：他的单人牢房，带有监视孔的牢门，准点报时的钟声，砌得结结实实的城堡监狱，还有那个挎着枪，鞋跟在走廊里磕打作响的看守，他更像机械玩偶，以及在监视孔先是可怕地瞪他一眼，然后一言不发再把牢饭递进来的家伙也是。他有这样的体验并不是真的怕死，他甚至希望快点死去。在所有神秘莫测、难以解释的事物中，相对于变得野蛮和无序的世界，死亡是理智可以解释的。在这个幽灵遍地的疯狂的机械玩偶世界里，死亡早已经完全失去了它那伟大而神秘的含义，变成了某种机械的，因而十分可怕的东西。他们抓人、逮人、押送人、吊死人，顺着脚把人拉下来。他们割断绳索之后，就把尸首装车运走，扔到乱坟岗上一埋了事。

一个人就会因此从世界上销声匿迹。

瓦西里・卡希林最为清醒的瞬间就是在法庭上受审的时候，因为和同志们站在一起，他又重新看见了人：他们坐在那里审判他，用人类话语商量事务，倾听别人的话，也明白其他人在说什么。但是，在与母亲会面的时候，他所熟知的那种出离了人类理智的恐惧感再度袭来，他感觉这个戴着黑头巾的老太婆——完全是一个被人操控的机械玩偶，就像那些也会说“爸爸”“妈妈”的人一样，只不过制作得精致些罢了。他极力想好好与她交谈，但就是浑身颤抖，不由自主地想道：

“老天啊！你跟一个玩偶谈什么呀。这就是一个玩偶妈妈。那便是一个玩偶卫兵，家里还有个玩偶父亲，而我呢，玩偶瓦西里・卡希林在此。”

好像只过了一会儿，他就听到了某种机械装置破裂开的声响和转轮缺少润滑油的嘎吱声。当他的母亲开始哭泣的时候，有那么一瞬间，人的理智有所回归，但是在母亲开始说话的时候，这种感觉立刻就烟消云散了，他开始恍惚而又好奇地观察，眼泪是如何从玩偶的眼睛里流出的。

后来，就在自己的牢房里，当恐惧变得无可忍受时，瓦西里・卡希林尝试着去祈祷。尽管他的少年时代是在父亲的商人之家里度过的，一直沉浸于宗教的氛围中，但是他厌烦那种形式，为那种氛围痛苦过，并且完全痛恨宗教，没有在身心中形成任何信仰。但，也许是在童年的某个时刻，他听到过一句话，这句话一下子打动了他，令他战栗不安，给他留下了终生的安宁诗意，即：“上帝是一切苦难之人的喜乐。”

每当生活中出现痛苦的时候，他就对自己默默诵读这句话，不算祈祷，也不是有意为之：“上帝是一切苦难之人的喜乐。”说完呢，他就会感到轻松，想找个亲近的人去倾诉心事，悄悄地诉点苦：

“我们的生活啊……还算是生活吗！哎呀，我亲爱的，你说，这叫什么生活呀！”

然后，他突然就会特别想整理好头发，跪在地上，敞开胸脯，听凭别人来击打：“来吧，朝这里打吧！”

他对任何人都没有说过“上帝是一切苦难之人的喜乐”这句话，对自己最亲近的同志也丝毫未露半点儿口风，甚至就好像自己都从来不知道有这么一句话一样——这句话就这样深深地埋藏在他的心底。他并不经常回忆起这句话，每次回忆起来都是小心冀冀地，非常谨慎。

于是，现在，当恐惧显而易见、无可掩饰，就像决堤的洪水淹没了沿岸的蒲柳一样，彻底地吞没了他的全部身心的时候，他想要祈祷了。他想跪下来，但怕看守窥到就太难为情了，所以就只把双手交叉到胸前，小声默念：

“上帝是一切苦难之人的喜乐！”

然后再一次面带忧愁地重复祷告：

“上帝是一切苦难之人的喜乐，降福于我吧，拯救罪人瓦西里・卡希林吧。”

很久以前，还是在上大学一年级的时候，在认识维尔纳并参加到组织中之前，他的生活完全是吃喝玩乐，说话也随便，那时管自己叫“罪人瓦西里・卡希林”——现在，不知为什么又想这样称呼自己了。就这样死气沉沉地重复着这句话，得不到任何的回应：

“上帝是一切苦难之人的喜乐！”

这时，好像有某种东西闪过。仿佛是某人安宁且悲苦的形象在向远方飘浮，还未来得及照亮死亡之前的黑暗，就消失得无声无息了。钟楼上的报时钟声铛铛地响起来了。看守的枪还是刺刀什么的，不知碰到哪里，也响了一下，接着他打了一个哈欠，开始来回走动。

“上帝是一切苦难之人的喜乐！你为什么还默不作声？你什么话也不想对罪人瓦西里・卡希林说吗？”

他就这样温柔地诉说并等待着。然而，无论是他的心里还是身外，都并无一人，虚空不已。那个安宁且悲苦的形象并没有返回或者再度出现。这时儿时的场景，诸如滚烫的蜡烛、穿着长袍的神父、画在墙上的圣像、不停地跪下又站起来的父亲都涌进了他痛苦而不情愿的回忆中，父亲一边祈祷，一边鞠躬，还时不时地皱眉观察，瓦西里是否在好好祈祷，是不是在调皮捣蛋。想到这些，他简直比祈祷之前更觉恐怖了。

一切都烟消云散了。

疯狂的感觉特别压抑地传导到他的全身。他的意识熄灭了，就犹如一堆被人为熄灭拨散的篝火，就犹如一具行将就木的尸体，心脏处的体温尚存，手脚却早已经冰凉僵硬了。他那行将熄灭、尚存一息的思想又说了一次话，即他，罪人瓦西里・卡希林，有可能在这里发疯，体验到那些无名的苦难，忍受还未有任何生物体验过的无边的疼痛与痛苦。他可能会把头死命地往墙上撞，可能会用手指抠出自己的双眼，很可能会歇斯底里地大喊大叫，很可能会痛哭流涕地哭诉，他再也受不了了——希望这种事不会出现。肯定不会出现的。

果然什么事也没有发生。双腿还没有失去自己的知觉和生命，继续行走并且承载着他那不停抖动、汗津津的身体。双手也还有知觉，总是徒劳地要把前胸敞开的囚服衣襟拉紧，好让冷得发抖的身体稍微暖和一点儿。他的身体打着寒战，简直透心凉了。他的眼睛一直在直勾勾盯着某处看。这种姿势已经持续不动很久了，称得上宁静不已。

然而，极端可怕的时刻还是到来了：这就是一帮人拥进牢房的时刻。他甚至没有想到，这就意味着——该去刑场行刑了。只是看着这些人，自己就已经像一个小孩子一样感到害怕。

“我再也不敢了！我再也不敢了！”他惊骇地躲到牢房的角落里，翕动着干硬的嘴唇，用几乎听不见的小声喃喃自语，像极了小时候父亲抬手要揍他时的样子。

“该走了。”

这帮人跟他说话，在他身旁走动，递给他某个东西。他闭着眼睛，身体一直摇摆——后来就心情沉重地开始收拾东西。看起来，他的神志清醒过来了，因为他突然张口向那个官员要一根香烟来吸。后者殷勤地打开了绘有颓废派画风图案的银质烟盒。

10.墙在倒塌

/

维尔纳只是化名，没人知道他的真名实姓，他呢，是一个对生活和斗争都厌倦了的人。原先有过一段时期，他非常热爱生活，酷爱戏剧和文学，喜欢交游，常常呼朋唤友。他记忆力惊人，意志相当顽强，学习并精通好几种欧洲语言，能够流利地和德国人、法国人或英国人交谈。他说德语时还带一点儿巴伐利亚口音，但必要时，他会像一个地道的土生土长的柏林人那样说话。他穿戴十分讲究，总是风度翩翩，在自己的同志中，他是唯一一个敢出现在上流社会的各种场合而不担心被识破的人。

但他的同志们长久以来并不知道，在维尔纳的心里早就形成了对人的蔑视，不仅如此，他心底也不断堆积沉重的绝望情绪和厌倦心理。从天性上来说，维尔纳更像是一个数学家，而不是一个诗人，因为他至今不知道何为写作灵感，何为文艺移情，却在很长一段时间里感觉自己是一个狂人，立志要在人类的血泊中解决化圆为方[9]的问题。他不尊敬与自己每日缠斗的敌人，因为这些都是由愚蠢、背叛和谎言甚至肮脏的口水和无耻的欺骗编织成的一张密实的大网。最终让他永远地丧失了生活愿望的原因，似乎是组织交给他的一项清除奸细的任务。他按组织要求完成了，在老练地打死奸细之后，看了一眼死去的人，生前是那么可恶虚伪的一张脸，现在已经变得安详，完全是一张令人怜悯的脸——他突然不再尊敬自己和自己的事业了。并不是感到了什么悔恨，只不过是突然不再自视甚高了。他开始觉得自己是一个无趣的人，一个无足轻重的人，一个乏味的局外人。不过，作为一个高度自律的人，他遵规守纪，并没有脱离组织，表面上和以前毫无二致——只是眼神变了，冷冰冰的，看上去很可怕。他没有与任何人交流过这些心理活动。

他还拥有一个罕见的特点：就像很多人从来不知道头疼是怎么回事一样，他呢，从来不知道什么叫害怕。每当别人感到害怕的时候，他对此既不加以谴责，也不特别同情，就像感冒是如此普及的一种疾病，但他本人却从未得过一样。他也怜悯自己的同志，尤其是像瓦西里・卡希林这样的。但是，他的可怜是冷冰冰的，居高临下的，几乎并不是真情实意的流露。这种怜悯，可能连法庭上的一些法官都会有的。

维尔纳清楚，绞刑并不仅仅是死刑，它还含有某种别的含义——但是，他决定，无论出现任何情况，都要平静地去迎接死亡，就像对待任何身外之事一样，就像什么也没发生，什么也不会发生一样，活到生命的最后一刻。他只能以此种方式来表明他对死刑的最高轻蔑，捍卫自己不可剥夺的精神自由。所以，在法庭上，他想的既不是死的问题，也不是如何活下去的问题，他专心致志地、聚精会神地、心无旁骛地在思考一盘难解的棋局，这一点，就连十分了解他那平时遇事冷静和大无畏性格的同志们也未必能想得到。维尔纳是一位国际象棋高手，从被捕的第一天起，他就开始下这盘棋了，一直持续不断地在棋盘上厮杀。就连对他的绞刑判决也未能干扰到他，他在意念中的棋盘上还未输掉一子呢。

甚至，明摆着他是下不完这盘棋了，这一点也没能让他放弃继续排兵布阵。他停留在人世间最后一天的那个早晨，是从他修正昨天走得不太睿智的随手棋开始的。他把双手放在两个膝盖中间，一动也不动地坐了好久，然后，站起身来，开始一边走动，一边思考。他的步态很特别，他上半身的躯干微微向前倾，而厚鞋跟则重重地磕在地上，叩地有响，以至于在干硬的地上留下了十分明显的脚印。他轻轻地用口哨声吹了一曲轻快的意大利咏叹调——这有助于他的思考。

但是，不知为什么，这天早上，棋下得不顺利。他感觉不好，觉得是走了一步昏着儿，而且是相当愚蠢的大败着儿。他几次从开局起，复盘所走的每一步棋。始终没有发现走错的那一步棋究竟落子何处了，但是，走错了一步棋的感觉如影随形，而且越来越强烈，越来越令他沮丧。但是一个突如其来的想法使他非常难堪：事情不在于他是否走了一步昏着儿，而在于他是否想用下棋来转移自己对于死刑这件事的注意力，逃避他对死亡的恐惧，逃避那对于每个犯人来说都无可逃避的死亡的恐惧？

“不！我才不会呢！”他冷冰冰地回答自己的这个疑惑，平静地合上了意念中的棋盘。于是，开始像下棋一样，专心致志地、聚精会神地、心无旁骛地思考起自己毫无出路的可怕的处境，就像是要为一场十分苛刻的考试做出标准答案。他环视了一遍单人牢房，尽量不漏掉任何东西，计算了一下到受刑之前还有多长的时间，在心里画了一幅大致的受绞刑时的场景图，画得相当准确，细节毕现，随即自己就耸了耸肩。

“那又能怎样呢？”他反诘式地回答，“不就是这些嘛。有什么可怕的呢？”

确实没有什么好怕的。不仅没什么可怕的，而且他心里还有一种与之相反的感觉——一种混沌不清的，但是巨大的、豪迈的、欢乐的感觉。于是，那遍寻不得的昏着儿已经引不起他的沮丧、他的愤怒，却带来了某种巨大的意想不到的好事，就好比他以为一位好朋友已经死了，结果是朋友出乎意料地毫发无损地回来了，且正在冲他微笑。

维尔纳重新又耸了耸肩膀，摸了一下自己的脉搏，心跳虽然很快，但脉搏有力、平稳、匀速，带着特有的怦怦的节奏感。他再一次像一个新来的犯人一样仔细打量了一遍墙壁、门上的插销以及固定在地上的椅子，心里想道：

“为什么我会感到这么轻松愉快、自由自在呢？尤其是自由自在？我想到明天的绞刑——就好像这件事根本不存在一样。我看着这堵墙——就好像墙也不存在一样。就这样自由自在，就好像我不是正在坐牢，而是刚刚从坐了一辈子的监狱里被刑满释放了一样。这是怎么回事呢？”

维尔纳的双手开始颤抖——这对他来说可算是从未有过的现象。一时间，他的思绪越来越汹涌，就像有无数条火舌在头脑中舔噬——这些火舌竭力要冲出头脑，照亮远方黑沉沉的夜色。它们终于冲了出来，把远方照得一片光明。

近两年来困扰维尔纳的混沌的厌倦感消失了，那条盘踞在他心口的冷冰冰的、紧闭口眼的、沉重的大蛇突然就不复存在了——代之返回的，是美妙的活生生的青春，就在临死前。而且，在神清志明的同时，随之而来的还有一种罕见的现象，即一个人精神上的觉悟能够使其进入到人生的巅峰时刻，维尔纳就是突然处于此种境界之中，同一时间内，既看到了生，也看到了死，他被这种罕有的、空前壮观的现象所震惊。仿佛他自己正在窄窄的、刀锋般的高山绝壁上行走。他看到的是一幅全景图，往这边看到的是生，而往另一边看到的则是死，恰如两片深不可测、美不胜收、波光粼粼的大海，在地平线处汇合为海天一色的无边无际的广阔海洋。

“太壮观了！竟有这么绝妙的景象！”他拉长声音说道，慢慢地欠起身，挺直后背，就像在面君朝圣一样。于是，在维尔纳那专注的、洞察一切的目光扫视下，墙壁、空间、时间都消失了，他极目远眺，一览无余地看到了即将与之告别的生活的最深处。

于是，生活变成了崭新的。但是，维尔纳并不想像以前那样，用语言来描述所见所闻，而且就是穷尽人类的语言，对于这般景象的描写也是苍白无力的，也是微乎其微的，也是词汇贫乏的。人们的脸上有过的渺小、肮脏和凶狠的样子，曾经让他轻蔑，甚至有时特别憎恶的表情，现在都彻底消失了。这情景就犹如一个乘坐高空中的热气球正在离开自己城市的人，在他看来，拥挤不堪的街道上那些争吵谩骂和污泥浊水都统统消失不见了，所有丑陋、破败的景象都变得美不胜收。

维尔纳下意识地走到桌子旁边，用他的右手掌撑住桌面。他生性高傲，威严，但还从来没有像现在这样摆出如此高傲、如此自由自在、如此威严的姿势。他连脖子也不转动一下，他的眼神从未如此的犀利——他从来没有像现在这样自由自在，这样威仪整肃，就在监狱里，就在离执行死刑不足几个钟头的时间里。

而且，在他清醒的目光扫视下，人，都变成了新人，都变成了可亲可爱的新人。他像一个穿越了时间的年轻小伙子，清楚地看见了，昨天还犹如森林间嚎叫的野兽一般的人类焕发了青春。原先人身上可怕的、不可饶恕的和令人憎恶的缺点突然间就变得可亲可爱了——就像刚刚学着走路的孩童，尽管不会像大人那样大步流星，但是，他的咿呀学语、他的蹒跚学步、他的天资聪颖、他的呆萌、跌跤、磕头碰脚都令人忍俊不禁。

“我可亲可爱的人们啊！”维尔纳突然情不自禁地笑了，保持了半天的姿势一下子就变形了，重新又像一个犯人那样，被牢牢地禁锢在方寸监舍中，因为厌恶贴在门上的那双监视的眼睛而感到心烦意乱，无所适从。说来也怪，他几乎是陡然间就忘记了刚才清清楚楚所看到的一切；甚至更可怕的是，他连回想一下的愿望都没有。他只是坐姿稍稍随便了一点儿，不像平时那么身正背直了，神情完全变成了非维尔纳式的样子，脸上带着一抹松弛的、温柔的微笑看着牢房四周的墙壁和铁栅栏。接下来就发生了更不像维尔纳以往行为处事的一幕：他突然放声痛哭起来。

“我亲爱的同志们啊！”他一边大哭，一边声泪俱下地低声诉说。

他的情感由高高在上的傲气和无限的自由自在一下子过渡到温柔和怜悯的激情中，这究竟是经由了怎样神秘的心路历程呢？对这一切，他不知道，也没有去想。至于他是否怜悯自己亲爱的同志们，抑或他的眼泪中是否还饱含着更为伟大崇高或者更为炙热的情感呢？他那颗重新复活和重返青春的心恐怕对此也一无所知。他就只管放声痛哭：

“我亲爱的同志们啊！我亲爱的同志们啊！”

谁也不会在这个痛哭流涕的人身上认出以前那个冷冰冰的、傲慢的维尔纳，谁也不会把这个含泪微笑的人等同于以前厌倦一切、无所畏惧的维尔纳——法官们不会认出他来，同志们不会相信自己的眼睛，就连他自己也不会认同的。

[9] 指代无法解决的问题。

11.押解上路

/

在分别被押上各自的囚车前，五名死囚被集中在一间阴冷的大房间里，那里拱形的天花板使其显得更加空旷，像是一间废弃已久的办公场所，也可能，以前是被用作宽敞的接待室的。他们被允许相互交谈。

可是，只有丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克立即就开始使用这项许可。其他人都默不作声，只是紧紧地握手。有人的手凉冷如冰，有人的手热如火炭——他们不想说话，也不互相凝望，他们很不自然地围成一个松散的小圈。现在，他们大家聚在一起了，这当中的每个人似乎都为自己单独囚禁时的想法感到羞愧。他们不敢互相凝望，这是因为怕看到别人，或者向别人展示出自入狱以来每个人都曾想到过和怀疑过的东西，那些新的、很特别的但说出来有点儿令人羞愧的想法。

但是，一两次对视之后，他们立刻都释然了，仍然像以前一样，微笑着开始无拘无束地交谈起来，仿佛没有什么变故一样；要是说有什么已经发生，那对大家也是一样的，每个人身上的变化是同等的，所以对个人来说也就不明显了。所有人都开始说话了，而且言谈举止都特别奇怪。大家的谈话不是断断续续，就是滔滔不绝，不是抢着说，就是谁也不说。有时候大家抢着说，同样的话会被重复几遍；有时候，有人一句话只说了半截，也以为自己已经说完了，停下来也没人注意到。大家都在好奇地互相打量，就像是戴眼镜的人突然摘掉了眼镜，仔细地观察那些以前视为寻常的东西一样。他们所有人都几次突然转身向后张望，仿佛恍惚间有人在背后吼叫和下了什么指示。不过，他们都对自己的反常表现并未察觉。两位女士穆夏和丹妮雅的脸颊和耳朵都烧得绯红，谢尔盖一开始脸还发白，但很快就恢复原样，和平时毫无二致了。

只有瓦西里一人引起了大家的注意。即使在他的同志们中间，他也不能恢复常态，仍然是一副害怕的样子。维尔纳还是十分担忧，小声和穆夏说了自己的不安：

“他这是怎么搞的呢，穆夏琪卡[10]？难道他真的怕成那个样子吗？怎么办？应该和他谈谈。”

瓦西里站得稍远一点儿，向维尔纳望了一眼，就好像不认识他一样，垂下了自己的目光。

“瓦夏，你的头发是怎么弄的呀，啊？你是怎么啦？没什么大不了的，老弟，没什么大不了的，没什么大不了的，这马上就结束了。应当坚持住啊，要坚持，要坚持。”

瓦西里默不作声，似乎无话可说。当维尔纳已经觉得，瓦西里不会再开口说点什么了的时候，他却给了一句闷声闷气的回答。这回答给所有人的问候听上去并不能让人安心，反倒像是从遥远的坟墓里发出的哀鸣：

“我可没什么好害怕的。我能坚持住。”

他又重复了一遍：

“我能坚持住。”

维尔纳一下子就高兴起来了。

“我说你没事的嘛，对。真是好样的。就该这样，就该这样。”

但是，当维尔纳与瓦西里的目光相遇时，他发现瓦西里眼神十分呆滞、暗淡，像是从一个遥远的深处递出来的茫然失措的目光，这使他在那一瞬间痛心不已：“他这是从哪里看过来、从哪里说的话呢？”他立即就用恋人们才有的温柔劲儿，像是对还未醒的人说：

“瓦夏，你能听见吗？我非常爱你。”

“我也非常爱你。”他吞吞吐吐地回答说。

忽然，穆夏抓住维尔纳的一只手，像站在舞台上的演员一样，语句清晰地表达了自己的惊讶，她说：

“维尔纳，你怎么啦？你刚才当真说了‘我爱你’？你可是个从来不说‘我爱你’的人。你怎么突然变得这么温柔，这么和蔼可亲了啊……？哎，你这是怎么啦？”

“哎，你这是怎么啦？”

于是，维尔纳也像一个演员一样，紧握着穆夏的手，同样语句清晰地表达了自己的感受：

“是的，我现在非常爱大家。请不要告诉别人，不要告诉他们。挺难为情的，但是，我确实非常爱大家。”

他们两个人的目光碰到一起，电光石火般燃烧起来，周围的一切都黯淡无光了，犹如瞬间的闪电使一切光源都熄灭了，只有闪电那黄色且沉重的影子掠过大地。

“是的。”穆夏说，“维尔纳，是的。”

“是的。”他回答，“是的，穆夏，是的。”

某种东西在两个人之间已经心领神会，并由他们两人坚定地将其确定下来了。于是，维尔纳的目光不再犹疑，他重新振作了一下，又走向了谢尔盖。

“谢廖扎！”

但是，回答他的是丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克。她拽着谢尔盖的衣服袖子，特别兴奋，几乎有一种母亲般的自豪感，都快落泪了。

“维尔纳，你听我说！我这阵子一直担心他，几乎一直在哭，都要伤心死了，可他倒好——人家在做体操！”

“穆勒那套？”维尔纳笑了笑。

谢尔盖挺腼腆地皱了皱眉头，说道：

“维尔纳，你还真别笑，我已经完全确信它有益……”

大家都笑了起来。大家从互相交谈中汲取了坚强的精神，获得了力量。渐渐地，他们又变成了从前的样子，但他们没有察觉的也正是这一点，他们还认为，他们和从前是一样的。突然，维尔纳止住了笑声，特别严肃地对谢尔盖说：

“你是对的，谢廖扎。你是完全正确的。”

“不，你要明白……”戈洛温挺高兴，“当然，我们……”

但这时候，卫兵已经开始催促他们上车了。押解他们的人这时候都十分和蔼，允许他们三两结伴坐同一辆车，或随意同车乘坐。总之，押送人员非常和善可亲，甚至过于和善了。也许是想尽量展示他们的人道态度，也许是想竭力表明，这一切自有其规律，与他们全无任何关系。不过，这些人的脸色都不好，很苍白。

“穆夏，你和他坐一起吧。”维尔纳示意她和站着不动的瓦西里同坐一辆车。

“明白。”穆夏立即点头，“那你呢？”

“我吗？丹妮雅和谢尔盖坐一辆车，你去和瓦夏坐一辆车……剩我一个人了。这没关系，你知道，我是能行的。”

当大家走到院子里来的时候，夜色黑暗，空气湿润，暖风强劲地扑面而来，使人睁不开眼，呼吸都不畅了。有什么东西突如其来地一下子就穿透了犯人们颤抖的身体，令他们感到清新和惬意。以前很难相信，这令人惊奇的东西，不过就是春风而已，是温暖湿润的春风。正是这个真正的、令人惊奇的春天的夜晚，辽阔无边的大地正在散发着冬雪融化的气息，四处都是融化了的水滴在嗒嗒作响。水滴嗒嗒不断线地散落，一滴接着一滴，极速而又和谐地演奏出欢快的曲目。但也有突然哑然的时候，整个欢快的曲目就出现了混乱的无序状态。直到后来有一大滴水珠慨然落下，这一组欢快的曲目才得以准确地、和谐地继续叮咚演奏下去。在城市的上空，在监狱的楼顶上，泛着电灯反射过来的白光。

“啊哈……”谢尔盖・戈洛温深深地呼出了一口气，然后屏住呼吸，仿佛不愿意把这么清新、这么美妙的空气从肺部呼出体外。

“天气早就这样了吗？”维尔纳不敢相信，“这已经完全是春天了呀。”

“这才是第二个暖和天，”旁边有一个机警但礼貌的声音回答道，“这里以前一直相当冷呢。”

乌黑的囚车一辆接一辆慢慢地驶过来，每辆车带走两名犯人，驶入黑暗之中，向大门口驶去，那门上挂着一盏不停摇晃的电灯。那些灰色的影子是负责此次押解任务的骑兵团卫兵，他们紧紧地围住每一辆囚车，他们所骑的马匹踩在石板上便发出嘚嘚的清脆蹄声，踩在融化的湿漉漉的雪上就发出闷闷的啪啪声。

当维尔纳弯腰俯身准备钻进囚车时，一个卫兵语焉不详地说：

“里面还有一个犯人要和你同乘一辆走。”

维尔纳显然吃了一惊：

“上哪里去？他要去哪里？啊，怎么可能呢？还有一个？这又是谁？”

卫兵不作声了。确实，这辆囚车的里头，一个个头不大但却一动也不动的人——当然不是动物——畏缩在黑洞洞的角落里，大门口那盏摇晃的灯射过来的光线就照在他那只睁开的眼睛上。维尔纳坐下的时候，碰到了这个人的膝盖。

“对不起，同志。”

那个人没有回答。只是在车辆向外走动了的时候，那个人才突然用根本不地道的俄语讷讷地问维尔纳：

“您是什么人？”

“我是维尔纳，因预谋行刺要员被判处绞刑。您是谁？”

“我——是扬松。不该绞死我。”

他们一起坐车走，为的是在两小时以后去面对那个无法破解的伟大秘密，在从生走向死的路上，他们就这样互相认识了。生与死——这两者同时并行着。生，是有始有终的，有最可笑的阶段，也有毫无意义的琐碎，但是，生活毕竟是生活。

“扬松，你干了什么事？”

“我拿刀把主人给捅啦，还偷拿了他的钱。”

听那声音，扬松好像要睡着了。维尔纳在黑暗中摸到了扬松的一只手，软塌塌的一只手，握了握，扬松萎靡不振地缩回了手。

“你害怕吗？”维尔纳问他。

“我不情愿被绞死。”

他们两个都不说话了。维尔纳重新把这个爱沙尼亚人的手拉过来，紧紧地握在自己那两个干燥、滚烫的手掌中。这只手就像一块小木板一样立在维尔纳的两个手掌之间，但是扬松再也没有把手缩回去。

囚车里又拥挤又闷不透气，散发出卫兵身上制服的汗味、霉味、马粪味和湿漉漉的皮靴味道。坐在维尔纳对面的小个子卫兵还不断朝他呼出一阵阵的大蒜和廉价烟草混合的气味。幸好不断有清冽、馥郁的空气从囚车的缝隙中钻进来。所以，在这个行驶中的小盒子里，在这个狭小的、闷罐一般的囚车里，比在车外面更能感受到强烈的春天的气息。囚车一路颠簸摇晃，一会儿向左倾斜过去，一会儿又倒向车体右侧，有时候感觉囚车是在往回走，有时又觉得已经过了几小时囚车还在原地打转转。一开始，路灯的光线还透过囚车的厚实的小窗帘照进来，后来囚车拐了一个弯之后，突然就没有任何光亮了，外面漆黑一片，伸手不见五指了，他们只能据此猜到，自己已经被带到了比较偏僻的街巷——接近C火车站的地方。维尔纳坐在晃来晃去的囚车里，只要一拐弯，弯曲的双膝不由自主地就会碰到对面坐的卫兵的双膝，他们都是生机勃勃的躯体，所以，简直令人难以置信，他竟然是去赴死。

“我们这是去哪儿呀？”扬松突然就发问了。

因为在黑洞洞且狭小的车厢里闷着，又颠簸得过久，他有点儿头晕和恶心了。

维尔纳回答了他，并更紧地握住了这个爱沙尼亚人的手。他想对这个个子小且老是睡眼惺忪的人说点特别友好、特别亲切的话，他爱这个人，胜过以往生活中遇到的任何一个人。

“亲爱的！看样子，你坐得很不舒服。过来，靠在我身上好了。”

扬松好一会儿不作声，后来回答说：

“不用了，谢谢！我还行，坐着没事。那，你也要被绞死吗？”

“对呀！”出乎意料，维尔纳一听这话立即高兴起来，赶紧回答他，特别轻松，满不在乎地挥了挥手。仿佛他们交谈的内容是自己那些爱好恶作剧的好朋友开的一个无伤大雅的玩笑，只是想捉弄他一下而已的玩笑。

“你有老婆吗？”扬松问。

“没呢。哪有什么老婆！我是一个单身汉呢。”

“我也是一个光棍。一个人过。”扬松说完，想了一下，又改口说道。

维尔纳的头也开始晕乎乎的了。竟然不时出现一种幻觉，仿佛他们这是去参加某种盛大的节日。这听起来很奇怪，但是，几乎所有被押赴死刑场的人都会有这种感觉，与痛苦和恐惧伴生相随的是不同寻常的狂喜，这是一种对从未体验过的事物混沌的期待。在死刑犯人的认知中，现实沉湎于他们的非理智状态，和生活交织在一起的死亡使他们产生出各种幻觉。很有可能，是房屋上迎风招展的旗帜诱发了这种感觉。

“看哪，我们到了！”囚车一停下来，还有点儿晃动时，维尔纳就既好奇又快活地说。可是，扬松却失神了：整个人都蔫蔫的，一言不发，赖在车里根本就不想下车。他抓住车门的把手不放，他的手也没啥劲了，押解的卫兵过去把他的手一下子就掰开了；他又赶紧抓住囚车一角、门边和高高的车轱辘，可是卫兵稍一松手，他就整个人瘫软下来，他完全不像是要抓住什么东西抵抗下车，而是睡眼惺忪的，像是要倚靠个东西就瞌睡过去了——所以卫兵只是那么轻轻一提，他就松了手。终于下了囚车。

房屋上也没有什么飘飘彩旗。这时仍旧是夜间，车站周围笼罩在一片黑暗之中，空旷无人，无声无息。这个时候已经不再发送普通的旅客列车，只有一节静候这批旅客的列车，无声地在轨道上等候发车，没有明亮的灯光，也没有旅客候车时的人声嘈杂。突然，维尔纳感到了无聊——不是恐惧，也不是感伤，而是一种突如其来的、巨大的、持续了好一会儿的无聊感，他因此只想找一个地方，躺下来，紧闭上自己的双眼。维尔纳就这样先是打了一个大呵欠，然后连着又打了几次呵欠，呵欠连天。

“但愿一切快一点儿过去吧！”维尔纳完全倦怠了。

扬松一直没话，就是全身都蜷缩着。

被士兵们封锁的站台上没有任何闲杂人等，犯人们有序地朝着一节灯光暗淡的车厢走过去，维尔纳挨着谢尔盖・戈洛温。谢尔盖抬手指着别的方向，开始说话，但是，维尔纳听清楚的只有“灯笼”一个词，后面的话都被他那连天的呵欠给吞没了，什么也没听清楚。

“你说什么？”维尔纳打着呵欠问道。

“我说灯笼。里面的灯泡把灯罩都熏黑了。”

维尔纳这才扭身看了一下：确实，灯泡烤炙得厉害，外面的透明玻璃罩都已经是暗黑色的了。

“可不是嘛，都熏黑了。”

突然间，他意识到：“都这个时候了，灯罩是否被熏黑还与我有什么关系呢……”很显然，谢尔盖也同时想到了一样的问题，所以他飞快地看了一眼维尔纳就把身子转过去了，但是，两个人都不再打呵欠了。

所有的人都是自行向车厢里走过去，只有扬松需要人搀扶。一开始他的脚底板像是被站台上的木板给粘上了一样，根本就抬不起脚来，后来两个卫兵架起他的胳膊，拖着他走，他的两条腿弯曲着耷拉在地上，像是一个酩酊大醉的人一样，靴子的尖头从站台的木板上吱嘎作响地划过。卫兵们折腾好半天才把他塞入车厢里，倒也没废什么话。

瓦西里・卡希林也是自己走过去的。他就是迷迷糊糊地模仿着同志们的动作，大家做什么，他就做什么，亦步亦趋而已。但是，在来到站台上，往车厢里走的时候，他脚下滑了一下，一个卫兵及时地抓住了他的一只手肘，扶住了他，瓦西里却浑身颤抖，缩回自己的手臂，大声尖叫起来：

“哎呀！”

“瓦夏，你怎么啦？”维尔纳立即跑到了他身边。

瓦西里也不说话了，身体颤抖得更剧烈了。卫兵有点儿尴尬，甚至有点儿委屈地解释说：

“我想扶他一下，可是……”

“来，瓦夏，我们走，我扶着你。”维尔纳说着，就去搀扶瓦西里的手臂，但是瓦西里推开他的手，又一次大声尖叫起来：

“哎呀！”

“瓦夏，是我呀，维尔纳。”

“我知道是你。别碰我，让我自己走。”

于是，他就这样，浑身颤抖着，自己走进了车厢，坐到角落里去了。维尔纳则转身对着穆夏，用目光指着瓦西里，示意穆夏并小声地问她：

“他这是怎么啦？”

“他的状态很糟糕。”穆夏小声地回答，“他已经算是死了。维尔纳，你告诉我，难道真有什么死亡吗？”

“我不知道，穆夏，但我认为，死亡不存在。”维尔纳回答得既相当认真，又若有所思。

“我也是这样想的。可是他呢？刚才和他坐在同一辆囚车里可真够我受的，我就像是和一具死尸一起过来的。”

“我真的弄不懂，穆夏。也许，对某些人来说，死亡可能真的存在。那也是暂时的，时过境迁就不会存在了。譬如，对我来说，死亡存在过，但是现在它已经不存在了。”

穆夏那苍白的脸颊泛起了红晕。

“死亡曾在你头脑中出现过？真的出现过吗？”

“出现过了。现在没有了。就像对你来说一样，已经不存在了。”

车厢门口传来一阵嘈杂声。米什卡・茨冈诺克踏着铛铛作响的鞋后跟，喘着粗气，呸呸地吐着唾沫，走进了车厢。他用眼睛四下张望了一会儿，就站住不动了。

“卫兵！这里没有地方了！”他气呼呼地冲着那个看他的卫兵嚷嚷，显然后者已经很疲倦了。“你得给我找一个宽敞的地方坐着，不然的话，我可不走了，你就在外面的路灯上吊死我得了。还弄个马车来送站，狗娘养的，那个也能叫马车吗？鬼知道来了一辆啥玩意儿，反正他妈的不是马车！”

突然，他不喊了，低下头，就伸长脖子一直朝前面走去，径直走到其他囚犯跟前。他带着几分狂野的表情，头发和胡子都乱蓬蓬的，黑色的眼睛看起人来还是那么粗野和犀利。

“啊！先生们！”他拉长声音说道，“原来是你们呢。你好哇，老爷。”

他碰了碰维尔纳的手臂，坐到了他的对面。一面俯身凑近维尔纳，一面眯起一只眼，用手挠了挠脖子。

“也是去刑场？啊？”

“也是！”维尔纳笑着回答他。

“难道这些人全都是？”

“全是。”

“嗯哼！”茨冈诺克龇牙大笑，很快就将所有人扫视了一番，在穆夏和扬松的身上稍微多停留了一会儿。又转过头来，朝维尔纳做了个鬼脸：

“这次是把部长干掉了？”

“是部长。那你呢？”

“我嘛，老爷，是因为别的案子。我们这种人可够不上部长！我是啥人呢，老爷，我可是个强盗。杀人越货的主儿！没什么，老爷，我也没想到，挤到这里来了，要和你们大家一起上路。那个世界里，地方够大，肯定咱们大伙儿都有地方坐的。”

他顶着一头乱蓬蓬的头发，瞪着一双粗野的大眼睛，眼珠骨碌碌，打量着所有人，目光中满是不信任。但所有人都默不作声地看着他，甚至大家看他的目光中倒是带着明显的关切。他龇着牙，在维尔纳的膝盖上拍了几下。

“老爷，这也有趣！这挺像一首歌里唱的那样：请你不要大声说话呀，那青翠的橡树呀，我的母亲。”

“都这时候了，你干吗还管我叫老爷……”

“你说得对呀，”茨冈诺克满意地随声附和，“都要和我一块儿被吊死啦，你还当啥老爷呢！瞧哇，这家伙才是个老爷呢。”他就用手指头指着那个默不作声的卫兵，然后说，“哎，你们的那一位，不比我们差呀，”他用眼睛示意瓦西里，“老爷，这位老爷，你是有点儿害怕了还是怎的？”

“没什么。”瓦西里费劲地转动舌头嘟囔了一句。

“哎呀，还说没什么呢。你可不用感到害臊，这也没什么可害臊的。只有狗才会在人家吊死它的时候龇牙咧嘴、摇尾乞怜呢，可你是个人呢。这个，这个垂头耷耳的又是谁？跟你们不是一伙的吗？”

茨冈诺克飞快地骨碌碌地转动着他的眼珠，不停地把嘴里腥甜的唾沫啐到地上。扬松龟缩在角落里，头上那顶脱了毛的破皮帽子不停地微微地抖动着，听到了他的话但是什么也没有回答。维尔纳替他回答说：

“他把主人给宰了。”

“我的天哪，”茨冈诺克大为吃惊，“他这个熊样还能杀人啊！”

茨冈诺克早就乜斜着眼睛，瞟了穆夏好几眼了。这时，他很快地转过身来，直勾勾地盯着她看，冲着她说话。

“大小姐啊，你这大小姐！您干吗要干这种事！红红的脸蛋，还总在笑。瞧哇，她还真的在笑哇！”他用干硬的大手抓住维尔纳的膝盖，“你瞧，你瞧哇！”

穆夏的脸一下子就涨得通红了，有点儿羞怯地微笑着。她并不躲避，同样直视茨冈诺克那张脸，看着他那有点儿疯狂、粗野却也沉重的眼睛和那副探寻的眼神。

大家都沉默了。

为数不多的几节车厢哐当哐当地行进在窄轨上，以连续而细碎的节奏不停地飞奔。每当进入拐弯处或者是到了十字路口，火车的汽笛声就不失时机地、呜呜地不停地鸣叫起来——司机最怕轧死人了。这样一想也怪荒谬的，为了把人送去绞死，人们还要在火车上费这么多的事，地球上最疯狂的事就是用最普通的方式，一丝不苟地，按部就班地，理智地去完成毫无理智的事情。列车在飞奔，车厢里坐着的人们，和他们平时坐火车时毫无二致。而火车行驶着，也像平时的火车那样运行着，然后到了一个车站，就像平时一样，“停车五分钟”。

于是，死亡即刻就降临了——永恒来临了——这就是那个伟大的秘密。

[10] 穆夏的小名。——编者注

12.他们被带走了

/

小专列在风驰电掣地行驶中。

谢尔盖・戈洛温曾经连续几年都和亲人们一起到这条线路附近的别墅度假，他白天和夜里都乘坐过这条线路上的火车，对这附近相当熟悉。此刻如果双目微合，他会觉得这是回家的路程——也许只不过是在城里的朋友家里逗留过久，只好乘坐夜班车赶回家而已。

“现在快到了。”他睁开眼睛说道，看了一眼被铁栏杆钉死的窗户，黑洞洞的毫无任何光亮，对他的话也无任何的反应。

没有任何人动一下，也没有人对他的下意识反应做出回答，只有茨冈诺克一次又一次快速地吐着他那腥甜的唾沫。并且他的眼睛又开始重新骨碌碌地在车厢里逡巡，目光依次扫过列车的窗子、车厢的门以及站着的卫兵。

“真冷啊。”瓦西里・卡希林确实冻得嘴唇已经僵硬了，在说出这个词的时候，只能翕动上下唇打战，以至于把“冷”这个字说得更形象了。

丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克立刻就觉得“英雄有用武之地”了。

“把我的头巾给你吧，把头巾围在脖子上。头巾很暖和的。”

“脖子？”谢尔盖突如其来地问了一句，并被自己的问题吓了一跳。

但是，因为大家都很冷，都想的是同一个问题，所以，没人听到他的这句问话，就好像没人说过任何话一样，或者也非常可能，所有人在同一瞬间说出了同样一个词。

“没关系的，瓦夏，你就围上这头巾吧，快围上吧，会暖和的。”维尔纳劝了瓦西里几句。然后，他转过身，对着扬松，亲切地问道：

“亲爱的，你觉不觉着冷啊？”

“维尔纳，可能，他更想抽支烟。同志，你是不是想抽烟？”穆夏问道，“我们有烟。”

“想抽呢！”

“谢廖扎，给他一支烟。”维尔纳高兴地说。

但谢尔盖早就把烟递给了扬松。于是，所有人都爱怜地看着扬松用手指夹住香烟，点燃了火柴，从嘴里徐徐地喷出了蓝色的烟雾圈。

“哎，谢谢啦。”扬松说，“不错。”

“真奇怪呀！”谢尔盖说。

“有什么可奇怪的？”维尔纳转过身来，“什么事奇怪？”

“这香烟啊。”

他手里拿着一支香烟，就是普普通通的香烟，夹在他虽有点儿苍白但还是活人的手指之间，他惊奇地，甚至有点儿害怕地看着这支香烟。于是大家的目光都集中到这支精细的香烟上，看着它的一端袅袅地冒出丝带一样的青烟，被吸烟者呼出的气息吹散开，而剩下的那一段就是黑如焦炭般的灰烬。最终熄灭了。

“烟灭了。”丹妮雅说。

“是啊，熄灭了。”

“那就去他的吧！”维尔纳说，他皱起眉头，不安地看着扬松，而后者还夹着香烟的手像是死人的手一样僵住了。倒是茨冈诺克，突然转身，几乎把脸凑到维尔纳的脸上，瞪着像马眼一样的眼睛，小声说：

“老爷，要不，咱把看守的卫兵干掉……咋样？试一下子？”

“用不着啦，”维尔纳也小声说，“咱就干了死亡这杯酒吧。”

“为啥呀？打一架再去死不是更开心点吗？我揍他，他揍我，不知不觉就完事了。就不像是去送死嘛。”

“不，这可不用啦。”维尔纳说着，然后又转身对着扬松说，“亲爱的，你怎么不抽烟了？”

扬松的脸原本很松弛，突然间就好像被人用一根线拉紧了一样，脸上的褶子全都皱巴巴地挤在一起，那些皱纹都不停地抽搐起来。扬松像如梦初醒一样，放生哀号起来，就是用假嗓子干号，没有一滴眼泪那种：

“我不要抽烟啊！啊——呜！啊——呜！啊——呜！不该绞死我啊！啊——呜！啊——哼！啊——哼！”

大家都围着他，乱成一团。

丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克一边失声痛哭，一边替扬松拉拉衣服袖子，又把他那脱了毛的帽子拉一拉，使其戴得端正一点儿，嘴上还念叨：

“你可是我们的亲人呢！亲爱的，别哭啦，我们的亲人啊！我的苦命不幸的亲人啊！”

穆夏把目光转到别处。茨冈诺克捕捉到了她的目光，龇牙笑了。

“这位先生是个怪人！嘴上喝着热茶，却一肚子冰凉啊。”他讥讽地说，笑了一下。但是，他自己的脸色也变得铁青了，嘴里的两排大黄牙咬得咯咯直响。

突然间，小专列抖动了一下，明显地放慢了速度。除了扬松和瓦西里・卡希林，大家一下子都站起身来，旋即又坐了下来。

“到站啦！”谢尔盖说。

就仿佛有谁从车厢里抽取了所有可供呼吸的空气一般，喘气都变得困难起来。心脏仿佛也开始扩张膨胀，撑满了胸腔，快提到嗓子眼儿一般，疯狂地跳动起来——仿佛这鲜血，成了心脏的喉咙，不断发出喊声。大家的眼睛都盯着抖动的地板，耳朵则竖起来倾听火车车轮越来越慢的滚动声，滚动——滑行——再滚动——突然就刹车不动了。

火车停了。

自此，梦境开始了。这不只是因为害怕，而是害怕引起了幻觉，造成了失去记忆状态。所有这一切，对不得不面对的人们来说，都是陌生的：做梦者自身已经退避三舍，只有他的幻觉在毫无意识地四处走动，毫无声音地在诉说，毫无痛感地在体验痛苦。大家梦游一般地走出车厢，两人一排，贪婪地嗅着早春时节森林中特别新鲜的空气。扬松仍然是睡眼惺忪、快睡着了一样地抗拒下车，但毕竟从来都是缩手缩脚、软弱无力，到底还是被不出一声的卫兵拖出了车厢。

大家一起走下了站台的石阶。

“难道就这么步行过去吗？”不知是谁还挺高兴地问了一句。

“离这里不远呗。”不知是谁也挺高兴地回答了一句。

然后这一大群黑压压的人，默然无声地向森林中穿行。正值春天，林中的道路坎坷不平，潮湿泥泞。从森林中，从雪地里散发出十分新鲜的、春天特有的气息。有时候，脚下一滑，就会陷进雪地里去，双手就会不由自主地伸手去抓同伴以撑住不倒。押送人员在道路两边没有踩实的雪地里深一脚浅一脚地行进，呼呼地喘着粗气。不知是谁，生气地来了一句：

“连路也不给扫干净。跑来在雪里翻跟头玩呢。”

“大人，扫是扫过了。现在是解冻天气，也没有什么办法呀。”

犯人们的知觉意识稍稍清醒了一些，但还没有完全回归正常，只是不连贯地、片段式地小范围有感觉了。蓦然间，又有人意识到了这个十分确定的想法：

“的确，他们连路都不给清扫一下呀。”

但是，这感觉只有一小会儿，随即一切就都变得模糊不清了，只有嗅觉还是灵敏的，可以尽情地呼吸清新的空气、森林中的清香、雪在融化的气息。过了一会儿呢，一切又都清晰得不同寻常，所有的一切——森林、夜晚、路途，以及他们再过几分钟就要被送上绞刑架这事——都变得清晰可见。犯人们之间的零星的低声交谈也相当克制：

“快四点了。”

“我就说嘛，出来得太早了。”

“到五点天才会亮呢。”

“可不嘛，得五点。就是应该晚一点儿出来……”

在一片黑暗的林中空地旁边，犯人的队伍停住了。就在离此不远处，有几棵树，因冬季里已经掉光了叶子，显得枝丫稀疏，依稀可见两盏马灯无声无息地摇来晃去，在向前方移动：绞刑架就是设置在那里。

“套鞋走丢了。”谢尔盖・戈洛温说。

“什么？”维尔纳没明白他说的话。

“套鞋走丢了。好冷。”

“瓦西里在哪儿？”

“不清楚。呃，在那里站着哪。”

瓦西里站在那里，像一个黑影，一动也不动。

“穆夏在哪儿呢？”

“我在这里呢。是你吗，维尔纳？”

犯人们都开始环顾四周，但是竭力避免往马灯径直移动的方向看，大家心里清楚，马灯所在就是那无声而可怕之地所在。在左边，掉光树叶的枝丫使得树木看上去更加稀疏，能看见一大片盖了雪的白色而空旷的大地。森林里湿润的风就是从那里吹过来的。

“是海。”谢尔盖・戈洛温说，他张开嘴巴使劲地吸吮潮湿的空气，“那里是大海。”

穆夏欢快地回应他：

“我的爱情像大海一样宽广！”

“穆夏，你在说什么？”

“我的爱情像大海一样宽广，生活的堤岸无法容纳它。”[11]

“我的爱情像大海一样宽广。”谢尔盖若有所思，用穆夏的语调又重复了一遍这个诗句。

“我的爱情像大海一样宽广……”维尔纳也重复了一遍诗句，忽然他十分惊喜地说：

“穆希卡[12]！你可真够年轻的呀！”

突然，就在维尔纳的耳旁，传来了一个急切的声音，气喘吁吁的茨冈诺克正在向他耳语：

“老爷，哎，老爷，这是树林子吧，啊？我的天哪，这是怎么回事！亮灯的地方有绞刑架啊？这是怎么回事，啊？”

维尔纳看了他一眼，这位茨冈诺克正在被临死前的痛苦折磨呢。

“该告别啦……”丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克说。

“再等一会儿，临行前还要宣读判决书的。”维尔纳说，“扬松在哪儿？”

扬松瘫倒在雪地里了，周围有几个人拿着东西在忙活。突然大家都闻到了一股刺鼻的氨水味。

“医生，怎么样？你们快弄好了吧？”有人不耐烦地问了一句。

“没什么，就是昏厥了。抓点雪擦擦他的耳朵就好了。他会醒过来的，可以宣读判决书了。”

就这样，一抹神秘的马灯的光亮照在那张致命的纸和一双摘了手套的苍白的手上。这张纸在抖动，这双手也在抖动，连说出话来的嗓音也在发抖：

“诸位，也许，不用读判决书了吧，你们不是都已经知道了吗？你们觉得呢？”

“不用读了。”维尔纳代替所有人回答道。照着判决书的马灯就立即熄灭了。

所有人都拒绝了让神父来为他们作终傅[13]。茨冈诺克说：

“我说呀，神父，就别来糊弄傻瓜了，这时候你倒是想宽恕我了，他们还不是照样得把我绞死。快走吧，滚一边去得啦。”

马上，一个巨大的黑影默默无言地退到树林的深处，消失不见了。看来，天色已经破晓：雪已经泛白，人影的暗色依稀可辨，森林里稀疏的树木都显露出来了，周围的氛围也愈发地悲伤和无聊。

“诸位，要两个一组过去。哪两个人一起，你们自行选择，但请动作快一点儿。”

维尔纳指着被两个卫兵架着才勉强站着的扬松，说：

“我和他一起吧。谢尔盖，你就带着瓦西里。你们先往前走。”

“好。”

“穆夏琪卡，我们就一起吧？”丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克说，“来吧，咱们就此吻别。”

大家就迅速地互相亲吻了。茨冈诺克亲吻得很用力，所以被他亲吻到的人都能感觉到他的牙齿。扬松的亲吻软绵绵的，还是无精打采的，只是半张着嘴，而且，他好像也不明就里，这时候为啥要亲吻。当谢尔盖・戈洛温和卡希林已经向前走出了几步的时候，卡希林突然站住了，用特别大的声音清楚地说了一句话，但完全是和以前判若两人的嗓音：

“永别了，同志们！”

“永别了，同志！”大家都异口同声地回答他。

他们离去了。此刻周围寂静无声。树上挂着的马灯已经不再左摇右晃。大家肃穆静候，以为那个方向会传来叫声、呻吟声、某种不期而至的声音。但那里却和这里一样寂然无声，不再晃动的马灯射出了昏黄的灯光。

“哎，我的上帝啊！”不知道是谁突然哑着嗓子冒失地来了一句。大家转头一看，原来是茨冈诺克正在饱受死前的折磨，“这两个人被绞死了！”

大家重又转过身来，一切又归于寂静。茨冈诺克忍不住难受，两手不断地在脸前扇风：

“这算怎么回事呀，啊！先生们，啊？我就只能一个人去死啦，啊？怎么也是有个伴儿才好吧。先生们呢！怎么办才好呀？”

他用灵敏的手指抓住维尔纳的一只手，一会儿握得紧紧的，一会儿又松开：

“老爷，我的好老爷，你就和我一起吧，啊？发发善心吧，别扔下我一个人呀！”

维尔纳十分痛苦地回答茨冈诺克，说：

“不行啊，亲爱的，我得和他一起呀。”

“哎呀，你这个人哪，我的上帝呀！这么说，我就只能一个人去死啦。这怎么办呢？天哪！”

穆夏往前走了一步并轻声说：

“我和你一起去吧。”

“和你？”

“是的。”

“你可拉倒吧。你可太小了点！你就不害怕吗？我看我还是一个人去死要好点。又能怎么样呢！”

“不，我才不害怕呢。”

茨冈诺克龇出了大板牙。

“你可拉倒吧。怎么说我也是个绿林强盗。你不厌恶我呀？要不最好别这么办啦，我还是一个人去死得了。我可不会生你的气。”

穆夏没有说话，在黎明微弱的光晕中，她的脸庞显得苍白，有一种神秘的美感。后来，她就一个箭步走到茨冈诺克跟前，用手搂住了他的脖子，用力亲吻了他的双唇。他呢，两只手放在她的肩上，稍稍把她推开一点儿距离，摇了摇她的身子，开始出声地亲吻她，亲她的双唇，亲她的鼻子，亲她的眼睛。

“咱们走吧！”

一个站得很近的看守不知道是怎么弄的，身子一晃，手就松开了，握着的枪直接掉到了地上。但是，他也没有弯腰去捡枪，而是愣愣地站着片刻没动，然后就转过身，像个瞎子一样，走到没人踏过的雪地里去了。

“你去哪儿？”另一个看守惊慌失措地小声喊他，“站住！”

但是，那个看守依旧没有说话，就踩着积雪，深一脚浅一脚地走进雪里。脚底下可能被什么东西绊了一下，就张着双手扑倒在雪地上。他就脸朝下，一动也不动地趴在那里。

“快把武器捡起来！你这个没用的废物！不然的话，我可要捡起来啦！”茨冈诺克冲着他们咆哮如雷，“连自己的职责都忘了！”

有人又摇晃着那两盏马灯过来了。这次轮到维尔纳和扬松了。

“永别了，老爷！”茨冈诺克大声地说，“到了那个世界，我们还做朋友，到那时，你见到了我，可千万别不理我呀。给我赏碗水就行——我在那里会热死的。”

“永别了。”

“我不情愿被绞死。”扬松还是有气无力地说。

但是，维尔纳已经挽起了他的手，这个爱沙尼亚人自己倒也走了几步。然后，大家都看到了，他站住不动了，后来就倒在雪地上了。押解的卫兵俯身过去，把他拉起来，把他拖出雪地，他还手脚乱动，试图挣脱拉他的卫兵。他为什么一声不吭？大概，他早已经忘了自己还有嗓子。

终于，那两盏马灯又重新在那个方向不再晃动了。

“这么说来，就只剩我一个人了，穆夏琪卡，”丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克伤心地说，“过去我们都是一起生活，到头来……”

“丹涅琪卡，亲爱的……”

可茨冈诺克马上过来干涉她俩说话。他抓住穆夏的手臂，好像害怕她被夺走一样，快速而认真地长篇大论了一通：

“哎呀，小姐！你是可以一个人的，你心地纯洁，所以，你去哪里，一个人都可以。你明白吗？我可不行啊。我可是一个货真价实的强盗哇，你明白了吗？我一个人可不行。我一个人，大家就会说，你又想往哪里钻，你这个江洋大盗？我还偷过马，这都是真的呀！我和她一起吧，就像……就像带着一个婴儿，懂了吧。还没弄明白？”

“我明白了。好哇，你们俩就一起去吧。让我再吻你一下吧，穆夏琪卡。”

“亲亲吧，好好亲亲吧。”茨冈诺克大度地鼓励两个女人，“事到如今，是需要好好告别一下的。”

穆夏和茨冈诺克向前走了。穆夏走路很小心，地上很滑，她习惯性地把裙子稍稍拎起来一点儿；茨冈诺克则用力挽住她的胳膊，每一步都十分小心地踩实在路面上，把和他一起的女士领到死亡跟前。

马灯挂在那里一动也不动。丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克的周围，寂静而空旷。卫兵们都沉默不语，在一天初始的宁静的晨光中，颜色还不能分辨得十分清楚，他们就是一群灰色的影子。

“就剩下我一个人了。”丹妮雅・科瓦利丘克突然开口说道，而且还叹了一口气，“谢廖扎死了，维尔纳和瓦夏也死了。只剩我一个人啦。当兵的，哎！当兵的，哎！只剩我一个人啦。一个人……”

太阳跃出了海面。

死刑犯人们的尸体被放入棺材。随后，就被运走了。这些尸体的脖子都被抻得老长，眼睛暴凸在眼眶之外，肿胀发暗的舌头，犹如一朵不知名的可怕的鲜花一样，在双唇之间，浸泡在口腔里的血沫中。这些尸体重新又沿着他们活着时来的路游荡回去。春天的雪还是那么地柔软，那么地清新，同样清新和馥郁的还有春天的气息。谢尔盖弄丢了的那只破套鞋湿漉漉、黑乎乎的，陷在雪地里。

人们就这样迎接着冉冉升起的太阳。

[11] 引自俄国小说家、诗人阿列克赛・康斯坦丁诺维奇・托尔斯泰的诗篇。——编者注

[12] 穆夏的小名。

[13] 宗教用语。天主教圣事之一，即教徒病重垂危时，由神父傅圣油并为之祝祷，则可有助于赦免罪恶，获得善终。——编者注

1. At One O’Clock, Sir

The minister was a big fat man prone to apoplexy, so, to avoid unhealthy excitement, all possible precautions were taken before he was warned of a very serious attempt on his life that was being planned. Once the minister had been seen to take this news in his stride, even managing a smile, they gave him the details. The attempt was scheduled for the following morning, when he would be going out in his carriage to deliver his report: a number of terrorists, denounced by an informer and now under roundtheclock police surveillance, were due to meet up at one o’clock, armed with bombs and revolvers, and to wait for him to come out of the front entrance. That was where they would be arrested.

‘Hang on,’ said the minister in some surprise. ‘How could they know that I’ll be going out with my report at one o’clock, when I didn’t know about it until just the other day?’

The Chief of Police spread his hands in bemusement. ‘It’s at one o’clock, sir.’

The minister shook his head, partly nonplussed, partly to acknowledge the good police work, and his dark, thick lips twisted into a sardonic smile, a smile that stayed on his face as he hurried to get out of the way of the police by following their instructions, which were to pack a few things and go off and spend the night in some hospitable mansion away from home. His wife and two children were also relocated away from the dangerous house where the bombthrowers were due to meet up the next day.

With the lights burning in the borrowed mansion and welcoming familiar faces all around him, with much bowing and scraping, accompanied by smiles and expressions of indignation, the mandarin experienced a pleasant feeling of uplift, as if he had just received, or was about to receive,a great honour that had not been anticipated. But soon the people drove away to their various destinations, the lamps were put out and a stream of bright light flowed in from the electric streetlights through the plateglass windows, looking lacy and spooky as it settled on the walls and ceiling. Penetrating intrusively into a house filled with pictures,statues and a silence also brought in from outside, this light, although gentle and hazy in itself, gave rise to uneasy feelings about the futility of bolts, fences and walls. And then, in the nighttime stillness and solitude, in an unfamiliar bedroom, the mandarin was overcome by an unbearable feeling of dread.

A martyr to kidney trouble, he had found that any sudden agitation soon had his face, hands and feet bloated with water, the effect of which was to make him seem bigger,

fatter and bulkier than ever. And now, lying there, a heap of swollen flesh weighing down the squashed bedsprings,he felt like a suffering patient, hurting all over, with a swollen face that didn’t seem to belong to him, and he couldn’t stop thinking about the cruel fate that some people had had in store for him. One after another he recalled all the recent atrocities when people of his standing, or even higher rank,had had bombs thrown at them, bombs that had torn bodies to shreds, spattered brains down dirty brick walls, and torn out teeth by the roots. And these memories had made his own fat and sickly body, now stretched out across the bed,seem like someone else’s, having taken the full blazing impact of the explosion. His arms seemed to have been torn out at the shoulders, his teeth had been scattered, his brain tissue atomized, while his legs had gone numb and he lay there, toes up, like a corpse. He made a huge effort to stir himself, gasped out loud, and gave a good cough to make himself as uncorpselike as possible. Snuggling down into the rustling bedclothes, vibrating with jangling springs, and determined to show the world that he was very much alive -nowhere near dead, miles away from death just like anyone else - he spoke out into the silence and loneliness of the bedroom with a deep staccato growl. ‘Good lads! Well done,lads! Well done!’

It was his way of praising the detectives, policemen, soldiers and other men guarding his life, who had so cleverly prevented his assassination with their timely intervention. But, however much he stirred himself, praised his men,skewed his mouth into a forced grin of contempt for the stupid terrorists - miserable failures! - he still couldn’t quite believe in his salvation. He wasn’t sure that life wouldn’t slip away from him, suddenly, any minute now. The death that those people had planned for him, which existed only in thought and intention, seemed to be still there, and it was going to stay there, it wouldn’t go away until they were caught, stripped of their bombs and dumped in a dungeon.

There it was, death, lurking in the corner, not going away,not allowed to go away, like a soldier placed on guard duty under orders from above.

‘At one o’clock, sir.’

The familiar phrase rang out in a deluge of different voices, voices of gleeful contempt, rage, pigheadedness,meaningless noise. It was as if hundreds of windup gramophones had been installed in the bedroom, and all of them,one after another, were belting out what they had been programmed to say, with the singleminded stupidity of a machine.

‘At one o’clock, sir.’

And that time, tomorrow’s ‘one o’clock’, which until recently had been no different from any other time, nothing more than hands gliding around the dial of a gold watch,had now assumed an ominous authority, hopped off the dial and taken on a life of its own, growing into a great black partition which had divided his entire life in two. It was as if there had been no other time before or after, just this one time, strutting with barefaced arrogance, the only time that had any right to a special existence of its own.

‘What’s that? What do you want?’ raged the minister through clenched teeth.

A roar came from the gramophones.

‘At one o’clock, sir.’ And the black partition gave a grin and a bow.

Gritting his teeth, the minister sat up in bed with his head in his hands. He wasn’t going to get to sleep, for sure, not on a ghastly night like this.

With a rising sense of clarity and horror, burying his face in his podgy, perfumed hands, he imagined himself getting up in the morning, in complete ignorance, having a cup of coffee, still in ignorance, and then putting on his outdoor things in the hall. Neither he, nor the porter handing him his fur coat, nor the servant still serving coffee, none of them would be aware that there was no point in drinking coffee or putting a coat on when in a few seconds all of this - the coat, his body and the coffee inside it - would be blasted to bits, taken away by death. Look, there’s the porter opening the glass door . . . And that man, the nice, kind, polite porter,with his bright blue soldier’s eyes and a chest full of medals, he, with his own hands is opening the terrible door,opening it because he is still in ignorance. And all of them smiling because of their ignorance.

‘Oho!’ he boomed suddenly, taking his hands from his face.

And then, peering ahead into the deep darkness with a firm, fixed stare, he reached forward, found a switch and put the light on. Then he got to his feet and, ignoring his slippers, walked barefoot across the carpet, taking in the unfamiliar bedroom until he found another knob and switched on a walllight. It was now nice and light, only the rumpled bed with a blanket fallen to the floor bearing witness to a horror that had still not quite run its course.

In his nightclothes,

with his beard all matted from the tossing and turning and his eyes full of anger, the mandarin looked like any other angry old man kept awake by insomnia and asthma. He had been stripped naked by the death that those people had planned for him; this had torn away the magnificence and imposing splendour which normally enveloped him. It was hard to believe that he wielded so much authority, and that this body of his, such a straightforward,runofthemill human body, was destined for a horrible death, to be destroyed in the bang and blaze of a monstrous explosion. Without getting dressed and impervious to the cold, he sat down in the first armchair that came to hand, rested his tangled beard on one hand, and stared up at the decorated plaster on the unfamiliar ceiling with a look of deep concentration and gentle wistfulness.

So, that’s it then! That’s what made him so scared and worried! That s why that thing lurks in the corner, and won’t, can’t, go away! ‘Stupid fools!’ he said, with contempt and strong feeling.‘Stupid f ools!’ he r epeated in a l ouder t one, t urning slightly towards the door so that he could be heard by anyone whom it might concern. Yes, the involvement was shared by the very people he had just referred to as good lads, the ones who, in their boundless enthusiasm, had told him every last detail of the assassination attempt.

‘Of course!’ he thought, suddenly struck by a strong idea that had come effortlessly into his mind. ‘Now that I know about it - because they’ve told me everything - I feel terrified. But for them I would have been kept in ignorance, and I would have drunk my coffee with an easy mind. Of course,there’s still death to deal with - but am I all that scared of death? I do have this kidney problem, and I’ll have to die one day, but I’m not terrified, because my life goes on in ignorance. And those idiots kept saying, “At one o’clock, sir.” Stupid fools! They thought I would be delighted, whereas That Thing lurks in the corner and won’t go away. It won’t go away because it’s me thinking. And it’s not death that is terrifying, only my knowing about it. And it would be totally impossible to live if a man were to know with complete certainty the date and time when he was sure to die. And all I get from those idiots is that warning: “At one o’clock, sir.” ’

He was suddenly aware of a nice sensation, a pleasant uplift, as if someone had told him he was immortal in every way, and was never going to die. And, with a renewed sense of himself as a man of strength and intelligence standing out from that herd of stupid fools who were making such a senseless and brazen incursion into the mystery of the future, he found himself contemplating the bliss of not knowing things, though he did so with the weary thought processes of a sickly old man who has seen it all. Nothing that lives, neither man nor beast, is allowed to know the date and time of his death. Only recently he had been ill; the doctors had told him he was going to die and he ought to make his final arrangements. But he didn’t believe them, and, sure enough, he had remained alive. And something similar had happened when he had been young: his life was going nowhere, and he decided to commit suicide. He got a revolver ready, wrote his last letters, and even fixed the time of his death - but at the last moment he had thought better of it. At the last moment, anything can change, something completely unexpected can turn up, and this means that no one can ever tell himself when he is going to die.

‘At one o’clock, sir.’ That’s what those kindhearted asses had told him, and although they only told him because the death had already been prevented, the knowledge of its possible timing had been enough to fill him with horror. It was quite feasible that he could be killed one day, but it wouldn’t happen tomorrow - no, not tomorrow - he was immortal, and he could sleep easy. Stupid fools, they had no idea of the great law they had subverted, of the abyss they had opened up, by saying, with such idiotic kindheartedness, ‘At one o’clock, sir.’

‘No, not at one o’clock, sir; we don’t know when. No, we don’t know when. What’s that?’

‘Nothing.’ An answer from the darkness. ‘Nothing.’

‘No. You were saying something.’

‘Nothing. Nothing that matters. What I say is - tomorrow at one o’clock.’

And with a sharp sinking feeling, he realized there would be no sleep, rest or joy for him until that damned dark hour filched from the watchface had gone by. Of the knowledge to be gleaned by no living creature only a shadow remained, standing in the corner, but it was enough to blot out the light and swamp a man with the impenetrable darkness of horror. The fear of death, once aroused, had spread all over his body, got into his bones, and it peeped out, palefaced, at every pore.

Now it wasn’t tomorrow’s assassins that scared him - they had gone, disappeared into oblivion, merging into the host of enemies and hostile forces besetting his human existence - what he feared was something swift and inexorable: an apoplectic fit, a heart attack, a silly, skinny artery like the aorta suddenly giving way to bloodpressure and rupturing like a tightly stretched glove on bloated fingers.

He was horrified by his own short, fat neck, and he couldn’t stand the sight of his stubby, podgy fingers or the shock of realizing how short they were and how they were filled with deadly moisture. And if, earlier on in the darkness, he had felt the need to stir himself in order to seem uncorpselike, now, in this horribly cold and hostile brightness, it seemed terrifyingly impossible to move a muscle and reach for a cigarette or ring for assistance. His nerves were on edge, and every nerve seemed like a taut wire standing on end, topped by a tiny head with eyes staring in horror and a gaping mouth twitching in spasms and soundlessly gasping. He had no means of breathing.

And suddenly, down below in the darkness, in all the dust and cobwebs, an electric bell came to life somewhere up on the ceiling. A little metal clapper whirred in a spasm of horror against the rim of an echoing cup; then it stopped, then it rang again in a solid stream of jangling horror. It was Sir, ringing from his room.

Servants ran in. In some places among the chandeliers and on the walls some of the lamps lit up, not enough to provide light, but enough to allow shadows. They spread themselves everywhere, rising up in corners and crawling out across the ceiling, clinging tenuously to every protuberance and sticking to the walls. You couldn’t tell where they had been before, these silent shadows, ugly and uncountable, the voiceless souls of voiceless objects.

A deeply resonating bass voice spoke out loud and clear. Then they telephoned for a doctor. Sir was feeling poorly. Sir’s wife was also sent for.

2. Sentence: Death By hanging

It all worked out as the police had anticipated. Four terrorists - three men and one woman - armed with bombs, infernal machines and revolvers, were seized outside the entrance, and a fifth was discovered and arrested in the conspirators’ flat, she being the landlady. They also seized a large quantity of dynamite, some semicharged bombs and other weapons. All those arrested were very young; the eldest of the men was twentyeight years old, the younger woman was only nineteen. Their trial took place in the same fortress where they had been imprisoned after arrest; it was summary justice conducted in secret, the way they did things in those merciless times.

In court, all five behaved calmly; they were very seriousminded and very thoughtful. So great was their contempt for the judges that none of them wanted to put on a show of heroics with an uncalledfor smile or a false display of triumphalism. Their calmness was balanced against a need to shield their souls, and the great darkness about to descend upon them in death, from the vile, intrusive gaze of outsiders.

Sometimes they refused to answer; on other occasions their answers were laconic, matteroffact and strictly relevant, as if directed not at the judges but at the keepers of statistics so that special forms could be filled in. Three of them, one woman and two men, gave their real names, and two refused to name themselves, thus remaining unknown to the judges. And towards everything that went on in the court they displayed the kind of curiosity that is diluted by emerging through a misty haze typical of people who are either seriously ill or obsessed by one huge, allconsuming idea. They would look up suddenly to catch an unusually interesting word as it flew past, and then go back to where their thoughts had been interrupted.

Nearest to the judges stood one of the accused who had given his name as Sergey Golovin, the son of a retired colonel, himself a former officer. He was still a young man, blond and stocky, so full of good health that neither imprisonment nor the prospect of imminent death could wipe the bloom off his cheeks or take the youthful expression of naïve happiness out of his lightblue eyes. He never stopped plucking at his scruffy blond beard, which he had not yet grown used to, and he stared fixedly out of the window, narrowing his eyes and blinking. This was taking place at the end of winter, when, between the snowy blasts and the days of fog and frost, the approaching spring was sending out a herald in the form of a clear, warm, sunny day, or even a single hour, so springlike and radiant with the greedy passion of young life that the sparrows in the street went wild with joy, and people seemed almost intoxicated. And today, through the top window, uncleaned and accumulating dust since last summer, an unusually beautiful sky could be seen. At first glance it seemed to consist of a milkygrey, smoky haze, but on closer examination the eye could make out a brighter blue beginning to shine through, deeper, sharper and ever more boundless. And by revealing itself gradually, with its purity veiled in a cloud of mist, it seemed as winsome as a young girl and as easy to fall in love with. And Sergey Golovin squinted up at that sky through his long, fluffy eyelashes, first with one eye then the other, while pulling at his little beard and looking deeply preoccupied. On one occasion, his fingers jerked and his face screwed itself into a spasm of childish delight, but a glance around the court was enough to extinguish this like a spark underfoot. Almost immediately a change came over the redness in his cheeks; without really turning pale, they took on an earthy, deathly shade of grey and his whitetipped fingers twisted bits of his fluffy hair, painfully torn out by the roots, in a vicelike grip. Nevertheless, the joy of living and of springtime won through, and within minutes his young, ingenuous face was turned up again towards the spring sky.

It was in the same direction, up at the sky, that the anonymous pale young girl with the petname of Musya also turned her eyes. She was younger than Golovin, but the severity of her manner and the black gleam in her proudly focused eyes gave her an older look. Only her soft and very slender neck and her no less slender girlish arms bore witness to her age, though there was also an indefinable something about her, to do with youth itself, that rang out in her voice with true clarity of tone and the purest harmony, like a wellloved musical instrument tuned to perfection, adding musicality to the simplest of her words and exclamations. She looked pale, but it was not the pallor of death, it was that special flaming white heat that occurs when a huge great fire seems to have been lit inside a person so that their body glows with light from within as if it was shining through the finest Sèvres porcelain. She sat there scarcely moving a muscle; only now and then did a surreptitious movement betray the fingering of a circular mark on the third finger of her right hand, the trace of a ring recently removed. And she stared at the sky not from any tender feelings or happy memories but because, in this dingy hall of officialdom, that patch of blue sky was the most beautiful place, a realm of purity and truth that was not trying to winkle secrets out of her eyes.

Sergey Golovin had won the sympathy of the court; she was the one they hated.

Alongside her, the unidentified man known as Werner sat there equally unmoving, in a rather affected pose, hands folded between his knees. If you can slam a face like a thick door, the unidentified man had banged shut the iron door of his face and secured it with an iron padlock. He looked down at the dirty floorboards without stirring, and you couldn’t tell whether he was calm or intensely agitated, whether his thoughts were miles away or he was concentrating on the police giving their evidence. He was a small man with noble features finely drawn. His winsome appearance and sensitivity brought to mind a moonlit night in some southern clime under shadowy cypresses at the seaside, yet he also evoked a sense of formidable inner strength, indomitable selfassurance, cold control and heroic will. On his lips the very politeness with which he gave his terse, measured responses, accompanied by a slight bow, had an ominous ring, and if the prison smock looked like a ludicrous joke on the other prisoners, on this man it was such an alien form of dress that it went completely unnoticed. And although the other terrorists had been caught in possession of bombs and infernal machines, Werner was seized with nothing more than a black revolver; for some reason the judges took him to be the leader and when they addressed him, they did so with a touch of deference, in a laconic, businesslike manner.

The next one along was Vassily Kashirin, a man totally obsessed by an excruciating fear of death, accompanied by an equally desperate desire to suppress this dread and keep it from the judges. Since early morning, when they had been brought before the court, his galloping heartbeat had left him scarcely able to breathe, permanent beads of sweat stood out on his forehead, his hands were just as sweaty yet also cold, and a cold, sweaty shirt stuck to his body, hampering his movements. With a supreme effort of will, he stopped his fingers from trembling, his voice remained firm and clear, and his eyes kept steady. He took in nothing of his surroundings, voices seemed to come at him through a fog, and back into the same fog he dispatched his desperate responses in an attempt to reply in strong, loud tones. But once he had responded, he immediately forgot what had been asked and how he had answered, and relapsed into a terrible, wordless struggle with himself. And death emanated from him so obviously that the judges avoided looking at him, and his age was as hard to guess as that of a dead body well into decay. According to his papers he was only twentythree years old. Once or twice Werner gently nudged him on the knee, and each time he responded with a simple phrase. ‘It’s all right.’

The most terrible moments were when he felt a sudden urge to scream, to yell out with the desperate wordless cry of a wild beast. When this happened, he nudged up against Werner, who responded to him without looking up. ‘It’s all right, Vasya. Won’t be long.’

Then came the fifth terrorist, Tanya Kovalchuk, who, despite her own agonizing despair, enfolded the others with a watching maternal eye. She had not yet had any children, being as young and rosycheeked as Sergey Golovin, but she seemed like a mother to them all; there was so much concern and limitless affection in her every glance, every smile and all her terror. She completely ignored the court as if it were a kind of sideshow; all she took in was the way they answered the questions - was that a tremor in the voice, is that a show of fear, does that one need a drink of water?

She was too anguished to look at Vasya; all she could do was wring her chubby fingers. She watched Musya and Werner with pride, admiration and a look of serious concentration on her face. She did her best to pass a smile over to Sergey Golovin.

‘Dear boy, he’s looking up at the sky. Go on, keep on looking up there, my darling boy,’ she thought as she watched him. ‘But, oh dear, Vasya. What is it, what’s wrong with him? What can I do about him? I can’t say anything. That would make things worse. It might make him cry.’

And like a still pond at dawn reflecting every passing cloud, her sweet, kind, chubby face reflected every quick movement and every thought coming from the four of them. The idea that she was also being judged and would also be hanged never crossed her mind, such was her profound indifference. It was in her rooms that the supply of bombs and dynamite has been discovered and, oddly enough, she had been the one to fire at the policemen, wounding one of them in the head.

It was getting on for eight o’clock when the court proceedings came to an end. The sky had gradually turned dark blue and faded before the eyes of Musya and Sergey Golovin, but instead of radiating the pink hue and gentle smile of a summer’s evening, it just clouded over, getting greyer and greyer, and then suddenly it was all cold and wintry. Golovin heaved a sigh, stretched himself and glanced up at the window a couple of times, but there was nothing to be seen beyond the cold, dark night, so, still fingering his little beard, he turned like a curious child to have a good look at the judges and the soldiers with their guns, and he smiled across at Tanya Kovalchuk. As for Musya, when the sky faded, she avoided looking down at the floor and calmly transferred her gaze to a little cobweb in one corner that gently wobbled as warm air rose invisibly from the steamheating system. She stayed like that until sentence was pronounced.

After the sentencing, the condemned men and women took leave of their frockcoated lawyers, avoiding eye contact with these pitifully distraught and guiltridden people before coming together briefly in the doorway to exchange a few remarks.

‘It’s all right, Vasya. Won’t be long now,’ said Werner.

‘Yes, brother, I’m all right,’ said Kashirin in a loud, calm voice, almost enjoying himself.

And indeed, his face took on a pinkish hue, no longer like that of a decaying corpse.

Bugger them all, they’ve hanged the lot of us,’ said Golovin, reduced to a simple curse.

‘We had it coming to us,’ came Werner’s calm reply.

‘Tomorrow they’ll give formal pronouncement of the sentence,and we’ll all be locked up together,’ said Kovalchuk,reassuringly. ‘We’ll be together right up to the execution.’

Musya said nothing. Then she took a firm step forward.

3. Not Hang Me

Two weeks before the terrorists’ trial, different officials from the same regional military court had tried a peasant, Ivan Yanson, and sentenced him to death.

This man, Ivan Yanson, was a labourer employed by a wealthy farmer, virtually indistinguishable from all the other workmen in the local peasantry. He was Estonian by birth, from Wesenberg, and, after moving on from farm to farm over the years, he had ended up near the capital. He spoke very poor Russian, and since his master was a Russian, Lazarev by name, and there were no Estonians in the locality, he had hardly spoken a word for pretty well the past two years. Not that he seemed to have any desire for conversation. He didn’t talk to people, but he didn’t talk to the animals either; he kept quiet while watering or harnessing a horse, slowly and tentatively shuffling around it, and when the horse, disconcerted by the silence, started to play up and jump about, he would lay into it with a big whip, not saying a word. He would beat him viciously, with a cold and bitter determination, and if this was happening when he was roaring drunk, he would work himself up into a frenzy. Way back at the house you could hear the lashing whip and the staccato clatter of hooves from the scared and suffering animal as they echoed on the floorboards of the barn. The master would give Yanson a beating for having whipped the horse, but the Estonian proved incorrigible, so he gave up on him.

Once or twice a month Yanson got drunk, and this usually occurred on days when he drove the master to the big railway station, which had a bar. Having dropped the master off, he would drive out half a mile or so from the station, park the horse and sledge in some deep snow off the road, and wait patiently for the train to depart. The sledge would stand there, leaning to one side, almost recumbent, with the horse up to his belly in a snowdrift, legs splayed, occasionally nuzzling the soft, crunchy snow and licking at it, while Yanson sprawled awkwardly across the sledge, apparently dozing. The drooping earflaps of his tatty cap dangled down impotently like a setter’s ears, and his little buttonnose looked red and runny.

Then Yanson would go back to the station and lose no time in getting himself drunk. He completed the return trip to the farm, a good seven miles, galloping flatout. The shattered and terrified little horse ran itself into the ground, the sledge rocked all over the place, banking, bending and crashing against posts, while Yanson, who had dropped the reins and was in danger of flying out onto the road with every minute that passed, halfsang and halfyelled incoherently obscure bits of Estonian. But more often than not, he didn’t sing, he kept silent, gritting his teeth against an inscrutable upsurge of rage, pain and exuberance, and barrelled on, blind to oncoming traffic, without shouting out warnings or slowing down as he careered around bends or down slopes. How he avoided running somebody down or smashing himself to death during one of these mad chases is anybody’s guess.

He should have been sacked long ago, as he had been from other jobs, but he came cheap and the other workers weren’t much better, so he stayed on for two years. Yanson’s life was one in which nothing ever happened. One day he received a letter written in Estonian, but, since he was illiterate and there weren’t any other Estonianspeakers, the letter went unread, and in a spasm of savage, fanatical indifference, as if he had no idea that the letter might contain news from home, Yanson chucked it onto the manure heap. On one occasion, apparently lusting for a woman, Yanson tried it on with the cook, but he got nowhere; he was turned down and laughed at. He was a little runt of a chap with a sickly, spotty face and muddycoloured eyes that looked sleepy and boozy. But Yanson took this setback on the chin, and made no more approaches to the cook.

But, although he didn’t speak much, Yanson was always listening. He listened to the dreary snowcovered countryside with small pats of frozen manure looking like rows of little snowy graves, and the darkblue distant haze and the humming telegraph poles and people talking to each other. What the countryside and telegraph poles spoke about was known only to him, but what people were saying to each other worried him: nothing but rumours - of murder, robbery and arson. And one night a special sound had been heard: in the next village a little church bell rang out with a thin, helplessly tinkling noise like that of a carriagebell. Strangers had ridden up, pillaged the wealthy farm, murdered the owner and his wife, and set fire to the house.

And now anxiety was the rule, even on Yanson’s farm.

The dogs were allowed to run free not just at nighttime but also by day, and at night the master slept with a gun at his side. He wanted to give Yanson the same kind of gun, an older version with only one barrel, but the Estonian twisted it in his hands and refused inexplicably to accept it. The master, at a loss to understand the reason for his refusal, cursed him up hill and down dale, but the reason was simple: Yanson had more faith in his Finnish knife than this rusty old thing.

‘Be the death of me,’ said Yanson with a sleepy look in his beady, glassy eyes.

The master threw up his hands in desperation. ‘You’re a stupid fool, Ivan. Can’t do a damn thing with farmhands like you.’

And one winter night, when the other farmhand had been dispatched to the station, that same Ivan Yanson who didn’t believe in having a gun had carried out a very complex attempt at armed robbery, murder and rape. The way he did it was surprisingly simple: he locked the cook in her kitchen and then, at his leisure, with the air of a man dead on his feet for lack of sleep, he approached the master from behind and stabbed him repeatedly in the back. The master collapsed unconscious, and the mistress ran around the room screaming, while Yanson, baring his teeth and brandishing his knife, began ransacking the trunks and chests of drawers. He found some money, and then, apparently noticing the mistress for the first time, he surprised even himself by making advances with every intention of raping her. But by now he had dropped the knife, and when the mistress turned out to be stronger than him, not only did she decline to be raped, she came near to throttling the life out of him. At this point, the master showed signs of stirring, the cook was banging away with the ovenfork in an effort to break the kitchen door down, and Yanson ran outside. He was caught within the hour, squatting in a corner of the barn and striking match after dead match in an attempt at arson.

A few days later the master died from bloodpoisoning, and Yanson took his place in a queue of other robbers and murderers waiting to be tried and sentenced to death. In court he was the same as always: a puny little man with a spotty face and a sleepy look in his beady, glassy eyes. Somehow he didn’t seem to fully grasp what was going on, and he looked totally indifferent; his white eyelashes blinked as his lifeless eyes took in the unfamiliar courtroom in all its pomp without registering any curiosity, and he picked his nose crudely with a stiff, horny finger. Only those who might have seen him in church of a Sunday could have guessed that he had made an attempt at smartening up for the occasion; he wore a dirty, red knitted scarf around his neck and he had dampened his hair down in a few places that looked smoother and lay down flatter than on the other side, where it curled up in thin, blond tufts like wisps of straw left behind on a scanty hailblown meadow.

When the sentence was pronounced: ‘Death by Hanging’,

Yanson was shaken. He blushed to the roots of his hair and began twisting the scarf off and on, as if it was throttling him. Then he waved his hands about crazily, pointed to the judge who had read out the sentence, and spoke to the judge who had not.

‘She said to hang me.’

‘Who is “she”?’ came the deep voice of the presiding judge, who had read out the sentence.

There were smiles all round, hidden behind moustaches and court papers, but Yanson levelled his forefinger at the president, and scowled at him in an angry response.

‘You!’

‘Well?’

Yanson turned his eyes back to the unspeaking judge, who was struggling not to smile, in whom he sensed an ally, someone not party to the sentence, and he said again, ‘She said to hang me. Not hang me.’

‘Take the prisoner away.’

But Yanson had time to repeat what he had said, with grim determination. ‘Not hang me.’

He looked so stupid, with anger written all over his little face, as he strove vainly to invest it with gravitas, and with his finger still pointing, that even the soldier escorting him broke the rules by speaking to him in a low voice as he walked him away. ‘You’re a stupid fool, laddie.’

‘Not hang me,’ Yanson persisted.

‘Sorry, chum. You’re getting strung up. No time to kick.’

‘Hey, that’s enough!’ cried the other escort, incensed by this. But he gave in and couldn’t help adding, ‘You went out robbing. Why did you have to take a human life? Now you’re going to hang.’

‘Any chance of a pardon?’ asked the first guard, beginning to feel sorry for Yanson.

‘You what? Pardon the likes of ’im? Anyway, that’s enough talking.’

But Yanson had already stopped talking. He was locked up in the same cell he had been in for the past month and had got used to, as before he had got used to getting beaten, drinking vodka and looking at the snowy fields with round hillocks like a cemetery. He even felt a surge of happiness when he saw his bed and his window grille, and when they gave him some food - not having eaten anything all day. The only nasty thing was what had gone on in court, but he couldn’t think about that, he didn’t know how to. Death by hanging was beyond his imagination.

Even though Yanson had been given a death sentence, there were lots of others like him; in that prison he wasn’t seen as a special criminal. This meant that the staff talked to him without fear or respect, the way they talked to all the prisoners who hadn’t been sentenced to death. It seemed as if his death wasn’t really death at all. The head guard, when he heard what the sentence was, spoke as if he was teaching him a lesson.

‘Well, brother. They’ve gone and hung you then!’

‘When will they hang me?’ asked Yanson cautiously.

The guard gave it a moment’s thought. ‘Well, brother, it’s like this. You’re going to have to wait while they gets a party of you together. They won’t do it for one - especially one like you. They wants the numbers up.’

‘But when ? ’ Yanson insisted. It didn’t offend him in the slightest that he wasn’t worth hanging on his own, and he didn’t believe it anyway. He thought it was a pretext for delaying the execution and then cancelling it altogether. He felt bucked by this. The uncertain and terrible moment that he couldn’t begin to think about was moving steadily away into the distance, becoming as unlikely as a fairytale, no different from any other death.

‘You go on and on about when,’ said the guard in exasperation (he was a stupid and gloomy old man). ‘It’s not like hanging a dog. You don’t just nip round the back of the shed, and that’s it. Stupid fool, is that what you want?’

‘I don’t want at all!’ Yanson scowled with pleasure. ‘It was her what said to hang me. I don’t want!’

And he gave a little laugh, perhaps for the first time in his life, a jarring, idiotic laugh that was strangely cheerful and enjoyable. Like a goose honking, ‘haw, haw, haw!’ The guard looked at him in amazement, then gave a grim scowl; this absurd display of cheeriness from a man who was due to be executed was an insult to the prison and to execution itself, and it turned them both into something weird. Suddenly, for one moment, a split second, the old guard who had spent all his life in that prison, for whom its laws were the laws of nature, saw that place, and life itself, revealed as a madhouse, with himself, the head guard, as the chief madman.

‘Damn you! Fuck you!’ said the guard. ‘What are you grinning at? You’re not in the pub now.’

‘I don’t want! Haw, haw, haw!’ said Yanson, still laughing.

‘Satan!’ said the head guard, feeling the need to cross himself.

No one could have looked less like Satan than this man with his flabby little face, but there was something in his goosey honking that undermined the sanctity and strength of the prison. Let him go on honking a bit longer and you could see the walls crumbling away and the rusty grilles collapsing, and the chief guard leading the prisoners out through the gate . . . ‘There you are, gentlemen, have a stroll around town, or maybe some of you would like to see the countryside?’ Satan!

But by now Yanson had stopped laughing. He was left with a sly scowl on his face.

‘All right. Watch it, then!’ said the chief, with the vaguest of threats, and off he went, looking back over his shoulder.

All that evening Yanson was calm and you might even say cheerful. He kept on repeating the same phrase under his breath, ‘Not hang me,’ and it was so convincing, so full of wisdom, so incontrovertible, that there was nothing to worry about. His crime was long forgotten, except for the odd pang of regret for not having managed to rape the mistress. Soon he even forgot about that.

Every morning Yanson asked when he was going to be hanged, and every morning the chief gave the same angry response.

‘It’ll come, Satan, just you wait.’ And off he would go as fast as he could before Yanson could burst out laughing again.

And because of these identically repeated words, plus the fact that each day got off to a start, proceeded on its way and came to an end like every other ordinary day, Yanson became totally convinced there wouldn’t be an execution. It didn’t take him long to put the court right out of his mind and for days on end he lay sprawling on his bed, his head full of vague but joyful dreams about the gloomy, snowy fields with their little hillocks, the station bar, and something beyond that, gleaming in the distance. In the jail he was well fed, and quicker than you might think, within only a few days, he had put on weight and begun to strut about the place.

‘By now she would have been in love with me like this,’ he thought, with the mistress in mind, ‘I’m fattened out now, no worse than the master.’

What he did miss was a drink of vodka - a quick drink followed by a mad charge with the horse.

When the terrorists had been arrested, news of them reached the prison, and when Yanson asked his usual question, the chief gave a new response, sharp and unexpected. ‘Won’t be long now.’

His look was calm, and his speech heavy with meaning. ‘Won’t be long now. About a week, I’d say.’

Yanson’s face paled, and his glassy eyes went cloudy as if he was nodding off as he spoke. ‘You’re joking?’

‘You were the one who couldn’t wait, and you’re the joker. We are not allowed jokes. You like joking, but we are not allowed jokes,’ said the chief guard in a lofty tone before walking away.

By the evening Yanson had shrunk down a little. His skin, which had been stretched and temporarily smoothed down, had now shrivelled into a mass of tiny wrinkles, and in some places it looked quite droopy. His eyes had become shrouded with sleep, and his every movement was slow and sluggish, as if each turn of the head, fingermovement or footstep was a complex and cumbersome procedure requiring a lot of careful forethought. At bedtime he lay down on his bunk without closing his eyes, and they stayed like that, open but sleepy, all night long.

‘Aha!’ said the chief with some satisfaction when he saw him next morning. ‘See, me old darlin’. This ain’t no pub.’

It was with the satisfied feeling of a scientist whose experiment has come out right again that he scrutinized the condemned man from head to toe. Now things would go the way they should. Satan had been put to shame, the sanctity of the prison and execution had been reestablished, and now there was sympathy, even some genuine pity, in the way that the old man asked his questions.

‘Do you want to see anybody? No?’

‘What is this “see anybody”?’

‘Well, just to say goodbye. Maybe your mother, or a

brother?’

‘Not hang me,’ said Yanson in a soft voice, glancing sideways at the chief guard. ‘I don’t want.’

The guard took a look at him, and flung up a hand without saying another word.

By evening Yanson was a little calmer. The day had been such an ordinary one, the light from the cloudy winter sky had been so ordinary, the footsteps in the corridor and the animated talk had been so ordinary, and the sour smell of the cabbage soup had been so ordinary and so normal that once again he had ceased to believe in the execution. But as night came on, he began to feel terribly scared. Earlier on Yanson had treated night as nothing more than darkness, a particular period of blackness which you have to sleep through, but now he was aware of its essentially mysterious and ominous character. To avoid believing in death you must see and hear ordinary things around you: footsteps, voices, light, sour cabbage soup, and now everything was out of the ordinary. This silence and this darkness were in themselves akin to death.

And the more night dragged on, the more terrifying it became. With the naivety of a primitive creature or a child, who thinks all things are possible, Yanson felt like telling the sun to start shining. He begged and entreated the sun to do that, but night went on remorselessly, stretching its black hours out over the earth, and there was no force that could stop it in its course. And this impossibility, which had never before penetrated Yanson’s feeble brain with such clarity, filled him with terror; without yet being fully aware of it, he was now sensing the proximity of death, and had placed one dying foot on the first step of the scaffold.

Daylight calmed him down again, but then the night filled him with horror, and things went along like this until the night when he saw sense and admitted the inevitability of death - in three days’ time, in the early morning, at sunrise.

He had never thought about what it would be like to die, and he had no image of death, though now he could clearly sense - see and feel - that it had come into his cell to feel its way around and seek him out. And in an effort to save himself, he began running around the cell.

But the cell was so small it seemed to have no acute angles, only obtuse ones, and he kept on being bounced back into the middle. And there was nothing to hide behind. The door was locked, and there was light. He said nothing as his upper body bumped into the wall several times and once banged against the door with a hollow clang.

He crashed into something, and fell to the floor facedown.

It was now that he felt he was in its grasp. And as he lay there on his belly, clinging to the hard surface of the dark and dirty floor, Yanson gave a wail of terror. He lay there yelling at the top of his voice until they came to see to him. And even when they had picked him up, put him back on his bunk and poured cold water over his head, he still refused to open his rigidly closed eyes. When he halfopened one eye, all he saw was light in an empty corner and somebody’s boot in the open space, and this set him off wailing again.

But the cold water began to do its work. He was also helped by the fact that the duty officer was the same old man as before, and he gave him a few medicinal slaps around the head. And this sensation of being alive did manage to dispel death, Yanson did open his eyes, and then he slept soundly through the rest of the night with his brain greatly befogged. He lay on his back with his mouth open and a lot of loud, melodious snoring. And the whites of his eyes shone with the smoothness of a deathly pallor through his partly closed eyelids.

And from now on everything in the world - day and night, footsteps, voices and sour cabbage soup - blurred into a single shock of horror, plunging him into a state of primitive bewilderment beyond comprehension. His feeble mind could not reconcile the two monstrous contradictions: the normality of daylight and cabbage soup versus the idea that tomorrow, or the day after, he was going to die. He thought of nothing, had no sense of time passing; he just stood there facing this contradiction in silent horror, with his brain split in two. And, because his face was its normal colour, neither paler nor redder than usual, he seemed to be at peace. Except that he had stopped eating and didn’t sleep a wink. No, he spent the whole night either curled up on a stool, with his legs tucked timorously away, or creeping quietly around the room, with his sleepy eyes darting everywhere. His mouth hung halfopen all the time, as if he was in a permanent state of extreme shock, and before picking up the simplest everyday object, he would give it a close, dullwitted scrutiny and accept it only with great reluctance.

And once he had become like this, the guard and the soldier deputed to watch him through the little grille began to ignore him. His behaviour seemed normal for a condemned man, and the chief guard likened it (without ever having had the experience himself) to the stunning of cattle by the butt of an axe prior to slaughter.

‘He’s been stunned. From now on until he dies, he won’t feel a thing,’ he would say, observing him with a seasoned eye. ‘Can you hear me, Ivan? Eh? Ivan!’

‘Not hang me,’ came the lacklustre response from Yanson,

again with a drooping jaw.

‘If you hadn’t murdered somebody, they wouldn’t be hanging you,’ said the chief guard, still a young man, but an imposing figure with a chestful of medals. ‘You did the killing - now you don’t want to be hung.’

‘You wanted to kill, and get away with it. Stupid as hell,

but damned clever.’

‘I don’t want,’ said Yanson.

‘All right, my friend. You carry on not wanting. It’s up to you,’ said the senior man indifferently. ‘But you might be better off not talking nonsense, and sorting out your effects. Still things to be done.’

‘He hasn’t got any. Shirt and trousers, that’s it. Oh, plus the fur cap. Quite a dandy with that!’

And so the time passed until Thursday. And then, at midnight on Thursday, a lot of people walked into Yanson’s cell, and a gentleman wearing epaulettes spoke to him. ‘Right. Get yourself ready. Time to go.’

Yanson, moving at his usual slow and weary pace, got dressed in everything he had, and finished by tying the dirty red scarf around his neck. As he watched him getting dressed, the same gentleman, cigarette in hand, said to somebody, ‘Nice warm day, today. Real touch of spring.’

Yanson’s tiny eyes were glued up, he was full of sleep and his footsteps dragged so stiffly that the guard spoke to him. ‘Come on, get a move on. He’s gone to sleep!’

Suddenly Yanson came to a halt. ‘I don’t want,’ he said,weakly.

They grabbed him under the armpits and got him going; he took an obedient step forward, lifting his shoulders. Outside he was assailed by a springtime breath of moist air, and his little nose began to run. Although it was nighttime, the thaw was underway and drops of water cascaded merrily from above, tinkling on the stones below. And as he waited for the policemen to get into the black, unlit carriage,stooping and jingling their swords, Yanson wiped his runny nose lazily with one finger and straightened his badly tied scarf.

4. Us Lads From Oryol

The same regional military court judges that had tried Yanson also sentenced another man to death by hanging, a peasant from Yeléts in the province of Orlov, by the name of Mikhail Golubets, better known as Gypsy Mike, and a Tartar by birth. His latest crime, proven beyond doubt, was the murder of three people in an armed robbery, but his murky career went far back into the mysterious depths of time. There were vague rumours of his implication in any number of other robberies and murders, and he had left behind him in his wake much blood and drunken depravity. He described himself as a villain quite openly and sincerely, though he could also be ironical, as when he claimed allegiance to those who called themselves, using the latest catchphrase, ‘expropriators’. Seeing that denial would get him nowhere with his latest crime, he willingly confessed in detail, though when he was asked about his earlier career, he would do no more than bare his teeth, give a little whistle, and say, ‘Look for the wind in the fields!’

But when they put him under pressure, Gypsy Mike struck an attitude of stolid and dignified concentration.

‘Us lads from Oryol, we’re all nutcases,’ he would say in thoughtfully measured tones. ‘Oryol lads is best. We can outthieve the rest . . . We’re fathers and mothers - of all thieving brothers. But thieves from Yeléts - is the finest and best! Can’t say fairer than that.’

He was called Gypsy Mike because of the way he looked and his constant thieving. He was ridiculously darkhaired and skinny, with spots of yellow sunburn on his high Tartar cheekbones; he had the look of a horse when he rolled the whites of his eyes, and he galloped around everywhere. His eyes didn’t settle easily, but when they did, they were terrifyingly direct and eager to take things in; objects that he had glanced at seemed to lose something, transferring part of themselves to him and taking on a different character. A cigarette that had been no more than looked at by him became as repellent and disgusting to pick up as one that had been in somebody’s mouth. A kind of permanent fretfulness lived inside him, twisting him like braided rope or sending him flying all over the place in a shower of whirling sparks. Even when he needed water, he drank it like a horse, almost by the bucketful.

In court he answered all questions by jumping to his feet and giving a straight response in the tersest terms.

‘Right!’

Sometimes he added emphasis: ‘Rrright!’

And once, quite unexpectedly, when the subject had moved on, he jumped up and addressed the president.

‘Permission to whistle, sir!’

‘What on earth for?’ said the judge in surprise.

‘They was giving evidence how I used to signal to my mates. This is how. Highly interesting.’

The president had his doubts, but permission was given. Gypsy Mike lost no time in sticking four fingers in his mouth, two from each hand, and rolling his eyes in a frenzied glare. The lifeless atmosphere of the courtroom was pierced by a true wildman banditwhistle fit to deafen a horse, make it rear up on its haunches, and drain the colour from any human face. The desperate agony of a man being murdered, the savage thrill of a killer, a terrible pang of foreboding, a call for help, the darkness of foul weather in an autumn night, a sense of solitude - all of these things were there, in that shrieking, wailing sound, which belonged to neither man nor beast.

The president called out, and waved at Gypsy Mike, who obediently stopped his whistling. And like a solo singer who has triumphantly performed a difficult operatic aria which was always going to succeed, he took his seat, wiped his wet fingers down his smock and regarded his audience with an air of satisfaction.

‘True villain!’ said one of the judges, rubbing an ear.

But the other one, with a wide Russian beard and eyes no less Tartarlike than those of the defendant, cast a dreamy look into space above the gypsy’s head, then gave a grin and a different response: ‘That really was most interesting.’

And with easy hearts, without pity or any feelings of remorse, the judges sentenced Gypsy Mike to death.

‘Right!’ said Gypsy Mike when the sentence had been pronounced. ‘Out in the open on a crossbeam. That’s right!’

And, turning to his escort, he said with a young blade’s bravado, ‘Right. Let’s go, miseryguts. Hang onto your gun, or I’ll have it!’

The soldier glared, keeping a wary eye on him, exchanged glances with his comrade and fingered the bolt on his gun.

His opposite number did the same. And all the way back to the prison the soldiers seemed to be walking on air; totally absorbed in the criminal, they couldn’t feel the ground under their feet, and they were oblivious to the passage of time or any sense of themselves.

Like Yanson, Gypsy Mike was to spend seventeen days in prison before execution. All seventeen passed so quickly - like a single day - in an inextinguishable dream of escape, freedom and life. The restless spirit that had taken over Gypsy Mike’s personality was now contained within walls, grilles and a blank window, with nothing visible, and it had turned all its furious energy in on itself, burning his ideas away to nothing, like coals scattered across the floor. It was as if he was in a drunken stupor: a cloud of brilliant but halfformed images swarmed through his mind, jostling and blurring as they whirled past in a dazzling, unstoppable rush, all of them going in the same direction - towards escape, freedom and life. Some days Gypsy Mike would flare his nostrils like a horse and spend hours sniffing the air, imagining the smell of hemp and something burning with colourless, acrid smoke; sometimes he would spin around the cell like a top, feeling along the walls and tiptapping with a finger, his eyes measuring distances, studying the ceiling, sawing through the bars. His jumpy behaviour worried the soldier on peephole duty, and several times, in despair, he threatened to shoot Gypsy Mike, who rounded on him with filthy words and jeering taunts. All this wrangling was settled peacefully only because it gradually degenerated into the kind of inoffensive roughstuff between peasants in which any shooting would have been absurd and impossible.

Gypsy Mike got through his nights fast asleep, almost without stirring, in an ongoing state of dynamic immobility like a spring temporarily uncoiled. But once he was up on his feet he resumed the business of spinning around, weighing things up and groping about. His hands were invariably dry and hot, but sometimes his heart felt a flood of cold, as if an unmelting block of ice had been packed into his chest, giving him the dry shivers all over his body. At times like this, Gypsy Mike, already swarthy, turned black and took on the darkbluish hue of castiron. And he formed a strange habit: as if he had eaten something excessively sweet and indigestible, he began licking his lips all the time, champing and spewing out the flow of saliva through h is c lenched teeth all over the floor. And he didn’t finish what he was trying to say; his thoughts flashed past so quickly that his tongue couldn’t keep up with them.

One afternoon the prison chief dropped in on him, accompanied by an escort. He took one look at the floor covered in spit, and spoke in gloomy tones. ‘Huh. You’ve made a mess here.’

Gypsy Mike was quick to respond. ‘You’ve messed up the whole world, and I’ve said nothing. What have you skulked in here for?’

The chief’s gloomy tone did not change as he offered him the job of executioner.

Gypsy Mike grinned and laughed at him. ‘Haven’t you got one? Bloody marvellous! You do it. Ha, ha, ha! You’ve got necks and ropes, and nobody to do the hanging? By God, that’s bloody marvellous!’

‘You wouldn’t have to die.’

‘You bet I wouldn’t. Dead men don’t hang nobody. Stupid fool.’

‘What about it? No difference to you one way or the other.’

‘Anyway, how do you lot go about hanging people? I bet you smothers ’em on the quiet.’

‘No, we do it to music,’ snarled the chief.

‘Stupid fool, course you got to have music. Like this?’ And he let go with a rollicking song.

‘Seem to have made your mind up,’ said the chief. ‘What’s it to be? Let’s have some sense out of you.’

Gypsy gave a grin. ‘Hang on a minute! Go away, and come back. Then I’ll tell you.’

At this point a new idea burst into the maelstrom of brilliant, though halfformed and dispiriting images that had flooded through Gypsy Mike’s mind. Wouldn’t it be nice to be an executioner dressed in a red shirt? He could see a vivid picture: a square thronged with people, a high scaffold and himself, Gypsy Mike, strolling up and down, complete with red shirt and axe. The sun cast its light on every head, giving the axe a cheerful glint, and radiating such richness and good cheer that even those who were having their heads chopped off had a smile on their faces. Just behind the people you could see carts and horses’ muzzles - peasants in from the countryside - and, further away, the fields.

‘Pfwah!’ snorted the gypsy, slobbering and licking at his lips as he gobbed out a new stream of saliva.

But suddenly he felt as if a fur hat had been pulled over his head and yanked down right over his mouth. His eyes were going dim, he could hardly breathe and he felt that flood of cold in his heart, as if an unmelting block of ice had been packed into his chest, giving him the dry shivers again.

The chief called in a couple more times, but Gypsy Mike just grinned at him and said, ‘Too soon. Come back again.’

Then, eventually, the chief flashed open the peephole and shouted in. ‘You’ve had it now, dumbcluck! Got somebody else.’

‘Sod you. You hang ’em!’ snapped the gypsy. And he put the idea of executing people out of his mind.

But towards the end, with the execution getting nearer, the rushing flood of broken images became too much to bear. The gypsy wanted to stop, he wanted to plant his feet wide apart and stop there, but the swirling maelstrom swept him away and, with everything swimming past, he had nothing to hold onto. And he was too upset to get any sleep; his dreams were different now, sharpedged and bulking like coloured wooden blocks, still hurtling past faster than he could think. This was no longer a flow of water but a measureless torrent descending from a measureless height, swirling its way through the visible world of colour. When he had been free, Gypsy Mike had sported rather stylish moustaches and no other facial hair, but now he had grown a short, black, prickly beard which gave him a terrifyingly crazy look. Sometimes he would go berserk, wheeling right around his room without rhyme or reason, but still feeling his way over the roughcast walls. And he still drank his water like a horse.

One evening, when the lights had been put on, he got down on all fours in midcell, and came out with a quavering howl like a wolf. As he did so, he looked deadly serious, as if his howling was a thing of vital importance. He would take in a good chestful of air and release it slowly in a long drawnout quavering howl. He did this with his eyes screwed up tight and listening carefully to what was coming out. Even the trembling quality of his voice seemed rather calculated, and he seemed not to be making a senseless noise, but to be carefully composing every note of his wild animal howl and filling it with unspeakable terror and anguish.

Then, suddenly, he stopped howling and stayed where he was on all fours, without making another sound. Minutes passed, and then he started mumbling, breathing his words into the ground. ‘My little chickens, lovely sweeties . . . My little chickens, lovely sweeties, let me off . . . Little chickens! Lovely sweeties!...’

And again he seemed to be listening carefully to the sounds as they came out. Saying a word and listening to it.

Then he jumped up and spent the next hour, without stopping for a breather, cursing and swearing in the filthiest language. ‘Aargh! You lousy lot!’ he yelled out, rolling his bloodshot eyes. ‘Hanging’s hanging, but not like . . . Aargh! You lousy lot!’

And the soldier, chalkwhite and weeping with anguish and terror, banged on the door with his riflebarrel and screamed out helplessly. ‘I’ll shoot! By God, I’ll shoot. Hear me?’

But he didn’t dare shoot. Condemned prisoners were never shot at, unless there was a proper riot going on. Gypsy Mike gnashed his teeth and carried on swearing and spewing. His human brain, suddenly stuck on a razorsharp lifeanddeath borderline, was crumbling like a lump of driedout, weathering clay.

When they turned up in his cell during the night to take Gypsy Mike off to be executed, he shook himself and seemed to come back to life. He had a sweeter taste in his mouth and an unstoppable flow of saliva had welled up, but his cheeks took on a pinker tinge and his eyes sparkled with some of their old slyness and wild cunning. As he got dressed, he spoke to the official. ‘Who’s doin’ the ’angin’? That new bloke? Won’t have got his hand in yet, will ’e?’

‘No need to worry about that,’ said the official in a dry voice.

‘Course I’m worried, your honour. It’s me they’re hangin’, not you. Got plenty of government soap to hang us with?’

‘All right. All right. That’s enough from you.’

‘You can see who’s eaten all the soap,’ said the gypsy to the superintendent. ‘Look at his face. All shiny!’

‘That’s enough!’

‘Give it plenty of soap!’

Gypsy Mike laughed at them, but the sweet taste in his mouth was building up, and suddenly his legs went all funny and numb. Still, he managed to call out as they walked outside. ‘Carriage, please, for the Count of Bengal!’

5. Kiss And Keep Quiet

The sentence passed on the five terrorists was pronounced in its final form and ratified on the same day. The condemned prisoners were not told when the execution would take place, but, judging by the way things usually went, they knew they would be hanged that night, or the next night at the latest. And when a meeting with relatives was proposed for the following day, Thursday, they knew that the execution was scheduled for Friday morning at dawn.

Tanya Kovalchuk had no relatives, and any that she did have lived miles away in the sticks, somewhere in Little Russia; they would be unlikely to know about the trial or the impending execution. Relatives were unthinkable for the unidentified Musya and Werner, which meant that only two of them, Sergey Golovin and Vassily Kashirin, were due for a family meeting. And both of them anticipated that gettogether with a mixture of anguish and dread, though they could not refuse the old folk a final conversation and one last kiss.

Sergey Golovin was especially anguished by the prospect of meeting them. He loved his mother and father very dearly, he had spent time with them only recently, and now he was horrified that it had come to this. Execution itself, such an outrageous perversion with its demented potential to crush the human brain, was easier for his imagination to assimilate, and it seemed less terrifying, than those few short, incomprehensible minutes, which seemed to stand beyond time, beyond life itself. How to look at them, what to think, what to say - was more than his human brain could grasp. The simplest, everyday things - taking them by the hand, kissing them, saying, ‘Hello, Dad . . .’ - seemed unbelievably horrible because of the monstrous inhumanity, craziness and falsity of it all.

After being sentenced, the condemned prisoners were not sent together to one cell as Kovalchuk had assumed, but were returned to solitary confinement, and all morning, right up to eleven o’clock, when his parents arrived, Sergey Golovin walked furiously up and down his cell, plucking at his little beard, scowling pathetically and muttering to himself. Now and then he would stop in midstride, take in a chestful of air and blow it back out like someone who has been too long underwater. But he was so fit, so full of life and youth, that even in these moments of the utmost cruelty and suffering the blood surged strongly under his skin, giving his cheeks a rosy glow, and his blue eyes were radiant with innocence.

However, things turned out much better than expected for Sergey. First into the meeting room was Nikolay Sergeyevich Golovin, a retired colonel. He was white all over - face, beard, hair and hands - like a marble statue in men’s clothing, and he was wearing the same old short coat, showing its age a bit but nicely cleaned, smelling of benzine and sporting some nice new transverse epaulettes. He marched in decisively with the firm tread of a military man, extended a dry white hand and spoke in a loud voice. ‘Hello, Sergey.’

He was followed by Sergey’s mother, mincing in with an awkward smile on her face. But she too shook hands and spoke in a loud voice. ‘Hello, darling.’

She kissed him on the lips and sat down without saying anything more. She had not rushed in, cried out or made any kind of scene, as Sergey had feared. She had simply kissed him and sat down. And she had even begun to straighten her black silk dress with trembling hands.

What Sergey did not know was that all the previous night the colonel had locked himself away in his small study, summoned all his strength and worked on this ritual occasion. ‘We must lighten our son’s burden, not add to it in his last minutes’ was the colonel’s firm conclusion, and he carefully weighed every possible phrase, every gesture, that might come into tomorrow’s conversation. But he kept losing his way, forgetting the few bits he had managed to prepare, and he wept bitter tears as he sat there tucked into a corner of the oilcloth divan. And in the morning he outlined for his wife’s benefit how they were to conduct themselves at the meeting.

‘The main thing is - kiss and keep quiet,’ was his instruction. ‘You can say something a bit later on, but when you kiss him you mustn’t say anything. Don’t speak when you’ve just kissed him. Do you understand? If you do, it will come out all wrong.’

‘Yes, Nikolay.’

‘And don’t cry. For God’s sake, don’t start crying. You’ll be the death of him if you do, woman!’

‘Why are you crying then?’

‘You’d bring anybody to tears. But you mustn’t cry. Do you hear what I say?’

‘You’d bring anybody to tears. But you mustn’t cry. Do you hear what I say?’

He had intended to run through his instructions once again in the cab, but he forgot. So there they had been,driving along in silence, two bent figures, grey and old both of them, lost in thought, while the city was enjoying itself in noisy celebrations. It was Shrovetide and everyone was out on the noisy streets.

Now, they had sat down. The colonel assumed his wellrehearsed attitude, with his right hand tucked under his coat lapel. Sergey had been sitting down for no more than a moment when he caught sight of his mother’s wrinkled face close to and leapt up.

‘Don’t get up, Seryozha, darling,’ his mother implored.

‘Sit down, Sergey,’ said his father.

None of them spoke. His mother still had an awkward smile on her face. ‘We did what we could to help you, Seryozha, darling.’

‘Didn’t do any good, Mamma . . .’

The colonel’s response was firm. ‘We had to do it, Sergey, so you wouldn’t think your parents had abandoned you.’

There was another short silence. They were too scared to pronounce any word; it was as if every word on their tongues lost its meaning, and there was only one meaning: death. Sergey took a look at his father’s nicely cleaned coat, still smelling of benzine, and thought. ‘There’s no servant now, so he must have cleaned it himself. Why did I never notice him c leaning that coat b efore? Must h ave done i t e arly morning.’ Then suddenly he asked a question. ‘How’s my sister getting on? Is she all right?’

‘Ninochka doesn’t know.’ His mother was quick to respond.

But the colonel cut in sharply. ‘What’s the point in lying about it? She read about it in the papers, poor girl. Let Sergey know that we all . . . his nearest and dearest . . . at the right time . . . were thinking about . . .’

He stopped, unable to carry on. Suddenly his wife’s face crumpled all at once, swimming with tears, convulsing, wild and wet. Her lacklustre eyes darted around crazily; her breathing became more hurried, rushed and noisy.

‘ Se— Ser— Se— Se— ’ she kept on repeating without moving her lips. ‘ Se— ’

‘Mamma!’

The colonel took a step forward and, shaking all over in every fold of his coat and every line on his face, unaware of how terrifying he looked in his deathly whiteness and desperately agonizing determination, spoke to his wife. ‘Stop that! Stop tormenting him! Don’t! Don’t torment him! He’s going to die! Don’t torment him!’

She had been intimidated into silence, but he was still shaking his clenched fists in front of his chest, striving for selfcontrol. ‘Don’t torment him!’

Then he stepped back, tucked a trembling hand under his coat lapel, and with an expression of grimly forced calm, he asked a question, whitelipped. ‘When?’

‘Tomorrow morning,’ replied Sergey, equally whitelipped.

His mother looked down, her lips champing; she seemed not to be taking anything in.

Still champing, she seemed to be pouring out words that were primitive and unnatural. ‘Ninochka sends you a kiss, Seryozhenka.’

‘Send one back from me,’ said Sergey.

‘Right. And the Khvostovs want to be remembered to you.’

‘Who? Oh, yes, the Khvostovs.’

The colonel cut across them. ‘Well, we’d better be off. On your feet, Mother. It’s time.’

The two of them assisted the sagging woman to her feet.

‘Say goodbye,’ ordered the colonel. ‘Sign of the Cross.’

She did what she was told. But as she crossed herself and gave her son the lightest of kisses, she shook her head and her speech became incoherent. ‘No, not like that. No, no. Not like that. No, no. Me . . . after . . . What can I say? No, not like that.’

‘Goodbye, Sergey,’ said his father.

They shook hands, and held each other in a close but shortlived embrace.

‘You . . .’ began Sergey.

‘What?’ snapped his father.

‘No, not like that. No, no. Not like that. What can I say?’ His mother was still rambling and shaking her head. She had managed to get herself seated again, and she was shaking all over.

‘You . . .’ Sergey began again.

Suddenly his face was that of a pitiful child; it crumpled, and his eyes flooded with tears. Through their sparkling mist he could see his father’s white face close to, with tears like his own.

‘You’re a noble man, Father.’

‘What? What are you saying?’ said the colonel, horrified.

And suddenly, like a broken man, he let his head fall across his son’s shoulder. He had once been taller than Sergey, but now he had shrunk down to a smaller height, and his dry, fluffy head lay like a little white ball on his son’s shoulder. And they were both silently but warmly embracing; Sergey kissed the fluffy white hair, his father the prison smock.

What about me ? ’ came a sudden loud voice.

They turned to look. Sergey’s mother was standing there with her head thrown back, watching in fury, almost hatred.

‘What is it, Mother?’ cried the colonel.

‘What about me ?’ she said, shaking her head, with the intensity of a demented mind. ‘You can kiss goodbye, but what about me ? It’s all right for you men. But what about me ? Eh?’

‘Mamma, darling!’ Sergey threw himself at her.

What followed cannot and need not be conveyed.

The colonel’s last words were: ‘I give you my blessing as you go to your death, Seryozha. Die with courage, an officer’s death.’

Then they left. Left, but didn’t leave. They stayed on,

stood around, spoke - then they were gone. Mamma had been sitting there, Papa had been there, standing, and suddenly, somehow, they were gone. Back in his cell, Sergey lay down on his bunk, turned to face the wall to shield himself from the guards, and wept and wept. Then, weary from weeping, he fell into a deep sleep.

Only one person, his mother, came to see Vassily Kashirin; his father hadn’t wanted to come. When his mother arrived, Vassily was pacing up and down his room, shivering with cold even though it was a warm day, almost hot. Their conversation was brief and grim.

‘You shouldn’t have come, Mamma darling. It’s an ordeal for you and for me.’

‘Why, Vasya? Why did you do it? God in heaven!’

The old woman broke down in tears, wiping them away with the fringe of black wool on her scarf.

Doing what he and his brothers always did, he bawled at his mother, who was completely at a loss, and then suddenly stopped, shivering with cold, and snapped at her angrily. ‘Look at this! I knew it! Mamma, you just don’t understand - anything at all!’

‘All right. All right. What’s wrong with you? Are you cold?’

‘Yes,’ he said, cutting in, and off he went pacing around the room, scowling angrily at her in sideways glances.

‘Happen you’ve caught cold?’

‘Mamma, it’s got nothing to do with catching cold. It’s . . .’ And he gave up on her with a wave of despair.

The old woman was intending to say, ‘And our old man wants pancakes on Monday,’ but she lost her nerve and wailed at him. ‘It’s our son, I said. You must come . . . Forgive him his sins . . . Old goat wouldn’t listen . . .’

‘To hell with him. He’s no father of mine. Been a swine all his life, and he still is!’

‘Vasya, darling, he is your father!’ The old woman recoiled in disapproval.

‘My father, huh!’

‘Your own father!’

‘Oh yes?’

It was all frantic and absurd. Death lay ahead, yet this trivial, unnecessary, futile bit of nonsense was building up, and their words were crunching like empty nutshells underfoot. Almost in tears - tears of anguish caused by the perpetual failure to communicate that had walled him off throughout his life from friends and family and even now, in the hour of his death itself, stared him in the face with all its meanness and stupidity - Vassily cried out. ‘Can’t you see they’re going to hang me? Hang me. Can you see it, yes or no? Hang me!’

‘Well, if you hadn’t done things to people, maybe they wouldn’t . . .’

‘For the love of God! What are you on about? Wild animals don’t behave like this. Am I your son, or not ? ’

He burst into tears and sat down in one corner. The old lady wept too, in her own corner. Incapable of joining for a single minute in a bond of love and setting that against the horror of impending death, they wept cold tears of solitude that brought no warmth to the heart.

His mother spoke. ‘You’re asking me whether I’m a mother or not. You’re blaming me. But these last few days I’ve gone grey with worry. I’m an old woman now. And you keep on blaming me.’

‘All right, Mamma. It’s all right. I’m sorry. It’s time you went. Kiss my brothers for me.’

‘Am I really not a mother to you? Don’t I show any pity?’

Then at last she was gone. She had walked away weeping bitterly, wiping her eyes on the fringes of her scarf, and not seeing where she was going. And the further she got from the prison, the more she wept her scalding tears. She turned around and walked back towards the prison, only to get completely lost in the town where she had been born, raised and lived through to old age. She fetched up in a kind of rundown patch of garden under a few old trees with snappedoff branches, where she sat down on a bench wet from the thaw. And suddenly it came to her: they were going to hang him tomorrow.

The old woman leapt to her feet with every intention of running away, but suddenly her head spun violently and she collapsed. The little path was slippery, swimming with ice and, try as she might, she couldn’t get to her feet. She kept on spinning round, and when she tried to raise herself on her elbows and knees, she slipped back down on her side. The black scarf slithered off her head, exposing a bald patch among the dirtygrey hair at the back. For some reason she felt as if she was at a wedding, enjoying the celebrations - her son was getting married. She had had more than a glass or two of wine and was getting very drunk.

‘No more,’ she cried, turning it away. ‘For the love of God, I can’t take any more.’ Her head was reeling as she slithered over the thin crust of ice covering the snow, but still it came - more and more wine, poured out for her.

And her heart began to ache from the drunken laughter, the rich spread of food and the crazy dancing - but they went on pouring out more wine for her. More and more wine.

6. The Hours Fly By

In the fortress where the condemned terrorists were imprisoned, there was a belltower with an ancient clock. Every hour, every halfhour, every quarter of an hour, a chime rang out in a long, slow toll, a sound of sadness high overhead that gradually ebbed away, like the distant, plaintive call of passing birds. During the day this strange sad music was lost in the sounds of the wide and bustling city street that ran past the fortress. Trams rattled up and down, horses clipclopped, automobiles bounced and swooped, announcing their presence well in advance. It was Shrovetide, and some peasant drivers had come in specially from the city outskirts in carnival mood, and the little bells strung around the necks of their diminutive horses filled the air with a steady jingle. And there was a murmur of speaking voices, the slightly intoxicated and cheery tones of people on holiday. The discordant bustle was in tune with the early spring thaw with its dirty puddles on the pavements and the trees all around the square that had gone black overnight. A warm breeze wafted in from the sea in wide, wet flurries. It was almost as if the watching eye could observe tiny particles of fresh air being borne away in a cloud of goodwill, off into the freedom of infinite distance, laughing as they went.

At night the street lapsed into repose under the lonely glow of large electric suns. Now the huge fortress, its flat walls showing no spark of light, withdrew steadily into darkness and quietude, cutting itself off beyond a cordon of silence and stillness from the living and everactive city. At this time the chiming asserted itself again, its weird, unearthly tune slowly and sadly proceeding overhead from birth to death. It was born and reborn, its false message for the ears ringing out in soft and sombre tones and a dying fall, only to ring out anew. It was like big, limpid droplets of glass tinkling out a muted chime as they fell from ineffable heights into a metal bowl filled with hours and minutes. Or like birds of passage flying by.

By day and by night this chime was the only sound to penetrate the separate cells where the condemned criminals were held in solitary confinement. It came in through the roof and through the thick stone walls, shivering the silence, and it went away imperceptibly, only to return no less imperceptibly. Sometimes they didn’t hear it, and forgot about it; sometimes they waited for it in despair, living from chime to chime, no longer trusting the silence. Only the most serious criminals were assigned to this prison, which lived by its own rules - strict, harsh rules, as rough as a corner wall of the fortress itself - and if there could be nobility in a ruthless regime, it was the nobility of dead silence, hollow and soundlessly solemn, picking up whispers and the slightest breath.

And amidst this solemn silence, disrupted only by a lugubrious chime marking the fleeting minutes, five people - two women and three men - cut off from every living thing, awaited the onset of night, dawn and execution, each preparing for it in his or her own way.

7. There Is No Death

Tanya Kovalchuk behaved as she had done throughout her whole life in thinking only of other people and never about herself; here and now, suffering only on behalf of the others, she was most upset. She could imagine imminent death presenting itself as an agonizing reality for Seryozha Golovin, for Musya and the rest of them, but it did not seem to concern her at all.

And, as if to reward herself for her own muchneeded selfcontrol in court, she now wept for hours on end, in the way you would expect from old women who have known much sorrow, or young ones full of compassion, people of exceptional kindness. And the idea that Seryozha might not get his tobacco, or Werner might be deprived of his strong tea, together with the thought of them all inevitably dying, seemed to cause her more anguish than the idea of execution itself. Execution is something inexorable, even incidental, not worth thinking about, but for a man in prison, waiting for execution, the loss of his tobacco is intolerable. She started to reminisce, running through lovely details of their lives together, and she died a thousand deaths, terrified by the idea of Seryozha meeting his parents.

It was for Musya that she felt sorriest of all. For some time now she had been under the impression that Musya was in love with Werner, and although there was no truth in this, Tanya had persisted in dreaming up something nice and bright for the two of them. When they were still free, Musya had worn a little silver ring decorated with a skull and crossbones within a crown of thorns. Tanya Kovalchuk had often looked at this ring with an aching heart, seeing it as a symbol of doom, and she had begged Musya, half jokingly, half seriously, to take it off.

‘Give it to me,’ she had begged.

‘No, Tanya, I’m not doing that. You’ll soon have a different kind of ring on your finger.’

For some reason the others in their turn had assumed she was bound to get married very soon, and this annoyed her because she had no desire for a husband. And so, as she recalled that halfhumorous banter with Musya, and the fact that she was now definitely doomed, she found herself choking on tears of motherly compassion. And every time the clock chimed, she looked up with a tearstained face and listened to it, wondering how the others were reacting in their cells to the steadily insistent summons of death.

But Musya herself felt happy.

With her hands behind her back, tucked into the illfitting prison smock that made her look rather odd, like a man or a young lad dressed in someone else’s clothes, she paced the floor, up and down, tirelessly. The sleeves of the smock were too long for her, and she had rolled them up, with her thin, scrawny arms, almost those of a child, poking out from gaping holes like the stalks of flowers sticking out of a cheap and dirty old pot. The rough material had been rubbing and chafing her delicate white neck, and from time to time she would reach up with both hands to free her throat and finger the sore places on her livid skin.

Musya paced the floor, to and fro, her features flushing with the effort of vindicating herself in the eyes of the world. She wanted vindication because she was only a slip of a girl with nothing special about her, nothing heroic, not much in the way of achievement, and yet she was going to be subjected to the same kind of gloriously honourable death visited upon true heroes and martyrs before her time. With her unshakeable faith in human kindness, compassion and love, she could imagine people worrying about her at this moment, suffering with pain and pity, and the shame of it flooded her face red. It was as if she was doing something thoroughly disgraceful by going to the scaffold.

At the last meeting with the defence lawyer, she had asked him to get some poison for her, but she had thought better of it: what might he and the others think - that she was showing off or chickening out, and instead of dying a quiet, inconspicuous death she was making a song and dance about it? So she added hastily, ‘No, no, don’t bother.’

Now there was only one thing she wanted: to make people understand that she was not being at all heroic, that dying isn’t all that terrible and people shouldn’t feel sorry or worry about her. To let them see that it wasn’t her fault they were making such a meal of putting her to death like that when she was so young and insignificant.

Like someone charged with a real offence, Musya was looking for exoneration, for anything at all that would enhance her sacrifice and give it real value. This was her line of thinking: ‘Yes, I’m still young and I might have lived a long life, but still . . .’

It was like a candle fading in the bright light of the rising sun: her young age and life itself came out dark and dismal against the glorious radiance about to shine upon her modest head. There was no exoneration.

But what about that special spirit within her - limitless love, limitless readiness to take on big things, an unlimited capacity for selflessness? It really wasn’t her fault she had not been given the opportunity to do everything she had wanted and intended to do - that she had been killed on the temple threshold, at the foot of the sacrificial altar.

But if that’s how things go, if a person is to be judged not by what he has done, but by what he intended to do, well then . . . then she was worthy of a martyr’s crown.

‘Am I?’ thought Musya sheepishly. ‘Am I really worthy of that? Worthy enough for people to weep and grieve over me when I am so small and insignificant?’

And a feeling of indescribable joy came over her. There was no doubt about it, not a moment’s hesitation; she had been taken to their bosom, she had every right to stand alongside those noble souls who from time immemorial had attained the highest heaven by going to the stake, suffering under torture and submitting to execution. This was peace, resplendent and restful, a gentle glow of infinite happiness. It was as if she had already gone from the earth, soaring bodiless into the sunshine realm of truth and life.

‘So that’s death, is it? How can you call it death?’ thought Musya in her blissful state.

And if all the world’s scientists, philosophers and executioners had come together in her cell and laid before her their books, scalpels, axes and nooses to demonstrate that death exists, that man dies and gets killed, and that there is no immortality - she would have been bemused. What do you mean there is no immortality, when here she is, now, immortal? What price immortality, what price death, when, here and now, she is already dead and already immortal, as alive in death as she has been alive in life?

And if they had carried a foulstinking coffin into her cell, containing her own decomposing body, and said, ‘Look, that’s you,’ she would have taken one glance and told them, ‘No, that’s not me.’

And if they had tried to show her the menacing sight of decomposition, and scare into believing it was her - really her! - Musya would have responded with a smile, and said, ‘No. You think that is me, but it isn’t. I’m the person you are talking to. How could I be that ? ’

‘No, but you are going to die, and that’s w hat y ou’ll become.’

‘No. I’m not going to die.’

‘You’re going to be executed. Look, there’s the noose.’

‘I’m going to be executed, but I shan’t die. How can I die when I’m already immortal, here and now?’

And the scientists, philosophers and executioners would step back, and say in quavering tones, ‘Do not touch this place. It is holy ground.’

What did Musya have in mind? Many things - for her the thread of life, far from being broken by death, would go on spinning out smoothly and evenly. She thought of her comrades, both the faraway people who would be painfully hurt by their execution and those close to her who would mount the same scaffold. She was taken aback by Vassily’s terrible fear - he had always been so brave, even enjoying a joke with death. Take that Tuesday morning when they were tying the explosives onto their belts which would blow them to pieces in a few hours’ time. Tanya Kovalchuk’s hands were shaking so much from anxiety that she had to be taken away, but Vassily was in a jokey mood, clowning about and spinning round without a care in the world, and Werner had to take him to task: ‘Don’t mess about with death.’

So what was he now so afraid of?

But this incomprehensible fear was so alien to Musya’s spirit that she soon stopped worrying about him and trying to fathom its cause. Suddenly she felt a sharp urge to see Seryozha Golovin and have a laugh with him. After a few moments’ thought, she felt an even more desperate urge to see Werner and chew the fat with him. And, imagining that Werner was walking alongside her with his measured stride and his heels digging into the ground, Musya spoke to him. ‘No, Werner, my dear, that’s nonsense. It doesn’t matter whether you killed N.N. or not. You’re a clever man, but this is like one of your games of chess. You take one piece, then another, and eventually you win. The only thing that matters is that you and I are ready to die. Can’t you see that? Those gentlemen, what do they think? That there’s nothing more horrible than death? They have invented death, they’re scared of it, and they want us to be scared. I’ll tell you what I’d like to do - walk out on my own with a Browning in front of a whole regiment and shoot at them all. As long as there are thousands of them and I am alone, I won’t kill anybody. That’s the only thing - there must be thousands of them. When thousands kill one person, that person is the one who wins. That’s how it is, Werner, my dear.’

But this was so clear she felt there was no point in arguing any further. Werner must have seen it himself by now. Or maybe her thoughts simply didn’t want to settle in one place - they were like a blithely cruising bird with a view of limitless horizons, and a grasp of infinite space, ultimate depths and the serenity of blue skies, tender and caressing. The clock chimed incessantly, shocking the deadly silence, and her thoughts blended with the lovely harmony of that distant sound, which set them ringing too and turned all her fluid and fleeting impressions into music. For Musya, it was like going for a carriagedrive in the tender darkness of the night, down a smooth, wide highway, with the springs rocking gently and the little bells tinkling. All her cares and worries had gone, her weary body had melted away in the darkness, and her serenely sleepy mind formed the brightest of silent images for her to wallow in, revelling in their colours and the perfect rest that came with them. Musya brought to mind her three colleagues, recently hanged; their bright and joyful faces seemed so close to her - closer than anyone still living. She felt like a man looking forward happily in the morning to walking in that evening and greeting old friends at home with a smile upon his lips.

Musya felt very tired from so much walking. She lay down cautiously on the bunk, and carried on daydreaming with her eyes lightly closed. The clock chimed incessantly, shocking the unbroken silence, and bright images floated softly within its singing bounds. Musya was thinking: ‘Is this really death? Heavens, how beautiful it is! Or is it life? I don’t know. I really don’t know. I shall go on watching and listening.’

For some time now, ever since the first days of incarceration, her hearing had been playing tricks with her. Well attuned to music, it had been whetted by the silence, against which it turned tiny particles of reality - guards walking down the corridor, the chiming of the clock, the wind rustling over the iron roof, a creaking lantern - into musical patterns. To begin with, Musya was afraid of them, and she chased them away like morbid hallucinations, but then she saw that she was fine and there was nothing at all morbid about them. She began to relax and give in to them. And now, suddenly, she could definitely make out the clear strains of military music. She opened her eyes in astonishment and looked up. It was night outside, and the clock was chiming. That’s it again, she thought calmly, and closed her eyes. The moment they were closed, the music came again - clearly audible music from around the corner, with soldiers, a whole regiment, marching up the righthand side and going past her window. Their feet were beating out the time on the frozen ground - left, right, left, right - and you could even hear the creaking of a leather boot now and then, or a foot slipping somewhere and then picking up its stride. Nearer and nearer came the music, something completely unfamiliar - but a loud and cheery festival march. Some celebration was clearly underway in the fortress.

Now the band was outside her window, and the whole cell was filled with happy sounds and cheerful harmonies in different registers. One big brass instrument was painfully out, lagging behind the beat one minute, then ridiculously galloping ahead. Musya could see the diminutive soldier playing this instrument, and the effort on his face made her laugh.

They’re going now. Their steps trail away - left, right, left,

right. From far away the music sounds even better, jollier.

One or two departing false notes from the cheerily booming brass, and they’ve gone. And now the clock chimes again from the belltower, with its slow, sad tones barely troubling the stillness.

‘They’ve gone,’ thought Musya with a touch of regret. She misses the cheery, funny sounds, now they are lost. She even misses the lost soldiers, because those men with their squeaky boots, struggling so hard with their brass instruments, are not the same people, they are a completely different lot from the ones she wanted to shoot at with her Browning.

‘Please come back,’ she begged plaintively. And back they came. Here they are, bending over her, enveloping her in a limpid cloud, raising her up to where birds of passage soar on high, calling out like town criers. They swoop right and left, up and down, calling out like towncriers. They voice their cries, their proclamations, announcing their flight from afar. They spread their wings wide open, the darkness bears them up like the daylight, and the swell of their breasts, scything the air, radiates a blue reflection of the resplendent city below. Her heartbeat slows to a steady pace; her breathing is now gentle and easy. She is falling asleep. Her face is weary and pale, there are circles under her eyes, and her young girl’s arms look skinny and emaciated. There is a smile on her lips. Tomorrow at sunrise this human face will be contorted into an inhuman grimace, the brain will be clogged with thickened blood and glassy eyes will bulge from their sockets - but today she sleeps in peace, smiling in her splendid immortality.

Musya is asleep.

And prisonlife goes on, a life of deafness and hearing, of blindness and sight, a kind of unending angst. Someone, somewhere, is walking about. Someone, somewhere, is whispering. Somewhere, someone rattles a gun. Was that a scream? Maybe not - just a noise in the stillness.

The peephole in the door opens noiselessly. A dark, whiskered face appears in the dark aperture, stares in at Musya, watching her for some time in amazement, and disappears as softly as it came.

The chimes ring out with agonizing slowness, as if the weary hours are climbing the steep slope to midnight, and the upward movement gets heavier and harder. Then they slip and slide back down, moaning, only to crawl up again, agonizingly, towards their black summit.

Someone, somewhere, is walking about. Someone, somewhere, is whispering. And now horses are being harnessed to black carriages which carry no lights.

8. Death Exists. So Does Life

Sergey Golovin had given no thought to death, which had seemed so irrelevant, of no concern to him. He was a fit, strong and buoyant young man, endowed with a happygolucky attitude and sheer joie de vivre that allowed him to cope with any unpleasant or lifethreatening thoughts and feelings by absorbing them into his system quickly and without trace. In the same way that his cuts, wounds and grazes soon healed up, anything painful, wounding his spirit, worked its way out of him and gradually disappeared. And to everything, business or pleasure - photography, cycling or planning terrorism - he brought the same easygoing and lifeaffirming sense of application. Everything in life was good fun, everything in life was important, everything must be done well.

And everything he did was done well; he could manage a sail marvellously, he was very good with a pistol, devoted in friendship and in love, and he had a fanatical belief in one’s ‘word of honour’. His friends laughed at him; they said that if a police agent, a snout, a notorious spy, swore on his ‘word of honour’ that he wasn’t a spy, Sergey would believe him and shake him by the hand like a friend. If he had a fault, it was only that he fancied himself as a singer, when he had no ear for music: his singing was appalling. He couldn’t hold a tune, even in songs of revolution, and he wasn’t best pleased when they laughed at him.

‘You’re all stupid asses. Either that, or I’m one,’ he would say to them, looking serious and obviously offended. People would match his serious manner, but they were of one accord, and they came to the same considered opinion: ‘You’re the ass. You sound like one.’

Yet for this fault of character - as often happens with nice people - he was loved perhaps as much as he was for his virtues.

He was so unafraid of death, so uninterested in it, that before they left Tanya Kovalchuk’s flat on the fateful morning, he was the only one who had a good breakfast, putting away two glasses of tea, half full of milk, and a decentsized roll. Then he looked ruefully at Werner’s untouched roll, and said, ‘Why don’t you eat something? You should. You need building up.’

‘Don’t feel like it.’

‘You’re a good trencherman, Seryozha.’

Instead of replying, Sergey burst into song, with his mouth still full. His singing was raucous and tuneless: ‘Dark whirling winds swirl overhead . . .’

After his arrest, he could have been depressed: it had not been done well, they had failed, but now he thought, ‘Here’s something else that must be done well. We have to die well,’ and this cheered him up. And, strange to relate, from the second morning in the fortress, he had started doing exercises p rescribed i n a n e xtraordinary ‘ rationalized’ p rogramme created by some German by the name of Müller, which had caught his imagination. He would strip naked and, to the amazement and alarm of the watching sentry, he would work his way steadily through all eighteen set exercises. The fact that there was a sentry observing this with obvious surprise, delighted him, as a disciple of the Müller method, and, although he knew there would be no response, he would talk to the eye that was peering in through the little window.

‘Don’t worry, my friend. It’s building me up. You could do with this in your regiment,’ he would call out persuasively, keeping it short to avoid frightening anyone, without ever suspecting that the soldier simply thought he was mad.

The fear of death started to come over him bit by bit, in a kind of series of sudden shocks. It was like an uppercut, a fist smashing up into his heart, hard. More like a sharp pain than fear. Then the sensation would be forgotten, only for it to return a few hours later, lasting longer and hurting more every time it came. And it was clearly beginning to take on the rough outline of a ghastly, unbearable terror.

‘What - me scared?’ thought Sergey. ‘Stupid idea!’

It wasn’t him being scared, it was his young body, fit and strong, which he had been unable to fool despite the German’s physical exercises or any amount of rubbing down with a cold, wet towel. And as it gained strength and freshness from the application of cold water, it suffered all the more unbearably from fleeting shocks of dread. And it was during the very moments when he experienced a lift of the spirit from sheer joie de vivre and bodily strength, in the morning, after a good night’s sleep and a stiff workout, that he felt a sharp stab of terror that seemed to come from outside. He took note of this, and thought to himself: ‘Don’t be stupid, brother Sergey. To make death easier you have to weaken the body, not build it up. Don’t be so stupid!’

And he stopped doing the exercises and towelling down. For the benefit of the soldier, he shouted out, by way of explanation and justification: ‘I’m packing it in, but don’t get me wrong, brother. It is the right thing to do. It’s no good for anybody who’s going to get hanged. It’s still all right for everybody else.’

And it really did seem to make a difference. He also tried eating less to make himself feel weaker, but despite the lack of fresh air and exercise, he couldn’t stop feeling hungry. This was difficult to deal with, and he gobbled up everything they put before him. Then he tried something different: before starting his meal he would scrape half the hot food off into a pail. It seemed to help. He began to feel weary and drowsy.

‘I’ll show you what’s what!’ he warned his body, gently running saddened fingers over his feeble, rundown muscles. But it wasn’t long before his body got used to this new regime, and the dread of death came back. Admittedly the pain wasn’t quite as fierce or fiery, but it nagged at him and made him feel sick. ‘It’s because of all the waiting,’ thought Sergey. ‘Best thing would be to sleep right through to the hanging.’ And he tried that, trying to sleep as long as he could. At first it worked, but soon, either because he had slept too much or for some other reason, he began suffering from insomnia. And along with that came clear, sharp thinking and a longing for life.

‘What - me scared? To hell with that for an idea.’ He was obsessed with death. ‘It’s such a pity about life. It’s a wonderful thing, whatever the pessimists say about it. What happens when they hang a pessimist? He thinks it’s a pity about life. A real pity. And what’s this - why has my beard grown? For ages and ages it wouldn’t grow at all, and now it has. What for?’

And he would shake his head at the sadness of it all, heaving his heart out in great, long sighs. Silence - then a deep, long sigh. More silence - and another sigh, longer and heavier.

That was how things stood right up to the trial and that last ghastly encounter with the old men. He woke up in his cell acutely aware that everything to do with living was over, and that ahead lay nothing but a few hours of waiting in emptiness, and then death - and it all seemed very strange. He felt as if he had been completely stripped in a most unusual way - stripped not only of his clothes, but also robbed of the sun, the air, sound and light, action and speech. As yet there was no death, but life had gone, already replaced by something new, something impenetrably obscure, either without any meaning or possessed of a meaning that was so profound, so mysterious and inhuman, that it could never be grasped.

‘Hell’s teeth!’ said Sergey in anguished amazement. ‘What is all this? Where do I come into it? What’s left of me ? ’

He took stock of himself closely, all over, fascinated by what he saw, from the baggy prison slippers to his own belly sticking out from his prison smock. He walked around his cell with his arms stretched out, still absorbed in himself like a woman trying on a new dress which is too long for her. He willed his head to turn, and it did turn. And this . . . this thing that somehow seemed rather frightening . . . this was him, Sergey Golovin, and this is what would cease to be.

And everything had become unreal.

He tried walking around his cell - and walking seemed unreal. He tried sitting down - and sitting seemed unreal. He tried taking a drink of water - and it seemed unreal that he was drinking, swallowing, holding a mug, using fingers, trembling fingers. He choked on the water, and as he cleared his throat and gave a cough, he thought to himself, ‘I’m coughing. It’s not real.’

‘Am I going round the bend, damn it?’ thought Sergey with a chilly feeling. ‘Bloody hell, that’s all I need!’

He rubbed his forehead with one hand, and even that seemed unreal. Then, holding his breath, he froze and stayed motionless for what seemed hours on end, extinguishing all thought, suppressing his deep breathing and avoiding any kind of movement - because the slightest thought meant madness, the slightest movement meant madness. Time had gone, it seemed to have been converted into space - translucent and airless - a vast physical area with everything there upon it, the earth, life and people, and all of it could be absorbed at a single glance, all of it right up to the end, to the very edge of mystery, to death itself. Some sacrilegious hand had drawn aside the ageold curtain hiding the mystery of life and the mystery of death, rendering them no longer mysterious, though still incomprehensible. It was like a truth engraved in a foreign language. His human brain had no access to the concepts, and his human speech had no access to the words, needed to capture what he had seen. And if the words ‘I’m dead scared’ had any meaning, it was only because there were no other words available, no other concepts that corresponded to this new, inhuman condition - their existence was impossible. It would be like this if a human being, with only his human capacity for understanding, his experience and his feelings to go on, were suddenly to get a glimpse of God himself, seeing without understanding, even though he knew this thing was called God. He would be left shuddering with the unimaginable agony of unimaginable incomprehension.

‘That’s what Müller does for you!’ he shouted out loud with incredible passion, shaking his head. And with that sudden change of feeling that the human spirit is so prone to, he laughed with genuine delight. ‘Oh Müller! My dear old Müller! My truly wonderful German friend! But you are quite right, brother Müller. I’m the ass here.’

He walked around his cell a few times and then amazed the soldier observing him through the peephole by stripping himself naked and applying himself diligently to a performance of all eighteen exercises. He stretched his young, rather slimmeddown body upwards and outwards, squatted on his heels and strained up on tiptoes, inhaling and exhaling, flinging his arms and legs out wide. And after each exercise he spoke out smugly. ‘That’s the way to do it! That’s the real thing, brother Müller!’

His cheeks glowed, and droplets of lovely, hot sweat emerged from every pore; his heartbeat was steady and strong.

‘The thing is, Müller,’ thought Sergey, expanding his chest so that his ribs were clearly outlined under the taut, thin skin. ‘The thing is this. There is a nineteenth exercise: hanging by the neck from a fixed position. It’s called execution. Do you get that, Müller? They take a living being - say Sergey Golovin - they wrap him up like a doll, and hang him by the neck until he is dead. It’s a stupid thing to do, Müller, but it can’t be helped. It’s got to happen.’

9. Horror In Solitary

To the same chimes, only a few empty cells along from Sergey and Musya, though as desperately lonely as if he was the only living creature in the universe, the miserable Vassily Kashirin was ending his life in anguish and terror. Covered in sweat, with his wet shirt clinging to his body and his once curly hair all over the place, he rushed around his cell frantic with despair like a man with unbearable toothache. He would sit down for a while, then get up and run or press his forehead against the wall or search for something with his eyes, as if he was looking for medicine. He had changed so much that he seemed to have had two different faces: his earlier face, a young one, had gone away to be replaced by a new one, a terrible face emerging from darkness.

He had been suddenly overwhelmed by a fear of death, which had seized him completely and now held him in its grip. Only that morning, while staring death in the face, he had been ‘messing about’ with it, but by evening, in the solitary confinement of his cell, he had been engulfed and flattened by an inexorable tide of terror. While he had always been risking danger and death on his own terms, and had kept control over his own death, however terrible it might be, he had carried on flippantly, even enjoying himself. Any suggestion of a wrinkled, oldwomanish fear was submerged in a spirit of absolute freedom and the need to prove his daring and fearless character through sheer strength of will. Fastening the belt which carried the infernal machine, he seemed to become the infernal machine, assuming the ruthless reasoning of dynamite as he acquired its firepower and deathdealing energy. And as he made his way along the street through the busy throng of people absorbed in their own workaday concerns, skipping out of the way of cabhorses and trams, he felt like a new arrival from an unknown alien realm where there was no knowledge of death or fear.

Then suddenly - a sharp, savage, shattering change. He was no longer going where he wanted to go; he was being taken where other people wanted him to go. He could no longer choose a place to be; they were putting him into a stone cage and locking him up like an inanimate object. He was no longer free to make his own decisions about living or dying like everybody else; they were definitely and inevitably going to put him to death. In a splitsecond he, the incarnation of strong will, life and strength, had come to be a pathetic example of helplessness unique in all the world, newly transformed into an animal lined up for slaughter, an empty thing incapable of speech that could be moved around, set fire to, broken up. Not a word of anything he said would ever be heard, and if he started screaming they would gag him. If he moved his legs, they would take him away and hang him, and if he showed any resistance, put up a struggle or lay down on the ground, they would force him to his feet, tie him up and take him away, bound hand and foot to the gallows. And the fact that the mechanical procedure being thrust upon him was being carried out by people just like him made them seem weird, unreal and sinister, either phantoms, creatures of pretence intent on deception, or mechanized marionettes worked by springs: designed to fetch and grab, take away, hang, pull down on his legs. To cut through rope, haul down, cart away and bury. And from the very first day of his imprisonment, people and life became for him an unbelievably horrific world consisting of these phantoms and mechanized marionettes.

All but speechless from terror, he tried to convince himself that they did have tongues and the power of speech, but he couldn’t bring himself to believe it: they seemed unable to talk. He tried to remember them speaking and what their words had meant when they were in communication, but he couldn’t. Their mouths gaped open, sounds came out, they walked around, and that’s all they did.

This is what you would feel like if, one night when you were at home alone, all the pieces of furniture came to life, moved about and took complete control of you. Suddenly they would have you up before the court - cupboard, chair, desk and sofa. You could remonstrate and chase around, begging for mercy and screaming for help, but they would rabbit on with each other in their own language, and then dispatch you to be hanged - that cupboard, chair, desk and sofa. With the other household objects looking on.

And Vassily Kashirin, sentenced to be hanged by the neck until dead, began to see the whole thing as Toyland: his cell, the door with its peephole, the chiming of the wellwound clock, the intricately sculpted fortress building, and especially that mechanized marionette with a gun, stamping up and down the corridor, and all the others who stared at him scarily through the little window, and brought him food without talking. And what he was experiencing was not the fear of death - no, if anything he wanted to die. Death, in all its ageold, unfathomable mystery, was more susceptible to reason than this world, which had turned into something so savage and fantastic. Besides, death was somehow being steadily and completely extinguished in a crazy world of phantoms and puppets, and losing its enormous and mysterious significance as it also became a mechanical process and only for that reason something to be dreaded. Fetch and grab, take away, hang, pull down on the legs. Cut rope, haul down, cart away and bury.

A man has gone from the world.

In court, a spirit of comradeship had brought Kashirin to his senses, and just for a moment he had been able to see people again. They were sitting there, trying him and saying things to each other in human speech; they were also listening, and seemed to be taking things in. But at the meeting with his mother, with the horror of a man who is losing his reason and knows it, he had clearly sensed that this old woman in a black headscarf was nothing more than a cleverly constructed mechanical doll - one of those that can say ‘ Dada’ or ‘ Mamma’, only better made. He made an effort to talk to her, but he was thinking to himself, with a shudder, ‘God in heaven! This is a doll. It’s a mother doll. And that’s a toy soldier, and there’s a daddy doll at home - and this is a Vassily Kashirin doll.’

Any minute now, he felt sure, he would hear the whirr of a motor or the squeak of unoiled wheels. When his mother burst into tears, there was a momentary flash of humanity, but it vanished the moment she spoke, and he was nonplussed and horrified to see water coming from her doll’s eyes. Later on, in his cell, when the horror became unbearable, Vassily Kashirin turned to prayer. From all that had passed for religion in his life as a young man in the tradesman’s home headed by his father, only a nasty, bitter, disgusting aftertaste remained, and there was no faith in it. But at some time, probably in his early childhood, he had heard a short sequence of words which had made him shiver with emotion and had stayed with him throughout his life as a breath of pure poetry. The words were about ‘bringing joy to the afflicted’.

So it happened that in his darkest moments he would murmur to himself, ‘Joy to the afflicted’, without actually praying and with no real understanding, though this lifted his spirits and made him want to go up to some dear person and gently protest about things by saying, ‘This life of ours . . . can you call it life? Oh, my dear girl, can you really call it life?’

Then he would suddenly get an urge to fool about, ruffling his hair, dropping down on one knee and offering his breast to be beaten, with a cry of ‘Come on, strike me down!’

He never told anyone, not even his closest friends, about his ‘Joy to the afflicted’, and he seemed to be unaware of it himself, so deeply hidden was it inside him. He rarely brought it back to mind, and when he did it was with wary reluctance.

And now that all the horror of an insoluble mystery had come shockingly visible into his head and swamped him like a spring torrent rushing down a channel to the sea, he felt a sudden urge to pray. He wanted to get down on his knees, but he was too embarrassed to do so in front of the soldier, so he folded his arms across his chest and said in a whisper, ‘Joy to the afflicted!’

And in a voice full of anguish and emotion, he repeated himself slowly and clearly: ‘Joy to the afflicted, come unto me, give succour to Vaska Kashirin.’

Long ago, while still living it up as a firstyear student,before meeting Werner and joining the society, he had called himself, cockily and pathetically, Vaska Kashirin - and now he felt an urge to use that name again. But those few words, ‘Joy to the afflicted!’, still rang out with a deathly, hollow ring.

Something had stirred. It was as if a distant image of some gentle and sorrowful figure had come into view, only to fade away gently without lighting up the darkness of impending death. The clock chimed in the tower, dead on time. The soldier in the corridor made a rattling noise that could have come from a sword or gun, and then gave a prodigious yawn with juddering pauses.

‘Joy to the afflicted! Why don’t you speak? Haven’t you got anything to say to Vaska Kashirin?’

He gave a smile full of emotion, and waited. But there was only emptiness, inside and all around him. And the gentle and sorrowful figure did not come back. What did come back to him were needless and painful memories of lighted wax candles, a priest in his robes, a painted icon on the wall, and also the holy father, bending and unbending as he said his prayers and gave his bows, with one eye on Vaska to check that he was praying and not misbehaving. And it all became more ghastly than it had been before the prayer.

Everything had gone.

The madness crept on, unbearable. His mind was fading like the scattered embers of a dying campfire, and cooling like the corpse of a newly dead person with some residual warmth in the heart when the feet and hands have already gone stiff. Once again, with a rush of blood, the fading power of his thought told him that he, Vaska Kashirin, might be going out of his mind here and now, and might experience the kind of suffering for which there was no name, taking him to extremes of pain and agony the like of which no living being had ever known, that he could beat his head against the wall, gouge his own eyes out with a fingernail, say or shout anything that came into his head, weep and swear that he could not take any more of this - and it would mean nothing. Absolutely nothing.

And nothing is what ensued. There were legs down there with a mind and life of their own, still walking about and supporting his shaking, soaking body. There were hands with a mind of their own vainly trying to tighten the smock that kept falling open across his chest, and warm his shaking, soaking body. His body was shivering and freezing. There were eyes still looking. There was something akin to relief in this.

But there was still one shock of pure horror to come: when people walked into his cell. Not getting the message - that the time for his execution had come - he just saw people standing there, and he panicked, almost like a child.

‘Not going! Not going!’ he murmured inaudibly through deadened lips as he gently withdrew towards the back of the cell, as he had recoiled in childhood when his father had raised his hand.

‘Time to get on the road.’

They were saying things, walking about, giving him something.

He shut his eyes, swaying a little - and he took his time getting ready to go. It must have meant that his mind was beginning to come back to him when he asked an official for a cigarette. The man politely opened his cigarettecase with its decadent fancy patterning.

10. The Walls Come Tumbling Down

The unidentified prisoner known as Werner was a man who had grown weary of living and struggling. There had been a time when he had a great love of life, enjoying the theatre, literature and good company. Endowed with an excellent memory and strong willpower, he had studied several European languages in depth and could easily pass for a German, a Frenchman or an Englishman. He usually spoke German with a Bavarian accent, but he could switch at will and talk like a trueborn Berliner. He was a lover of fine clothes and a man of exquisite manners, the only member of his fraternity who dared to appear in highsociety ballrooms without risk of being recognized.

But long ago, imperceptibly to his comrades, he had become sardonically disaffected with people at some deep level of the spirit; it was a case of being weighed down by a fatal mixture of desperation and worldweariness. By nature more mathematician than poet, he had had no experience of inspiration or ecstasy, and with every passing minute he felt like a madman trying to square the circle by wading through puddles of human blood. The demon he fought against on a daily basis could not imbue him with selfrespect; it was the usual entanglement of stupidity, foul play and falsehood, dirty tricks and filthy deception. The last straw, the thing that seemed to have broken his will to live once and for all, was when he murdered a provocateur on orders from the centre. He did the killing calmly, but after one glance at that dead human face of treachery, now at peace, though also pathetic to look at, he immediately lost all selfrespect and belief in his cause. It wasn’t a question of sudden remorse; he simply lost every last trace of selfesteem and the slightest interest in himself - he had become insignificant, a tedious irrelevancy. As a man of singleminded, unbreakable will, he stayed on in the organization, ostensibly unchanged, though his eyes had now taken on the glint of something cold and terrible. He said not a word to anyone.

He possessed one other sharply defined quality. Just as there are some people who have never had a headache, so he was a man who had never known fear. And when other people were afraid of something, he looked on this without condemning them, but also without any particular sympathy, as if it was some kind of common ailment that he happened never to have suffered from. He did feel some pity towards his colleagues, especially Vasya Kashirin, but it was a frigid, almost officially sanctioned feeling, something that some of the judges were probably not unfamiliar with.

Werner had realized that execution is not just a matter of dying, but something more. Anyway, he decided to confront it calmly, as if it had no relevance, by living right up to the end as if nothing had happened and nothing was going to happen. This was the only means of expressing his lofty contempt for execution and preserving the last form of inalienable freedom - that of the spirit. Even in court - and this would have been almost unbelievable even to his colleagues, who were fully aware of his capacity for cool detachment and complete disdain - far from thinking about dying or living, he had been calmly working through a difficult game of chess, and this had held his closest and deepest powers of concentration. As a firstrate chessplayer, he had launched into this game on the first day of his imprisonment, and had kept it going without interruption. And when he was sentenced to death by hanging, not a single piece was moved on his imaginary board.

Even the fact that he would never be able to finish the game did not stop him, and he started the morning of the last day of his life on earth by going back to put right a rather unsuccessful ploy made the previous day. Squeezing his lowered hands between his knees, he stayed rigid in a sitting position for quite some time, then he got to his feet and began walking about, deep in thought. He had a strange way of walking. Tilting his upper body slightly forwards, he banged down sharply on his heels, so that even on the dry ground his steps rang out with an unmistakable clatter. Softly, only by breathing out, he whistled a little Italian arietta - it helped his thinking.

But this time, for some reason, things went wrong. With an uncomfortable feeling that he had committed a big mistake, even a terrible blunder, he went back on himself several times and checked his game almost from the start. There was no blunder, but the feeling of having made a mistake would not leave him; it grew stronger and more irksome. Then he was struck by an unexpected and offensive idea: maybe the mistake was to use a game of chess to distract his mind from execution and thus protect himself against the fear of death that would seem to be inevitable for a condemned man?

‘Hm. Why would I do that?’ he responded coldly, and calmly folded the board away. And, with the same degree of close attention that he reserved for the game of chess, like an examination candidate facing a stiff test, he tried to take account of his horrific situation, from which there was no escape. He looked around the room, trying to leave nothing out, worked out how many hours were left before the execution, sketched out an approximate, though reasonably accurate, picture of the execution itself, and then shrugged his shoulders.

‘So what’s it all about?’ he asked of no one in particular, halfquestioningly. ‘That’s all there is to it. Where’s the fear in that?’

No, there was nothing to fear. And not only was there nothing to fear, something had been creeping up on him that seemed to be the opposite of what he stood for - a hazy but challenging sensation of enormous joy. And the stillundiscovered mistake no longer seemed so irksome or disappointing; it, too, spoke strongly of something good and quite unexpected, as if he had lost a close friend in death, only to find that he was still alive, sound in wind and limb, and rejoicing.

Werner gave another shrug, and took his own pulse. His heartbeat was up a little, but still strong and regular, a resonant force. Once again, like a new inmate, he took a close look at the walls, the bars, the chair fastened to the floor,and a sudden thought struck him. ‘Why am I feeling so easy and happy and free? Especially free ? When I think about the execution tomorrow, it doesn’t seem to be there. When I look at the walls, they don’t seem to be there. And I feel so free it’s like being on the outside, newly released from a prison that I’ve been in all my life. What is it all about?’

His hands were beginning to tremble - a new experience for Werner. And his head was more and more filled with furious ideas. It was as if tongues of flame were leaping out inside his head, and the fire had been struggling to get out and shine all over a broad nocturnal landscape that stretched out into the dark distance. And now it was on the outside, and the longreceding landscape was lit up and shining.

Gone was the enervating lassitude that had worn Werner down for the last two years; a clammy, deadweight serpent with tightshut eyes and a ghastly pinchedup mouth had fallen away from his heart. In the presence of death, a wonderful youthfulness was being restored to him with its spirit of play. It was something more than wonderful youthfulness. With one of those amazing flashes of spiritual insight that occur to people on rare occasions, raising them to the highest heights of consciousness, Werner suddenly saw life and death brought together, and he was stunned by the splendour of this undreamtof spectacle. It was like walking along the knifeedge of the highest possible mountain range, seeing life on one side and death on the other in the form of two deep, gorgeous and gleaming seascapes merging at the horizon into a single expanse of infinite space.

‘What is this? What a heavenly vision!’ he said, speaking slowly and automatically raising himself and coming to attention as if he was in the presence of a supreme being. And all things - walls, time and space - were obliterated as he peered with piercing insight into the full depth and breadth of the life that he was leaving.

And life was suddenly different. No longer did he attempt to express what he had seen in words; there were no words in the sparse and meagre resources of human language. Gone for good was the tiny impulse of bitter unpleasantness that used to evoke in him a disdain for other people, and sometimes even a feeling of revulsion at the sight of a human face. It was like a man going up in a hotair balloon and watching the filthy rubbish of narrow streets disappear as his small town falls away, and ugliness turns into beauty.

Werner walked mechanically over to the table, and leant on it with his right hand. Proud and imperious by nature, he had never struck such a proud, liberated and imperious pose as this, never turned his neck in such a way, or adopted such a glare - because he had never before felt as liberated and imperious as he now did, here in prison just a few hours away from execution and death.

And people were suddenly different; they now looked all pleasant and charming under his newly enlightened gaze. Soaring away beyond time, he could see clearly how young humanity was, only yesterday a beast howling in the forest; and the things that had seemed disgusting in people, horribly unforgivable, had turned into something rather nice - not unlike a toddler’s inability to walk properly like an adult, or its babbling chatter filled with sparkling gems of wit, its amusing blunders, slips and painful bruises.

‘My dear friends!’ Werner gave a sudden, unexpected smile, and instantly lost all the authority of his pose, becoming a prisoner again, suffering the narrowness and discomfort of confinement, increasingly irritated by the intrusively searching eye that stood out against the flatness of the door. And there was something odd: almost instantly he had forgotten what he had been seeing with such sharpness and clarity. Odder still: he made no attempt to recall it. He simply shifted into an easier sitting position, disregarding his usual indifference to bodily discomfort, and with an uncharacteristically feeble and tender smile, nothing like the old Werner grin, he stared at the walls and bars. Then something else occurred that was so unlike Werner it had not happened before: he burst into tears.

‘My dear comrades!’ he whispered through bitter tears. ‘My dear comrades!’

By what secret ways had he travelled from that feeling of pride and limitless freedom to this pathetic display of tenderness and passion? He did not know and didn’t even wonder about it. And whether he was simply feeling sorry for those people, his dear comrades, or whether there was something else, something nobler and more impassioned, hidden behind his tears, even this was unknown to his heart, so suddenly resurrected and springlike.

‘My dear comrades! Oh, my dear comrades!’

In this bitterly weeping figure, smiling through his tears, no one would have recognized the cold, aloof, worldweary,arrogant Werner - not the judges, nor his comrades, nor Werner himself.

11. On Their Way

Before the condemned prisoners were put into their carriages, all five were brought together in a large, cold room with a vaulted ceiling that looked like a disused office or an empty waitingroom. They were allowed to talk among themselves.

But the only one to take immediate advantage of this permission was Tanya Kovalchuk. The others were silently squeezing each other’s hands, cold as ice or hot as fire - and silently avoiding eyecontact as they crowded together in an embarrassed little gang with blank faces. Now that they were together again, they were all rather ashamed of what they had been feeling when they were alone, and they were afraid to look at each other, not wanting to see or to display the various, peculiar and rather shameful things they had experienced, or suspected in themselves, as individuals.

But once a couple of glances had been exchanged, they started smiling at each other, and immediately everything felt as natural and easygoing as before; no change had occurred, and if something had occurred, the weight of it was shared between them so equally that it was barely noticeable to each individual. They all spoke and moved about awkwardly, in quick bursts and snatches, or else much too slowly, or too rapidly; sometimes words stuck in throats, and there was much repetition; some sentences were left unfinished or taken as understood, and nobody took any notice. They were all screwing up their eyes and staring at everyday objects with close attention as if they couldn’t recognize them, like people used to wearing spectacles who had suddenly taken them off. All of them kept turning around and taking a sharp look behind them, as if someone at their back had called out with something to show them. But this too went unnoticed. Musya and Tanya Kovalchuk had burning cheeks and ears; Sergey had seemed rather pallid at first, but he soon came through it and began to look like his old self.

Vassily was the only one who attracted their attention. Even amongst these people he looked awful, and out of place. This roused Werner to a mixture of sympathy and anxiety, and he spoke to Musya. ‘What’s wrong with him, Musechka? Is he . . . you know . . . ? We ought to go over and talk to him.’

Vassily gave them a vacant stare, staring at Werner as if he didn’t recognize him, and then looking down.

‘What have you done to your hair, Vasya, eh? Now, what’s all this? Nothing to worry about, brother. Soon be over now. Got to tough it out. That’s what we’ve got to do.’

Vassily did not speak. For a long time it seemed as if he wasn’t going to say anything at all, but then a response came, a belated, lifeless sound from terribly far away, like the grave itself reacting to endless calls.

‘I’m all right. I will tough it out.’ And he repeated: ‘I will tough it out.’

Werner was delighted to hear it. ‘There you are. Good lad. That’s the way.’

But he was met by a dark, leaden stare coming from the distant deeps, and an anguished thought flashed across his mind. What was his angle of vision? Where was he coming from when he said things? And, with the deepest sensitivity, he spoke out in sepulchral tones. ‘Vasya, listen to me. I love you, very dearly.’

‘I love you too.’ His leaden answer quavered on the tongue.

Suddenly Musya took hold of Werner’s hand, and spoke to him, overplaying her surprise, like an actress on the stage: ‘What’s this, Werner? You - talking about love? You’ve never talked about love to anybody. Suddenly you’re all . . . you know . . . brighteyed and gentle. What’s it all about?’

‘What are you getting at?’

And Werner, also overplaying things like an actor, squeezed Musya’s hand. ‘Yes, I do feel love now. Don’t tell on me, please. It’s embarrassing. But I do feel love.’

Their eyes met and flashed with brightness while everything around them faded, the way that all other lights are dimmed in a sudden flash of lightning as the intense yellow flame casts a dark shadow on the ground.

‘Yes, yes,’ said Musya. ‘It’s all right, Werner.’

‘Yes, Musya,’ he said. ‘Yes, it is.’

Something had passed between them, something understood and firmly established. And Werner’s eyes were still flashing when he felt another rush of feeling and strode over to Sergey.

‘Seryozha!’

But it was Tanya Kovalchuk who responded. In a transport of delight and on the verge of tears from maternal pride, she snatched furiously at Sergey’s sleeve. ‘Werner,’ she said, ‘Listen to me. I’m in tears over him. Out of my mind. And he’s doing his exercises.’

‘The Müller system?’ said Werner with a smile.

Sergey frowned with embarrassment. ‘You can laugh, Werner, but I’m absolutely sure . . .’

They all shared a good laugh. Coming together like this, and gathering strength in the black fortress, they were steadily reverting to what they had been before, but they didn’t see this and thought nothing had changed. Suddenly Werner put a stop to their laughter and spoke to Sergey with some gravity.

‘You’re right, Seryozha. Quite right.’

‘No, you don’t understand,’ said Golovin, more cheerfully. ‘Of course, we . . .’

But at this point an announcement was made: it was time to get on the road. And the guards were kind enough to let them sit together in pairs as they chose. They were indeed kindness itself, almost too kind, either making a display of their humanity or else pretending they were not there at all, and everything was running itself. But they looked pale.

‘Musya, you go with him,’ said Werner, pointing to Vassily, who was standing there transfixed.

‘I get your meaning.’ Musya nodded. ‘What about you?’

‘Me? Tanya goes with Sergey, and you’re with Vasya . . . I’ll be on my own. That’s all right. I can cope with that. You know me.’

Once they were outside, the warm dampness of a dark night struck them, softly but sharply, straight in the face and eyes, taking their breath away in a gentle, cleansing stream that swept right through their shivering bodies. It was hard to believe that this bewildering feeling came from nothing more than a spring breeze, warm and moist. It was a real spring night, astonishingly beautiful, with a scent of melting snow amid tinkling droplets in the boundless empty space. Tumbling showers of rapid raindrops busily chased each other down, pitterpattering in the close harmony of song until one of them lost the beat and the whole thing collapsed into the muddle of a happy fandango. After that, a big strong raindrop would set up a new beat, and off went the pitterpatter into another fast spring song, neatly and resonantly performed. And a pale glow from the electric lights shone down on the town, and the fortress roofs.

‘ Ooh!’Sergey Golovin took a deep breath and held it, as if reluctant to let such lovely fresh air out of his lungs.

‘How long has the weather been like this?’ Werner wanted to know. ‘It’s just like spring.’

‘Only a couple of days.’ The response was obligingly polite. ‘But we still get bad frosts.’

One by one the dark carriages were brought up. Each of them accepted two passengers before trundling off into the darkness towards a lantern swinging at the gates. Each was surrounded by the grey silhouettes of guards, and the horses’ hooves rang out, clattering on the road surface or slithering through the wet snow.

Just as Werner bent down to get into his carriage, one of the guards made a casual observation: ‘Somebody else travelling with you.’

Werner was taken aback. ‘Where to? Where’s he going? What do you mean -somebody else?’

The guard said nothing. Sure enough, something small and still but obviously alive was squashed into a dark corner of the carriage, as he could see from an angled shaft of light from a lantern that picked out the glint of an open eye. In the process of getting into his seat, Werner bumped against somebody’s knee.

‘Sorry, my friend.’

There was no response. It was only when the carriage had started to roll forward that he asked a question in halting Russian, with a stammer. ‘Who . . . who are you . . . ?’

‘My name is Werner. Sentenced to death by hanging for the attempted assassination of N.N. Who are you?’

‘Er, Yanson. Not to hang me.’

Here they were, riding along a couple of hours from facing the huge, inscrutable mystery of passing over from life to death, and they had just met. Life and death were operating together in two simultaneous planes, but life was still life, down to the silliest laughable details.

‘What did you do, Yanson?’

‘Stabbed my boss. Killed him. For the money.’

To judge by his voice, Yanson seemed halfasleep.

Werner found his limp hand in the darkness and gave it a squeeze. Yanson extracted his hand just as feebly.

‘Are you feeling scared?’ asked Werner.

‘I don’t want.’

Neither of them spoke. Werner found the Estonian’s hand a gain a nd g ave i t a s trong s queeze b etween h is own two dry, burninghot palms. It lay there, lifeless and stiff as a bit of board, and Yanson no longer tried to withdraw it.

It was cramped and stuffy in the carriage; there was a smell of soldiers’ clothes, stale air, manure and sodden bootleather. A junior guard was sitting across from Werner, and his hot breath reeked of onions and cheap tobacco. But there were a few cracks through which pungent fresh air made its way into this stuffy little box on wheels, and this was more springlike than outside. The carriage lurched right and left, and even seemed to turn back on itself; sometimes it gave an impression of circling for hours on end without moving from one spot. To begin with, a bluish electric light shone in through the thick blinds which had been lowered over the windows, then suddenly, following one particularly sharp turn, it went slightly darker, this being the only means of guessing that they had turned off into the godforsaken streets of the outskirts and were getting close to the S— railway terminal. Now and again, at sharp turns, Werner’s bent knee, still living, bumped chummily against the guard’s living bent knee, and execution was a hard thing to believe in.

‘Where are we going?’ Yanson suddenly asked.

His head was spinning a little from the constant twisting and turning of the dark box, and he felt slightly sick.

Werner g ave h is a nswer, a nd squeezed the E stonian’s hand all the harder. He felt like saying something particularly friendly and affectionate to this sleepy little man, and he felt a greater love for him than for anyone ever before.

‘My dear friend! You don’t look too comfortable sitting like that. Come a bit closer.’

Yanson was quiet for a moment, and then gave his response. ‘No, thanks. I’m all right. You going to be hung?’

‘Yes!’ Werner answered in a surprisingly cheerful tone,

almost laughing, and he waved his hand casually, almost exaggeratedly relaxed, as if this was a laughing matter, some silly trick that nice people with a terrible sense of humour wanted to play on him.

‘You married?’ asked Yanson.

‘Oh no. No wife for me. I’m on my own.’

‘I’m not . . . not married, I mean,’ said Yanson, correcting himself after a bit of thought.

By now, even Werner’s head was beginning to swim. And as the minutes went by it seemed more and more as if they were on their way to some kind of celebration. It is a strange fact that almost all people on their way to execution have had this feeling; along with all the anguish and terror, they have a vague sense of enjoying the bizarre event that was about to take place. Reality runs away with fantasy, and death joins forces with life to create new visions. It seemed quite likely that bunting would have been put out for them.

‘Here we are,’ said Werner cheerily, looking up with new interest, when the carriage stopped, and he nipped out smartly. But Yanson was taking his time. Saying nothing, but holding onto things with a feeble grip, he refused to get out. When he took hold of a handle, the guard had no trouble in loosening the lifeless fingers and prising his hand free; when he took hold of a corner, the door, one of the tall wheels, he was eased away from them by a guard who hardly had to exert himself. He hadn’t really got hold of these things; the uncommunicative Yanson was simply sticking sleepily to anything that came to hand, and he was quickly and effortlessly pulled away. At last he was out and on his feet.

There was no bunting. It was nighttime,

and the station was dark, deserted and lifeless. It was too early for the passenger trains to be running, and the silent train that awaited these passengers needed neither bright lights nor ceremony. And suddenly Werner felt bored with the whole thing. Not troubled by fear, but bored out of his mind and wearied by a hugely oppressive sense of tedium which made him want to go away somewhere and lie down with his eyes tight shut, Werner stretched himself and gave a prodigious yawn. Yanson followed him by stretching and giving a series of quick, short yawns.

‘Let’s get it over and done with!’ said Werner wearily. Yanson, with nothing to say, shrank into himself.

While the condemned prisoners were moving down the deserted platform, which had been cordoned off by soldiers, towards dimly lit carriages, Werner fetched up alongside Sergey Golovin, who pointed to one side and started talking, though only one thing was audible - the word ‘lantern’ - and even that was swallowed up in a great long and weary yawn.

‘What do you mean?’ asked Werner with an answering yawn.

‘That lantern. The lamp inside - it’s smoking,’ said Sergey.

Werner turned and looked at it: sure enough, the lamp inside the lantern was giving off thick smoke, and the glass panels were blackening at the top.

‘Yes, it is.’

And a sudden thought occurred to him. ‘Why on earth should I be bothered if the lamp’s smoking, when . . .’ The same thing had evidently occurred to Sergey; he glanced at Werner, and looked away. But both of them had stopped yawning.

All seven were heading for the carriages, and only Yanson needed to be taken by the arms. First, he had dragged his feet as if the soles of his shoes were sticking to the wooden platform, then he had bent his knees and hung in midair, held up by the guards, or dragged his legs like a drunk, with his socks scraping the boards. It took some time to get him in through the door, though he wasn’t speaking.

Vassily Kashirin got along on his own, but only by vaguely copying his friends - what they did, he did. But as he stepped through onto the carriage floor, he stumbled, and the guard took his arm to steady him, at which Vassily shuddered and gave a great roar as he shoved the hand away. ‘Aaargh!’

‘What’s up, Vasya?’ said Werner, moving in quickly.

Vassily said nothing. He was shaking all over. The guard, embarrassed and rather offended, explained himself.

‘I was only trying to help, but he . . .’

‘Come on, Vasya, I’ll give you a hand,’ said Werner, trying to take his arm. But once again Vassily shoved the hand away, and his roar was even louder. ‘Aaargh!’

‘Vasya, it’s me, Werner.’

‘I know. Leave me alone. I can manage.’ Still shaking, he got in on his own, and sat down in a corner of the carriage. Bending down towards Musya,Werner signalled with his eyes and spoke softly to her. ‘What do you make of that?’

‘Not good,’ she answered just as softly. ‘He’s already dead. Werner, is death real?’

‘I don’t know, Musya. I don’t think so,’ said Werner, seriousminded and thoughtful.

‘I thought you’d say that. But him? He wore me out in the carriage. Like riding with a corpse.’

‘I don’t know, Musya. Maybe death is real for some people. Just for a while. Then, afterwards, it won’t be. Death’s been real with me, but it isn’t now.’

Musya’s rather pallid cheeks flushed red. ‘Been real, Werner? Been?’

‘It’s been, and gone. Same for you.’ There was a racket at the carriage door. All banging heels, noisy breathing and reckless spitting, in came Gypsy Mike. He cast his eyes around, and stood his ground.

‘No room in here, guard!’ he shouted to the wornout guard who was watching him resentfully. ‘Give me some room, or I’m not going. You can hang me here on a lamppost. And that damn carriage, you bastards! Call that a carriage? Devil’s shit, that’s what it was!’

But then, suddenly, he lowered his head, stuck his neck out and walked in like that to be with the others. Framed by a wild shock of hair and beard, his piercing black eyes glared at them, on the brink of insanity. ‘Hello there, gentlemen! There we have it, then! Good morning, sir!’

Nudging Werner, he sat down across from him. Then, lowering his head into close proximity, he winked at him and flashed a hand across his neck. ‘You too, eh?’

‘Yes,’ said Werner with a smile.

‘All of ’em?’

‘All of ’em?’

‘Aha!’ Gypsy Mike gave a grin, and his eyes quickly probed them all, lingering for a while on Musya and Yanson. He winked again at Werner. ‘That minister?’

‘Yes. What about you?’

‘I, sir, am here on special business. No time for ministers!

I, sir, am a villain, that’s what I am. A killer. Don’t you worry, sir. Come a bit closer. I’m not here in your company because I want to be. Plenty of room for us all in the world to come.’

Then, from under his tousled mass of hair, his wild eyes swept across them all in one swift, suspicious stare. They returned his look without comment, but seriously and with evident sympathy. He gave another grin and several times he tapped Werner on the knee. ‘There you have it, sir. Like in that song: “Mother oaktree, oh so green, make no sound for me . . .” ’

‘Why do you keep calling me sir, when . . . ?’

‘That’s right,’ agreed Gypsy Mike with some satisfaction.

‘How can you be a sir when you’re going to hang next to me? Now that man’s a sir,’ he continued, pointing to the silent guard. ‘But that one of your lot is no worse than us.’ His eyes had picked out Vassily. ‘Sir . . . you’re scared too, aren’t you, sir?’

‘Not too bad,’ came the answer, dragged out thickly from a stiff tongue.

‘What do you mean “not too bad”? Don’t be ashamed.

No need to be ashamed. Only a dog wags its tail and grins at you when it’s going to be hung, and you’re a man, aren’t you? And who’s that with the big long ears? Not one of yours, is he?’

His eyes kept darting about, and he was constantly slurping on sweet saliva as it welled up, and spitting it out. Yanson, who had squeezed himself into a rigid lump in the corner, slightly stirred the flaps on his fur cap, but he didn’t say anything.

‘Killed his boss.’

‘Good God!’ said Gypsy Mike in some surprise. ‘Do they really let blokes like him go around killing people?’

Gypsy Mike had been furtively eyeing Musya for some time, and now he suddenly rounded on her, staring hard and straight. ‘You, missy. How are you mixed up in this, missy? Look, she’s gone all pink, and she’s laughing. Look, she is, you know.’ He grabbed Werner by the knee, and his clutching fingers exerted a grip of iron. ‘Look at her. Look.’

Blushing a little and with a tiny smile of embarrassment, Musya stared straight into his piercing, halfcrazy eyes with their wild and wearily pleading look.

Nobody spoke.

The busy wheels drummed on, and the tiny carriages rocked on their narrow railway, going flat out. When the little engine came to a bend or a crossing, it gave a shrill, keen whistle, the driver not wanting to run over anybody. And it was barbarous to think that such a degree of routine human effort and efficiency should be applied to the hanging of people, and that the craziest deed on earth was being done in such a simple and rational manner. On went the carriages, with the people sitting there as they always do, travelling like normal travellers, waiting, as always, for the next stop. ‘This train will halt for five minutes.’

After that comes death - eternity - the great mystery.

12. Journey’s End

On went the little carriages, flat out.

Sergey Golovin had lived for several years with his parents in a house on this very route; he had travelled it by day and night, and he knew it well. If he closed his eyes it was easy to imagine that he was now on his way home; he had stayed late with friends in town and had caught the last train.

‘Not long now,’ he said, opening his eyes and peering out through the uncommunicatively dark window and its protective grille.

Nobody stirred or responded; only Gypsy Mike did anything,

and he was spitting out gobbets of saliva. He began to give his eyes a free run of the carriage, taking in the walls and feeling at the windows, the doors, the soldiers.

‘’S cold,’ said Vassily Kashirin through tight lips that seemed literally frozen. It came out as ‘’S coo— ’

Tanya Kovalchuk was fumbling with something. ‘Here’s a scarf. Tie it around your neck. It’s very warm.’

‘Round his neck ? ’ asked Sergey to everyone’s surprise, and he was shocked by his own question.

But since everybody was thinking the same thing, nobody heard it, as if no one had spoken or they had all said the same thing at the same time.

‘Never mind, Vasya. Wrap yourself up. Wrap up warm,’

was Werner’s advice, then he turned to Yanson and spoke to him in a kindly voice. ‘My dear friend, you must be feeling the cold.’

‘Werner, maybe he wants a smoke. Listen, my friend, do you fancy a smoke?’ asked Musya. ‘We’ve got fags.’

‘Oh, yes.’

‘Give him a cigarette, Seryozha,’ said Werner, perking up.

But Sergey was already getting one out. And they all looked on with affection as Yanson’s fingers accepted the cigarette, the match flared and a stream of deepblue smoke issued from Yanson’s mouth.

‘Oh, thanks,’ said Yanson. ‘That’s nice.’

‘Very funny thing,’ said Sergey.

‘What’s funny? asked Werner, turning towards him. ‘What’s funny about that?’

‘Well - just this cigarette.’ He was holding the cigarette,

an ordinary cigarette, in his ordinary, living fingers, and staring at it in amazement, as if he was transfixed with horror. And they all turned their eyes onto that thin little tube, watching as a ribbon of blue smoke curled up from the end to be blown away by their breath, and the ash built up and went dark. It went out.

‘It’s gone out,’ said Tanya.

‘Yes, it has.’

‘To hell with it!’ said Werner, scowling anxiously at Yanson, whose hand looked dead as it drooped down, still holding his cigarette. Suddenly Gypsy Mike whipped round and leaned across, bringing his face right up to Werner’s and rolling the whites of his eyes like a horse as he whispered to him. ‘Shall we get one of them guards, sir, eh? ’ave a little go?’

‘Don’t do that,’ said Werner, also in a whisper. ‘Just take what’s coming to you.’

‘What for? Bit of fun, ’avin’ a scrap, eh? I gives ’im one, ’e does me, and you don’t know when you’ve ’ad it. As if you wasn’t dead at all.’

‘No, don’t do it,’ said Werner, turning to Yanson. ‘Why aren’t you smoking, my friend?’

Suddenly Yanson’s flabby face crumpled pathetically. It was as if someone had pulled a string that worked his face, and his wrinkles had all crisscrossed each other. And he seemed to be halfasleep as he started whimpering, without shedding any tears, in a voice that was dry as dust, almost like playacting. ‘Don’t feel like smoking. Aargh! Aargh! Aargh! Nobody not to hang me. Aargh! Aargh! Aargh!’

Things were going on around him. With tears streaming down her face, Tanya Kovalchuk stroked his sleeve, straightened the sagging flaps of his tattered cap and spoke to him. ‘My lovely little man! Please don’t cry, my dear little boy! I know how unhappy you are!’

Musya looked away. Gypsy Mike caught her eye and gave one of his grins. ‘Funny chap, his honour. Drinks tea with the rest of us, but he’s got a chill in his belly,’ he said with a bit of a laugh. But his own face had turned a blueblack colour, and it looked like castiron. His big yellow teeth were chattering.

Then the little carriages jolted and noticeably slowed down. Everybody except Yanson and Kashirin rose up in their seats, and then, just as quickly, sat back down again.

‘Our stop!’ said Sergey.

All the air seemed to have been sucked out of the carriage, it was so hard to breathe. Swelling hearts threatened to burst through the walls of their chests, blocking throats, thumping wildly and screaming from terror in voices coursing with blood. All eyes were cast down at the shuddering floor; all ears followed the sound of wheels going round and round, slower and slower, skidding, going round again, then - coming to a sudden stop.

The train had halted.

Then the dreamworld took over. Not that it was all that terrifying; it was a ghostworld, mindbendingly weird and alien, with the dreamer himself left out of things and only his bodiless shade moving about, speaking without sound and agonizing without agony. They were sleepwalking their way out of the carriage, forming up in pairs and drinking in the woodland air with all its special springtime freshness. Yanson was dumbly sleepwalking as he put up a show of feeble resistance, only to be forcibly ejected from the carriage without a word.

They dropped down from the little steps.

‘Are we walking it?’ someone asked, almost cheerily.

‘Not far to go,’ said someone else, just as cheerily.

Then they set off in a large, black group of silent people, walking through woodland down a badly maintained road in all the gentle springtime dampness. Bracing air blew at them fresh from the woods; it was slippery underfoot and when they ran into deeper snow, hands reached out instinctively for a companion. Heavy breathing came from the escorting guards, who were having a tough time struggling through nothing but deep snow. A voice spoke out angrily. ‘They might have cleared the road. Fancy leaving us to muck about in this lot!’

Someone else put in an apologetic explanation. ‘They did clear it, sir. Can’t do nothing about the thaw, though.’

Consciousness was coming back, but only partly, in odd little bits and pieces. A moment’s sensible thought confirmed it.

‘That’s right. They couldn’t possibly have cleared the road.’

Then everything started to fade away again, leaving nothing but a sense of smell, the unbearably pungent aroma of air, woodland and melting snow, and the next moment everything stood out with unbelievable clarity - the woods, the night, the roadway, and the fact that they were on their way to being hanged - any minute now, straightaway. The snatches of whispered talk were strained and desultory.

‘Soon be four o’clock.’

‘I said we were leaving early.’

‘Gets light at five.’

‘Yes, it does. Ought to have . . .’

It was still dark when they stopped in an open space. Not far ahead was a thin patch of trees that could be seen through because it was winter, and there you could see two silent lanterns bobbing about. And the gallows.

‘I’ve lost one of my galoshes,’ said Sergey Golovin.

‘You what?’ said Werner, not getting his idea.

‘I’ve lost one of my galoshes. It’s cold.’

‘Where’s Vassily got to?’

‘Don’t know. Oh, that’s him over there.’

It was Vassily, a dark, motionless figure.

‘What about Musya?’

‘I’m here. Is that you, Werner?’

They were now taking a good look around, though avoiding the place where the lanterns were bobbing about with a horrific meaning that was only too clear. To their left, the bare woods seemed to have thinned out, allowing a huge, smooth, white shape to stare through at them, and a wet wind to blow.

‘It’s the sea,’ said Sergey Golovin, sniffing the air and tasting it in his mouth. ‘That’s the sea.’

Musya’s response was sonorously poetic. ‘My love is wider than the open sea . . .’

‘What’s all that about, Musya?’

‘My love is wider than the open sea, unbounded by the shoreline of our lives . . .’

‘My love is wider than the open sea . . .’ Sergey repeated the words pensively, succumbing to the voice, the sounds, the words.

‘My love is wider than the open sea . . .’ Werner repeated them too, then suddenly a thrill of delight took him by surprise. ‘Muska, you’re still such a young thing!’

Close upon him, straight into Werner’s ear, came an urgent, gasping whisper from Gypsy Mike: ‘Sir, listen. Sir. Look at them woods, eh? What the hell is that? Them lanterns over there. See? Is that where they does the ’anging? What is it?’

Werner took a look. Gypsy Mike was in a desperate state, aware of his impending death.

‘We should start saying goodbye . . .’ said Tanya Kovalchuk.

‘Hang on, they’ve still got to read out the sentence,’ said Werner. ‘What’s happened to Yanson?’

Yanson was lying in the snow, and there were people nearby, seeing to him. There was a sudden strong whiff of ammonia.

‘What’s holding you up, doctor? Nearly ready?’ The question sounded impatient.

‘It’s all right. He’s only fainted. Wipe his ears with snow. Look, he’s coming round. You can start the reading.’

Light from a hidden lantern fell across a document held in white, ungloved hands. Document and hands were all a bit shaky, as was the voice.

‘Gentlemen, shall we do without the reading? I think you all know what it says. What do you think?’

‘Don’t read it,’ said Werner, answering for them all, and the little lantern went out.

They also refused the services of a priest, and a large, black silhouette slipped away silently into the depths of darkness. Dawn seemed to be coming up; the snow looked a little whiter than before, the bodies a little darker, as the woods thinned out, taking on a more ordinary, yet more pathetic, appearance.

‘Gentlemen, you must walk on in twos. Please pair off as you wish, but I must ask you to get a move on.’

Werner pointed to Yanson, who was back on his feet, supported by two guards. ‘I’ll go with him. Seryozha, you take Vassily. Off you go.’

‘Right.’

‘Are we going together, Musechka?’ asked Kovalchuk. ‘Come on. Give us a kiss.’

Kisses were rapidly exchanged. Gypsy Mike’s kiss was heavy - you could feel his teeth; Yanson’s was soft and limp,with his mouth halfopen - he didn’t seem to know what he was doing. When Sergey Golovin and Kashirin had taken a few steps, Kashirin came to a sudden stop and called out loud and clear, in a strange voice that didn’t belong to him:‘Bye, comrades!’

‘Bye, comrades!’ came the answering call.

They walked off. It was now calm. The little lanterns through the trees had stopped bobbing about. They were expecting to hear a scream, a voice, some kind of noise - but it was just as calm up ahead and the little lanterns, now still, gave off a yellow gleam.

‘Oh, good God!’ came a w ild, hoarse c ry f rom one of them. They looked round. It was Gypsy Mike, still in his desperate condition with death now upon him. ‘They’ve started hanging them!’

They recoiled, and all was calm again. Gypsy Mike showed his desperation by clutching at the air. ‘This isn’t right! I ask you, gentlemen - me, all on my own? More fun with a bit of company, gentlemen. It’s not right !’

He grabbed Werner by the arm, his fingers squeezing tight and then relaxing as if it was some sort of game. ‘You, sir. My dear friend. Let me go with you. Please . . . Don’t say no.’

Werner agonized over his reply. ‘I can’t, my friend. I’m with him.’

‘Oh, my God! So, I’m on my own, am I? It’s not right, is it? Gentlemen !’

Musya took a step forward, and spoke softly. ‘Come on. You come with me.’

Gypsy Mike recoiled with a wild glare, rolling the whites of his eyes. ‘You?’

‘Yes.’

‘Look at you . . . slip of a girl . . . aren’t you scared? Might be better off on my own. Forget it.’

‘No, I’m not scared.’

He gave his wide grin. ‘Look at you . . . and I’m a real villain . . . you must be feeling queasy . . . If you are, I’d be better on my own. Won’t hold it against you.’

Musya said nothing. In the thin light of early dawn, her face looked pale and mysterious. Then she went straight up to Gypsy Mike, put both hands around his neck and gave him a firm kiss on the lips. He took her by the shoulders with his fingers, pushed her away at arm’s length, and gave her another shake. Then, slobbering out loud with emotion, he kissed her on the lips, nose and eyes.

‘Come on, then!’

Suddenly the nearest soldier seemed to reel back, and his hands opened up, dropping his gun. But instead of bending down to pick it up, he stood still and hesitated for a moment, made a sharp turn and ran off like a blind man towards the woods and the untrodden snow.

‘Where are you off to?’ whispered his fellow soldier, frightened. ‘Stop!’

But the first man kept on, wading silently through the deep snow. He must have tripped over something because then he fell facedown in the snow with his arms flailing. He just lay there.

‘Pick your gun up, birdbrain, or I’ll do it for you,’ said Gypsy Mike ominously. ‘Don’t you know what duty is?’

The little lanterns were busy again. Werner and Yanson were next in line.

‘Goodbye, sir,’ said Gypsy Mike in a loud voice. ‘We’ll know each other in the next world. Don’t ignore me when you see me. And bring me a drink of water. It’s hot where I’m going.’

‘Goodbye.’

‘I don’t want,’ said Yanson.

But Werner took him by the hand, and the Estonian managed a few steps on his own before ostentatiously coming to a halt and throwing himself down on the snow. They bent over him, pulled him to his feet and carried him along; he put up only a feeble struggle against the hands that were holding him. Why wasn’t he screaming? He had probably forgotten that he still had a voice.

Again the little lanterns with their yellow light stopped all movement.

‘Oh well, Musechka, that means I’m on my own,’ said Tanya Kovalchuk sadly. ‘We’ve lived together, but here we are . . .’

‘Tanechka, my dear friend . . .’

But Gypsy Mike made an emotional intervention. Holding Musya’s hand, as if he was frightened of her being taken away from him, he spoke quickly, spelling things out. ‘Oh miss, you can manage on your own. You’re a pure soul. You can go wherever you want without anybody else. Do you see? I can’t. I’m a villain . . . know what I mean? I can’t do it on my own. They’re going to say, “You’re a murderer - where do you think you’re off to?” I’ve done the lot - even horsestealing, for God’s sake. But going with her . . . well, it’s like being with a child. See what I mean?’

‘Yes, I do see. Go on then . . . Musechka, one last kiss . . .’

‘Yes, don’t forget the kissing,’ Gypsy Mike said, encouraging the two women. ‘It’s your thing. Got to say goodbye, and get it right.’

Musya and Gypsy Mike moved off together. She, the woman, proceeded with great care, holding her skirts off the ground as always; he, the man, kept tight hold of her, moving forward cautiously, feeling the way with his foot as he walked her to her death.

The lights had stopped moving. Tanya Kovalchuk was surrounded by empty silence. The soldiers kept quiet - grey figures in the soft, uncoloured light of early day.

‘I’m the only one left,’ said Tanya suddenly, with a sigh. ‘Seryozha’s dead. Werner’s dead, and Vassily. Only me left. Soldier boys, all soldier boys, and me on my own. Only me to go . . .’

The sun was coming up over the sea.

The bodies were carefully stowed in boxes. And driven away. With their elongated necks, savagely bulging eyes and swollen blue tongues protruding like ghastly, unidentifiable flowers from lips flecked with bloody foam, the corpses came cruising back along the road they had followed when they had walked there, still alive. And the springtime snow was just as soft and scented; and the springtime air was just as fresh and keen. One black thing stood out in the snow, wet and trampled - Sergey’s lost galosh.

And this was how people welcomed the rising sun.

我为什么如此智慧

一

我的此在生命的幸福及其独一无二性，也许就在于它的厄运：用谜语形式来表达，作为我的父亲，我已经死了，而作为我的母亲，我还活着，而且将衰老。这种双重的来源，仿佛来自生命阶梯的最高一级和最低一级，既是颓废者又是开端——这一点，要是有某种意思的话，那就是说明了那种也许使我卓然超群的对于生命总体问题的中立性、无偏袒性。对于升起和没落的征兆，我具有一种比人们向来拥有的更为精细的嗅觉，在这方面我是卓越的教师——我知道两者，我就是这两者。——我父亲三十六岁就去世了，他柔弱、可亲而病恹恹的，就像一个注定要一味匆匆消逝的人——与其说他是生命本身，还不如说是一种对生命的善意回忆。在我父亲生命衰落的同一个年纪，我的生命也开始衰落了：三十六岁时，我的生命力降到了最低点——我还活着，却看不到离我三步远的东西。当时——那是1879年——我辞去了在巴塞尔大学的教授职务，整个夏天就像一个幽灵般活着，住在圣莫里兹，冬天则住在瑙姆堡。那是我生命中最暗无天日的时光。那是我最低潮的时期，《漫游者及其影子》就是在此间写成的。无疑地，当时我认为自己就是幽灵了……下一个冬天，也就是我在热那亚的第一个冬天，差不多由一种血液和肌肉上的极度贫乏而引起的轻松愉快和超凡脱俗，使我创作了《曙光》一书。在我身上，精神的完全明亮和喜悦，乃至精神的繁茂兴旺，不仅与最深刻的生理虚弱一致，而且甚至与一种极端的痛苦感一致。持续三天的头疼连同非常艰辛的咳痰带来了种种折磨——置身其中，我拥有了一种卓越的辩证法家的清晰性，并且十分冷静地深思了各种事物，而在比较健康的情况下，我对于这些事物就不是一个善于攀登者，就不够精巧、不够冷静了。我的读者们也许知道，我何以把辩证法视为颓废的征兆，例如最著名的个案：苏格拉底的案例。所有对理智的病态干扰，甚至发烧引起的半昏迷状态，至今对我来说都是完全陌生的东西。对于它们的本性和频率，我唯有通过博学的途径才能加以了解。我的血液流得缓慢。从来没有人能够在我身上发现发烧现象。有一位医生，他在相当长一段时间里把我当作神经病患者来治疗，最后甚至说道：“不！您的神经没什么，我3自己倒是神经质了。”任何一种局部的退行性病变都是完全不可证实的，没有任何器质性的胃病，尽管由于全身疲惫，确实存在着胃部系统的极度衰弱。眼疾亦然，不时接近失明的危险，这只是结果而不是原因：以至于随着生命力的每一次增长，视力也重又改善了。漫长的，过于漫长的岁月对我来说就意味着康复——遗憾的是，它也意味着复发、衰落，以及一种颓废的周期。尽管如此，我需要说明我对颓废问题是有经验的吗？我前前后后地解读了这些问题。即便那种把握和理解的艺术，那种对于细微差别的感触，那种“明察秋毫”的心理学，以及我通常独具的东西，都是在当时学会的，是那个时代真正的馈赠——那是一切都在其中变得精细化的时代，无论是观察本身还是一切观察的器官。从病人的角度出发去看比较健康的概念和价值，又反过来根据丰富生命的充盈和自信来探视颓废本能的隐秘工作——这乃是我最长久的训练，是我最本真的经验，如果说是某个方面的训练和经验，那我在这方面就是大师了。我现在已经胜券在握，我有能力转换视角：这是首要的原因，说明也许唯有对我来说，一种价值的重估竟是可能的。

二

因为，除了我是一个颓废者不说，我也是它的对立面。我为此提出的证据之一是，针对那些恶劣的状态，我总是本能地选择恰当的手段，而自在的颓废者总是选择对自己不利的手段。作为至高无上者，我是健康的；作为隐僻一隅，作为特性，我是颓废者。那种绝对的孤独和摆脱惯常情况和任务的力量，对我自身的强制力，不再照料自身，不进餐，不就医——这些都透露出对于急需之事的绝对的本能确信。我对自身负责，我使自己恢复健康：这方面的前提是——任何一个生理学家都会承认这一点——人们根本上是健康的。一个典型的病态之人是不会康复的，更不能自我康复了；相反，对一个典型的健康人来说，患病甚至可能是一种有力的兴奋剂，一种促使更丰富地生活的兴奋剂。现在，在我看来，那个漫长的疾病时期实际上就是这样：我仿佛重新发现了生命，也包括我自身，我品尝了一切美好的甚至微小的事物，那是别人不能轻易品尝到的——我从自己求健康的意志、生命意志中做出我的哲学……因为人们要注意：我生命力最低下的年头也就是我停止成为悲观主义者的时候：我自我恢复的本能不允许我有一种贫困和沮丧的哲学……人们到底要从哪里识别发育良好的状态呢？一个发育良好的人使我们的感官适意：他是由一块坚硬又柔润、芳香袭人的木头雕成的。他中意的是有益于他健康的东西；一旦超出了这个有益性尺度，他的乐意，他的快乐就终止了。他猜到了对付损害的良药，他充分利用恶劣的偶然事件的好处；凡是不能置他于死地的，都能使他变得更强壮。他本能地从自己所见、所闻、所体验的一切中搜集自己的全部：他就是一个选择原则，他淘汰了许多东西。无论是与书本、人打交道，还是与自然风光打交道，他始终都在自己的团伙中：他通过选择、许可，信赖而有所尊重。他对于形形色色的刺激反应迟钝，带着那种由长期的谨慎和蓄意的骄傲养成的慢条斯理——他检验正在临近的刺激，他远不能直面这种刺激。他既不相信“灾祸”，也不相信“罪责”：他能对付自己，也能对付他人，他善于遗忘——他十分强壮，足以使一切都必然为他带来最佳的东西。——好吧，那我就是颓废者的对立面：因为，上面我描写的正是我自己。

三

拥有这样一位父亲，我视之为一大特权：我父亲曾经对农民们布道——因为他在阿尔滕堡宫生活了若干年，最后几年成了牧师——那些农民说，他看起来很像一位天使。——而由此我便触及了种族问题。我是一位纯正的波兰贵族，不掺点滴不良血统，是完全没有德国血统的。如果我要寻找自己最深刻的对立面，那无法估量的本能共性，那么，我总是发现我母亲和我妹妹——相信自己与这等暴民有亲属关系，这或许是对我自己神性的亵渎了。我从自己母亲和妹妹这边得到的待遇，直到眼下为止，都会引起我不可名状的恐惧：在此工作的是一台令人恐惧的完美机器，带着一种对于人们能够使我血淋淋受伤的时刻的可靠把握——在我至高的时刻里……因为这里没有任何抵御有毒害虫的力量……生理上的同时发生使得这样一种先定的不和谐成为可能……但我得承认，对于我真正深邃的思想“永恒轮回”最深刻地抗辩和反驳的，始终是我母亲和妹妹。——不过，即便作为波兰人，我也是一个非同寻常的返祖现象。人们或许得后退几百年，方能纯粹本能地按照它所表现出来的样子，找到这个世上存在过的最高贵的种族。我反对今天被称为高贵的一切，一种绝对的出众高雅之感——我不会给予那个年轻的德国皇帝当我的马车夫的荣誉。有一种唯一的情形，在其中我会承认自己的同类——我怀着深深的感恩之心承认之。柯西玛・瓦格纳女士绝对是最高贵的人物；而且——毫无表示总归是过了[1]——我要说，理查德・瓦格纳绝对是与我最亲近的人……剩下的就是沉默了……关于亲缘程度的全部流行概念都是一种无法超越的生理学上的荒谬。教皇今天还在与这种荒谬做交易呢。人们与自己的父母最不亲近，这或许是与自己的父母亲近的卑劣行径的极端标志。高等人物有自己无限深远的渊源，着眼于高等人物，不得不做最长久的收集、储存和积累。伟大的个体乃是最老的个体：我理解不了，但恺撒可能是我的父亲——或者亚历山大，这个真正的狄奥尼索斯……就在我写下这些文字的当儿，刚好邮局给我捎来一个狄奥尼索斯的脑袋……

四

我从来都不了解这种对付我的艺术——这也要归功于我那无与伦比的父亲——即便在我看来这是具有重大价值的。我甚至从来不曾激起过人们对我的反感——不论看起来这是多么非基督教。人们不妨来回地反复检查我的生活，除了那唯一的例外，人们在其中发现不了任何踪迹，可以表明有人曾对我心怀恶意——相反，也许可以发现过多善3意的踪迹……有些人让人人都大感麻烦，而我对于这些人的经验也毫无例外地向他们表露了好意；我能驯服每一头熊，我能使小丑们变得不失庄重。我在巴塞尔教育机构教授过高年级的希腊文，在那七年里，我未曾乘机对学生施加过什么处罚；在我这里，最懒惰的学生也变得勤奋了。我总能对付偶然事件；我必须能够即兴控制自己。无论何种乐器，不论它多么走调，哪怕可能像“人”这种乐器那样走调——倘若我不能成功地在它上面奏出某种动听的乐章，那么我一定是生病了。而且，我是多么经常地从这些“乐器”本身那里听说，它们还从未听过自己有这般声音……也许最美好的就属于那位不幸英年早逝的海因里希・冯・斯泰因了。有一次，根据小心取得的许可，此人在塞尔斯-马利亚待了三天，向每个人申明，他并不是因为恩加丁而来的。这位杰出的人物，以一位普鲁士容克地主的全部狂热的单纯和天真，陷入瓦格纳的泥潭中了（此外还有杜林[2]的泥潭！）。在这三天当中，他犹如经历了一场自由风暴的改造，就像一个人突然升上他的高空，振翅翱翔。当时我总是对他说，这是高山上的好空气带来的，人人都有此种感觉，要不然，我们不是白白地待在高于拜罗伊特6000英尺[3]的地方了嘛——但他却不愿意相信我的话……尽管如此，如果说人们对我做了一些大大小小的坏事，那么，个中原因并不是“意志”，至少不是恶意[4]；而毋宁说，我抱怨的——我刚刚指出了这一点——乃是善意[5]，那种给我的生命造成了不小祸害的善意。我的经验赋予我一种权利，让我从根本上怀疑所谓的“无私的”冲动，怀疑全部乐于助人的“博爱”。这种“博爱”在我看来本身就是虚弱，就是无能于抵抗刺激的个案——唯有在颓废者那里，同情才意味着一种德性。我谴责同情者，他们会轻易失掉对于间距的羞耻感、敬畏感和敏锐感，同情一转眼就会散发出群氓的气息，并且看似会与恶劣的举止混为一谈——这种同情之手有时可能径直灾难性地深入到一种伟大的命运之中，深入到一种饱受创伤的孤独之中，深入到一种对于深重罪责的优先权之中。对同情的克服，我把它当作高贵的德性：我曾经虚构了一种情形作为“查拉图斯特拉的诱惑”，在此情形中，一种尖厉的呼救声传到那里，同情犹如一种最终的罪恶向他袭来，想使他背弃自身。在这里保持主人地位，保持其崇高使命的纯洁性，摆脱十分低级和短视的原动力（它们是在所谓无私的行动中起作用的），这乃是查拉图斯特拉要经受的一种考验，也许是最后的考验——是他真正的力量证明……

还有在另一点上，我也只不过是我的父亲，可以说就是他过早去世后的生命的延续。如同每一个从来不曾在同类中生活，并且对于“报复”概念就像对于“同等权利”概念一般充耳不闻的人，当我碰上一件小小的蠢事或者很大的蠢事时，我也一样不允许自己有任何防护手段、任何保护措施——多么合理啊，也不允许有任何防卫、任何“辩护”。我的报复方式就是，尽可能快速地为这种愚蠢送上一种聪明：这样，人们兴许还能对之做一点弥补。用比喻方式来讲：为了摆脱一个辛酸的故事，我会送上一罐果子酱……有人一味要对我使坏，我会“报复”之，那是人们有把握的：我不久就会找到一个机会，向“作恶者”表示感谢（甚至对恶行表示感谢）——或者向他请求某些东西，这可能比给予某些东西更友好……我也觉得，最粗野的语言、最粗野的书信，都比沉默更良性、更正派。那些保持沉默者，差不多总是缺乏心灵的精细和谦恭；沉默乃是一种抗辩，忍气吞声必然弄出一种坏性格——甚至会败坏胃口。一切沉默者都是消化不良的。——你会看到，我并不想贬低粗野，它绝对是最有人情味的反抗形式，在现代的柔弱化过程中，它是我们的首要德性之一。——如若有人足够粗野，那么，即便有不公和失当也是一种幸福。一个来到人间的上帝，根本上无非是要来行3不公的——不是承受惩罚，而是担当罪责，方才堪称神性。

六

摆脱怨恨，澄清怨恨——有谁知道即便在这个方面，我也应当多么感谢我那长期的疾病啊！问题并不那么简单：人们必须从力量出发，也从虚弱出发，才能对之有所体验。如若一定要提出某个对付疾病、对付虚弱的东西，那就是这样一点：在其中，一种真正的救治本能，也就是人身上的防御本能和战斗本能，会变得脆弱而松软。人们知道摆脱不了什么，人们知道对付不了什么，人们知道拒斥不了什么——一切皆会伤人。人和事紧紧纠缠，体验深深的刺痛，记忆是一道化脓的伤口。疾病本就是一种怨恨。——对此，患病者只有一剂良药，我称之为俄罗斯式的宿命论，那种毫无反抗的宿命论——一个俄罗斯士兵觉得远征太艰苦，最后就怀着这种宿命论想法躺在雪地里了，再也不接受、保存、吸收任何东西，竟再也没有任何反应了……这种宿命论并非始终只是赴死的勇气，其伟大的理性在最性命攸关的情况下具有保存生命的作用，那是新陈代谢的降低，是新陈代谢的减缓，是一种要求冬眠的意志。以这个逻辑继续往前走几步，就有了会在墓穴里躺上几个星期的苦行僧……因为当人们有所反应时，他会过快地精疲力竭，所以他再也不能反应了：这就是逻辑。而且，没有什么东西比怨恨情绪能更快地将人烧个精光。烦恼、病态的脆弱、无能于复仇、欲望、复仇的渴望、各式各样的荼毒——对于衰竭者来说，这确实是最不利的反应方式：神经力量的快速消耗，有害分泌物的病态提高，例如胆汁流入胃中，都是以此为条件的。怨恨乃是病者的禁物本身——是他的恶；遗憾的是，也是他极自然的癖好。——那个深邃的生理学家佛陀掌握了这一点。他的“宗教”，我们最好称之为养生学，才不至于把自己与像基督教这样可怜的事物混为一谈；这种“宗教”的效果取决于对怨恨的战胜：使心灵摆脱怨恨——此乃走向康复的第一步。“以怨报怨，怨无尽头；以德报怨，怨始终止”，这是佛祖教义之始——并非道德如是说，而是生理学如是说。——由虚弱产生的怨恨对虚弱者本身损害最大——而在另一种情形下，前提是有一种丰裕的天性，这时候，怨恨就成了一种多余的情感，对这种情感的控制差不多就是精力丰裕的证明了。谁若知道我的哲学以何种严肃态度向复仇感和同情感宣战，乃至与“自由意志”学说做斗争——与基督教的斗争只不过是其中的一个个案而已——他就会理解，为什么我恰恰要在这里阐明个人的态度，我在实践中的本能可靠性。在颓废时期，我不允许自己有这些有害的情感；一旦生命又变得足够丰裕和高扬时，我还是不允许自己有这些情感，而是要把它们抑制起来。我上面讲过的“俄罗斯式的宿命论”，在我身上是这样表现出来的，即：多年以来，我顽强地固守那些偶然出现的几乎不堪忍受的环境、地点、居所和社交圈——这种做法胜于对它们的改变，胜于对它们的可变性的感受——胜于对它们的反抗……当时，凡在此宿命论方面干扰我的，粗暴地把我唤醒的，我都对之极其生气——实际上，这在每一次都是有致命危险的。——把自身当作一种天命，而不愿意“改变”自己——在此类状态下，这就是伟大的理性本身了。

七

另一件事就是战斗。按我的本性来讲，我是好战的。攻击乃是我的本能之一。能够成为敌人、成为敌人——这也许是以一种强壮的天性为前提的，无论如何，它都取决于每一种强壮的天性。强壮的天性需要反抗，因此它寻求反抗：侵略性的激情同样必然地属于强者，正如复仇感和同情感必然地属于弱者。举例来说，女人是有强烈报复欲的，这是由女人的虚弱所决定的，正如她对于外来困苦是十分敏感的。——攻击者的强壮是在他必需的敌对方中获得一种尺度的；每一种增长都是在对更强大的敌人——或者难题——的寻求中显露出来的，因为一个好战的哲学家也要向难题挑战，进行决斗。其使命并不是从根本上控制反抗和阻力，而是要战胜那些人，我们必须投入自己全部的力量、韧性和武艺才能制服的那些人——也就是战胜旗鼓相当的敌人……势均力敌——此乃正派的决斗的第一条件。当人们蔑视敌人时，就不可能开战；当人们发号施令，视某物比自己低下时，人们就不必开战了。——我的战斗实践可以概括为四个定律：第一，我只攻击那些胜利的东西——可能我会等待，直到它们获胜。第二，我只在找不到盟友、孤立无援的时候才攻击这些东西——在只会让自己出丑而大丢面子的时候才攻击这些东西……我从未公开采取一个不让自己出丑的步骤：这是我的公正行为的标准。第三，我从不搞人身攻击——我只把个人当作一个有力的放大镜，用它来弄清楚某个一般的，但潜滋暗长的、难以把握的危急状态。我就是这样来攻击大卫・施特劳斯[6]的，更确切地讲，我攻击的是德国“教化”方面的一本老朽之书的成功——我当场揭穿了这种教化……我也是这样来攻击瓦格纳的，更准确地讲，我攻击的是我们“文化”的虚伪，我们“文化”的本能混杂，后者把精巧者与富有者、迟暮者与伟大者混为一谈。第四，我只攻击那些排除了任何个人差异、没有任何恶劣经验之背景的事物。相反，攻击在我这里乃是善意的证明，或许也是感恩的证明。我把我的名字与某个东西、某个人的名字联系起来，以此来表达我的尊重和赞扬：赞成抑或反对——这在我看来都是一样的。如果说我对基督教宣战，那是我有权这样做，因为在这个方面，我还未曾经历过不幸和阻碍——最严肃的基督徒也总是对我表示了友善。我本人绝对是基督教的死敌，我决不至于把千百年来的厄运添加到个人身上。

八

我胆敢再指出自己天性中的最后一个特征么？这个特征使我在与他人打交道时麻烦不小、困难不少。我有一种完全不可名状的清洁本能的敏感，以至于我能在生理上感知到——嗅到——每个心灵的切近之处，或者——我该怎么来说呢？每个心灵最内在的东西，每个心灵的“内脏”……以此敏感，我就有了心理上的触角，借以触摸和掌握任何秘密：有些人物骨子里有许多隐蔽的污垢，也许是由坏血统决定的，但通过教育得到了掩饰，我几乎一接触就能把它们看清楚。如果说我正确地进行了观察，那么，我的清洁感所不能忍受的这些人物，他们本身也会感受到我的厌恶的谨慎，而他们并没有因此变得芳香一些……正如我向来已经习惯了的——我对于自己的一种极端的纯净要求，乃是我的此在的前提条件，在不干净的状况下我会丧命的——可以说我不断地在水中，在某种完全透明、光亮的元素中游泳、沐浴和嬉戏。这就使得我在与他人的交往中受了不小的耐心考验；我的人性不在于同情人的存在方式，而是在于忍受我对人的同情……我的人性乃是一种持久的自我克制。——然而我需要孤独，也就是说，我需要康复、回归自我，需要呼吸一种自由而轻松活泼的空气……我的整部《查拉图斯特拉如是说》就是一首赞美孤独的酒神颂歌，或者，如果人们理解了我，就是一首赞美清洁的酒神颂歌……幸好它不是赞美纯粹的愚蠢的。——富有色彩感的人会把这本书称为金刚石般。——对人类、对“痞子”的厌恶，始终是我最大的危险……你们愿意来听听查拉图斯特拉谈论厌恶之解脱时所讲的话吗？

然则我出了事？我如何来解脱厌恶呢？谁使我的眼睛变得年轻了？我怎样飞到了那个高处，那个不再有流氓痞子坐在井泉旁的高处？

难道是我的厌恶本身为我提供了飞翔的翅膀和预感泉源的力量吗？真的，我必须飞到最高处，才能重新找到欢乐的源泉！

呵，弟兄们，我找到了它！在这里，在最高处，欢乐的源泉向我涌流！而且有一种生命，没有一个流氓痞子共饮之！

欢乐之泉呵，你几乎涌来得太猛烈！而且，因为你想要把杯子注满，你常常又把杯子倒空！

我还必须学会更谦卑地接近你：我的心太过猛烈地向你喷涌——

我的心啊，我的夏天就在我心上燃烧，这个短促、炎热、忧郁、极度快乐的夏天：我的夏天之心是多么渴望你的清凉！

我那春天踌躇的悲伤过去了！我那六月雪花的恶毒过去了！我已经完全成了夏天和夏天的正午！

一个至高的夏天，带着清凉的泉水和福乐的宁静：呵，我的朋友们，来吧，让这份宁静变得更福乐！

因为这就是我们的高空和我们的家乡：对于所有不洁者及其渴望来说，我们在此居住得太高太陡峭了。

朋友们啊，只管把你们纯洁的眼光投向我那欢乐的源泉！它怎会因此变得浑浊呢？它当以它的纯洁对你们微笑。

我们在未来树上建筑我们的窝巢，而鹰当为我们这些孤独者叼来食物！

真的，没有那些不洁者可以分享的食物！他们会误以为自己吞了火焰，烧了自己的嘴！

真的，我们在此根本没有为不洁者们准备住所！对于他们的肉体和精神来说，我们的幸福或许就是一个冰洞！

我们愿意像狂风一般生活在他们之上，与鹰为邻，与雪为邻，与太阳为邻——狂风就是这样生活的。

有朝一日，犹如一阵风，我还要吹到他们中间，以我的精神夺取他们精神的呼吸——我的未来就愿意如此。

真的，查拉图斯特拉乃是席卷一切低地的狂风；对于自己的敌人和所有吐唾沫者，他给出这样的忠告：“当心呵，不要逆风而唾！”……

[1] 德语原文为“ich sage kein Wort zu wenig”，意为“我不得不说，我必须承认”。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明之外，均为译者注。）

[2]杜林（Eugen Dühring，1833-1921）：德国哲学家，柏林大学讲师，因批评德国大学制度而被剥夺授课资格。恩格斯曾撰《反杜林论》，批判杜林的社会主义思想。

[3]1英尺约等于0.3米。——编者注

[4] 此处“恶意”（der böse Wille）亦可译为“恶的意志”。

[5] 此处“善意”（der gute Wille）亦可译为“善的意志”。

[6] 大卫・施特劳斯（David Strauss，1808-1874）：德国哲学家、新教神学家、青年黑格尔派代表人物之一。以对基督教的批判而著名。著有《耶稣传》《基督教教义》《旧信仰与新信仰》等。尼采于1873年发表第一篇《不合时宜的考察》，“施特劳斯”成为批判对象。

我为什么能写出如此好书

一

我自己是一回事，我的著作是另一回事。——在这里，在谈论我的著作之前，我先要来说说这些著作何以得到理解或者得不到理解的问题。我如此漫不经心地做这件事，而这是以某种方式与此事合适的：因为根本还没有到谈论这个问题的时候。我自己的时代也尚未到来，有些人是死后才得以诞生的。——到某个时候，人们将不得不需要一些机构，人们在其中生活和说教就如同我理解的生活和说教一样；也许，甚至人们到那时也要开设专有的教席来阐释《查拉图斯特拉如是说》。可是，倘若我今天就指望人们来听取和接受我的真理，那或许是与我自己完全矛盾的：人们今天还不听取，人们今天还不懂接受我，这不仅是可理解的，而且在我看来本就是对的。我不愿被混为一谈，这也包括我不混淆自己。——再说一遍，在我的生活中，人们难以证明有什么“恶意”；连文字上的“恶意”，我也几乎举不出一个事例。相反，纯粹的蠢行却太多了……如果有人拿起我的一本书——我甚至假定他为此要脱掉鞋子，更不用说要脱掉靴子了——那么，在我看来，这就是人们能够向我表示的最稀罕的一个奖赏了……海因里希・冯・斯泰因博士有一次真诚地抱怨说，理解不了我的《查拉图斯特拉如是说》里的任何一句话，当时我就对他说，这就对了：弄懂了其中的六句话，也就是体验了其中的六句话，凡人就能提升到一个比“现代”人所能达到的更高的层次上了。有这种距离感的我，怎么可能指望我所认识的“现代人”来读我的书呢！我的成功刚好与叔本华的成功相反——我要说的是“我现在没有被阅读，将来也不会被阅读”（non legor, non legar）。——人们在否定我的著作时表现出来的天真无辜屡屡让我满足，我并不想低估这种满足感。还是在今年夏天，当时我也许能够以我重要的文学、太过重要的文学使其余的文学失去平衡，柏林大学的一位教授善意地暗示我，我得用另外一种形式：这种东西是没人读的。——最后，不是德国，而是瑞士，提供了两个极端的事例。维特曼博士[30]在《联邦报》上发表了一篇文章，是关于《善恶的彼岸》的，题为《尼采的一本危险的书》；还有，卡尔・施皮特勒先生[31]写的一篇关于我的书的总体报告，同样也发表在《联邦报》上面。这两篇文章乃是我一生中的极限——我要小心谨慎地说这个……举例来说，后者把我的《查拉图斯特拉如是说》当作“更高的风格尝试”，希望我今后也关心一下内容；维特曼博士则对我在努力取缔所有正派情感方面表现出来的勇气表示了敬重。——在这里，通过一个偶然的小小诡计，每个句子都是顺理成章的，让我钦佩，但却是一种头足倒立的真理：根本上，人们什么也不用做，只要“重估”一切“价值”，就能以一种甚至值得注意的方式击中我的要害——用不着拿钉子钉进我的脑袋……我就越发要尝试一种说明了。——说到底，没有人能够从包括书本在内的事物中听到比他已经知道的更多的东西。凡是人们从自己的体验出发达不到的东西，人们是听不到的。现在让我们来想想一个极端的例子：一本书谈的是纯粹体验，后者完全处于一种常见的或者哪怕只是罕见的经验之可能性之外——这本书就是一种新的经验系列的第一语言。在这种情形下，干脆什么也听不到，由于听觉上的欺瞒，在什么也听不到的地方，就什么也不存在……这终归是我通常的经验吧，也可以说是我的经验的独特性。谁若以为已经理解了我的什么东西，他其实只是根据自己的形象编造了我的什么东西——当中不乏我的对立面，例如一个“理想主义者”；谁若对我毫无了解，他便会否认终竟把我考虑在内了。——“超人”一词被用来表示一个至高的发育良好的类型，这种人对立于“现代”人，对立于“好”人，对立于基督徒和其他的虚无主义者——该词出自查拉图斯特拉这个道德的毁灭者之口，成了一个十分令人深思的词语，几乎处处都完全无辜地被理解为那样一种价值，这种价值的对立面表现在查拉图斯特拉形象上，可以说表现为一个高等人的“理想主义”类型，半是“圣徒”，半是“天才”……因为这个词，另一个博学的、长角的畜生竟然怀疑我是达尔文主义者；甚至于在这个词中重又现出了那个违逆知识和意志的大骗子卡莱尔1的“英雄崇拜”，那原是我深恶痛绝的。如若我低声细语地告诉某人，与其去寻找一个帕西法尔倒不如寻找一个恺撒・波尔查[32]，那他是不会相信自己的耳朵的。——人们务必要原谅我，对于有关我的书的评论，尤其是报纸上的，我是没有任何好奇心的。我的朋友们、我的出版商是知道这一点的，他们不跟我谈论诸如此类的事。在某个特殊场合，我看见了关于我的一本书——《善恶的彼岸》——的全部指责；对此我或许得好好写一篇报道。《国民报》——普鲁士的一份报纸，为了告诉我的外国读者，恕我直言，我自己是只读《辩论报》的——极其严肃地把这本书理解为“时代的标志”，是地地道道的容克哲学，而对此，《十字报》[33]只是缺乏勇气而已——人们该相信吗？……

二

上面是就德国人来说的：因为在别的地方，我到处都有读者——都是些出类拔萃的有识之士，都是些经受考验、受过高等地位和责任方面教育的人物；我的读者中甚至有真正的天才。在维也纳，在圣彼得堡，在斯德哥尔摩，在哥本哈根，在巴黎和纽约——到处都有人发现了我：而在欧洲的平原德国，我却没有被发现……而且，我承认，我更喜欢那些没有读过我的书的读者，他们既没有听说过我的名字，也从来没有听说过“哲学”一词；但不论我走到哪儿，比如说在这儿，在都灵，人们一见到我，就都感到轻松愉快。迄今为止最让我得意的事情是，那些市场上的老妇，她们在没有为我挑出最甜的葡萄之前是不会歇手的。到这步田地，人们就必定是哲学家了……不无道理地，人们把波兰人称为斯拉夫人中的法国人。一个迷人的俄国女子一刻都不会弄错我的归属。我做不到庄重严肃，我顶多会把这种庄重变成难堪……用德语思考，用德语感觉——我能做到一切，但这一点却超出了我的能力……我从前的老师李彻尔甚至于断言，我还像巴黎小说家一般来构思我的语文学文章——紧张得荒唐。即便在巴黎，人们也惊奇于“我所有的大胆和精细”[34]——这是丹纳先生的说法——我担心，哪怕达到了酒神颂歌的最高形式，人们也会发现，我身上掺杂了那种永远不会变得愚蠢的——“德国式的”——精华，即精神……我别无所能。上帝助我啊！阿门。——我们全都知道，有些人甚至凭着经验就知道，长耳朵是什么意思。好吧，我敢断言我有着最短的耳朵。这一点甚至使女人们不无兴趣——我觉得，她们感觉我更好地理解了她们？……我是卓绝的反驴，因而是一个世界历史的怪物，——用希腊语来讲，而且不光是用希腊语来讲，我是敌基督者……

三

在某种程度上，我知道自己作为作家的特权；在个别情况下我也确信，习惯读我的著作是会“败坏”趣味和鉴赏力的。人们干脆再也受不了其他的书了，至少是受不了哲学书了。进入这样一个高贵而微妙的世界，乃是一种无与伦比的荣誉——要做到这一点，绝不可能是一个德国人；说到底，这是人们一定已经获得的荣誉。但是，谁若通过意志的高度与我相近相类，他就能在这方面体验到学习的真正狂喜：因为我来自鸟儿从来都飞不到的高空，我知道还没有人误入其中的深渊。有人曾对我说，他对我的书爱不释手——我甚至打破了长夜的宁静……世上绝不会有更骄傲，同时也更精致的书了——它们在有些地方臻于地球的顶峰了，达到了犬儒主义的境界；人们必须同时用最温柔的手指和最勇敢的拳头来征服它们。任何脆弱的心灵都无缘于此，永远地，甚至连消化不良也不行：人们不能异想天开，人们必须有一个快乐的腹部。不光是心灵的贫困和褊狭使人不可能领会我的书，更要命的是内脏的怯懦、不洁、隐秘报复欲所造成的障碍：我说出的一个词语就能使人直面那些邪恶本能。在我的熟人当中有相当多的实验动物，在他们身上，我会感受到对我的著作的不同反应，那是一些富有教益的不同反应。谁若不想关心我的著作的内容，例如我的所谓朋友们，那就会成为“无个性的”：人们希望我有幸又走得“这么远”——也或许在腔调的更大明快方面有一个进步……这些恶习重重的“精灵”，“美好心灵”，彻头彻尾的骗子，他们绝对不知道该怎样开始读这些书，因此他们就看不上这些书，这是所有“美好心灵”的美好逻辑。我的熟人当中的这些笨牛蠢驴，恕我直言，就是纯粹的德国人，他们使我弄懂了，人们并非总是同意我的看法，但偶尔却是同意的，例如……甚至关于《查拉图斯特拉如是说》，我也听说过这样的话……同样地，人身上的任何“女性主义”，包括男人身上的“女性主义”，对我来说也是一种闭门羹：人们从来都不能进入这个大胆知识的迷宫。人们必须从来不顾惜自己，人们必须具有冷酷的习惯，方能在全然冷酷的真理当中感到愉快而明朗。如若要我设想一位完美读者的形象，那么总不外乎是一个有勇气和好奇心的怪物，此外还有某种坚韧、狡黠、谨慎的性格，一个天生的冒险家和发现者。最后，我不知道怎么来更好地言说，我根本上只跟谁说话，就像查拉图斯特拉所言：他只想跟谁叙述自己的谜团？

向你们，你们这些勇敢的探求者和冒险者，以及总是随狡猾的帆船在恐怖大海上航行的人啊——

向你们，你们这些沉醉于谜团者，欣喜于黄昏者，你们的灵魂被笛声引向每一个迷津——

因为你们不愿用胆怯的手摸索一根引线；而且，在你们能够猜解的地方，你们就仇视推断——

四

同时，我还要来约略说说自己的风格枝巧。用符号（包括这种符号的速度）来传达一种状态，一种激情上的内在紧张——此即任何风格的意义；而且，鉴于我的内在状态的异乎寻常的多样性，在我这里也就有了多种风格可能性——那竟是一个人向来拥有过的最多样的风格技巧。任何优秀的风格，都要能真正传达某种内在状态，它通过符号，通过符号的速度，通过表情——所有周期性法则都是表情的艺术——概无错失。我的本能在这里是不会犯错的。——优秀的风格本身——那是一种纯粹的愚蠢，单纯的“唯心主义”，就好比“美本身”“善本身”“物本身”……此事总归还有一个前提假设，假设有听众存在——假设有这样一种人，他们能够产生同一种激情并且也配得上这种激情，假设并不缺乏我们可以对之传达自己的人们。——举例来说，我的查拉图斯特拉此间就还在寻找这种人——啊！他还得长久地寻找！——人们一定值得去倾听他……可直到那时，都不会有人能够把握我在其中运用的技巧：再也没有人运用过全新的、闻所未闻的、真正为此创造出来的艺术手段。有人说此类情况恰恰在德语中可能有过，此种说法尚有待证明：我自己从前曾严厉地拒斥此说。在我之前，人们不知道能干些什么——说到底就是用语言能干些什么。——伟大韵律的技巧，周期性的伟大风格，以表达高贵的、超人的激情的一种巨大起落，这是我首先发明的；凭借一种酒神颂歌，好比《查拉图斯特拉如是说》第三部末节“七个印记”[35]，我就飞越以往所谓的诗歌千里之外了。

五

——我的著作中有一位无与伦比的心理学家在发言，这也许是一位优秀的读者所达到的第一个见识——我应得的一个读者，他读我的书，就像优秀的老语文学家读贺拉斯的书一样。那些人人皆能同意的句子，更不消说那些平凡的哲学家、道德家以及其他的笨蛋蠢货，在我看来都是幼稚的失误：例如那种信念，相信“不自私”与“自私”是对立面，而“自我”（ego）本身只是一种“更高的欺诈”，一种“理想”……既没有自私的行为，也没有不自私的行为：这两个概念在心理学上都是荒唐的。或者“人人都追求幸福”这个句子……或者“幸福是德性的报答”这个句子……又或者“痛苦与快乐是对立的”这样的句子……道德这个人类的妖精彻底地伪造了全部心理，把它们道德化了 ，臻于那种可怕的荒唐境地，以为爱情是某种“非自我、不自私的东西”……人们必须坚守自己，人们必须勇敢地独立自主，要不然人们就根本不可能爱。说到底，小女子们最清楚不过地知道这一点：她们对那些忘我的、纯客观的男人嗤之以鼻……附带插一句，我胆敢猜测自己是了解女人的吗？这是我的狄奥尼索斯嫁妆的一部分。谁知道呢？也许我就是永恒女性的第一位心理学家。她们全都爱我——这是一个老故事了：除了那些不幸的女人，那些不能生育的“被解放者”。——所幸我不愿意被人撕碎：完美的女人一旦恋爱，是会把你撕碎的……我知道这些可爱的狂野女人[36]……啊！那是何等危险的、潜行的、隐秘的小小食肉动物！而与她们在一起，又是多么惬意呵！……一个力争报复的小女人或许会把命运本身撞倒。——女人要比男人凶恶无数倍，也比男人聪明无数倍；女人身上的善已然是一种蜕化形式了……尽管有种种所谓的“美好心灵”，但根本上还是存在着一种生理上的弊端，——我没有说全部，要不然我就会变成医学犬儒派[37]了。围绕平等权的斗争甚至就是一种疾病的征兆：每个医生都知道这一点。——的确，女人越是有女人味，就越是竭尽全力抵制一般权利：自然状态，两性间的永恒战争，确实绝对给予女人以头等地位。——人们听到我给爱情下的定义了吗？这是值得一位哲学家来下的唯一定义。爱情——其手段是战争，其基础是两性间的殊死仇恨。——人们听见我关于如何治愈——“拯救”——女人这个问题的答案了吗？让她生个小孩。女人必须有小孩，而男人始终只是手段：查拉图斯特拉如是说。——“女性解放”——此乃失败女人也即不孕女人对健全女人的本能仇恨——对“男人”的斗争始终只不过是手段、借口、策略。她们想通过抬高自己，成为“自在女人”，成为“高等女人”，成为女人中的“理想主义者”，由此来降低女人的一般等级水平；为此，没有比人文中学教育、裤衩和政治上的投票畜生权利更可靠的手段了。根本上，获解放者是“永恒女性”世界里的无政府主义者，是败类，她们最下作的本能就是复仇……极端恶毒的“理想主义”的整个种类——此外，这种“理想主义”也出现在男人身上，例如在易卜生“这个典型的老处女”那里——怀有毒害性爱之自然本性的好良心，以之为目标……而且，为了不让人怀疑我在这方面既正直又严格的信念，我还想根据自己反恶习的道德法典来传达一个定律：用恶习一词，我要与任何种类的反自然行为做斗争，或者如若人们喜欢漂亮辞令，那就是要与任何种类的理想主义做斗争。这个定律说的是：“贞洁之说教就是公然煽动反自然。任何一种对性生活的蔑视，任何用‘不洁’概念对性生活的玷污，本身都是对生命的犯罪，都是违反生命之神圣精神的真正罪恶。”

六

为了给出一个关于我之为心理学家的概念，且让我端出一门在《善恶的彼岸》中出现的古怪心理学——此外，我不允许人们对我此处描写的人物做任何推测。“心灵的天才，正如那伟大的隐秘者所具有的那样，诱惑者之神以及有良知的天生捕鼠者，其声音可以下达到每一个灵魂的深度世界里，他一言不发，一眼不看，在其中不会有一种引诱的顾盼和皱纹，其高超技艺也包括，他懂得表现——而且并不是表现为他所是的东西，而是表现为对跟随他的人来说更多的是一种强制力的东西，为的是愈来愈近地逼近他，愈来愈内在地、彻底地跟随他……心灵的天才，他使所有喧嚣和自满哑然失声，他教人服从，使粗野的灵魂平静下来，让它们品尝一种新的渴望——静静地躺着如一面镜子，使之映照出那深邃的天空……心灵的天才，他教会那鲁莽而急促的手变得踌躇，使之能更纤柔地去把握；他猜到隐蔽而被遗忘的财宝，在浑厚的冰层下面的点滴善良和甜蜜灵气，他是探寻长久地埋在深深泥沙之下的每一颗金子的魔杖……心灵的天才，跟他接触，每个人都可以满载而归，并非受了恩赐，得了惊喜，并非仿佛受了外来的财富而生出愉快或者沮丧之情，而是本身变得更富有，变得比从前更新鲜，洞开心扉，为一阵解冻的暖风所吹拂和窃听，也许更不可靠、更娇柔、更脆弱、更破碎，但却充满了无可名状的希望，充满了全新的意志和潮流，充满了全新的非意志和逆流……”

[30]维特曼（V.Widmann，1842-1911）：瑞士作家、《联邦报》编辑。

[31]卡尔・施皮特勒（Karl Spitteler，1845-1924）：瑞士诗人、小说家，1919年诺贝尔文学奖得主。

[32]恺撒・波尔查（Cesare Borgia，1475-1507）：意大利文艺复兴时代的诸侯，瓦伦丁公爵，是教皇亚历山大六世与其情妇贾旦妮之子。

[33]《十字报》（Kreuzzeitung）：即《新普鲁士报》，因报头有醒目的黑十字而被称为《十字报》，1848-1939年在德国出版。

[34] 原文为法语“toutes mes audaces et finesses”。

[35] 参看尼采《查拉图斯特拉如是说》，中译本，孙周兴译，上海人民出版社，2009年，第295页以下。

[36] 此处“狂野女人”原文为Mänade，原义为酒神狄奥尼索斯的女祭司，转义为狂野女人。

[37] 此处“医学犬儒派”原文为medicynisch，意为“对医学愤世嫉俗的”。

Why I Am so Clever

1

Why do I know a few more things? Why am I so c lever altogether? I have never reflected on questions that are none – I have not squandered myself. – I have, for example, no experience of actual religious difficulties. I am entirely at a loss to know to what extent I ought to have felt ‘sinful’. I likewise lack a reliable criterion of a pang of conscience: from what one hears of it, a pang of conscience does not seem to me anything respectable ... I should not like to leave an act in the lurch afterwards, I would as a matter of principle prefer to leave the evil outcome, the consequences, out of the question of values. When the outcome is evil one can easily lose the true eye for what one has done: a pang of conscience seems to me a kind of ‘evil eye’. To honour to oneself something that went wrong all the more because it went wrong – that rather would accord with my morality. – ‘God’, ‘immortality of the soul’, ‘redemption’, ‘the Beyond’, all of them concepts to which I have given no attention and no time, not even as a child – perhaps I was never childish enough for it? – I have absolutely no knowledge of atheism as an outcome of reasoning, still less as an event: with me it is obvious by instinct. I am too inquisitive, too questionable, too high spirited to rest content with a crude answer. God is a crude answer, a piece of indelicacy against us thinkers – fundamentally even a crude prohibition to us: you shall not think! ... I am interested in quite a different way in a question upon which the ‘salvation of mankind’ depends far more than it does upon any kind of quaint curiosity of the theologians: the question of nutriment. One can for convenience’ sake formulate it thus: ‘how to nourish yourself so as to attain your maximum of strength, of virtù in the Renaissance style, of moraline- free virtue?’ – My experiences here are as bad as they possibly could be; I am astonished that I heard this question so late, that I learned ‘reason’ from these experiences so late. Only the perfect worthlessness of our German education – its ‘idealism’ – can to some extent explain to me why on precisely this point I was backward to the point of holiness. This ‘education’ which from the first teaches one to lose sight of realities s o a s t o h unt after altogether p roblematic, so- called ‘ideal’ objectives, ‘classical education’ for example – as if it were not from the first an utterly fruitless undertaking to try to unite ‘classical’ and ‘German’ in one concept! It is, moreover, mirth- provoking – just think of a ‘classically educated’ Leipziger! – Until my very maturest years I did in fact eat badly – in the language of morals ‘impersonally’, ‘selflessly’, ‘altruistically’, for the salvation of cooks and other fellow Christians. With the aid of Leipzig cookery, for example, which accompanied my earliest study of Schopenhauer (1865), I very earnestly denied my ‘will to live’. To ruin one's stomach so as to receive inadequate nutriment – the aforesaid cookery seems to me to solve this problem wonderfully well. (It is said that 1866 produced a change in this domain –.) But German cookery in general – what does it not have on its conscience! Soup before the meal (in Venetian cookery books of the sixteenth century still called alla tedesca ) ; meat cooked to shreds, greasy and floury vegetables; the degeneration of puddings to paperweights! If one adds to this the downright bestial dinner- drinking habits of the ancient and by no means only the ancient Germans one will also understand the origin of the German spirit – disturbed intestines ... The German spirit is an indigestion, i t can have done w ith nothing. – But to the English diet too, which compared with the Germans, even with the French, is a kind of ‘return to nature’, that is to say to cannibalism, my own instinct is profoundly opposed; it seems to me to give the spirit heavy feet – the feet of Englishwomen ... The best cookery is that of Piedmont. Alcoholic drinks are no good for me; a glass of wine or beer a day is quite enough to make life for me a ‘Vale of Tears’ – Munich is where my antipodes live. Granted I was a little late to grasp this – I experienced it really from childhood onwards. As a boy I believed wine- drinking to be, like tobaccosmoking, at first only a vanity of young men, later a habit. Perhaps the wine of Naumburg is in part to blame for this austere judgement. To believe that wine makes cheerful I would have to be a Christian, that is to say believe what is for precisely me an absurdity. Oddly enough, while I am put extremely out of sorts by small, much diluted doses of alcohol, I am almost turned into a sailor when it comes to strong doses. Even as a boy I showed how brave I was in this respect. To write a long Latin essay in a single night's sitting and then go on to make a fair copy of it, with the ambition in my pen to imitate in severity and concision my model Sallust, and to pour a quantity of grog of the heaviest calibre over my Latin, was even when I was a pupil of venerable Schulpforta in no way opposed to my physiology, nor perhaps to that of Sallust – however much it might have been to venerable Schulpforta ... Later, towards the middle of life, I decided, to be sure, more and more strictly against any sort of ‘spirituous’ drink: an opponent of vegetarianism from experience, just like Richard Wagner, who converted me, I cannot advise all more spiritual natures too seriously to abstain from alcohol absolutely. Water suffices ... I prefer places in which there is everywhere opportunity to drink from flowing fountains (Nice, Turin, Sils); a small glass runs after me like a dog. In vino veritas : it seems that here too I am again at odds with all the world over the concept ‘truth’ – with me the spirit moves over the water ... A couple more signposts from my morality. A big meal is easier to digest than one too small. That the stomach comes into action as a whole, first precondition of a good digestion. One has to know the size of one's stomach. For the same reason those tedious meals should be avoided which I call interrupted sacrificial feasts, those at the table d’hôte. – No eating between meals, no coffee: coffee makes gloomy. Tea beneficial only in the morning. Little, but strong: tea very detrimental and sicklying o’er the whole day if it is the slightest bit too weak. Each has here his own degree, often between the narrowest and most delicate limits. In a very agaçant climate it is inadvisable to start with tea: one should start an hour earlier with a cup of thick oil- free cocoa. – Sit as little as possible; credit no thought not born in the open air and while moving freely about – in which the muscles too do not hold a festival. All prejudices come from the intestines. – Assiduity – I have said it once before – the actual sin against the holy spirit. –

2

Most closely related to the question of nutriment is the question of place and climate. No one is free to live everywhere; and he who has great tasks to fulfil which challenge his entire strength has indeed in this matter a very narrow range of choice. The influence of climate on the metabolism, its slowing down, its speeding up, extends so far that a blunder in regard to place and climate can not only estrange anyone from his task but withhold it from him altogether: he never catches sight of it. His animalic vigor never grows sufficiently great for him to attain to that freedom overflowing into the most spiritual domain where he knows: that I a lone can do ... A never so infinitesimal sluggishness of the intestines grown into a bad habit completely suffices to transform a genius into something mediocre, something ‘German’; the German climate alone is enough to discourage strong and even heroic intestines. The tempo of the metabolism stands in an exact relationship to the mobility or lameness of the feet of the spirit; the ‘spirit’ itself is indeed only a species of this metabolism. Make a list of the places where there are and have been gifted men, where wit, refinement, malice are a part of happiness, where genius has almost necessarily made its home: they all possess an excellent dry air. Paris,Provence, Florence, Jerusalem, Athens – these names prove something: that genius is conditioned by dry air, clear sky – that is to say by rapid metabolism, by the possibility of again and again supplying oneself with great, even tremendous quantities of energy. I have in mind a case in which a spirit which might have become significant and free became instead narrow, withdrawn, a grumpy specialist, merely through a lack of instinctive subtlety in choice of climate. And I myself could in the end have become this case if sickness had not compelled me to reason, to reflect on reason in reality. Now, when from long practice I read climatic and meteorological effects off from myself as from a very delicate and reliable instrument and even on a short journey, from Turin to Milan for instance, verify on myself physiologically the change in degrees of humidity, I recall with horror the uncanny fact that my life up to the last ten years, the years when my life was in danger, was spent nowhere but in wrong places downright forbidden to me. Naumburg, Schulpforta, Thuringia in general, Leipzig, Basel, Venice – so many ill- fated places for my physiology. If I have no welcome memories at all of my whole childhood and youth, it would be folly to attribute this to so- called ‘moral’ causes – the undeniable lack of adequate company, for instance: for this lack exists today as it has always existed without preventing me from being brave and cheerful. Ignorance in physiologis – accursed ‘idealism’ – is the real fatality in my life, the superfluous and stupid in it, something out of which nothing good grows, for which there is no compensation, no counter- reckoning. It is as a consequence of this ‘idealism’ that I elucidate to myself all the blunders, all the great deviations of instinct and ‘modesties’ which led me away from the task of my l ife, that I b ecame a philologist for example – why not at least a physician or something else that opens the eyes? In my time at Basel my entire spiritual diet, the division of the day included, was a perfectly senseless abuse of extraordinary powers without any kind of provision for covering this consumption, without even reflection on consumption and replacement. Any more subtle selfishness, any protection by a commanding instinct was lacking, it was an equating of oneself with everyone else, a piece of ‘selflessness’, a forgetting of one's distance – something I shall never forgive myself. When I was almost done for, because I was almost done for, I began to reflect on this fundamental irrationality of my life – ‘idealism’. It was only sickness that brought me to reason.

3

Selectivity in nutriment; selectivity in climate and place; – the third thing in which one may at no cost commit a blunder is selectivity in one's kind of recreation. Here too the degree to which a spirit is sui generis makes ever narrower the bounds of what is permitted, that is to say useful to him. In my case all reading is among my recreations: consequently among those things which free me from myself, which allow me to saunter among strange sciences and souls – which I no longer take seriously. It is precisely reading which helps me to recover from my seriousness. At times when I am deeply sunk in work you will see no books around me: I would guard against letting anyone speak or even think in my vicinity. And that is what reading would mean ... Has it really been noticed that in that state of profound tension to which pregnancy condemns the spirit and fundamentally the entire organism, any chance event, any kind of stimulus from without has too vehement an effect, ‘cuts’ too deeply? One has to avoid the chance event, the stimulus from without, as much as possible; a kind of self- walling- up is among the instinctual sagacities of spiritual pregnancy. Shall I allow a strange thought to climb secretly over the wall? – And that is what reading would mean ... The times of work and fruitfulness are followed by the time of recreation: come hither, you pleasant, you witty, you clever books! Will they be German books? ... I have to reckon back half a year to catch myself with a book in my hand. But what was it? – An excellent study by Victor Brochard, les sceptiques Grecs, in which my Laertiana are also well employed. The Sceptics, the only honourable type among the two- and five- fold ambiguous philosophical crowd! ... Otherwise I take flight almost always to the same books, really a small number, those books which have proved themselves precisely to me. It does not perhaps lie in my nature to read much or many kinds of things: a reading room makes me ill. Neither does it lie in my nature to love much or many kinds of things. Caution, even hostility towards new books is rather part of my instinct than ‘tolerance’, ‘largeur du coeur ’ and other forms of ‘neighbour love’ ... It is really only a small number of older Frenchmen to whom I return again and again: I believe only in French culture and consider everything in Europe that calls itself ‘culture’ a misunderstanding, not to speak of German culture ... The few instances of high culture I have encountered in Germany have all been of French origin, above all Frau Cosima Wagner, by far the first voice I have heard in questions of taste. – That I do not read Pascal but love him, as the most instructive of all sacrifices to Christianity, slowly murdered first physically then psychologically, the whole logic of this most horrible form of inhuman cruelty; that I have something of Montaigne's wantonness in my spirit, who knows? perhaps also in my body; that my artist's taste defends the names Molière, Corneille and Racine, not without wrath, against a disorderly genius such as Shakespeare: this does not ultimately exclude my finding the most recent Frenchmen also charming company. I cannot at all conceive in which century of history one could haul together such inquisitive and at the same time such delicate psychologists as one can in contemporary Paris: I name as a sample – for their number is by no means small, Messrs Paul Bourget, Pierre Loti, Gyp, Meilhac, Anatole France, Jules Lemaitre, or to pick out one of the stronger race, a genuine Latin to whom I am especially attached, Guy de Maupassant. Between ourselves, I prefer this generation even to their great teachers, who have all been ruined by German philosophy (M. Taine for example by Hegel, whom he has to thank for this misunderstanding of great human beings and ages). As far as Germany extends it ruins culture. It was only the war that ‘redeemed’ the spirit in France ... Stendhal, one of the fairest accidents of my life – for whatever marks an epoch in my life has been brought to me by accident, never by a recommendation – is utterly invaluable with his anticipating psychologist's eye, with his grasp of facts which reminds one of the proximity of the greatest man of the factual (ex ungue Napoleonem –); finally not least as an honest atheist, a rare, almost undiscoverable species in France – with all deference to Prosper Mérimée ... Perhaps I am even envious of Stendhal? He robbed me of the best atheist joke which precisely I could have made: ‘God's only excuse is that he does not exist’ ... I myself have said somewhere: what has hitherto been the greatest objection to existence? God ...

4

The highest conception of the lyric poet was given me by Heinrich Heine. I seek in vain in all the realms of millennia for an equally sweet and passionate music. He possesses that divine malice without which I cannot imagine perfection – I assess the value of people, of races according to how necessarily they are unable to separate the god from the satyr. – And how he employs German! It will one day be said that Heine and I have been by far the first artists of the German language – at an incalculable distance from everything which mere Germans have done with it. – I must be profoundly related to Byron's Manfred: I discovered all these abysses in myself – I was ripe for this work at thirteen. I have no words, only a look for those who dare to say the word Faust in the presence of Manfred. The Germans are incapable of any conception of greatness: proof Schumann. Expressly from wrath against this sugary Saxon, I composed a counter- overture to Manfred, of which Hans von Bülow said he had never seen the like on manuscript paper: it constituted a rape on Euterpe. – When I seek my highest formula for Shakespeare I find it always in that he conceived the type of Caesar. One cannot guess at things like this – one is it or one is not. The great poet creates only out of his own reality – to the point at which he is afterwards unable to endure his own work ... When I have taken a glance at my Zarathustra I walk up and down my room for half an hour unable to master an unendurable spasm of sobbing. – I know of no more heartrending reading than Shakespeare: what must a man have suffered to need to be a buffoon to this extent! – Is Hamlet understood ? It is not doubt, it is certainty which makes mad ... But to feel in this way one must be profound, abyss, philosopher ... We all fear truth ... And, to confess it: I am instinctively certain that Lord Bacon is the originator, the self- tormentor of this uncanniest species of literature: what do I care about the pitiable chatter of American shallow- pates and muddle- heads? But the power for the mightiest reality of vision is not only compatible with the mightiest power for action, for the monstrous in action, for crime – it even presupposes it ... We do not know nearly enough about Lord Bacon, the first realist in every great sense of the word, to know what he did, what he wanted, what he experienced within himself ... And the devil take it, my dear critics! Supposing I had baptized my Zarathustra with another name, for example with the name of Richard Wagner, the perspicuity of two millennia would not have sufficed to divine that the author of ‘Human, All Too Human’ is the visionary of Zarathustra ...

5

Here where I am speaking of the recreations of my life, I need to say a word to express my gratitude for that which of all things in it has refreshed me by far the most profoundly and cordially. This was without any doubt my intimate association with Richard Wagner. I offer all my other human relationships cheap; but at no price would I relinquish from my life the Tribschen days, those days of mutual confidences, of cheerfulness, of sublime incidents – of profound moments ... I do not know what others may have experienced with Wagner: over our sky no cloud ever passed. – And with that I return again to France – I cannot spare reasons, I can spare a mere curl of the lip for Wagnerians et hoc genus omne who believe they are doing honour to Wagner when they find him similar to themselves ... Constituted as I am, a stranger in my deepest instincts to everything German, so that the mere presence of a German hinders my digestion, my first contact with Wagner was also the first time in my life I ever drew a deep breath: I felt, I reverenced him as a being from outside, as the opposite, the incarnate protest against all ‘German virtues’. – We who were children in the swamp- air of the fifties are necessarily pessimists regarding the concept ‘German’; we cannot be anything but revolutionaries – we shall acquiesce in no state of things in which the bigot is on top. It is a matter of complete indifference to me if today he plays in different colours, if he dresses in scarlet and dons the uniform of a hussar ... Very well! Wagner was a revolutionary – he fled from the Germans ... As an artist one has no home in Europe except in Paris: the délicatesse in all five senses of art which Wagner's art presupposes, the fingers for nuances, the psychological morbidity, is to be found only in Paris. Nowhere else does there exist such a passion in questions of form, this seriousness in mise en scène – it is the Parisian seriousness par excellence. There is in Germany absolutely no conception of the tremendous ambition which dwells in the soul of a Parisian artist. The German is good- natured – Wagner was by no means good- natured ... But I have already said sufficient (in ‘Beyond Good and Evil’ §256) as to where Wagner belongs, in whom he has his closest relatives: the French late romantics, that high- flying and yet exhilarating kind of artists such as Delacroix, such as Berlioz, with a fond of sickness, of incurability in their nature, sheer fanatics for expression, virtuosi through and through ... Who was the first intelligent adherent of Wagner? Charles Baudelaire, the same as was the first to understand Delacroix, that typical décadent in whom an entire race of artists recognized themselves – he was perhaps also the last ... What I have never forgiven Wagner? That he condescended to the Germans – that he became reichsdeutsch ... As far as Germany extends it ruins culture. –

6

All in all I could not have endured my youth without Wagnerian music. For I was condemned to Germans. If one wants to get free from an unendurable pressure one needs hashish. Very well, I needed Wagner. Wagner is the counter- poison to everything German par excellence – still poison, I do not dispute it ... From the moment there was a piano score of Tristan – my compliments, Herr von Bülow! – I was a Wagnerian. The earliest works of Wagner I saw as beneath me – still too common, too ‘German’ ... But I still today seek a work of a dangerous fascination, of a sweet and shuddery infinity equal to that of Tristan – I seek in all the arts in vain. All the strangenesses of Leonardo da Vinci lose their magic at the first note of Tristan. This work is altogether Wagner's non plus ultra ; he recuperated from it with the Meistersinger and the Ring. To become healthier – that is retrogression in the case of a nature such as Wagner ... I take it for a piece of good fortune of the first rank to have lived at the right time, and to have lived precisely among Germans, so as to be ripe for this work: my psychologist's inquisitiveness goes that far. The world is poor for him who has never been sick enough for this ‘voluptuousness of hell’: to employ a mystic's formula is permissible, almost obligatory, here. I think I know better than anyone what tremendous things Wagner was capable of, the fifty worlds of strange delights to which no one but he had wings; and as I am strong enough to turn even the most questionable and most perilous things to my own advantage and thus to become stronger, I call Wagner the great benefactor of my life. That in which we are related, that we have suffered more profoundly, from one another also, than men of this century are capable of suffering, will eternally join our names together again and again; and as surely as Wagner is among Germans merely a misunderstanding, just as surely am I and always will be. – Two centuries of psychological and artistic discipline first, my Herr Germans! ... But one cannot catch up that amount. –

7

I shall say another word for the most select ears: what I really want from music. That it is cheerful and profound, like an afternoon in October. That it is individual, wanton, tender, a little sweet woman of lowness and charm ... I shall never admit that a German could know what music is. What one calls German musicians, the greatest above all, are foreigners, Slavs, Croats, Italians, Netherlanders – or Jews: otherwise Germans of the strong race, extinct Germans, like Heinrich Schütz, Bach and Handel. I myself am still sufficient of a Pole to exchange the rest of music for Chopin; for three reasons I exclude Wagner's Siegfried Idyll, perhaps also a few things by Liszt, who excels all other musicians in the nobility of his orchestral tone; finally all that has grown up beyond the Alps – this side ... I would not know how to get on without Rossini, even less without my south in music, the music of my Venetian maestro Pietro Gasti. And when I say beyond the Alps I am really saying only Venice. When I seek another word for music I never find any other word than Venice. I do not know how to distinguish between tears and music – I do not know how to think of happiness, of the south, without a shudder of faintheartedness.

Lately I stood at the bridge

in the brown night.

From afar there came a song:

a golden drop, it swelled

across the trembling surface.

Gondolas, lights, music –

drunken it swam out into the gloom ...

My soul, a stringed instrument,

touched by invisible hands

sang to itself in reply a gondola song,

and trembled with gaudy happiness.

– Was anyone listening?

8

In all this – in selection of nutriment, of place and climate, of recreation – there c ommands a n i nstinct o f s elfpreservation which manifests itself most unambiguously as an instinct for self- defence. Not to see many things, not to hear them, not to let them approach one – first piece of ingenuity, first proof that one is no accident but a necessity. The customary word for this self- defensive instinct is taste. Its imperative commands, not only to say No when Yes would be a piece of ‘selflessness’, but also to say No as little as possible. To separate oneself, to depart from that to which No would be required again and again. The rationale is that defensive expenditures, be they never so small, become a rule, a habit, lead to an extraordinary and perfectly superfluous impoverishment. Our largest expenditures are our most frequent small ones. Warding off, not letting come close, is an expenditure – one should not deceive oneself over this – a strength squandered on negative objectives. One can merely through the constant need to ward off become too weak any longer to defend oneself. – Suppose I were to step out of my house and discover, instead of calm and aristocratic Turin, the German provincial town: my instinct would have to blockade itself so as to push back all that pressed upon it from this flat and cowardly world. Or suppose I discovered the German metropolis, that builded vice where nothing grows, where every kind of thing, good and bad, is dragged in. Would I not in face of it have to become a hedgehog ? – B ut to have spikes is an extravagance, a double luxury even if one is free to have no spikes but open hands ...

Another form of sagacity and self- defence consists in reacting as seldom as possible and withdrawing from situations and relationships in which one would be condemned as it were to suspend one's ‘freedom’, one's initiative, and become a mere reagent. I take as a parable traffic with books. The scholar, who really does nothing but ‘trundle’ books – the philologist at a modest assessment about 200 a day – finally loses altogether the ability to think for himself. If he does not trundle he does not think. He replies to a stimulus (– a thought he has read) when he thinks – finally he does nothing but react. The scholar expends his entire strength in affirmation and denial, in criticizing what has already been thought – he himself no longer thinks ... The instinct for self- defence has in his case become soft; otherwise he would defend himself against books. The scholar – a décadent. – This I have seen with my own eyes: natures gifted, rich and free already in their thirties ‘read to ruins’, mere matches that have to be struck if they are to ignite – emit ‘thoughts’. – Early in the morning at the break of day, in all the freshness and dawn of one's strength, to read a book – I call that vicious! –

9

At this point I can no longer avoid actually answering the question how one becomes what one is. And with that I touch on the masterpiece in the art of self- preservation – of selfishness ... For assuming that the task, the vocation, the destiny of the task exceeds the average measure by a significant degree, there would be no greater danger than to catch sight of oneself with this task. That one becomes what one is presupposes that one does not have the remotest idea what one is. From this point of view even the blunders of life – the temporary sidepaths and wrong turnings, the delays, the ‘modesties’, the seriousness squandered on tasks which lie outside the task – have their own meaning and value. They are an expression of a great sagacity, even the supreme sagacity: where nosce te ipsum w ould b e t he r ecipe f or destruction, self- forgetfulness, self- misunderstanding, selfdiminution, -narrowing, -mediocratizing becomes reason itself. Expressed morally: love of one's neighbour, living for others and other things can be the defensive measure for the preservation of the sternest selfishness. This is the exceptional case in which I, contrary to my rule and conviction, take the side of the ‘selfless’ drives: here they work in the service of selfishness, self- cultivation. – The entire surface of consciousness – consciousness is a surface – has to be kept clear of any of the great imperatives. Even the grand words, the grand attitudes must be guarded against! All of them represent a danger that the instinct will ‘understand itself’ too early ––. In the meantime the organizing ‘idea’ destined to rule grows and grows in the depths – it begins to command, it slowly leads back f rom s idepaths a nd w rong turnings, it prepares individual qualities and abilities which will one day prove themselves indispensable as means to achieving the whole – it constructs the ancillary capacities one after the other before it gives any hint of the dominating task, of the ‘goal’, ‘objective’, ‘meaning’. – Regarded from this side my life is simply wonderful. For the task of a revaluation of values more capacities perhaps were required than have dwelt together in one individual, above all antithetical capacities which however are not allowed to disturb or destroy one another. Order of rank among capacities; distance; the art of dividing without making inimical; mixing up nothing, ‘reconciling’ nothing; a tremendous multiplicity which is none the less the opposite of chaos – this has been the precondition, the protracted secret labour and artistic working of my instinct. The magnitude of its higher protection was shown in the fact I have at no time had the remotest idea what was growing within me – that all my abilities one day leapt forth suddenly ripe, in their final perfection. I cannot remember ever having taken any trouble – no trace of struggle can be discovered in my life, I am the opposite of an heroic nature. To ‘want’ something, to ‘strive’ after something, to have a ‘goal’, a ‘wish’ in view – I know none of this from experience. Even at this moment I look out upon my future – a distant future! – as upon a smooth sea: it is ruffled by no desire. I do not want in the slightest that anything should become other than it is; I do not want myself to become other than I am ... But that is how I have always lived. I have harboured no desire. Someone who after his forty- fourth year can say he has never striven after honours, after women, after money ! – Not that I could not have had them ... Thus, for example, I one day became a university professor – I had never had the remotest thought of such a thing, for I was barely twenty- four years old. Thus two years earlier I was one day a philologist: in the sense that my first philological work, my beginning in any sense, was requested by my teacher Ritschl for his ‘Rheinisches Museum’. (Ritschl – I say it with respect – the only scholar gifted with genius whom I have encountered up to the present day. He was characterized by that pleasant depravity which distinguishes us Thuringians and which can render even a German sympathetic – to get to the truth we even prefer to go by secret paths. I should not with these words like to have in any way undervalued my close compatriot, the sagacious Leopold von Ranke ...)

10

I shall be asked why I have really narrated all these little things which according to the traditional judgement are matters of indifference: it will be said that in doing so I harm myself all the more if I am destined to fulfil great tasks. Answer: these little things – nutriment, place, climate, recreation, the whole casuistry of selfishness – are beyond all conception of greater importance than anything that has been considered of importance hitherto. It is precisely here that one has to begin to learn anew. Those things which mankind has hitherto pondered seriously are not even realities, merely imaginings, more strictly speaking lies from the bad instincts of sick, in the profoundest sense injurious natures – all the concepts ‘God’, ‘soul’, ‘virtue’, ‘sin’, ‘the Beyond’, ‘truth’, ‘eternal life’ ... But the greatness of human nature, its ‘divinity’, has been sought in them ... All questions of politics, the ordering of society, education have been falsified down to their foundations because the most injurious men have been taken for great men – because contempt has been taught for the ‘little’ things, which is to say for the fundamental affairs of life ... Now, when I compare myself with the men who have hitherto been honoured as pre- eminent men the distinction is palpable. I do not count these supposed ‘ pre- eminent men’ as belonging to mankind at all – to me they are the refuse of mankind, abortive offspring of sickness and vengeful instincts: they are nothing but pernicious, fundamentally incurable monsters who take revenge on life ... I want to be the antithesis of this: it is my privilege to possess the highest subtlety for all the signs of healthy instincts. Every morbid trait is lacking in me; even in periods of severe illness I did not become morbid; a trait of fanaticism will be sought in vain in my nature. At no moment of my life can I be shown to have adopted any kind of arrogant or pathetic posture. The pathos of attitudes does not belong to greatness; whoever needs attitudes at all is false ... Beware of all picturesque men! – Life has been easy for me, easiest when it demanded of me the most difficult things. Anyone who saw me during the seventy days of this autumn when I was uninterruptedly creating nothing but things of the first rank which no man will be able to do again or has done before, bearing a responsibility for all the coming millennia, will have noticed no trace of tension in me, but rather an overflowing freshness and cheerfulness. I never ate with greater relish, I never slept better. – I know of no other way of dealing with great tasks than that of play : this is, as a sign of greatness, an essential precondition. The slightest constraint, the gloomy mien, any kind of harsh note in the throat are all objections to a man, how much more to his work! ... One must have no nerves ... To suffer from solitude is likewise an objection – I have always suffered only from the ‘multitude’ ... At an absurdly early age, at the age of seven, I already knew that no human word would ever reach me: has anyone ever seen me sad on that account? – Still today I treat everyone with the same geniality, I am even full of consideration for the basest people: in all this there is not a grain of arrogance, of secret contempt. He whom I despise divines that I despise him: through my mere existence I enrage everything that has bad blood in its veins ... My formula for greatness in a human being is amor fati : that one wants nothing to be other than it is, not in the future, not in the past, not in all eternity. Not merely to endure that which happens of necessity, still less to dissemble it – all idealism is untruthfulness in the face of necessity – but to love it ...

鸭子与袋鼠

鸭子对袋鼠说：

“天哪！你的跳跃可真行！

田野、河流你都能一跃而过，

就好像你永远都不会停！

这片脏池塘里无聊的生活就是我的一切，

我好想去看看外面的世界！

我多希望能像你一样跳起跳落！”

鸭子对袋鼠说。

“请载着我去兜风吧！”

鸭子对袋鼠说。

“我会乖乖坐着，只发出一种声音

‘嘎’，

一整天我都会这样做！

我们可以上天入地，去迪地和杰力波里，

跃过大海，踏过陆地——

带我去兜风吧！拜托拜托！”

鸭子对袋鼠说。

袋鼠对鸭子说：

“这你得让我想一想；

也许这件事会将幸运带给我，

除了一件事以外一切无妨，

那就是，如果你允许我直白地讲，

你的两只脚蹼又湿又凉，

很可能会让风湿找上我！”

袋鼠说。

鸭子说：“当时我在石头上坐下，

深思熟虑了这件事，

我带来了四双精纺毛袜，

仿佛就是为我相连的脚蹼定制。

为了抵御寒风我带了一件斗篷，

我还会每天点一支雪茄，烟雾蒙蒙，

这一切都是因为我爱你这只袋鼠，

我真挚热烈的爱让一切都不辛苦！”

袋鼠说：“我已经准备好！

月光清冷的夜晚我们就出发；

但为了我的平衡，亲爱的鸭子，坐稳了别摔倒！

我尾巴的末端位置就是最佳！”

于是它们助跑起跳，

围着整个地球绕了三绕；

还有谁能比鸭子和袋鼠，有谁，

比鸭子和袋鼠更心满意足？

扫帚、铲子、拨火棍与钳子

扫帚和铲子，有拨火棍与钳子来陪同，

他们一起乘着马车把公园逛，

他们每个人都唱了一首歌，叮啊咚，

叮啊咚，

他们唱完就又回到了黑乎乎的地方。

拨火棍先生在马车里坐得挺拔，

钳子先生发出了响声哗啦哗啦，

铲子小姐一袭黑衣（别着胸花），

扫帚夫人身着蓝色（缎带斜搭）。

叮啊咚！叮啊咚！

他们都各自唱了一通！

“哦，铲子姑娘你多么漂亮！”拨火棍唱颂，

“你完美地俘获了我的心！

叮啊咚！叮啊咚！如果我的歌

让你满意认同，

我将喂你吃凉苹果馅饼！

当你铲起煤堆，声音清脆犹存，

你为我的生活带来了无比的惊喜！

你的鼻子亮闪闪！你的头颅圆滚滚！

你的身体苗条又充满活力！

叮啊咚！叮啊咚！

我的歌是否让你心动？”

“唉！扫帚夫人！”钳子在他的歌唱中叹息心痛，

“哦，是否因为我太瘦，

我的双腿又太长，显得与众不同——叮啊咚！

叮啊咚！

所以我在你心里什么地位也没有？

啊！最优雅美丽的尤物，当你将房间里的灰尘扫走，

啊！你为何不理会我的哭诉！

你一定要如此残忍吗，你这只美丽的扫帚，

这是否因为你全身上下油漆遍布？

叮啊咚！叮啊咚！

你可真是大错特错，一点儿也不懂！”

扫帚夫人和铲子小姐一齐唱起：

“你们今天唱的都是些什么胡言乱语！”

铲子说：“我绝对要当啷一声敲醒你！”

扫帚说：“我要把你扫出去！”

于是马车夫以最快的速度往家中驶去，

因为他察觉到了他们的愤怒与痛苦；

但他们烧上了一壶水，于是过了一会儿，

他们又都重新将笑容展露。

叮啊咚！叮啊咚！

这就是我的歌的全部内容！

求爱的杨以邦以波

在科罗曼德半岛的海岸处，

未成熟的南瓜从空中飘落，

在树林的中央，

住着杨以邦以波。

两把旧椅子和半截蜡烛，

还有一只缺了把手的水壶——

这些便是他的全部家当，

在树林的中央，

这些便是他的全部家当，

它们属于杨以邦以波，

它们属于杨以邦以波。

一天，他散步在参天树林里，

未成熟的南瓜从空中飘落，

那里聚集了几块石礅，

杨以邦以波正好路过。

他听见有人说话，是一位女士，

对着一群雪白的杜金鸡说：

“这是叮当响的琼斯夫人！

坐在这片石礅上的果真

就是叮当响的琼斯夫人！”

杨以邦以波如是说，

杨以邦以波如是说。

“叮当响夫人！叮当响夫人你看！

你坐的地方有未成熟的南瓜从空中飘落，

你是否愿意嫁给我？”

杨以邦以波如是说。

“我受够了孤独的日子、无人陪伴，

在这片布满卵石的荒凉海滩——

我厌倦了这样的生活；

如果你愿意嫁给我，

平静便能降临我的生活！”

杨以邦以波如是说，

杨以邦以波如是说。

“这片科罗曼德半岛的海岸处，

是小虾和豆瓣菜的居所，

大虾又多又便宜得很，”

杨以邦以波如是说，

“你将拥有我的椅子和蜡烛，

还有我缺了把手的水壶！——

瞧瞧这片海翻滚之深

（丰富又便宜，这海里的鱼虾们）；

我的爱就和这片海一样深！”

杨以邦以波如是说，

杨以邦以波如是说。

叮当响夫人开始悲伤地讲起，

她的眼泪也开始掉落——

“你的求婚来得晚了一步，

这位先生，杨以邦以波！

我非常愿意成为你的妻子！”

（这时她开始不停地绞着手指。）

“但我在英国已经有了丈夫！

是的！你的求婚晚了一步，

我在英国已经有了丈夫，

这位先生，杨以邦以波！

这位先生，杨以邦以波！”

“琼斯先生，（亨德尔是他的称呼——

亨德尔・琼斯，他拥有自己的律师事务所。）

是他总乐于送来这些杜金鸡为我消愁，

这位先生，杨以邦以波！

留着吧，哦！留着你的椅子和蜡烛，

还有你缺了把手的水壶——

我只能成为你的朋友！

——如果我的琼斯先生再送来更多的杜金鸡，那时候

我会送给你三只，我的朋友！

这位先生，杨以邦以波！

这位先生，杨以邦以波！”

“尽管你的身体如此瘦小平凡，

尽管你的头比身体大得多得多，

尽管你的帽子随时会被风吹下，

这位先生，杨以邦以波！

虽然你头脑如此简单——

我依旧希望我能换

一种说法说出接下来的话！

能否请你离开，别再牵挂？

这就是我要说的话，

这位先生，杨以邦以波！

这位先生，杨以邦以波！”

走下默特尔湿滑的山坡，

未成熟的南瓜在空中飘摇，

向着那片平静无声的大海，

杨以邦以波飞也似的奔逃。

将哥特尔海湾越过，

那里趴着一只巨大的海龟，生气勃勃。

“你是我的避风港，”他说，“带我离开；

你将驮着我越过大海，

海龟，请你带我离开！”

杨以邦以波如是说，

杨以邦以波如是说。

在那片无声翻滚着的大海上，

海龟全速前进，风风火火；

紧紧抓着它的龟壳的

就是杨以邦以波。

他的样子充满脆弱与悲伤，

面对着波申日落群岛的方向，

海龟依旧稳稳地将他载着，

他则牢牢地抓着它的壳，

“叮当响的琼斯夫人，再见了！”

杨以邦以波如是说，

杨以邦以波如是说。

科罗曼德半岛的海岸处，

那位夫人再也不曾离开过；

在那片石礅上她哀悼着，

哀悼着杨以邦以波。

在科罗曼德半岛的海岸处，

对着他缺了把手的水壶，

她整日哭泣哀怨着；

在那片石礅上坐着的，

是对着杜金鸡的她在哀怨着，

为了杨以邦以波，

为了杨以邦以波。

斯库比皮皮

一天，斯库比皮皮出门了，

那时草是绿的，天是灰的，

斯库比皮皮坐了下来，

世界上所有的野兽都围了过来。

小猫、小狗，和袋鼠，

小羊、小牛，还有荷兰猪，

狼仰天呼号，马对地嘶鸣，

小猪厉声尖叫，驴子喊个不停，

当狮子开始咆哮怒吼，

那样的声音前所未有，

所有的野兽都踮起脚尖，

为了能看到斯库比皮皮一眼。

最后大家对狐狸说：“时至今日，

你是最睿智的野兽，你知道你是！

你快走到斯库比皮皮那里，

和他说‘请你介绍一下你自己！——

因为我们直到现在还在发愁，

你到底是鱼是虫，是鸟是兽’？”

斯库比皮皮随意地向四周一望，

用隆隆的声音开始歌唱：

“哩哩滴滴哩——滴滴哩哩滴——

我唯一的名字就是斯库比皮皮。”

斯库比皮皮站在树顶，离开陆地，

望见了遥远的杰力波里，

世界上所有的鸟儿都围了过来，

成群结队从空中飞来。

秃鹫、老鹰、公鸡和母鸡来报到，

还有鸵鸟、火鸡、沙锥和鹪鹩，

鹦鹉聒噪，乌鸦歌唱，

猫头鹰一言不发，摆出睿智的模样，

当孔雀开始尖叫，

整个世界变得无比吵闹。

所有的鸟儿都抖动着翅膀，

希望能将斯库比皮皮仔细地瞧。

最后大家对猫头鹰说：“时至今日，

你是最睿智的鸟儿——你知道你是！

你快飞到斯库比皮皮那里，

和他说‘请你介绍一下你自己！——

因为我们到现在还不曾知晓，

你到底是鱼是虫，是兽是鸟’？”

斯库比皮皮开心地向四周一望，

用轻快的声音开始歌唱：

“滴滴哩哩滴——哩哩滴滴哩——

我唯一的名字就是斯库比皮皮。”

斯库比皮皮钻进了大海，

就在杰力波里美丽的沙滩一带，

世界上所有的鱼儿都围了过来，

稀里哗啦地将海水劈开，

黍鲱、鲱鱼、比目鱼，

鲨鱼、鳎鱼和蓝色的鲭鱼，

——在扑腾，鼠海豚吐泡泡

——不知所措——

当鲸鱼喷出水柱。

所有的鱼儿都抖动着尾巴，

都把斯库比皮皮认真地观察。

最后大家对鲸鱼说：“时至今日，

你是最庞大的鱼儿——你知道你是！

你快游到斯库比皮皮那里，

和他说‘请你介绍一下你自己！

因为了解你是我们唯一的期许，

你到底是兽是虫，是鸟是鱼’？”

斯库比皮皮温柔地向四周一望，

用咕嘟咕嘟的声音开始歌唱：

“嘻嘻哩哩嘻——哩哩嘻嘻哩——

我唯一的名字就是斯库比皮皮。”

斯库比皮皮坐在树下乘凉，

就在杰力波里安静的海岸旁，

世界上所有的昆虫，

都围着斯库比皮皮旋转颤动。

甲壳虫和——紫色眼睛的

小飞虫还有嗡嗡叫的苍蝇，

蚂蚱、蝴蝶，还有蜘蛛爬行，

马蜂、蜜蜂，以及蓝色的蜻蜓，

当小飞虫开始哼哼

——像悲伤的鼓点一样跳动——

所有的昆虫都卷起了他们的长针，

对着斯库比皮皮看得出了神。

最后大家对蚂蚁说：“时至今日，

你是最睿智的昆虫，你知道你是！

你快溜到斯库比皮皮那里，

和他说‘请你介绍一下你自己！

因为我们不知道，我们也想不通，

你是兽是鱼，是鸟是虫’？”

斯库比皮皮快速地转身回望，

用窸窸窣窣的声音开始歌唱：

“唧唧嘁嘁唧——嘁嘁唧唧戚——

我唯一的名字就是斯库比皮皮。”

陆地上走的所有野兽

都围成一圈跳舞，手拉着手，

天空中飞的所有鸟类

都围成一圈旋转，来来回回，

杰力波里的所有鱼虾

都围成一圈游动，在那水下，

潜伏爬行的所有昆虫

都围成一圈振动，声音嗡嗡。

他们咆哮、歌唱、低语、叫喊，

直到声音将整个地球充满——

“滴滴哔哔滴！哔哔滴滴哔！

他唯一的名字就是斯库比皮皮。”

斯瓦特的阿空德

谁，或是为何，或是哪个，或是什么，才是斯瓦特的阿空德？

他是高是矮，皮肤是黑是白？

他坐凳子、沙发还是要找一把椅子来

或者蹲着，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他聪明还是愚蠢，是青年还是老翁？他的汤和咖啡是否要放到冰冰冷

还是要加热，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他唱歌还是吹口哨，胡言乱语还是头头是道？他出国旅行是快马加鞭还是走路就到

或者小跑着踩过车辙，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他戴头巾、毡帽还是檐帽？

他睡软垫、大床还是地毯一条

或者婴儿床更适合，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

如果碰到用花体字写信的情况，

他是否会给T画上一横、给I的头上

加点一颗，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他能否把信写得精简又清楚？

没有一丝油点、脏迹和污物

也不滴下斑斑墨色，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他是否得到了人民真心的爱戴？

还是只要逮着机会他们就造反起义、为非作歹

在背后暗中谋策，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

如果他抓到了谋逆的人民，不管年老还是年轻，

他会将他们碎尸万段，处以绞刑

还是开枪扫射，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他的人民是否在路上和公园里抢劫掠夺？

甚至有时日子苦难，只能小偷小摸

最终成了绞刑架上的空壳，

哦，斯瓦特的阿空德！

他是否会关注自己领土上人民的希冀？

还是他毫不在意

对公众的观点漠然得透彻，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他的臣民拿什么取悦他？

是用绘画，还是用谁最新的诗作

到底用什么以作乐，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

如果夜晚他突然尖叫着惊醒，

他们是否会拿几块小蛋糕为他压惊

还是满满一车，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他最爱的食物是萝卜、茶叶还是牛肚？

条纹是否是他最欣赏的披肩纹路

还是圆点更让他认可，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他是否喜欢在船里平躺，

就像那位住在遥远小岛的女人一样

她叫莎洛特，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他性格沉稳内敛，还是整日寻死觅活？

他的侍从是来自瑞士、瑞典还是俄国

或者来自苏格兰的异乡客，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他是喜欢在蓝色的平静大海旁歇脚，

还是在绿色的林间山洞里打鼾睡觉

抑或是巢穴来得更悠然自得，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他喝的淡啤酒是否用银质的罐子装？还是用碗？玻璃瓶？茶杯？或者缸？

抑或是用锅更解渴，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他是否会用顶部镶金的烟斗对他的妻子打骂训斥，在她每每忘记摘下熟过头了的醋栗

甚至腐烂变色时，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他和朋友进餐时，是否会戴一条白色的领带，整齐地打个蝴蝶结，两端下垂向外

还是系成扣就合格，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他是否喜欢奶油，痛恨肉饼？

他直视太阳时是否会眨眼睛

还是坚决不眨，直直盯着，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

他是否会教他的臣民烘焙与烧烤？

他是否会航行在内陆湖中绕

驾着游艇，

斯瓦特的阿空德？

我想是否前无古人，后无来者，

知道谁，或是哪个，或是为何，或是什么

才是斯瓦特的阿空德！

鼻子会发光的阿冬

可怕的黑夜与寂静

在广袤的格鲁布里安平原降临，

在无比漫长的冬夜里；

海浪愤怒地咆哮呼喊，

拍打着岩石嶙峋的海岸；

暴风雨前的乌云积聚在高耸的峭壁，

那是波尔禅岭的群山：

那时，在无限的黑暗和阴霾中，

似乎有一点星火在移动，

孤独地发出银色的光芒，

穿透了如炭一般黢黑的夜晚，

如一颗流星般奇异亮闪闪：

在这里和那里四处游荡，

一束触目惊心的亮光，形只影单。

那光慢慢地游移、暂停、鬼鬼祟祟，

又迅速地闪烁、惊现、跳跃起飞；

随着光芒继续向前行走，

光辉照射在了参天大树的枝头。

从礼堂、阳台和耸立的高塔上，

人们朝窗外的午夜时分张望，

跟随那无拘无束光芒的行踪，

人们喊道：“阿冬！阿冬！

阿冬又一次游走在树林里！

阿冬！阿冬！

阿冬有着会发光的鼻子！”

许多许多年前，

阿冬终日开心快乐，

直到一位樟布利姑娘登上岸，

那天他坠入了爱河。

樟布利人们乘着漏筛到来，是的，

他们傍晚登陆的地点靠近泽莫里菲德，

矩形的牡蛎生长在海边，

光滑的石头泛着灰色。

树林里和山谷中传来回响，

是樟布利人们不分昼夜在歌唱：

遥远又稀有，遥远又稀有，

樟布利人就从那样的地方来；

他们有着绿色的头，他们有着蓝色的手，

他们乘着漏筛，驶入了大海。

那些日子是多么令人愉快！

樟布利人们还没有离开；

他们整晚围成一圈舞蹈，

被兴奋的阿冬吹奏的忧伤笛声围绕，

月光下、树荫里，都有他们的身影在。

几天几夜阿冬都在那里，

和美丽的樟布利女孩一起，

她有着天蓝色的双手，海绿色的发丝。

直到糟糕的那天早上，

樟布利人们乘着他们的漏筛起航，

阿冬被残忍地留在了岸边，

久久凝视着海与天的交界线，

他疲惫的双眼在遥望

远方地平线上豆绿色的船帆，

在那长满青草的山坡上，他坐了一整天，

还在把樟布利人的那首歌唱念，

遥远又稀有，遥远又稀有，

樟布利人就从那样的地方来；

他们有着绿色的头，他们有着蓝色的手，

他们乘着漏筛，驶入了大海。

但当西方的天空挂上了落日，

阿冬边自言自语边慢慢站起：

“我曾经拥有的一点点理智，

现在也已经完全消失！”

从那天起他开始游荡

在湖边和森林里，沼泽和小山上，

边走边唱：“噢！有一个地方，在山谷或是平原，

我还能再见到我的樟布利女孩一面！

我将永远在湖边和岸边寻找，

直到我再次把我的樟布利女孩找到！”

从那以后他一直寻找着樟布利女孩，

仿佛银器发出的咯吱声从他的笛子中传来，

又因为夜里看不见，一切黑漆漆，

于是他收集了团格姆树的树皮，

它们生长的平原上鲜花烂漫。

他为自己编织了一只鼻子，令人惊叹，

那鼻子实在是无比怪异！

它又宽又大，被涂成了红色，

用绳子固定好，在脑后绑着。

里面中空的圆形空当，

有一盏点亮的灯在那里摆放，

再用结实的绷带缠绕，

把四周全部围好，

为了防止灯光被风吹灭熄掉；

四周还布满了小孔，这样才能

让光一束束地点亮黑夜的凄冷。

如今的每个夜晚，通宵达旦，

阿冬都在那一片片平原上游走寻探；

在黑猩猩和沙锥的哀号之上，

也许你能听到他的笛子在咯吱咯吱响，

他虽然一直在寻找，但寻找都是徒劳，

他徒劳地盼望着能再和樟布利女孩见到；

孤独又漫无目的，他整夜行走，

有着发光鼻子的阿冬哟！

从礼堂、阳台，和耸立的高塔上，

人们朝窗外的午夜时分张望，

跟随那闪耀流星的光辉，

穿过那苦闷的黑夜，

人们喊道：“每到这时他都在向前行走，

有着发光鼻子的阿冬哟！

在那边的平原上他在行走；

他走！

他走！

有着发光鼻子的阿冬哟！”

我叔叔阿尔利的一些往事

噢，我年迈的叔叔阿尔利！

坐上了一堆高高的麦粒，

夜晚的时光安谧寂静，

他紧挨着茂盛的灌木丛；

一只蟋蟀稳坐他的鼻头不动，

一张火车票藏在他的帽子中

（但他的鞋子还是系得太紧）。

很久以前，年轻的他挥霍无度，

最后他一无所有，只好整日漫步，

来到了遥远的提姆斯库山里。

在那里，每天的傍晚时分

他都在望着金色的落日下沉，

唱着：“圆球！你可真神！

我好想知道你是什么东西！”

和古老的米堤亚人和波斯人一样，

他总是能通过自己的力量，

在那片山上生存下来、克服困难；

有时靠教小孩子拼写字词，

或者大喊大叫就足矣，

或者偶尔卖卖东西，

比如“由此之故的尼哥底母药丸”。

后来，他在早上散步的途中

注意到黑莓灌木丛在动，

露出了一个东西，又白又方；

那是一张头等座的火车票，

他俯身去捡，刚一弯腰，

一只豆绿色的蟋蟀便助跑起跳，

落在了我叔叔的鼻子上。

从此以后，再也没有，噢！再也没有一天，

那只蟋蟀再也没有离开过他的身边，

清晨或傍晚，白昼或晚景；

它都像得了宝贝一样紧抓不放，

用欢快的声音高叫歌唱，

只为了我叔叔能开心地将烦恼遗忘

（但他的鞋子还是系得太紧）。

就这样又过了四十三个冬天，

直到他的鞋子都磨成了碎片，

他就在那片山上闲逛，

有时沉默，有时呼喊；

直到他来到了博利梅令山，

在那里，他的祖先曾经代代居住；

于是从那时起，他也便不再游荡。

我年迈的叔叔阿尔利，

在一小堆麦粒上咽了气，

一天晚上，人们为他下葬送殡；

地点就紧挨着那茂盛的灌木丛；

他的帽子和火车票也在其中，

他忠诚的蟋蟀也一起陪同

（但他的鞋子还是系得太紧）。

The Duck and the Kangaroo

Said the Duck to the Kangaroo,

‘Good gracious! how you hop!

Over the fields and the water too,

As if you never would stop!

My life is a bore in this nasty pond,

And I long to go out in the world beyond!

I wish I could hop like you!'

Said the Duck to the Kangaroo.

‘Please give me a ride on your back!'

Said the Duck to the Kangaroo.

‘I would sit quite still, and say nothing but

"Quack,"

The whole of the long day through!

And we'd go to the Dee, and the Jelly Bo Lee,

Over the land, and over the sea; -

Please take me a ride! O do!'

Said the Duck to the Kangaroo.

Said the Kangaroo to the Duck,

‘This requires some little reflection;

Perhaps on the whole it might bring me luck,

And there seems but one objection,

Which is, if you'll let me speak so bold,

Your feet are unpleasantly wet and cold,

And would probably give me the roomatiz!'

said the Kangaroo.

Said the Duck, ‘As I sate on the rocks,

I have thought over that completely,

And I bought four pairs of worsted socks

Which fit my web- feet neatly.

And to keep out the cold I've bought a cloak,

And every day a cigar I'll smoke,

All to follow my own dear true

Love of a Kangaroo!'

Said the Kangaroo, ‘I'm ready!

All in the moonlight pale;

But to balance me well, dear Duck, sit steady!

And quite at the end of my tail!'

So away they went with a hop and a bound,

And they hopped the whole world three times round;

And who so happy, – O who,

As the Duck and the Kangaroo?

The Owl and the Pussy- cat

The Owl and the Pussy- cat went to sea

In a beautiful pea- green boat,

They took some honey, and plenty of money,

Wrapped up in a five- pound note.

The Owl looked up to the stars above,

And sang to a small guitar,

‘O lovely Pussy! O Pussy, my love,

What a beautiful Pussy you are,

You are,

You are!

What a beautiful Pussy you are!'

Pussy said to the Owl, ‘You elegant fowl!

How charmingly sweet you sing!

O let us be married! too long we have tarried:

But what shall we do for a ring?'

They sailed away, for a year and a day,

To the land where the Bong- tree grows,

And there in a wood a Piggy- wig stood,

With a ring at the end of his nose,

His nose,

His nose,

With a ring at the end of his nose.

‘Dear Pig, are you willing to sell for one shilling

Your ring?' Said the Piggy, ‘I will.'

So they took it away, and were married next day

By the Turkey who lives on the hill.

They dinèd on mince, and slices of quince,

Which they ate with a runcible spoon;

And hand in hand, on the edge of the sand,

They danced by the light of the moon,

The moon,

The moon,

They danced by the light of the moon.

The Broom, the Shovel, the Poker, and the Tongs

The Broom and the Shovel, the Poker and Tongs,

They all took a drive in the Park,

And they each sang a song, Ding- a- dong,

Ding- a- dong,

Before they went back in the dark.

Mr Poker he sate quite upright in the coach,

Mr Tongs made a clatter and clash,

Miss Shovel was dressed all in black (with a brooch),

Mrs Broom was in blue (with a sash).

Ding- a- dong! Ding- a- dong!

And they all sang a song!

‘Oh Shovely so lovely!' the Poker he sang,

‘You have perfectly conquered my heart!

Ding- a- dong! Ding- a- dong! If you're pleased with my song,

I will feed you with cold apple tart!

When you scrape up the coals with a delicate sound,

You enrapture my life with delight!

Your nose is so shiny! your head is so round!

And your shape is so slender and bright!

Ding- a- dong! Ding- a- dong!

Ain't you pleased with my song?'

‘Alas! Mrs Broom!' sighed the Tongs in his song,

‘O is it because I'm so thin,

And my legs are so long – D ing- a-d ong!

Ding- a- dong!

That you don't care about me a pin?

Ah! fairest of creatures, when sweeping the room,

Ah! why don't you heed my complaint!

Must you needs be so cruel, you beautiful Broom,

Because you are covered with paint?

Ding- a- dong! Ding- a- dong!

You are certainly wrong!'

Mrs Broom and Miss Shovel together they sang,

‘What nonsense you're singing to- day!'

Said the Shovel, ‘I'll certainly hit you a bang!'

Said the Broom, ‘And I'll sweep you away!'

So the Coachman drove homeward as fast as he could,

Perceiving their anger with pain;

But they put on the kettle, and little by little,

They all became happy again.

Ding- a- dong! Ding- a- dong!

There's an end of my song!

The Courtship of the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò

On the Coast of Coromandel

Where the early pumpkins blow,

In the middle of the woods

Lived the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

Two old chairs, and half a candle, -

One old jug without a handle, -

These were all his worldly goods,

In the middle of the woods,

These were all the worldly goods,

Of the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò,

Of the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

Once, among the Bong- trees walking

Where the early pumpkins blow,

To a little heap of stones

Came the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

There he heard a Lady talking,

To some milk- white Hens of Dorking, -

‘ 'Tis the Lady Jingly Jones!

On that little heap of stones

Sits the Lady Jingly Jones!'

Said the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò,

Said the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

‘Lady Jingly! Lady Jingly!

Sitting where the pumpkins blow,

Will you come and be my wife?'

Said the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

‘I am tired of living singly, -

On this coast so wild and shingly, -

I'm a- weary of my life;

If you'll come and be my wife,

Quite serene would be my life!' -

Said the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò,

Said the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

‘On this Coast of Coromandel,

Shrimps and watercresses grow,

Prawns are plentiful and cheap,'

Said the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

‘You shall have my chairs and candle,

And my jug without a handle! -

Gaze upon the rolling deep

(Fish is plentiful and cheap;)

As the sea, my love is deep!'

Said the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò,

Said the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

Lady Jingly answered sadly,

And her tears began to flow, -

‘Your proposal comes too late,

Mr Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò!

I would be your wife most gladly!'

(Here she twirled her fingers madly,)

‘But in England I've a mate!

Yes! you've asked me far too late,

For in England I've a mate,

Mr Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò!

Mr Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò!'

‘Mr Jones – (his name is Handel, -

Handel Jones, Esquire, & Co.)

Dorking fowls delights to send,

Mr Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò!

Keep, oh! keep your chairs and candle,

And your jug without a handle, -

I can merely be your friend!

- Should my Jones more Dorkings send,

I will give you three, my friend!

Mr Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò!

Mr Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò!

‘Though you've such a tiny body,

And your head so large doth grow, -

Though your hat may blow away,

Mr Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò!

Though you're such a Hoddy Doddy -

Yet I wished that I could modify

the words I needs must say!

Will you please to go away?

That is all I have to say -

Mr Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò!

Mr Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò!'

Down the slippery slopes of Myrtle,

Where the early pumpkins blow,

To the calm and silent sea

Fled the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

There, beyond the Bay of Gurtle,

Lay a large and lively Turtle; -

‘You're the Cove,' he said, ‘for me;

On your back beyond the sea,

Turtle, you shall carry me!'

Said the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò,

Said the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

Through the silent- roaring ocean

Did the Turtle swiftly go;

Holding fast upon his shell

Rode the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

With a sad primæval motion

Towards the sunset isles of Boshen

Still the Turtle bore him well.

Holding fast upon his shell,

‘Lady Jingly Jones, farewell!'

Said the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò,

Said the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

From the Coast of Coromandel,

Did that Lady never go;

On that heap of stones she mourns

For the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

On that Coast of Coromandel,

In his jug without a handle,

Still she weeps, and daily moans;

On that little heap of stones

To her Dorking Hens she moans,

For the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò,

For the Yonghy- Bonghy- Bò.

The Dong with a Luminous Nose

When awful darkness and silence reign

Over the great Gromboolian plain,

Through the long, long wintry nights; -

When the angry breakers roar

As they beat on the rocky shore; -

When Storm- clouds brood on the towering heights

Of the Hills of the Chankly Bore: -

Then, through the vast and gloomy dark,

There moves what seems a fiery spark,

A lonely spark with silvery rays

Piercing the coal- black night, -

A Meteor strange and bright: -

Hither and thither the vision strays,

A single lurid light.

Slowly it wanders, – pauses, – creeps, -

Anon it sparkles, – flashes and leaps;

And ever as onward it gleaming goes

A light on the Bong- tree stems it throws.

And those who watch at that midnight hour

From Hall or Terrace, or lofty Tower,

Cry, as the wild light passes along, -

‘The Dong! – the Dong!

The wandering Dong through the forest goes!

The Dong! the Dong!

The Dong with a luminous Nose!'

Long years ago

The Dong was happy and gay,

Till he fell in love with a Jumbly Girl

Who came to those shores one day.

For the Jumblies came in a sieve, they did, -

Landing at eve near the Zemmery Fidd

Where the Oblong Oysters grow,

And the rocks are smooth and gray.

And all the woods and the valleys rang

With the Chorus they daily and nightly sang, -

‘Far and few, far and few,

Are the lands where the Jumblies live;

Their heads are green, and their hands are blue,

And they went to sea in a sieve.'

Happily, happily passed those days!

While the cheerful Jumblies staid;

They danced in circlets all night long,

To the plaintive pipe of the lively Dong,

In moonlight, shine, or shade.

For day and night he was always there

By the side of the Jumbly Girl so fair,

With her sky- blue hands, and her sea- green hair.

Till the morning came of that hateful day

When the Jumblies sailed in their sieve away,

And the Dong was left on the cruel shore

Gazing – gazing for evermore, -

Ever keeping his weary eyes on

That pea- green sail on the far horizon, -

Singing the Jumbly Chorus still

As he sate all day on the grassy hill, -

‘Far and few, far and few,

Are the lands where the Jumblies live;

Their heads are green, and their hands are blue,

And they went to sea in a sieve.'

But when the sun was low in the West,

The Dong arose and said; -

- ‘What little sense I once possessed

Has quite gone out of my head!' -

And since that day he wanders still

By lake and forest, marsh and hill,

Singing – ‘O somewhere, in valley or plain

Might I find my Jumbly Girl again!

For ever I'll seek by lake and shore

Till I find my Jumbly Girl once more!'

Playing a pipe with silvery squeaks,

Since then his Jumbly Girl he seeks,

And because by night he could not see,

He gathered the bark of the Twangum Tree

On the flowery plain that grows.

And he wove him a wondrous Nose, -

A Nose as strange as a Nose could be!

Of vast proportions and painted red,

And tied with cords to the back of his head.

- In a hollow rounded space it ended

With a luminous Lamp within suspended,

All fenced about

With a bandage stout

To prevent the wind from blowing it out; -

And with holes all round to send the light,

In gleaming rays on the dismal light.

And now each night, and all night long,

Over those plains still roams the Dong;

And above the wail of the Chimp and Snipe

You may hear the squeak of his plaintive pipe

While ever he seeks, but seeks in vain

To meet with his Jumbly Girl again;

Lonely and wild – all night he goes, -

The Dong with a luminous Nose!

And all who watch at the midnight hour,

From Hall or Terrace, or lofty Tower,

Cry, as they trace the Meteor bright,

Moving along through the dreary night, -

‘This is the hour when forth he goes,

The Dong with a luminous Nose!

Yonder – over the plain he goes;

He goes!

He goes;

The Dong with a luminous Nose!'